<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:48:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4296605" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4296605</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-01-26</datestamp>
        <setSpec>dpjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2176-9451</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2177-6709</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dental Press International</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4296605</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4296605</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4296605</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24945513</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24945513</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2176-9451.19.2.039-045.oar</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Transverse effect of Haas and Hyrax appliances on the upper dental arch
in patients with unilateral complete cleft lip and palate: A comparative
study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Façanha</surname>
                    <given-names>Anna Júlia de Oliveira</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lara</surname>
                    <given-names>Tulio Silva</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Garib</surname>
                    <given-names>Daniela Gamba</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>da Silva Filho</surname>
                    <given-names>Omar Gabriel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Specialist in Orthodontics, Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial
Anomalies - São Paulo University (HRAC-USP)</aff>
              <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> Professor of Interceptive Orthodontics (HRAC-USP)</aff>
              <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> Full professor, School of Dentistry - University of São Paulo/Bauru.
Professor of Orthodontics (HRAC-USP)</aff>
              <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> State University of São Paulo, MSc in Orthodontics, State University of
São Paulo (UNESP)</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Contact address: </bold>Tulio Silva Lara, Rua Sílvio Marchione, 3-20 - Vila
Universitária - Bauru/SP - Brazil. CEP: 17012-900 - E-mail:
<email>tuliolara@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>Mar-Apr</season>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Mar-Apr</season>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>19</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <fpage>39</fpage>
              <lpage>45</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>03</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2012</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2014 Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>The aim of the present study was to evaluate the transverse effect of rapid
maxillary expansion in patients with unilateral complete cleft lip and palate
while comparing the Haas and Hyrax appliances.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>The sample consisted of 48 patients divided into two groups: Group I - 25 patients
treated with modified Haas appliance (mean age: 10 years 8 months); and Group II -
23 patients treated with Hyrax appliance (mean age: 10 years 6 months). Casts were
taken during pre-expansion and after removal of the appliance at the end of the
retention period. The models were scanned with the aid of the 3 Shape R700 3D
scanner. Initial and final transverse distances were measured at cusp tips and
cervical-palatal points of maxillary teeth by using the Ortho
Analyzer<sup>TM</sup> 3D software.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>The mean expansion obtained between cusp tips and cervical-palatal points for
inter-canine width was 4.80 mm and 4.35 mm with the Haas appliance and 5.91 mm and
5.91 mm with the Hyrax appliance. As for first premolars or first deciduous
molars, the values obtained were 6.46 mm and 5.90 mm in the Haas group and 7.11 mm
and 6.65 mm in the Hyrax group. With regard to first molars, values were 6.11 mm
and 5.24 mm in the Haas group and 7.55 mm and 6.31 mm in the Hyrax group.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>Rapid maxillary expansion significantly increased the transverse dimensions of the
upper dental arch in patients with cleft palate, with no significant differences
between the Hass and Hyrax expanders.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objetivo</title>
                  <p>avaliar o efeito transversal na arcada dentária superior do procedimento de
expansão rápida da maxila em pacientes com fissura transforame incisivo
Aunilateral, comparando os expansores tipo Haas modificado e de Hyrax.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Métodos</title>
                  <p>a amostra constou de 48 pacientes divididos em dois grupos: grupo I, 25 pacientes
que utilizaram o aparelho expansor tipo Haas modificado, com média de idade de 10
anos e 8 meses; e grupo II, 23 pacientes que utilizaram o Hyrax, com média de
idade de 10 anos e 6 meses. Modelos de gesso foram realizados na fase pré-expansão
e após 6 meses de contenção, após a remoção do aparelho. Os modelos foram
digitalizados com auxílio do <italic>scanner</italic> 3Shape R700 3D e as
distâncias transversais iniciais e finais foram medidas entre as pontas de
cúspides e pontos cervicopalatinos de dentes superiores pelo método digital no
<italic>software</italic> OrthoAnalyserT 3D.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Resultados</title>
                  <p>a média de expansão obtida entre as pontas de cúspides e entre os pontos
cervicopalatinos, respectivamente, para a distância intercaninos, foi de 4,80mm e
4,35mm para o Haas e de 5,91mm e 5,91mm para o Hyrax; 6,46mm e 5,90mm para os
primeiros molares decíduos ou primeiros pré-molares no grupo Haas, 7,11mm e 6,65mm
no grupo Hyrax; e 6,11mm e 5,24mm para os primeiros molares no grupo Haas e 7,55mm
e 6,31mm no grupo Hyrax.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusão</title>
                  <p>o procedimento de expansão rápida da maxila produziu aumentos significativos das
dimensões transversais da arcada dentária superior em pacientes com fissura, sem
diferenças significativas entre os expansores Haas modificado e Hyrax.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Palatine expansion technique</kwd>
                <kwd>Cleft palate</kwd>
                <kwd>Dental arch</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Unilateral complete cleft lip and palate simultaneously involves the primary and
secondary palate and accounts for 30% of all clefts. This condition requires more
extensive treatment, as the cleft divides the maxilla and the alveolar arch into two
completely distinct segments.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>
Treatment initially involves primary functional and esthetic surgeries for the closing
of the lip and palate, which have a long-term impact on mid face growth.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>
The patient is then followed up throughout the growth period until entering the
orthodontic phase (end of the deciduous dentition phase).<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Primary surgeries of the lip and palate usually potentiate reductions in the transverse
and sagittal dimensions of the upper arch as a consequence of the restricted growth of
the mid face and the approximation of the initially separated maxillary
segments.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> These sagittal and
transverse deficiencies of the upper alveolar arch is expressed already at the mixed
dentition phase and tend to become aggravated in adolescence.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Thus, the task of orthodontists is to counteract the
harmful effects of the altered facial growth also characterized by posterior and
anterior cross bite - often found in patients with cleft lip and palate.<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Besides other occlusion issues,<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
posterior cross bite is the most common malocclusion in these patients, involving a
single tooth or the entire dental arch, showing a tendency toward exacerbation from the
mixed to the permanent dentition. Interceptive orthodontic interventions should be
performed during the mixed dentition phase for correction of the compromised transverse
dimension.<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Moreover, the
expansion of the upper arch also plays an important role in preparing the arch and cleft
region for the secondary alveolar bone graft, which is performed at the end of the mixed
dentition prior to the eruption of the permanent canine adjacent to the cleft
region.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Rapid maxillary expansion performed by means of a Haas or Hyrax appliance is the most
common method employed at the Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial Anomalies
(USP, Brazil) to increase the width of the maxilla. The main difference between the two
appliances is the type of anchorage: tooth-supported with the Hyrax appliance and
tooth-mucosa-supported with the Haas appliance.</p>
              <p>The active expansion phase in patients with unilateral complete cleft lip and palate
promotes distancing of the maxillary segments and widening of the cleft.<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Expansion in these patients is not
followed by bone formation at the median palatine suture, as it occurs in patients
without cleft palate,<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> because the
distancing of the maxillary halves occurs in the region of the cleft. Thus, retention
should remain after the appliance is removed and until bone graft is performed.
Expansion in such patients involves similar restrictions to those found in patients
without cleft palate, as the other maxillary sutures offer considerable resistance to
widening, requiring orthopedic appliances.</p>
              <p>Motivated by the interest in evaluating the results of the expansion philosophy of the
team at the Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial Anomalies/USP, the aim of the
present prospective study was to assess alterations in the transverse dimension of the
upper dental arch in patients with unilateral complete cleft lip and palate who have
undergone rapid maxillary expansion, comparing the results achieved with the Haas and
Hyrax appliances with the aid of digital models.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <p>This study was approved by the Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial Anomalies/USP
Institutional Review Board (protocol 255/2010-SVAPEPE-CEP).</p>
              <p>The sample consisted of 48 patients enrolled in the orthodontic sector of the hospital.
All patients had unilateral complete cleft lip and palate, had undergone primary
surgeries at an early age and were in the mixed dentition phase, exhibiting maxillary
atresia with an indication for rapid maxillary expansion.</p>
              <p>The patients were randomly divided into two groups. Group I comprised 25 patients
treated with the modified Haas appliance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig 1A</xref>),
with bands on the permanent molars and orthodontic clip bonded to the deciduous molars
(16 males and 9 females; mean age: 10 years 8 months; age range: 8 years to 19 years and
2 months). Group II comprised 23 patients treated with the Hyrax appliance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig 1B</xref>) (13 males and 10 females; mean age: 10 years
6 months; age range: 8 years and 2 months to 18 years and 1 month). All patients
underwent the same activation protocol. The expander was activated for seven days with
2/4 turns in the morning and 2/4 turns in the evening. Whenever necessary, further
activation was performed until overcorrection was reached (palatine cusps of the upper
molars occluding the vestibular cusps of the lower molars). Hooks for a facial mask were
welded to the inverse traction of the maxilla for patients that also had sagittal
discrepancy with good prognosis for orthopedic treatment.</p>
              <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Occlusal photographs of two patients from the sample illustrating both expanders:
Modified Haas (A) and Hyrax (B)</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-19-02-0039-g01"/>
              </fig>
              <p>After achieving overcorrection, the screw was stabilized with acrylic resin. The
expander was maintained passive with a retention protocol for six months, after which
the expander was removed and a fixed retainer was installed.</p>
              <p>Dental cast of the maxillary arch were obtained at two different times: immediately
before banding for the expander (T<sub>1</sub>), and after the six-month period of
retention immediately following the removal of the expander (T<sub>2</sub>). The
impressions were made with alginate and filled with Paris plaster. The dental casts were
then scanned by a 3Shape R700 3D scanner (3Shape A/S, Copenhagen, Denmark), which
reproduces a three-dimensional digital image based on laser beams scans projected over
the plaster models in different directions. The Ortho Analyzer <sup>TM</sup> 3D program
was used to obtain the three-dimensional image of the scanned models, allowing frontal,
lateral, posterior and occlusal visualization. The reference points were marked on the
model in the occlusal view for the calculation of the distances between teeth. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref> illustrates the measurements made on the
digital models of the upper dental arches.</p>
              <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Initial and final digital models showing the results of rapid maxillary expansion
(A and B); reference points (C) and measurements made (D) on postexpansion
models</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-19-02-0039-g02"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Analyses were performed by a single examiner. Sixty percent of the sample was analyzed a
second time after a seven-day interval in order to determine the measurements
reliability using the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) for which the following
scores were used: 0.80 to 1.00 = excellent agreement; 0.60 to 0.80 = substantial; 0.40
to 0.60 = moderate; 0.20 to 0.40 = fair; 0 to 0.20 = discreet; and -1 to 0 = poor.</p>
              <p>Mean, standard deviation (SD), maximum and minimum values were calculated. The paired
Student's t-test was employed to determine statistically significant differences between
the initial and final measurements of each group. The independent t-test was used for
inter-group comparison. The level of significance was set at 5% (p &lt; 0.05).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Tables 1</xref> to <xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">4</xref> display the results of the measurement reliability and transverse distances
measured on the models.</p>
              <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Error of the method (Intraclass Correlation Coefficient).</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#54b4e6;color:#ffffff">
                      <th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Measure</th>
                      <th colspan="2" style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid" rowspan="1">ICC
(Haas)</th>
                      <th colspan="2" style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid" rowspan="1">ICC
(Hyrax)</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#54b4e6;color:#ffffff">
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICpc</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICc</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdpc</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdc</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMppc</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMpc</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Transverse distances measured on initial and final digital models and mean amount
of expansion (Dif.) in millimeters for patients using the modified Haas
expander.</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#54b4e6;color:#ffffff">
                      <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Measure</th>
                      <th align="center" style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial model</th>
                      <th align="center" style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final model</th>
                      <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Dif.</th>
                      <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">p</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#54b4e6;color:#ffffff">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± S.D.</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± S.D.</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.81 ± 3.13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.60 ± 3.35</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.15 ± 3.39</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.50 ± 3.76</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.35</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.39 ± 3.67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.85 ± 4.22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.25 ± 3.03</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.15 ± 3.36</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMppc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.20 ± 3.91</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.31 ± 3.28</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.29 ± 2.84</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.54 ± 3.24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN01">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Transverse distances measured on initial and final digital models and mean amount
of expansion (Dif.) in millimeters for patients using the Hyrax expander.</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#54b4e6;color:#ffffff">
                      <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Measure</th>
                      <th align="center" style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial model</th>
                      <th align="center" style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final model</th>
                      <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Dif.</th>
                      <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">p</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#54b4e6;color:#ffffff">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± S.D.</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± S.D.</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.63 ± 3.98</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.54 ± 2.95</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN02">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.37 ± 2.96</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.28 ± 3.91</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN02">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.10 ± 3.71</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.21 ± 3.96</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN02">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.72 ± 3.59</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.37 ± 3.50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN02">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMppc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.68 ± 4.26</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.23 ± 3.73</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN02">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.32 ± 3.90</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.63 ± 3.79</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.31</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN02">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN02">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Comparison of modified Haas and Hyrax appliances groups regarding mean increase in
transverse dimensions of the maxilla following rapid maxillary expansion.</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#54b4e6;color:#ffffff">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measure</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group Haas (n)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group Hyrax (n)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference (mm)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80 (18)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91 (18)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.35 (11)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46 (19)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPMdc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90 (19)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.65 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMppc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11 (24)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55 (22)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN03">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#d5e9f8">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMpc</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24 (24)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.31 (21)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>ns = non-significant.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN03">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Cleft lip and palate occurs in the mid face and causes structural problems in the
alveolar bone and maxilla. The urgent relationship with the malocclusion is demonstrated
by the anatomic rupture that compromises the alveolar ridge as well as dental problems,
such as agenesis and malpositioning, as well as sagittal and transverse maxillary
difficiencies.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> The treatment
protocol adopted by the Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial Anomalies/USP for
patients with unilateral complete cleft lip and palate emphasizes early surgical
procedures (cheiloplasty and palatoplasty), with no orthopedic intervention in the
preoperative or immediate postoperative periods. As a general rule, orthodontic
treatment is initiated at the onset of the mixed dentition phase. Two reasons justify
the lack of orthodontic intervention in the deciduous dentition phase: the instability
of the early correction of cross bites, which leads to an excessively long treatment and
retention time; and the fact that alterations in the shape of the dental arch and the
occlusion are exacerbated in the mixed dentition phase.<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Expansion is the first step of orthodontic treatment (pre-alveolar bone graft). It aims
at reestablishing the transverse dimensions of the atresic maxilla. The maxillary
expander designed by Haas is the main appliance used for lateral repositioning of the
collapsed maxillary processes<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> and
follows the same activation protocol used for patients without cleft palate. In this
phase, the inverse traction of the maxilla may be associated with the post-expansion
period to revert cases of negative sagittal discrepancy, expressed by anterior
crossbite.<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> The Hyrax appliance
is also commonly used for maxillary expansion. The main difference between the two
expanders is the acrylic support on the palate in the Haas appliance. However, both
expanders are effective in increasing the transverse dimension of the maxilla. The
choice of one over the other is based on the shape of the patient's palate. Whenever the
transverse width and depth allow, the Haas expander is the appliance of choice due to
the anchorage provided by its acrylic portion. In the present study, the modified Haas
expander was used, which differs from the original by the presence of two orthodontic
bands instead of four, and by bonded orthodontic clips on the deciduous molars.</p>
              <p>Following the tendency of using digital records in Orthodontics,<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> the evaluation of the transverse effect
of the Haas and Hyrax expanders was performed with digital models, which offer
advantages in terms of storage, retrieval, durability, diagnostic versatility and
transmitting information.<sup><xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Moreover,
studies comparing digital and conventional models report considerable accuracy and
reproducibility in the measurements of tooth width, overjet and overbite.<sup><xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> The ICC of the measurements obtained
from the digital models by a single examiner on two different occasions demonstrate the
reliability of the method (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>).</p>
              <p>Both appliances were capable of restoring the adequate upper arch morphology and
correcting the posterior cross bite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figs 1</xref> and
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). The results demonstrate significant
increase (p &lt; 0.0001) in all transverse dimensions measured (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">3</xref>), which is in
agreement with findings reported in the literature.<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The increases in the inter-molar, inter-premolar or inter-deciduous molar and
inter-canine widths were statistically significant in both groups. The group treated
with the Haas expander had an increase in inter-molar distance of 6.11 mm on the tips of
the mesiovestibular cusps, 5.24 mm on the palatine-cervical portion of the molars, and
an increase in the inter-canine distance of 4.79 mm when measured on the cusps and 4.35
mm when measured on the palatine-cervical portion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>). These values are similar to those reported by previous
studies.<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In a study involving digital models of 32 children
without cleft palate and with unilateral or bilateral cross bite (16 children treated
with the Haas expander and 16 treated with the Hyrax expander),the Haas group had an
increase in inter-molar distance of 6.33 mm on the tips of the mesiovestibular cusps and
6.04 mm on the central sulcus of the first molars; an increase in the inter-canine
distance of 2.27 mm when measured on the cusps and 4.74 mm when measured on the cervical
portion.<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></p>
              <p>In the present study, the patients treated with the Hyrax expander had an increase in
inter-molar distance of 7.55 mm on the tips of the mesiovestibular cusps and 6.31 mm in
the palatine-cervical portion; an increase in the inter-canine distance of 5.91 mm when
measured on the cusps or on the palatine-cervical portion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>). These results are similar to findings reported in the
literature for patients in the mixed dentition phase treated with the Hyrax
expander.<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> However,
another study reports larger increases (9.97 mm in inter-molar distance on the tips of
the mesiopalatine cusps and 9.51 mm in the in the mesial portion of the central sulcus
of the and 7.93 mm in the inter-canine distance when measured on the cusps and 6.29 mm
when measured on the cervical portion).<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></p>
              <p>No statistically significant differences were found between groups in the comparison of
the inter-molar and inter-canine distances obtained with the Haas or Hyrax appliances,
except for the inter-molar distance measured on the tips of the cusps, which was greater
in the Hyrax group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table 4</xref>). This was likely
due to the greater tooth tipping caused by this appliance. Discrepant results are
reported in the literature, with some studies reporting a greater increase in
inter-molar and inter-canine distances using the Hyrax expander<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and others reporting a greater tendency
of vestibular tipping of molars using the Haas expander.<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Both appliances generally demonstrate similar behavior
regarding the expansion of the dentoalveolar region of the maxilla.<sup><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> However, the Haas expander may cause
greater vestibular tipping of the anchoring teeth (3.5º for the first molar) in
comparison to the Hyrax expander (1.6º), although this is not a clinically relevant
difference.<sup><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <list list-type="simple">
                <list-item>
                  <p>- Rapid maxillary expansion using the modified Haas and Hyrax expanders proved
efficient in increasing the transverse dimensions of the upper dental arch in
patients with unilateral complete cleft lip and palate.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>- No significant differences between appliances were found regarding the
transverse effects produced by the modified Haas and Hyrax expanders in the
present study.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>» Patients displayed in this article previously approved the use of their facial and
intraoral photographs.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>» The authors report no commercial, proprietary or financial interest in the products
or companies described in this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Façanha AJO, Lara TS, Garib DG, Silva Filho
OG. Transverse effect of Haas and Hyrax appliances on the upper dental arch in
patients with unilateral complete cleft lip and palate: A comparative study. Dental
Press J Orthod. 2014 Mar-Apr;19(2):39-45. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/2176-9451.19.2.039-045.oar">http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/2176-9451.19.2.039-045.oar</ext-link></p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="r01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferrari</surname>
                      <given-names>FM</given-names>
                      <suffix>Júnior</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mazzottini</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">A cirurgia ortognática na reabilitação do paciente
portador de fissura unilateral completa de lábio e palato</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Dental Press Ortod Ortop Facial</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <lpage>70</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>JAS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">Caracterização morfológica e origem
embriológica</article-title>
                  <person-group person-group-type="compiler">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trindade</surname>
                      <given-names>IEK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Fissuras labiopalatinas: uma abordagem interdisciplinar</source>
                  <publisher-loc>São Paulo</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Ed. Santos</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <comment>cap. 2</comment>
                  <year>2007</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramos</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abdo</surname>
                      <given-names>RC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The influence of unilateral cleft lip and palate on maxillary dental
arch morphology</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <lpage>290</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1456475</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cavassan</surname>
                      <given-names>AO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Abordagem ortodôntica</article-title>
                  <person-group person-group-type="compiler">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trindade</surname>
                      <given-names>IEK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Fissuras labiopalatinas: uma abordagem interdisciplinar</source>
                  <publisher-loc>São Paulo</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Ed. Santos</publisher-name>
                  <comment>cap. 12</comment>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <lpage>238</lpage>
                  <year>2007</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Athanasiou</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mazahery</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zarrinnia</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental arch dimensions in patients with unilateral cleft lip and
palate</article-title>
                  <source>Cleft Palate J</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <lpage>145</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3163289</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capelozza</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ursi</surname>
                      <given-names>WJS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rapid maxillary expansion in cleft lip and palate
patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Orthod</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <lpage>39</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8040239</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reis</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capelozza</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ozawa</surname>
                      <given-names>TO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cavassan</surname>
                      <given-names>AO</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">Avaliação da angulação e inclinação dos elementos
dentários em pacientes adultos jovens portadores de fissura transforame incisivo
bilateral</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Dental Press Ortod Ortop Facial</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>123</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Long</surname>
                      <given-names>RE</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Semb</surname>
                      <given-names>GS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaw</surname>
                      <given-names>WC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Orthodontic treatment of the patient with complete lip and palate:
lessons of the past 60 years</article-title>
                  <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J.</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Access in 2010 set 10</date-in-citation>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cpcjournal.org/doi/pdf/10.1597/1545569%282000%29037%3C0533%3AOTOTPW%3E2.0.CO%3B2">http://www.cpcjournal.org/doi/pdf/10.1597/1545569%282000%29037%3C0533%3AOTOTPW%3E2.0.CO%3B2</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lara</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>HC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bertoz</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">Comportamento da sutura palatina mediana em crianças
submetidas à expansão rápida da maxila: avaliação mediante imagem de tomografia
computadorizada</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Dental Press Ortod Ortop Facial</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <lpage>103</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garib</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>JHN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Etiologia das más oclusões: perspectiva clínica (parte III) - fissuras
labiopalatinas</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Clín Ortod Dental Press</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abdo</surname>
                      <given-names>RCC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramos</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">Comportamento do arco dentário superior de crianças
fissuradas de lábio e palato, operadas - estudo longitudinal de 3 a 6
anos</article-title>
                  <source>Ortodontia</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <lpage>26</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>OG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capelozza</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wernech</surname>
                      <given-names>VA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>JAS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">Abordagem ortodôntica ao paciente com fissura unilateral
completa de lábio e palato</article-title>
                  <source>Ortodontia</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Creed</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kau</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>English</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xia</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>RP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of the accuracy of linear measurements obtained from cone
beam computerized tomography images and digital models</article-title>
                  <source>Semin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <lpage>56</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joffe</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>OrthoCAD: digital models for a digital era</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>344</fpage>
                  <lpage>347</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608352</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santoro</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Galkin</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teredesai</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nicolay</surname>
                      <given-names>OF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cangialosi</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of measurements made on digital and plaster
models</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>124</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <lpage>105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12867904</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weissheimer</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source xml:lang="pt">Efeitos imediatos da expansão rápida da maxila no sentido
transversal, com os disjuntores tipo Haas e Hyrax, em tomografia computadorizada
cone beam [dissertação]</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Porto Alegre (RS)</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio Grande do
Sul</publisher-name>
                  <year>2008</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McNamara</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baccetti</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franchi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herberger</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rapid maxillary expansion followed by fixed appliances: a long-term
evaluation of changes in arch dimension</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>344</fpage>
                  <lpage>353</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12940553</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>RMA</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bolognese</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Long-term clinical outcome of rapid maxillary expansion as the only
treatment performed in class I malocclusion</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>416</fpage>
                  <lpage>420</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15898383</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>NL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Da Silveira</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kusnoto</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viana</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Three-dimensional assessment of morphologic changes of the maxilla: a
comparison of 2 kinds of palatal expanders</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>126</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <lpage>362</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15356500</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mundstock</surname>
                      <given-names>KS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source xml:lang="pt">Estudo dos efeitos da expansão rápida de maxila em pacientes
com mordida cruzada posterior tratados com aparelhos de Haas e de Hyrax
[tese]</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Araraquara (SP)</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Universidade Estadual Paulista</publisher-name>
                  <year>2006</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adkins</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nanda</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Currier</surname>
                      <given-names>GF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Arch perimeter changes on rapid palatal expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>97</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <lpage>199</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2178393</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiavini</surname>
                      <given-names>PCR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source xml:lang="pt">Efeitos da expansão rápida da maxila com aparelho expansor tipo
Hyrax: avaliação cefalométrica póstero-anterior em modelos de estudo
[tese]</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Araraquara (SP)</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Araraquara</publisher-name>
                  <year>2004</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ciambotti</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ngan</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Durkee</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kohli</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of dental and dentoalveolar changes between rapid palatal
expansion and nickel-titanium palatal expansion appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>119</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11174532</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garib</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriques</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coelho</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rapid maxillary expansion - Tooth tissue-borne versus tooth-borne
expanders: a computed tomography evaluation of dentoskeletal
effects</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>548</fpage>
                  <lpage>557</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16097223</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
