<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:37:21Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10463426" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10463426</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-08-30</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcorhl</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10463426</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10463426</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10463426</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37612722</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37612722</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3286</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-023-03286-3</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Serious game as oral histology learning strategy for undergraduate dental students; crossover randomized controlled trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Amir</surname>
                    <given-names>Lisa R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>lisa.amir@ui.ac.id</email>
                    <email>lisa.amir@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Leonardy</surname>
                    <given-names>Irene C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dewatmoko</surname>
                    <given-names>Salsabila N.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yanuar</surname>
                    <given-names>Rezon</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Suniarti</surname>
                    <given-names>Dewi F.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Idrus</surname>
                    <given-names>Erik</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sipiyaruk</surname>
                    <given-names>Kawin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Puspitawati</surname>
                    <given-names>Ria</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0116zj450</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9581.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2019 1471</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral Biology, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Universitas Indonesia, </institution></institution-wrap>Salemba Raya No. 4, Jakarta Pusat 10430, Jakarta, Indonesia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0116zj450</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9581.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2019 1471</institution-id><institution>Dental Education Unit, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Universitas Indonesia, </institution></institution-wrap>Jakarta, Indonesia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0116zj450</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9581.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2019 1471</institution-id><institution>Dentistry Study Program, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Universitas Indonesia, </institution></institution-wrap>Jakarta, Indonesia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04tqcn816</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412021.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1769 5590</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmacology, School of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Health Sciences University of Hokkaido, Ishikari- Tobetsu, </institution></institution-wrap>Hokkaido, Japan </aff>
                <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01znkr924</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10223.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0490</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthodontics, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Mahidol University, </institution></institution-wrap>Bangkok, Thailand </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>23</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>23</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <elocation-id>585</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">Oral histology is perceived by dental students as a challenging subject and often struggle to recognize the long-term relevance of understanding the cells and tissues at the microscopic level. Serious games have been reported to have a positive effect on student cognitive skills and learning motivation. However, there is still a limited amount of research supporting the effectiveness of serious games as a learning method in dentistry. The present study aimed to evaluate the impact of serious game of <italic>HistoRM</italic> as a complementary learning strategy for oral histology.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">The study design was a crossover randomized controlled trial. A total of 74 first year dental students of Universitas Indonesia participated in the study and divided into 2 groups. Study intervention included <italic>HistoRM</italic> game for 3 days followed by a combination of <italic>HistoRM</italic> and script-based handouts for another 4 days. The groups represented different intervention sequences. Evaluation was performed using pre-test, post-test on day 3 and 7 and a questionnaire.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">The data showed significant improvement of student cognitive skills (p &lt; 0.001) and it was influenced by the number of game missions completed. Students who completed the whole 15 missions have a higher day-7 post-tests scores (p = 0.03). Perception of dental students on <italic>HistoRM</italic> was positive in all domains tested, the learning content, games and learning experience domains. Immediate feedback given after each gameplay helped the students understand the subject matters.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">Serious game of <italic>HistoRM</italic> effectively improved students’ understanding of oral histology learning outcome and provided more interesting learning experiences. This innovative learning can be recommended as a complementary learning strategy of oral histology for dental students.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Supplementary Information</title>
                  <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12903-023-03286-3.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Serious Games</kwd>
                <kwd>Oral histology</kwd>
                <kwd>Undergraduate students</kwd>
                <kwd>Innovative learning</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100006378</institution-id>
                      <institution>Universitas Indonesia</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>NKB-610/UN2.RST/HKP.05.00/2022.</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par13">Oral histology course, study the science of the microscopic structure of cells and tissues, is an integral part of the dental curriculum. Previously, it was reported that dental students find oral histology as a difficult subject [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The lack of understanding of the importance of recognizing the complexity of tissue organization and its function to support the learning and understanding the pathogenesis of diseases might contribute to this perception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Lesson materials may be partially or entirely forgotten by students when a large amount of complex study materials is provided for students to learn in a short period of time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Moreover, student disinterest may play a role in weak performances in higher education [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Conventionally, the didactic learning approach of oral histology materials is delivered as knowledge transfer through classroom lectures and practical demonstrations of slides under the microscope. The approach does not stimulate students’ interactive discussion in the classroom nor active engagement. As the current medical and dental students are of the digital natives generation, they gravitated toward modern electronic learning tools that provide fast and efficient feedback [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Clearly, there is a need for a new learning approach that could engage students in the learning process, emphasize the learning outcomes and the relevance of oral histology in dentistry. An interactive learning environment that could create an interesting learning atmosphere without neglecting the learning materials, will increase student’s knowledge, skills, and motivation, encouraging student engagement, and at the same time increasing learning and solving problems.</p>
              <p id="Par14">Contemporary educational technology is implemented in recent years to scaffold knowledge transfer to the learners in a situated and multimodal approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Gamification refers to the application of game theory, techniques and mechanics outside the context of traditional game activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In the past several years, trends in educational research show an increasing interest in incorporating games in learning approaches. Game-based learning refers to a strategy to enhance knowledge and skill acquisition, through game content and game play, where game activities involve problem solving and challenges that provide players/learners with a sense of achievement of the defined learning outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Games are called serious when they have a pedagogical purpose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The introduction of games in education has been demonstrated to stimulate learning and improve learner satisfaction. Previous reviews on serious games in healthcare education indicate the most frequent outcome investigated was the improvement in knowledge acquisition and is perceived as a more engaging learning approach compared to traditional methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Although serious games are not considered mainstream material in medical and dental teaching, it provides tools to enhance interactivity in healthcare education including dental education. Serious games could overcome limitations of asynchronous learning, the learning strategy that became widely used during this frequent pandemic time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par15">The evaluation of undergraduate dental curriculum in the Universitas Indonesia demonstrated a similar phenomenon with others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Student perception towards their level of understanding of oral histology was still unsatisfactory. In particular, their understanding of the long-term relevance of oral histology, which includes the complexity of functional networks and pathological processes. The implementation of innovative learning strategies such as serious games to enhance knowledge acquisition, motivation and engaging learning environment can therefore be a solution. However, research on the effectiveness and use of serious games as a complementary learning method in dentistry has not been well-studied. The present study was aimed to evaluate the effectiveness of the implementation of a <italic>HistoRM</italic> serious game specifically designed as a complementary learning of oral histology for undergraduate dental students.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p id="Par16">This research was conducted in August 2022 - January 2023, using a crossover randomized controlled trial, two-arm RCT with 1:1 allocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Ethical approval was obtained from Dental Research Ethics Committee Universitas Indonesia (87/ethical approval/FKGUI/X/2022). The trial was registered to ISRCTN Registry Service (23.03.2023), registration number ISRCTN11006820. The results of the study were reported using the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) Guidelines (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par36">
                  <fig id="Fig1">
                    <label>Fig. 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>CONSORT Flow Diagram of the Randomized Controlled Trial</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_3286_Figa_HTML" id="d32e378"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Study participants</title>
                <p id="Par17">Study participants were undergraduate 1st year dental students who studied the basic oral biology practicum course in the 1st semester of the 2022/2023 academic year. Their participation was voluntary-based and third year dental students (ICL and SND) were involved in the recruitment of study participants. All respondents filled out and submitted the informed consent form. G*power statistical software was used to calculate sample size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. We estimated sample size of 45 participants in each group would be sufficient to detect statistical significant with a power of 0.8, significant level of 0.05, assuming an effect size of 0.6. Students were randomly divided into two groups. Prior to the intervention, the GPA score, pre-test knowledge score and game preference in the two groups were evaluated to minimize bias. It was revealed that there were no significant difference of the scores nor the preference between the two groups. Pre-tests were given before the study started to evaluate their prior knowledge. Two learning materials were prepared with complementary learning of <italic>HistoRM</italic> game, topic 1 was the histology of oral mucosa, and topic 2 was the histology of tooth and its supporting structure. The intervention consisted of the <italic>HistoRM</italic> game and the practicum handouts (script-based). Group A played <italic>HistoRM</italic> game of topic 1 for three days, and were later given the practicum handouts, while group B received the practicum handouts of topic 1 in the first three days, and played <italic>HistoRM</italic> game between day 3–7. After three days, students in group A and B could access both interventions. Post-tests evaluation was carried out on day 3 and day 7 (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The experimental study was repeated for topic 2. In the first three days, group A received the practicum handouts while group B played HistoRM game, implementing the crossover experimental design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. At the end of study, participants were asked to fill out a survey to evaluate their understanding level of the learning material and their perception of learning experiences (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p>
                <p id="Par028">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Description of Intervention Groups</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="3">
                            <bold>Topic 1 (Microscopic Structure of Oral Mucosa)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="2">Post-test</td>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2">Intervention</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group A</td>
                          <td align="left">Group B</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Day 3</td>
                          <td align="left">Game only</td>
                          <td align="left">Script-based Hand-out only</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Day 7</td>
                          <td align="left">Game (3 days) + Script-based Hand-out (4 days)</td>
                          <td align="left">Script-based Hand-out (3 days) + Game (4 days)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="3">
                            <bold>Topic 2 (Microscopic Structure of Tooth and Its Supporting Structures)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="2">Post-test</td>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2">Intervention</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group A</td>
                          <td align="left">Group B</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Day 3</td>
                          <td align="left">Script-based Hand-out only</td>
                          <td align="left">Game only</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Day 7</td>
                          <td align="left">Game (3 days) + Script-based Hand-out (4 days)</td>
                          <td align="left">Script-based Hand-out (3 days) + Game (4 days)</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p id="Par37">
                  <fig id="Fig2">
                    <label>Fig. 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Research timeline</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_3286_Figb_HTML" id="d32e495"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Serious game</title>
                <p id="Par18">Serious game called <italic>HistoRM</italic> was developed with Unity game platform and was integrated in the SCORM activity in the Universitas Indonesia moodle-based learning management system (EMAS). This education puzzle-based game consisted of four gameplays: (1) jigsaw puzzle; (2) find the differences; (3) match the pictures; and (4) crosswords (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A-D). Two topics of oral histology learning subjects were used in <italic>HistoRM</italic> game consisted of: (1) Histology of oral mucosa, and (2) histology of tooth and its supporting structure. Each topic was divided into three stage levels, and each stage contained five missions, a total of 15 missions for each topic (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>E). Mission can be divided into two sessions (puzzle game session and quiz session). Students were required to clear the puzzle game session first before continuing to the quiz session, and were able to repeat the mission multiple times if they wanted to relearn the subject matter. One-to three-star points can be collected in every mission, depending on the winning condition such as the time to complete the mission, the number of mistakes, and the number of hint-feature used. These star points were collected and determined the player ranking in comparison to other players and were monitored in the leaderboard ranking system (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>F). There was no time limit in playing <italic>HistoRM</italic> game.</p>
                <p id="Par38">
                  <fig id="Fig3">
                    <label>Fig. 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p><italic>HistoRM</italic> Games. The gameplay included jigsaw puzzle (<bold>A</bold>); find the differences (<bold>B</bold>); match the pictures (<bold>C</bold>); and crosswords (<bold>D</bold>); Custom-made avatar design was created as entertainment elements of the games (<bold>E-F</bold>); Leaderboard showed student achievement and number of rewards (<bold>G-H</bold>) Molara character was created to give game instruction, hints and feedback (<bold>I</bold>)</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_3286_Figc_HTML" id="d32e553"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p id="Par19">We incorporated the fun elements into the <italic>HistoRM</italic> game which included the custom-made avatars that represented the players, custom-made background and music. Players can design the avatars (hairstyle, hair color, clothes and other accessories) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>G-H). Facial expression of the avatar changes based on the process when they played the games. A character known as Molara, a human-tooth form creature was developed and served to guide the students. In the beginning, Molara gave the explanation of learning outcomes of each stage, and gave instruction on how to play the puzzle-based game. During the puzzle game session, Molara offered the hint-feature when the players had difficulties to complete the mission. At the end of the quiz session, Molara provided immediate feedback and explanation related to the quiz topics (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>I).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Assessments</title>
                <p id="Par20">Pre-test was carried out to determine student’s prior knowledge before the intervention. The impact of <italic>HistoRM</italic> as complementary learning was assessed with post-tests. Post-tests were given at day 3, to compare student’s cognitive skills in <italic>HistoRM</italic> group with practicum handouts (script-based) group, while post-test was carried out at day 7 to assess students’ cognitive skills between the groups tested which have been given both interventions in a different order. Pre- and post-test consisted of 30 multiple-choice questions that were shuffled between and within questions, and were carried out in EMAS.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Questionnaire</title>
                <p id="Par21">The questionnaire consists of 21 questions in which 14 questions were answered by a 4-point Likert scale. Questions were divided into general information (7) and 3 domains consisted of learning content domain (3), game aspect domain (5), and learning experience domain (6). Fifteen students were selected for validity and reliability test of the questionnaire. The validity and reliability of the questionnaire were tested using face validity, Cronbach alpha, and the ICC test. The total Cronbach alpha score was 0.85 and can be categorized as reliable. The reliability of the questionnaire evaluated from the Intraclass Correlation Coefficient score had an excellent agreement (r = 0.98, 95% Confidence Interval (CI), 0.94–0.99).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par22">Descriptive statistics were computed and data normality was tested with Shapiro-Wilk. Bivariate analyses were performed using the SPSS 25.0 version. The level of statistical significance was accepted at 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>General information</title>
                <p id="Par23">Initially, there were 100 (73%) out of 137 undergraduate 1st year dental students from regular and international class who filled out the informed consent for their participation in the study. Students were randomly assigned into 2 groups (A and B). During the trial, a total of twenty-six students did not complete a minimum of 10 missions per topic within the designated time frame, and were excluded from the analyses. The reasons for students not being able to complete the required missions were high study load and <italic>HistoRM</italic> game could be played only on a laptop/desktop. Therefore, seventy-four students (53.6% of all first-year students) were included in the analysis.</p>
                <p id="Par24">Before the intervention, students were given pre-tests, and the scores revealed no statistically significant difference of student cognitive skills in group A and B for both oral histology topics (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). A total of 59 (79.5%) participants like to play games in their spare time, and 54 students (72.4%) were not familiar with serious games prior to the trial (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The frequencies of students playing <italic>HistoRM</italic> game were varied, 42 (56.7%) of students played <italic>HistoRM</italic> game more than 2 times during the study, followed by 2 times (31 students, 42%) and 1 time (1 student, 1.3%). The average duration of play in the <italic>HistoRM</italic> game was 85 ± 25.7 min. The most liked puzzle-based gameplay types were jigsaw puzzles (58.1%), followed by find the difference (37.8%) and match the picture (2.7%). Crosswords games had the least favored gameplay (1.4%).</p>
                <p id="Par28">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab2">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>General Information of Study Participants</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Topic 1</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Topic 2</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left">Group A (n = 40)</th>
                          <th align="left">Group B (n = 34)</th>
                          <th align="left">Group A (n = 40)</th>
                          <th align="left">Group B (n = 34)</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="4">Gender</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">Male</td>
                          <td align="left">8 (20%)</td>
                          <td align="left">3 (8.8%)</td>
                          <td align="left">8 (20%)</td>
                          <td align="left">3 (8.8%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">Female</td>
                          <td align="left">32 (80%)</td>
                          <td align="left">31 (91.2%)</td>
                          <td align="left">32 (80%)</td>
                          <td align="left">31 (91.2%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2">Age in years (mean ± SD)</td>
                          <td align="left">18.1 ± 0.6</td>
                          <td align="left">17.9 ± 0.6</td>
                          <td align="left">17.9 ± 0.6</td>
                          <td align="left">18.1 ± 0.6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="4">Do you like playing games?</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">Yes</td>
                          <td align="left">33 (82.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">26 (76.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">33 (82.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">26 (76.5%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">No</td>
                          <td align="left">7 (17.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">8 (23.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">7 (17.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">8 (23.5%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6">How often do you play games in a week? (in hours)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">0–9 h</td>
                          <td align="left">36 (90%)</td>
                          <td align="left">33 (97.1%)</td>
                          <td align="left">36 (90%)</td>
                          <td align="left">33 (97.1%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">10–19 h</td>
                          <td align="left">4 (10%)</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (2.9%)</td>
                          <td align="left">4 (10%)</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (2.9%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">&gt;20 h</td>
                          <td align="left">-</td>
                          <td align="left">-</td>
                          <td align="left">-</td>
                          <td align="left">-</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6">Have you previously known what serious games are?</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">Yes</td>
                          <td align="left">15 (37.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">6 (17.6%)</td>
                          <td align="left">15 (37.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">6 (17.6%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left">No</td>
                          <td align="left">25 (62.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">28 (82.4%)</td>
                          <td align="left">25 (62.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">28 (82.4%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2">
                            <p>Pre-test score</p>
                            <p>(mean ± SD)</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">54.25 ± 14.20</td>
                          <td align="left">51.18 ± 12.17</td>
                          <td align="left">50.67 ± 13.78</td>
                          <td align="left">45.88 ± 12.34</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>The impact of HistoRM Game on cognitive skills</title>
                <p id="Par25"><italic>HistoRM</italic> game interventions were carried out for two topics of oral histology. In topic 1 (histology of oral mucosa), the significant increased of cognitive skills score were observed at day-3 compared to pre-tests score in group A who received <italic>HistoRM</italic> game intervention first (p &lt; 0.001) as well as in group B who received practicum handouts first (p = 0.014). Similarly, cognitive skills scores were observed at day-7 compared to pre-tests (p &lt; 0.001). Day-7 post-tests were carried out to determine whether the increase in cognitive skills score was related to the order of intervention, <italic>HistoRM</italic> game followed by practicum handouts (group A) or practicum handouts in the first three days, followed by <italic>HistoRM</italic> game (group B). It was found that the increases in cognitive skills scores were higher in group A (1.35-fold) than group B (1.28-fold) at day-3 (p = 0.003)and day-7 post-tests (p = 0.02)(Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>i-iv).</p>
                <p id="Par39">
                  <fig id="Fig4">
                    <label>Fig. 4</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Results of student cognitive skill scores. Significant increased of cognitive skills scores were observed pre- and post tests in topic 1 (i) and topic 2 (ii); The order of intervention influenced the scores at day 3 (iii); but no significant different in the two groups tested at day 7 for topic 2 (iv)</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_3286_Figd_HTML" id="d32e819"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p id="Par26">The positive impact of <italic>HistoRM</italic> game on student understanding of topic 2 (histology of tooth and its supporting structure) was also observed (p &lt; 0.001). However, it was found that the increase in cognitive skills scores were higher in group A than group B at day-3 (p = 0.039) and not significantly different at day-7 post-tests (p = 0.06). Although the intervention of group A and B was changed (crossover). The data indicated the order of intervention did not influence the results. Furthermore, the improvement of cognitive skills scores was influenced by the number of missions completed. Pearson correlation analysis revealed positive correlation of students who completed the 15 missions have a higher day-7 post-tests score (p = 0.03).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Student perceptions of HistoRM game as complementary learning of oral histology</title>
                <p id="Par27">In the learning content domain, students responded positively to the content of <italic>HistoRM</italic> game. Over 95% of participants reported that they gained a better understanding of histology content. More than 90% of students perceived the quiz sessions in <italic>HistoRM</italic> game helped them to understand the oral histology practicum lessons. They agreed (81%) that the content of <italic>HistoRM</italic> game has been previously studied. The practicum course is integrated with the theory of oral biology course and serves as the reinforcement of the theory class. In the <italic>HistoRM</italic> game domains, all of the questions received more than 90% positive responses, although not all students like to play games in their spare time for entertainment purposes. In the learning experience domain, the immediate feedback given after each quiz session helped the students understand the subject matters (98.3%) and agreed that serious games can be implemented as a complementary learning method. They suggested the serious games approach is not only used for learning oral histology but for other learning materials (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p>
                <p id="Par29">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab3">
                    <label>Table 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Student Perception of Serious Games as Complementary Learning of Oral Histology</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Statements</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4">N (%)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Mean Preference ± SD</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">Strongly Disagree</th>
                          <th align="left">Disagree</th>
                          <th align="left">Agree</th>
                          <th align="left">Strongly Agree</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5">A. Learning Content Domain</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="4">1.676 ± 0.626</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">1. Histologic images was clear</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (1.4%)</td>
                          <td align="left">38 (51%)</td>
                          <td align="left">35 (47.6%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">2. Educational content in the game has been studied before</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (1.4%)</td>
                          <td align="left">13 (17.6%)</td>
                          <td align="left">50 (67.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">10 (13.5%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">3. The questions in the games helped me understand the practicum learning material</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">2 (2.7%)</td>
                          <td align="left">27 (36.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">45 (60.8%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5">B. HistoRM Games Domain</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="2">1.662 ± 0.625</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">4. Gameplay was fun</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">6 (9%)</td>
                          <td align="left">36 (49%)</td>
                          <td align="left">31 (42%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">5. Gameplay was easy</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (1,4%)</td>
                          <td align="left">6 (9%)</td>
                          <td align="left">42 (57%)</td>
                          <td align="left">25 (32,6%)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">6. Game design is good (including visual elements such as images, illustration, animation, colors, and layout)</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">37 (50%)</td>
                          <td align="left">37 (50%)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">7. Text for questions and instructions were clear (size and number of text)</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (1.4%)</td>
                          <td align="left">35 (47.6%)</td>
                          <td align="left">38 (51%)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">8. Language use was easily understandable</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">34 (46.2%)</td>
                          <td align="left">39 (53.8%)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5">C. Learning experience Domain</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="4">1.601 ± 0.620</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">9. The feedback helped me understand the practicum learning material</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">2 (2.7%)</td>
                          <td align="left">29 (40.3%)</td>
                          <td align="left">42 (57%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">10. Games based learning method can be developed as a complementary learning method</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (1.4%)</td>
                          <td align="left">3 (4.8%)</td>
                          <td align="left">35 (47.6%)</td>
                          <td align="left">34 (46.2%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">11. I have a hobby of playing electronic games for entertainment purpose</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">23 (31.6%)</td>
                          <td align="left">32 (43.7%)</td>
                          <td align="left">18 (24.7%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">12. The games help me to recall the previously learned subject materials</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">1 (1,4%)</td>
                          <td align="left">27 (36,5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">46 (62,1%)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">13. Serious games as learning strategy helped me to understand learning materials of oral histology</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">3 (4,8%)</td>
                          <td align="left">27 (36,5%)</td>
                          <td align="left">43 (58,7%)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">14. The allocated time to play the games was sufficient</td>
                          <td align="left">0 (0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">9 (12.2%)</td>
                          <td align="left">38 (51.0%)</td>
                          <td align="left">27 (36.8%)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par30">The present study was conducted to evaluate new learning strategies for interactive learning environments with asynchronous settings in dental education, in particular, the study of oral histology. The results of this study showed <italic>HistoRM</italic> as complementary learning of oral histology could improve students’ understanding of the content of knowledge acquisition, increase student interest to learn dental basic science and increase their learning motivation. The data demonstrated <italic>HistoRM</italic> game significantly improved students cognitive skills of oral histology compared to practicum handouts script-based group. The improvement was related to the duration to play the <italic>HistoRM</italic> and the number of missions completed. Student perception toward <italic>HistoRM</italic> game to increase their understanding of the microscopic structure of oral tissues was positive. They acknowledged the <italic>HistoRM</italic> game provided a more interesting learning environment. The data was in agreement with other studies on serious games in various health sciences that demonstrated an increase in learning satisfaction and positive attitude of students who use serious games as a learning medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The improvement in cognitive skills can be attributed to several game characteristics that encourage learning and changes in attitude and behavior, such as the presence of goal setting, decision making, problem solving, social rewards, and the use of stories in games that incorporated the concept of behavior change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Moreover, strong engagement in learning has been reported related to academic achievement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par31">The main consideration for combining games with education is the ability of games to provide high motivation and potentially make the learning process easier, especially for the learning subjects that students perceive as less interesting. Serious games are different from traditional learning and are considered to provide a more interactive learning environment, support increased motivation, and safe training for students [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. This occurs because of the different characteristics between conventional learning and games. Conventional learning emphasizes the transmission of information and memory. Meanwhile, games confront players with engaging problems and offer ways to explore the problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In this way, players have the opportunity to develop a higher level of learning such as analysis and evaluation. Analysis of serious games explains how student competence can be increased with formative feedback until the game is over [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In <italic>HistoRM</italic>, we provided direct feedback, to allow students to identify the results, to recognize mistakes based on previous experiences and reconsider strategies to complete the game. Students can improve their competence from the feedback provided by the game system to complete the games. Immediate feedback on serious games encourages users to learn from experience and is perceived by students as one of the strong features in the <italic>HistoRM</italic>.</p>
              <p id="Par32">The application of challenges in serious games can make learning activities more interesting and motivate students to complete the games. However, there must be a balance between the challenge and the student’s ability. If the challenge is too difficult to complete, the students could lose motivation to complete the game [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. On the other hand, if the game is too simple, students may be bored and stop playing the game as well. This argument could be explained by the flow theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Good game design creates appealing experiences for players that integrate the engagement with educational effectiveness. In <italic>HistoRM</italic>, the game tasks were designed to be challenging, however we provided a hint feature that became available when students could not complete the mission at the designated time frame. In the process of solving challenges, the learning process occurs when students build their own concepts when they fail. Errors or failures in the games could improve the competence and skills of students in completing the games. Furthermore, the entertainment element is also needed to maintain the user’s attention in each game cycle, to avoid users who stop playing before successfully completing the game and do not understand the intended learning outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. An interesting entertainment component is also important and has an impact on knowledge acquisition. The use of video games, interactive music, high-quality graphics, color combinations, animation, and presentation of material is intended to increase visualization, sensations of interactivity, motivation, interest, player involvement in the game cycle and the impact on knowledge acquisition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Game cycle is an iterative learning process that involves user assessment, user behavior, and a feedback system which, with repetition or repetition of cycles, can lead to the achievement of learning outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Games need to be created interesting enough so that players are interested and motivated to repeat the game cycle. A game cycle can be triggered by two components, namely a combination of learning content with game characteristics so that students are stimulated to learn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par33">The present study highlights the importance of introducing an innovative learning approach to enhance knowledge acquisition and improve the overall learning environment. However, this study had some limitations. The first limitation of the study was the relatively low response rate of 53.6% of total first year dental students, although students were strongly encouraged to take part in this study, their participation remained voluntary. The number of non-respondents might undermine the power of the study and therefore the potential response bias can not be completely ruled out. The results of the study must be interpreted with caution. Second, the generalizability of the results of the present study was limited by the use of data from a single university with a discrete population of first year dental students. As each dental school may have different conditions that influence the use of serious games in their curriculum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], the results of the study must therefore be interpreted with caution. Further studies are needed to explore serious games as learning approaches in other settings. Third, future cohort studies evaluating the impact of <italic>HistoRM</italic> in knowledge retention are also crucial to measure long-term benefit to the learning method. Finally, as social interactions can have an impact on how students could gain knowledge from game-based learning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], future research should also investigate whether collaborative or competitive approaches could be supportive for the game.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec14" sec-type="conclusion">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="Par34">Based on the results of the present study, it can be concluded that <italic>HistoRM</italic> serious game effectively improved students’ understanding of oral histology learning outcomes and provided more interesting learning experiences. This innovative learning tool can be recommended as a complementary learning strategy of oral histology for dental students.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <sec id="Sec15">
                <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
                <p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p>
                <p>
                  <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
                    <media xlink:href="12903_2023_3286_MOESM1_ESM.mp4">
                      <caption>
                        <p>Supplementary Material 1</p>
                      </caption>
                    </media>
                  </supplementary-material>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2">
                    <media xlink:href="12903_2023_3286_MOESM2_ESM.pdf">
                      <caption>
                        <p>Supplementary Material 2</p>
                      </caption>
                    </media>
                  </supplementary-material>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ICC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par51">Inter correlation coefficient</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>This study was supported by Universitas Indonesia International Publication Grant NKB-610/UN2.RST/HKP.05.00/2022.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>LRA, EI, RP, KS contributed to the conception of the study and supervised ths study. LRA contributed to grant finding. ICL, SND, RY, contributed to data acquisition. LRA, ICL, SND, RY contributed to data analyses. All authors (LRA, ICL, SND, RY, DFS, KS, RP) contributed to the drafting and finalizing of the manuscript. All authors have given final approval of the article.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This study was funded and supported by Universitas Indonesia International Publication Grant NKB-610/UN2.RST/HKP.05.00/2022.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data availability</title>
              <p>All datasets used and analyzed in this study will be available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar2">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par49">Ethical approval was obtained from Dental Research Ethics Committee Universitas Indonesia and this study was conducted in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration (87/ethical approval/FKGUI/X/2022). Students participated voluntarily in the study following the official invitation. The name and other personal information of the study participants were protected. Students were informed about the study and informed consent was obtained from all the participants and/or their LAR.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar3">
                <title>Consent for publication</title>
                <p id="Par50">N/A.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par48">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Felszeghy</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pasonen-Seppänen</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koskela</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nieminen</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Härkönen</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paldanius</surname>
                      <given-names>KMA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gabbouj</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ketola</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lundin</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haapaniemi</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sointu</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bauman</surname>
                      <given-names>EB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gilbert</surname>
                      <given-names>GE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morton</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahonen</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using online game-based platforms to improve student performance and engagement in histology teaching</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Med Educ</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12909-019-1701-0</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teshome</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Attitude and perception of medical students towards histology subject at Wollo University, Ethiopia</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Med Educ Pract</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>1913</volume>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/AMEP.S359703</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qasim</surname>
                      <given-names>WF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Khafaji</surname>
                      <given-names>LK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alhamdani</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>E-Learning attitude in Dental Class between oral histology and embryology (comparative study)</article-title>
                  <source>Pakistan J Med Health Sci</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>1299</fpage>
                  <lpage>302</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janssen</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaw</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodyear</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kerfoot</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bryce</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A little healthy competition: using mixed methods to pilot a team-based digital game for boosting medical student engagement with anatomy and histology content</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Med Educ</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12909-015-0455-6</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiang</surname>
                      <given-names>CP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of virtual microscopy and real microscopy for learning oral histology laboratory course among dental students</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Sci</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>1201</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jds.2022.04.008</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 35784135?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35784135</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnson</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Purkiss</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holaday</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Selvig</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hortsch</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Learning histology - dental and medical students’ study strategies</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Dent Educ</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <lpage>73</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eje.12104</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24809952?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24809952</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wheeler</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ewers</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buonanno</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Different rates of forgetting following study versus test trials</article-title>
                  <source>Memory</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>571</fpage>
                  <lpage>80</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09658210244000414</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 14982124?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14982124</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortright</surname>
                      <given-names>RN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lujan</surname>
                      <given-names>HL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blumberg</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cox</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>DiCarlo</surname>
                      <given-names>SE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Higher levels of intrinsic motivation are related to higher levels of class performance for male but not female students</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Physiol Educ</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/advan.00018.2013</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24022768?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24022768</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bauman</surname>
                      <given-names>EB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Games</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Virtual environments, Mobile Applications and a futurist’s crystal ball</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Simul Nurs</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <lpage>14</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecns.2016.02.002</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Gaalen</surname>
                      <given-names>AEJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brouwer</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schönrock-Adema</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bouwkamp-Timmer</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jaarsma</surname>
                      <given-names>ADC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Georgiadis</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gamification of health professions education: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>683</fpage>
                  <lpage>711</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10459-020-10000-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33128662?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33128662</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qian</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clark</surname>
                      <given-names>KR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Game-based learning and 21st century skills: a review of recent research</article-title>
                  <source>Comput Hum Behav</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>63</volume>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2016.05.023</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gorbanev</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Agudelo-Londoño</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>González</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortes</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pomares</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Delgadillo</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yepes</surname>
                      <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muñoz</surname>
                      <given-names>Ó</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A systematic review of serious games in medical education: quality of evidence and pedagogical strategy</article-title>
                  <source>Med Educ Online</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1438718</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10872981.2018.1438718</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29457760?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29457760</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Krath J, Schürmann L, von Korflesch HFO. Revealing the theoretical basis of gamification: a systematic review and analysis of theory in research on gamification, serious games and game-based learning. Comput Hum Behav 2021;125,106963, ISSN 0747 – 563.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sipiyaruk</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gallagher</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hatzipanagos</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A rapid review of serious games: from healthcare education to dental education</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Dent Educ</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <lpage>57</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eje.12338</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29573165?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29573165</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sipiyaruk</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hatzipanagos</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gallagher</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Serious Games and the COVID-19 pandemic in Dental Education: an integrative review of the literature</article-title>
                  <source>Comput</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/computers10040042</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sailer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Homner</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The gamification of learning: a Meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Educ Psychol Rev</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <lpage>112</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10648-019-09498-w</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nieto-Escamez</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roldán-Tapia</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gamification as Online Teaching Strategy during COVID-19: a Mini-Review</article-title>
                  <source>Front Psychol</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <fpage>648552</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.648552</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alharbi</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alazmi</surname>
                      <given-names>KF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Momani</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Muzian</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wertheimer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almukhtar</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almuzian</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Phone-based audience response system as an adjunct in orthodontic teaching of undergraduate dental students: a cross-over randomised controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Med Educ</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>435</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12909-020-02363-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33198761?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33198761</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lang</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Willuth</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haney</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Felinska</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wennberg</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kowalewski</surname>
                      <given-names>KF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                      <given-names>MW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wagner</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Müller-Stich</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nickel</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Serious gaming and virtual reality in the multimodal training of laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair: a randomized crossover study</article-title>
                  <source>Surg Endosc</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>2050</fpage>
                  <lpage>61</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00464-022-09733-6</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 36289083?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36289083</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schulz</surname>
                      <given-names>KF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Altman</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moher</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <collab>CONSORT Group</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>CONSORT 2010 statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>c332</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.c332</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kang</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sample size determination and power analysis using the G*Power software</article-title>
                  <source>J Educ Eval Health Prof</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3352/jeehp.2021.18.17</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34325496?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34325496</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Orsini</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Binnie</surname>
                      <given-names>VI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tricio</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Motivational profiles and their relationships with basic psychological needs, academic performance, study strategies, self-esteem, and vitality in dental students in Chile</article-title>
                  <source>J Educ Eval Health Prof</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>1120</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smiderle</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rigo</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marques</surname>
                      <given-names>LB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of gamification on students’ learning, engagement and behavior based on their personality traits</article-title>
                  <source>Smart Learn Environ</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40561-019-0098-x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Welbers</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Konijn</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burgers</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Vaate</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eden</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brugman</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gamification as a tool for engaging student learning: a field experiment with a gamified app</article-title>
                  <source>E-Learn Digit Media</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <lpage>109</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2042753018818342</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diehl</surname>
                      <given-names>LA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gordan</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Esteves</surname>
                      <given-names>RZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coelho</surname>
                      <given-names>IC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>InsuOnline, an electronic game for Medical Education on insulin therapy: a Randomized Controlled Trial with Primary Care Physicians</article-title>
                  <source>J Med Internet Res</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>e72</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.6944</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boeker</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andel</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vach</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frankenschmidt</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Game-based e-learning is more effective than a conventional instructional method: a randomized controlled trial with third-year medical students</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>e82328</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082328</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moro</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Phelps</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stromberga</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Utilizing serious games for physiology and anatomy learning and revision</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Physiol Educ</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>505</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/advan.00074.2020</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Du</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>CY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Development and questionnaire-based evaluation of virtual dental clinic: a serious game for training dental students</article-title>
                  <source>Med Educ Online</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1983927</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10872981.2021.1983927</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34694980?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34694980</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arayapisit T, Pojmonpiti D, Dansirisomboon K, Jitverananrangsri K, Poosontipong D, Sipiyaruk K. An educational board game for learning orofacial spaces: an experimental study comparing collaborative and competitive approaches. Anat Sci Educ 2023;25.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sipiyaruk</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hatzipanagos</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vichayanrat</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gallagher</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluating a Dental Public-Health game across two learning contexts</article-title>
                  <source>Educ Sci</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>517</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/educsci12080517</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sipiyaruk K, Hatzipanagos S, Gallagher JE, Reynolds PA. Knowledge Improvement of Dental Students in Thailand and UK Through an Online Serious Game in Dental Public Health. In: Vaz de Carvalho C, Escudeiro P, Coelho A, editors. Serious Games, Interaction, and Simulation: 5th International Conference, SGAMES 2015, Novedrate, Italy, September 16–18, 2015, Revised Selected Papers. Cham: Springer International Publishing, p 80–85.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kapralos</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fisher</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clarkson</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Oostveen</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A course on serious game design and development using an online problem-based learning approach</article-title>
                  <source>Interact Technol Smart Educ</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/ITSE-10-2014-0033</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vlachopoulos</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Makri</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of games and simulations on higher education: a systematic literature review</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Educ Technol High Educ</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41239-017-0062-1</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borit</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stangvaltaite-Mouhat</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>GoDental! Enhancing flipped classroom experience with game-based learning</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Dent Educ</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>763</fpage>
                  <lpage>72</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eje.12566</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32648661?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32648661</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Udeozor</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russo Abegão</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Glassey</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An evaluation of the relationship between perceptions and performance of students in a serious game</article-title>
                  <source>J Educ Comput Res</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>322</fpage>
                  <lpage>51</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/07356331211036989</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Francesco Bellotti B, Kapralos K, Lee P, Moreno-Ger R, Berta. “Assessment in and of Serious Games: An Overview”, Adv Hum Comput Interact 2013;Article ID 136864.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Csikszentmihalyi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Flow: the psychology of optimal performance</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>HarperCollins Publishers</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arias-Calderón</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castro</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gayol</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Serious Games as a method for enhancing Learning Engagement: Student Perception on Online Higher Education during COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Front Psychol</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>889975</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.889975</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
