<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:39:36Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9132504" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9132504</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-04-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jips</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Indian Prosthodont Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Indian Prosthodont Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIPS</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>The Journal of the Indian Prosthodontic Society</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0972-4052</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1998-4057</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer - Medknow</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9132504</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9132504</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9132504</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36511030</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JIPS-22-188</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jips.jips_228_21</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Comparative evaluation of effect of microcurrent electrical stimulation on acupoints to control gag reflex in patients receiving prosthodontic treatment: An <italic>in vivo</italic> study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Agrawal</surname>
                    <given-names>Shanvi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kambala</surname>
                    <given-names>Seema Sathe</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Borle</surname>
                    <given-names>Anjali Bhoyar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Balwani</surname>
                    <given-names>Tanvi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1">Department of Prosthodontics and Crown and Bridge, Sharad Pawar Dental College and Hospital, DMIMS (DU), Wardha, Maharashtra, India</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Shanvi Agrawal, Department of Prosthodontics and Crown and Bridge, Sharad Pawar Dental College and Hospital, DMIMS (DU), Sawangi (Meghe), Wardha, Maharashtra, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="ag.shanvi95@gmail.com">ag.shanvi95@gmail.com</email>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Apr-Jun</season>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>13</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>22</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <fpage>188</fpage>
              <lpage>194</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2022 The Journal of Indian Prosthodontic Society</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="st1">
                  <title>Aims:</title>
                  <p>The aim of this study is to see if microcurrent electrical stimulation on two acupoints, auricular and Hegus, can help patients prevent their gag reflex.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st2">
                  <title>Settings and Design:</title>
                  <p>This was an <italic>in vivo</italic> cross-sectional study.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st3">
                  <title>Materials and Methods:</title>
                  <p>Thirty patients were randomly assigned to three groups: A, B, or C, of ten patients present in each group. Group A and Group B undergone electroacupuncture (microcurrent electrical stimulation) using electroacupuncture device on auricular point and Hegus point (Li 4), respectively, for 1 min and Group C formed the placebo group, point Shou San Li (Li 10). The gag severity index and the gag prevention index were used to measure the gag reflex, which was done in two steps.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st4">
                  <title>Statistical Analysis Used:</title>
                  <p>SPSS (SPSS Inc., Chicago IL, USA) version 24 software was used for statistical analysis. Paired <italic>t</italic>-test, one-way analysis of variance test, <italic>post hoc</italic> Bonferroni test was used to analyse and compare the data.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st5">
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>It was found that Point A and Point B were significantly effective in reducing the severity of gag reflex. Point C demonstrated insignificant results. In addition, Point B (Hegus [Li4]) is more effective than Point A (auricular) in controlling the gag reflex in patients within the set age group of 20–70 years of age.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st6">
                  <title>Conclusions:</title>
                  <p>Microcurrent electrical stimulation is a useful adjuvant in the treatment of unfavorable gag reflexes during routine dental procedures. Point Hegus and point auricular acupuncture are both useful in decreasing the severity of gag reflex, with point Hegus being more effective than point auricular.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Alginate impression</kwd>
                <kwd>electroacupuncture device</kwd>
                <kwd>gag reflex</kwd>
                <kwd>gagging prevention index</kwd>
                <kwd>gagging severity index</kwd>
                <kwd>microcurrent electrical stimulation</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>The gag reflex is a defensive and physiological system that protects the pharynx, larynx, and trachea from invading noxious stimuli or foreign objects. It is most commonly seen in the practice of dentistry during various dental procedures which can be debilitating, leading to an avoidance behavior and eventually compromising the quality of the treatment.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p>
              <p>Gagging may be caused by either somatic or psychological factors. Somatic gagging can occur due to the stimulation of the trigger zones around the oropharynx and psychogenic gagging can occur due to any thought, smell, sound, or sight.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p>
              <p>Different methods to prevent gag reflex involve relaxation, desensitization, distraction, pharmacological, and psychological techniques as well as other complementary medicine therapies including acupuncture as well as acupressure.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p>
              <p>Mild gagging can be easily managed with simple chairside techniques (applying topical anesthetics drugs, table salt, nitrous oxide, and distracting the patient during treatment), but severe gagging can be triggered by any contact with an instrument or previous dental experience, resulting in a compromise in treatment quality and ultimately affecting the treatment outcome.</p>
              <p>Gagging is an area of dental study that has yet to be investigated. A hyperactive gag reflex can make dental treatments difficult, such as a simple examination, or even complex procedures such as impressions for crowns and bridges, leaving the patient unwilling to accept complex clinical procedures.</p>
              <p>Acupuncture is a modality well explained in the literature for the prevention of gag reflex. It involves the application of needle, vacuum, pressure, electrical, or laser stimulus to specific parts/points on the human body for the prevention of disease, as a therapy or for the maintenance of health.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p>
              <p>According to traditional Chinese medicine, energy flows along 14 meridians present in the human body, on which certain energy points lies, which when stimulated produces specific effects on the human body.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</p>
              <p>Electroacupuncture has a definitive role in dentistry, but it is not a substitute for conventional treatments. Controlling this hyperactive reflex will make it easier to provide care.</p>
              <p>The overall benefits of an acupuncture-based approach include reduced emetic response, increased patient comfort during dental treatment, and decreased patient/doctor stress, all of which improve treatment success.</p>
              <p>The external acoustic meatus's skin and the region adjacent to the auricle correspond to the anti-gagging point present on the ear, i.e., auricular point.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] The second metacarpal's radial palmar side has a point termed Hegus (LI4), which runs between the adductor pollicis and the first dorsal interosseus muscle.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] It is possible that stimulating this anti-gagging acupuncture point will prevent the musculature from contracting, thus inhibiting the gag reflex.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p>
              <p>There are several researches which suggest that acupuncture on auricular point is helpful in preventing severe gag reflex, while some suggest similar results in regard to Hegus point.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p>
              <p>Therefore, the impact of microcurrent electrical stimulation, a variant of electroacupuncture, which induces low-frequency electrical stimulation of skin sensory receptors, using a meridian acupuncture pen on two acupoints to regulate gag reflex in patients was investigated in this research.</p>
              <sec id="sec2-1">
                <title>Aim of the study</title>
                <p>This study aimed to evaluate the effect of microcurrent electrical stimulation on two acupoints, auricular and Hegus to control the gag reflex among the patients receiving prosthodontic treatment.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-2">
                <title>Objectives of the study are</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="order">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>To evaluate the effect of microcurrent electrical stimulation on auricular point to control gag reflex in patients</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>To evaluate the effect of microcurrent electrical stimulation on Hegus point to control gag reflex in patients</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>To evaluate whether there is an effect of microcurrent electrical stimulation on placebo acupoint (Shou San Li) that is not documented to control gag reflex</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>To compare if there exists any difference in control of gag reflex among patient who receive microcurrent electrical stimulation at documented acupoints and placebo group.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2">
              <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
              <p>The research was a 6-month cross-sectional study that began in October 2019–March 2020 after receiving approval from the institutional review board. Ethical committee number- DMIMS(DU)/IEC/Sept-2019/8434.</p>
              <p>A total of 30 patients of age 20–70 years were included in the study.</p>
              <sec id="sec2-3">
                <title>Inclusion criteria</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="roman-upper">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>A maxillary alginate impression is needed for current dental care (edentulous/partially dentulous/dentulous)</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>According to the gagging severity index (GSI), patients with moderate (Grade III) to very severe gagging (Grade V)</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Patients who have had a history of gag reflex during the dental impressions procedure</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>The individual who is capable of giving informed consent.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-4">
                <title>Exclusion criteria</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="roman-upper">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Subjects with systemic disorders and comorbidities affecting psychomotor function</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Patients who were aware of electroacupuncture as a modality to control gag reflex were also excluded</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Antiemetic drugs or medications were taken by the patients</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Various precautions undertaken to reduce gagging involved consistency (not too thin), position of chair (upright), as well as patients were instructed not to eat for the duration of 2 h before the appointment.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-5">
                <title>Equipments used in the study</title>
                <p>Equipment used in the study was electroacupuncture device (meridian acupuncture pen [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>] ).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Electroacupuncture device (meridian acupuncture pen)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-188-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-6">
                <title>About the meridian acupuncture pen</title>
                <p>Depending on the various areas of application, the electric acupuncture instrument comes with two distinct heads. Sensitivity, intensity, and frequency controls are all customizable as well as it helps in the auto-detection of meridian energy points. It features nine different intensity settings that can be changed according to your needs, and it automatically switches off to prevent overheating and save energy. There is no skin piercing. It is easy to use and transport. There are no adverse effects, and it is completely safe. Both traditional Chinese medicine and western science support the efficacy of the therapy.</p>
                <p>Device details-</p>
                <p>Size of the device: 15 cm × 10 cm × 8 cm</p>
                <p>Use with: Massage Gel (shock absorber)</p>
                <p>Battery: 1 × AA battery</p>
                <p>Output: 3.7V 300 Ma ±/50 mA</p>
                <p>Pulse frequency: 0.01–300 Hz</p>
                <p>Pulse width: 100 us–320 us.</p>
                <p>Two massage gels – ultrasound gel and biofreeze gel were applied before use to lubricate the skin and increase comfort.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-7">
                <title>Data collection tools</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="roman-upper">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>GSI[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>]</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Gagging prevention index (GPI)[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>].</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Gagging severity index</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">The GSI[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">The gagging reflex is:</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very mild, occasional and controlled by the patient</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild, and control is required by the patient with reassurance from the dental team</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate, consistent and limits treatment options</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe and treatment is limited</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very severe, affecting patient behaviour &amp; dental attendance and making treatment impossible</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>GSI: Gagging severity index</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Gagging preventive index</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">The GPI[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment management method employed</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obtunded gag reflex; treatment successful</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partially controlled gag reflex; all treatment possible</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partially controlled gag reflex but frequent gagging; simple treatment possible</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inadequately controlled gag reflex; simple treatment unable to be completed</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gag reflex severe; no treatment possible</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>GPI: Gagging preventive index</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-8">
                <title>Location of acupoints</title>
                <p>Point A: The auricular point on the ear refers to the external acoustic meatus's skin and the region adjacent to the auricle [Figures <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>].</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Auricular point</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-188-g002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F3">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Auricular point (clinical depiction)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-188-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Point B: The second metacarpal's radial palmar side has a LI4, which runs between the adductor pollicis and the first dorsal interosseus muscles [Figures <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>].</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F4">
                  <label>Figure 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Hegus point</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-188-g004" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F5">
                  <label>Figure 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Hegus point (clinical depiction)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-188-g005" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Point C: The placebo group, Shou San Li (Li 10), location of acupoint is on the outer surface of the forearm, three-finger space distal to elbow crease when the elbow is bent 90° [Figures <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>].</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F6">
                  <label>Figure 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Shou San Li point (placebo)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-188-g006" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F7">
                  <label>Figure 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Shou San Li point (placebo) (clinical depiction)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-188-g007" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-9">
                <title>Methodology</title>
                <p>A thorough case history, examination, diagnosis was carried out for the patients reporting to the outpatient department. Before being included in the study, all participants received information about it and signed a written informed consent document.</p>
                <p>Patients were randomly assigned to one of three groups: A, B, or C. There were a total of ten patients present in each group within a range of 20–70 years of age. Group A and Group B underwent microcurrent electrical stimulation using meridian acupuncture pen on auricular point and L4, respectively, for 1 min and Group C formed the placebo group with Li 10 point to eliminate the bias. The placebo point served the purpose of blinding the subject and also the observant. The observer was independent of the study group without having any knowledge about the study acupoints and single observers recorded the observations to eliminate the observer bias.</p>
                <p>The GSI and the GPI were used to measure the gag reflex, which was done in two steps. Before the application of microcurrent electrical stimulation, the gag reflex severity was determined using the GSI for each treatment group. The GPI was used to evaluate the microcurrent electrical stimulation efficacy after the procedure. In Stage I, the patient's tolerance for an empty tray[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] being placed intraorally was assessed, in which GSI was taken, while in Stage II, the patient's tolerance for a loaded tray being placed intraorally was assessed, in which GPI was taken. Impressions were made during the microcurrent electrical stimulation. The empty tray was used to assess the severity of gag index in place of any other instrument such as mouth mirror or finger with the purpose that if the severity of gag is more while placing an empty tray, it will definitely be much more when it will be loaded. Hence, the necessary prevention will be required after loading the tray.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-10">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>Three groups (10 patients in each group divided randomly):</p>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="order">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Participants receiving microcurrent electrical stimulation on Hegus point</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Participants receiving microcurrent electrical stimulation on auricular point</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Participants receiving microcurrent electrical stimulation on Shou San Li point which is not documented to reduce gag reflex (placebo).</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-11">
                <title>Statistical analysis of observations</title>
                <p>Statistical analysis was done using the SPSS (SPSS Inc., Chicago IL, USA) version 24 software. To determine the scores of GSI and GPI, Paired <italic>t</italic>-test was used. Intergroup comparison was done by one-way analysis of variance test. Intragroup comparisons were assessed by <italic>post hoc</italic> Bonferroni test and <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was taken as a standard level of significance.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>From the above statistical analysis, it was observed that <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 is the level of significance. Out of the 30 subjects, the results were tabulated for preapplication and postapplication of acupuncture at the respective points [Tables <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>-<xref rid="T10" ref-type="table">10</xref>]. It was found that Point A and Point B were significantly effective in reducing the severity of GR. Point C demonstrated insignificant results. In addition, Point B – Hegus (Li4) – is more effective than Point A – auricular in controlling the GR in patients within the set age group of 20–70 years of age.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Results-gagging severity index and gagging preventive index (Hegus)</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>n</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>t</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSI</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.69</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPI</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>=0.0001 (S)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>GPI: Gagging preventive index, GSI: Gagging severity index, SEM: Standard error mean, SD: Standard deviation, S: Significant</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Results-gagging severity index and gagging preventive index (auricular)</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>n</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>t</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSI</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.58</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPI</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>=0.0001 (S)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>GPI: Gagging preventive index, GSI: Gagging severity index, SEM: Standard error mean, SD: Standard deviation, S: Significant</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T5">
                <label>Table 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Results-gagging severity index and gagging preventive index (placebo)</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>n</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>t</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSI</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPI</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>=0.16 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>GPI: Gagging preventive index, GSI: Gagging severity index, SEM: Standard error mean, SD: Standard deviation, NS: Not significant</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T6">
                <label>Table 6</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Comparison of gagging severity index score in three groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Group</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                        <italic>n</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">SE</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI for mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                        <italic>F</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower value</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hegus</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auricular</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>=0.56 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.76</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>SD: Standard deviation, NS: Not significant, SE: Standard error, CI: Confidence interval</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T7">
                <label>Table 7</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Gagging severity index-bonferroni multiple comparison test</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Group</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Mean difference (I-J)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">SE</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                        <italic>P</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower value</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hegus</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Auricular</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000(NS)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.82</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Placebo</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000 (NS)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.52</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auricular</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Placebo</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901 (NS)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>NS: Not significant, SE: Standard error, CI: Confidence interval</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T8">
                <label>Table 8</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Comparison of GPI score in three groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Group</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                        <italic>n</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">SE</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI for mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                        <italic>F</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower value</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hegus</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.82</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auricular</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>=0.0001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(S)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>S: Significant, SE: Standard error, CI: Confidence interval, SD: Standard deviation</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T9">
                <label>Table 9</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Gagging preventive index-bonferroni multiple comparison test</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Group</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Mean difference(I-J)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">SE</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                        <italic>P</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower value</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hegus</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Auricular</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038 (S)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.17</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Placebo</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001 (S)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.57</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.42</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auricular</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Placebo</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.40</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001 (S)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.97</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.82</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>S: Significant, SE: Standard error, CI: Confidence interval</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T10">
                <label>Table 10</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Percentage of improvement amongst all the three groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of improvement</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hegus</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.66</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auricular</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.35</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.88</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Acupuncture can be used as an adjunct therapy or as an appropriate substitute for a variety of medical conditions, and it can be incorporated into a comprehensive management program (National Institutes of Health, 1997). The gag reflex is triggered when trigger zones in the posterior region of the oral cavity, which are innervated by the glossopharyngeal nerve, are activated. Acupuncture activates muscular myelinated nerve fibers, which deliver impulses to the spinal cord and then activate the midbrain and pituitary–hypothalamus.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Enkephalin, beta-endorphin, serotonin, dynorphin, and noradrenalin have all been found to be involved in the process.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] The activation of acupoints such as Hegus and auricular causes impulses to flow to the nucleus of the raphe magnus in the midbrain, which is the brain's primary source of serotonin (5-HT). This is converted to beta-endorphin, which has anti-emetic properties. As a result, when acupoints are activated, the serotonin pathway is triggered, releasing 5-HT, which helps to suppress the gag reflex.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</p>
              <p>Several studies were conducted in the literature for the prevention of gag reflex among patients.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] In a study of 48 patients, Sivinagini V used acupuncture and acupressure to avoid gag reflexes and discovered that the Hegus point (LI4) is successful in regulating the gag reflex.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Another research, conducted on ten patients by Hashim <italic>et al</italic>., found that ear acupuncture on the auricular point is effective in the management of the gag reflex.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Fiske G in his study conducted on 10 subjects for the prevention of gag reflex using acupuncture in the auricular point concluded the ear acupuncture to be effective in its management.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p>
              <p>Microcurrent electrical stimulation, a form of electroacupuncture, induces low-frequency electrical stimulation of skin sensory receptors, which causes the hypothalamus to release endorphins. Compelling literature exists to support the use of microcurrent electrical stimulation in various other human applications.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] In a meta-analysis comparing microcurrent electrical stimulation, laser acupuncture, acupressure, and acupuncture, it was found that microcurrent electrical stimulation has a greater effect in prevention of the gag reflex.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] Furthermore, according to a research conducted by Ulett GA <italic>et al</italic>., in 1998, electroacupuncture was found to be more efficient than manual acupuncture.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</p>
              <p>The impact of microcurrent electrical stimulation on two acupoints to regulate gag reflex in patients was investigated in this research. The two acupoints which were chosen are auricular and Hegus points. A third point was also included Shou San Li (Li 10) (placebo), to eliminate the bias. This placebo point served the purpose of blinding the subject and also the observant. The chosen placebo point is used to treat anxiety in traditional Chinese medicine. To test the efficacy of microcurrent electrical stimulation on a point that does not have any anti-gag reflex action, the placebo point was chosen differently from the acupuncture points Hegus and auricular.</p>
              <p>In this research, a meridian acupuncture pen was used for the application of microcurrent electrical stimulation. It is a dual-purpose handheld device which is battery operated, provided with a gel which act as a shock absorber. It provides painless stimulation without any piercing of skin.</p>
              <p>The results of this study showed that there was a statistically significant reduction in the gag reflex among patients after the microcurrent electrical stimulation was applied on the points Hegus and auricular. There was no significant reduction in the gag reflex in the placebo group of patients after receiving the microcurrent electrical stimulation. In addition, point Hegus was proved to be more effective than point auricular in the reduction of gag reflex.</p>
              <p>Other studies concerning other methods for the prevention of gag reflex such as laser acupuncture or needle acupuncture has its own disadvantages such as pain at the respective sites, vertigo, or drop of blood pressure if the vessel is close to the site.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] But in this study, none of the above disadvantages were observed.</p>
              <p>This research aids to the knowledge that an easily available device like a meridian acupuncture pen can be easily used in daily clinical practice for the application of microcurrent electrical stimulation on two easily identifiable points over the body aiding in the reduction of troublesome gag reflex.</p>
              <sec id="sec2-12">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>Several other anti-gag points have been documented in the literature that were not taken into consideration in this study, and their effectiveness remains unknown.</p>
                <p>Gender predilection was not taken into account in this study.</p>
                <p>Microcurrent electrical stimulation has not been compared to other management techniques for reducing gag reflexes.</p>
                <p>Long-term investigations will provide more substantial results.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>As per the results of this study, it is recommended that microcurrent electrical stimulation is a useful adjuvant in managing unfavorable gag reflexes during conventional dental procedures. The effectiveness of microcurrent electrical stimulation at point Hegus and point auricular in decreasing the severity of gag reflex has been demonstrated in this study, with point Hegus being more effective than point auricular. The procedure is safe, rapid, low cost, and noninvasive. As a result, it appears as a novel method of controlling gag reflex in patients receiving the prosthodontic treatment.</p>
              <sec id="sec2-13">
                <title>Declaration of patient consent</title>
                <p>The authors certify that they have obtained all appropriate patient consent forms. In the form the patient (s) has/have given his/her/their consent for his/her/their images and other clinical information to be reported in the journal. The patients understand that their names and initial s will not be published and due efforts will be made to conceal their identity, but anonymity cannot be guaranteed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-14">
                <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
                <p>Nil.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec2-15">
                <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
                <p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="ref1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eitner</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wichmann</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holst</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>“Hypnopuncture” – A dental-emergency treatment concept for patients with a distinctive gag reflex</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Clin Exp Hypn</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>53</volume>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <lpage>73</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15788244</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fiske</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dickinson</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of acupuncture in controlling the gagging reflex using a review of ten cases</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dent J</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>190</volume>
                  <fpage>611</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11441900</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dickinson</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fiske</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A review of gagging problems in dentistry: 2. Clinical assessment and management</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Update</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15819150</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pol</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katge</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krishna</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poojari</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Balgi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shetty</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of laser stimulation (Electro-acupuncture) in alginate impression making for patients with a gag reflex</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Assoc Thai</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>67</volume>
                  <fpage>4</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abhimanyu</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohit</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamlesh</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ankita</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Acupuncture therapy in orthodontics – A review</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Dent Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <fpage>555586</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adyanthaya</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prathyusha</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sidharth</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thusha</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The point of a hundred diseases, acupuncture for gag reflex in children – A review</article-title>
                  <source>Paripex Indian J Res</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ernst</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>White</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Acupuncture as a treatment for temporomandibular joint dysfunction: A systematic review of randomized trials</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>125</volume>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <lpage>72</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10190797</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sivinagini</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jain Ashish</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Role of acupuncture and acupressure in preventing gag reflex</article-title>
                  <source>Drug Invent Today</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dickinson</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gagging problems in dental patients: literature review for the diploma in dental sedation</article-title>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>GKT Dental Institute of King's College</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anand</surname>
                      <given-names>MV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rai</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bettie</surname>
                      <given-names>NF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramachandiran</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Solomon</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Praveena</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Acupuncture – An effective tool in the management of gag reflex</article-title>
                  <source>J Pharm Bioallied Sci</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>S677</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26538942</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daneshkazemi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daneshkazemi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davoudi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Badrian</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Firouzabadi</surname>
                      <given-names>VP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is acupuncturing effective in controlling the gag reflex during dental procedures. A review of literature?</article-title>
                  <source>Anesth Essays Res</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27212742</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dundee</surname>
                      <given-names>JW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McMillan</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>P6 acupressure and postoperative vomiting</article-title>
                  <source>Br J Anaesth</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1540472</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hashim</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaltoni</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamal</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khanfar</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of acupuncture in the treatment of prosthodontic patients with a gagging reflex</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Gen Dent</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <lpage>21</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Armstrong</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gokal</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chevalier</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Todorsky</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lim</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microcurrent point stimulation applied to lower back acupuncture points for the treatment of nonspecific neck pain</article-title>
                  <source>J Altern Complement Med</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28266863</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheung</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chan</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yip</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microcurrent stimulation at shenmen acupoint facilitates EEG associated with sleepiness and positive mood: A randomized controlled electrophysiological study</article-title>
                  <source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>2015</volume>
                  <fpage>182837</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25767551</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kwon</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>An</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kwak</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Short-term microcurrent electrical neuromuscular stimulation to improve muscle function in the elderly: A randomized, double-blinded, sham-controlled clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <fpage>e7407</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28658177</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Helmrich</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pamela</surname>
                      <given-names>SY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dune</surname>
                      <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Meta-analysis of acustimulation effects on nausea and vomitting in pregnant women</article-title>
                  <source>J Explore</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ulett</surname>
                      <given-names>GA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Han</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Han</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Electroacupuncture: Mechanisms and clinical application</article-title>
                  <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <lpage>38</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9646895</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosted</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Use of acupuncture in dentistry</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9973720</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
