<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:43:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8023368" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8023368</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-09</datestamp>
        <setSpec>eortho</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eortho</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>The European Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0141-5387</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2210</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8023368</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8023368</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8023368</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32133486</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32133486</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjaa010</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cjaa010</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00500</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Comparison of post-treatment changes with and without retention in adolescents treated for maxillary impacted canines—a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Naraghi</surname>
                    <given-names>Sasan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4588-3543</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ganzer</surname>
                    <given-names>Niels</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bondemark</surname>
                    <given-names>Lars</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sonesson</surname>
                    <given-names>Mikael</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
                  <!--<email>mikael.sonesson@mau.se</email>-->
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Orthodontic Clinic, National Health Service</institution>, Växjö, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Orthodontics, University of Malmö</institution>, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label><institution>Orthodontic Clinic, Public Dental Health</institution>, Gävle, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="AF0004"><label>4</label><institution>Centre for Research and Development Uppsala University/Region Gävleborg</institution>, Gävle, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Correspondence to: Mikael Sonesson, Department of Orthodontics, Faculty of Odontology, Malmö University, Carl Gustavs väg 34, SE-205 06 Malmö, Sweden. E-mail: <email>mikael.sonesson@mau.se</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-03-05">
                <day>05</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>05</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
              <volume>43</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <fpage>121</fpage>
              <lpage>127</lpage>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Orthodontic Society </copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="cjaa010.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Summary</title>
                <sec id="s0100">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>To evaluate whether retention is needed after orthodontic treatment of impacted maxillary canines.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0101">
                  <title>Trial design</title>
                  <p>Two-arm parallel group single-centre randomized controlled trial.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0102">
                  <title>Materials and methods</title>
                  <p>Sixty-three patients, 39 girls and 24 boys, were recruited to the study. The inclusion criteria were patients with at least one impacted or unerupted maxillary canine, and moderate irregularity of the maxillary six anterior teeth according to Little’s index (LI). After gaining informed consent from the patient and their custodians, the patients were randomized to one of two groups, i.e. to a non-retention group or a retention group. The randomization process was prepared and carried out by an independent person not involved in the trial and the randomization used blocks of 20 (10 + 10). Primary outcomes were changes in single contact point discrepancy, and LI measured on digitalized three-dimensional study casts 1-year post-treatment. The study casts were anonymized before assessment and the changes were blinded for the assessor. Data were evaluated on an intention-to-treat basis. Thus, all randomized patients were incorporated into the final analysis. In the non-retention group a 10-week interim period was used to detect patients who eventually have a relapse immediately after treatment. If so, the patient got the arch-wire reinserted. Most patients in the retention group received a vacuum-formed retainer and pretreatment spacing cases got a bonded retainer.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0103">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Mean irregularity change was 0.4 mm in the retention and 1.3 mm in the non-retention group (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Maximum change was 2.5 mm in the retention and 3.2 mm in the non-retention group (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Most changes in the non-retention group occurred during the 10-week interim period. In the non-retention group, one patient developed contact point discrepancy of &gt;2 mm during the interim period and was realigned.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0104">
                  <title>Harms</title>
                  <p>One patient met the stopping guideline criteria. This patient had the arch wire reinserted for 2 months. After realignment, the patient received a retention appliance.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0105">
                  <title>Limitations</title>
                  <p>The trial was a single-centre study and short-term changes were evaluated.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0106">
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Changes between the retention and the non-retention group were statistically but not clinically significant. Since satisfactory clinical results 1-year post-treatment were found in the non-retention group, retention does not appear to be needed. The 10-week interim period was useful in detecting patients who might have a relapse immediately after treatment.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0107">
                  <title>Trial registration</title>
                  <p>The trial was not registered.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Public Dental Service</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Department of Research and Development</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Swedish Dental Association</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100005300</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="7"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Aesthetics, and in particular the aesthetics of maxillary anterior teeth, are the primary reason for patients seeking orthodontic treatment (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Therefore, the stability of the maxillary anterior teeth is crucial for both the patients and the orthodontist (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2–5</xref>). Since retention is one of the most challenging problems in orthodontics, every orthodontist has a philosophy, strategy, and strong belief as to how retention should be provided (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). This belief is rarely evidence-based but instead usually based on clinical experience. The dominant opinion is to keep the retention for a very long time and in many cases life-long retention is recommended (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p>
              <p>It has been shown that relapse occurs independently of retention methods. Removable retainers are dependent on the compliance of the patients and bonded retainers are exposed to wire fractures or composite breakages (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10–13</xref>). Furthermore, difficulties in cleaning approximal surfaces might increase the prevalence of periodontal complications (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Thus, it may be desirable to identify patients who do not need any retention.</p>
              <p>Previous studies on retention and mandibular anterior teeth show promising results in patients treated solely by interproximal enamel reduction (IPR) (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref>). However, trials on patients without any retention or IPR do not appear to exist.</p>
              <p>Maxillary anterior teeth have been presented as being more stable to post-treatment changes compared to mandibular teeth (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19–22</xref>). Moreover, among the six maxillary anterior teeth, the canines were reported to be more stable than the incisors (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). This implies that patients with reasonably straight maxillary incisors before treatment potentially do not need any retention. As the incidence of maxillary canine impaction is between 1.8 and 3.3 per cent (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), a considerable number of patients must be treated. These patients might benefit from an improved retention regimen. Therefore, the purpose of this trial was to evaluate whether retention is needed after orthodontic treatment for impacted maxillary canines and with moderate pre-treatment irregularity in the maxilla. We hypothesized that no statistically or clinically significant difference will occur in the position of the maxillary anterior teeth of patients with and without retention, 1-year post-treatment.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2">
              <title>Subjects and methods</title>
              <sec id="s3">
                <title>Trial design</title>
                <p>The trial was a single-centre randomized controlled trial (RCT) with two parallel arms and a 1:1 allocation ratio. The primary outcome was post-treatment changes in irregularity of the maxillary six anterior teeth in patients with and without retention. The trial period lasted between the removal of the fixed orthodontic appliances (T1) and 1 year after debond (T2). The Regional Ethical Research Board, Linköping, Sweden, who follows the Declaration of Helsinki, approved the trial (Dnr 2013/130).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>All participants were recruited from patients referred to the Orthodontic Clinic in Växjö, Public Dental Service, Kronoberg County, Sweden.</p>
                <p>The inclusion criteria were patients who had at least one impacted or unerupted maxillary canine; and moderate irregularity of the maxillary six anterior teeth of 4–6 mm according to Little’s index (LI) (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p>
                <p>The exclusion criteria were patients with agenesis or extracted maxillary anterior teeth; patients with rotations exceeding 45 degrees of one of the maxillary incisors; patients in need of orthognathic surgery; and patients with syndromes.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s5">
                <title>Randomization</title>
                <p>After gaining informed consent from the patient and their custodians, the patients were randomized to one of two groups, i.e. to a non-retention group or a retention group. The randomization process was prepared and carried out by an independent person not involved in the trial and the randomization used blocks of 20 (10 + 10). Opaque envelopes contained 20 sealed notes each (10 notes signed retention, and 10 notes signed non-retention). Every new participant in the trial took a note from the first envelope. When the first envelope was empty, the next envelope was opened, and so on, until the number of participants met the estimated sample size.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s6">
                <title>Intention-to-treat</title>
                <p>Data on all participants were evaluated on an intention-to-treat (ITT) basis. Consequently, all patients that were randomized remained in the allocated group. Patients with discontinued observation or lost to follow-up were regarded as treatment failure. Hence, the group’s maximum value for change in the primary outcome (irregularity of the maxillary six anterior teeth) as well as for the secondary variables representing the change in arch length, intercanine width and the molar width was recorded.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s7">
                <title>Blinding</title>
                <p>Because of the type of treatment, neither participant nor operator was blinded for the allocation. The study casts were anonymized before assessment, as was the changes of the maxillary anterior teeth for the assessor, who was not involved in the trial.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s8">
                <title>Clinical procedure</title>
                <p>After registration of the pre-treatment records (T0), all patients were treated by one experienced orthodontist (SN) and with pre-adjusted fixed appliance in the maxilla and mandible (0.022 slot size, MBT prescription, Victory Series, 3M Unitek, Monrovia, California, USA). After insertion of the fixed appliance and if the canine did not spontaneously erupt, the patient was referred for surgical exposure of the impacted canine. During surgical exposure, a gold chain was bonded to the impacted canine, which was then moved by the appliance to its correct place in the dental arch. After the active treatment, post-treatment records were taken (T1). The two groups were followed up 1 year after the end of active treatment when further study casts were taken (T2).</p>
                <p>Following an interim period of 10 weeks, an analysis was performed for each patient in the non-retention group. Thus, at the end of the active treatment, the arch-wire was removed but the brackets were left in place. Then, if the orthodontist observed no changes after the 10-week period, the brackets were removed. However, if an increase in LI corresponding to greater than 3 mm or a single contact point discrepancy (CPD) of ≥2 mm was measured during the interim period, the patient continued treatment with a reinserted arch-wire. After that, a removable vacuum-formed retainer (Essix™, Erkodur, 1.5 mm 120 ø, Erkodent® Erich Kopp GmbH, Pfalzgrafenweiler, Germany) was used as a retention appliance and such patients were counted as a failure in the trial analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s9">
                <title>Retention procedure</title>
                <p>Patients in the retention group were fitted with the upper removable vacuum-formed retainer on the day of debond and were instructed to wear the retainer 22–24 hours/day until the first visit after 4 weeks. Following that, patients were instructed to wear the vacuum-formed retainer for 10–12 hours/day. In case of pre-treatment spacing, the vacuum-formed retainer was replaced by a bonded retainer to all six teeth from canine to canine (Penta-One 0.0195, Masel, Carlsbad, California, USA).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s10">
                <title>Outcomes</title>
                <p>The primary outcomes were changes in single CPD and the sum of five CPDs (LI) of the maxillary six anterior teeth and measured on digitalized three-dimensional (3D) study casts between the non-retention and retention group before treatment (T0), at the end of active treatment (T1) and at the 1-year follow-up (T2).</p>
                <p>Before assessment of measurements, the study casts were digitized with a stationary 3D scanner (D700, 3Shape, Copenhagen, Denmark). On the digital models, the measurement points were located using the OnyxCeph<sup>3</sup>™ software (v3.2, Image Instruments, Chemnitz, Germany) with semi-automatic segmentation. The measurement points were then manually adjusted in order to improve consistency. The CPD was measured as a projection on the occlusal plane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Primary and secondary outcome measures in OnyxCeph3™.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjaa010f0001"/>
                </fig>
                <p>The secondary outcomes were:</p>
                <list list-type="simple">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>- Change in arch length defined as the sum of the distances between the mesial contact point of the first permanent molar and the incisal contact point.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>- Change in intercanine width, defined as the distance between the maxillary canines’ cusp tips.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>- Change in intermolar width, defined as the distance between the mesiobuccal cusp tips of the maxillary first permanent molars.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>- Change in the rotations of the six maxillary anterior teeth, defined as the angle between the line from the distal to the mesial contact point and the sagittal plane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s11">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The sample size calculation was based on a clinically relevant difference in LI of 3 mm (SD = 3 mm) between the groups. The level of significance was set to 5 per cent and the power to 90 per cent. The calculation resulted in a sample size of 23 patients in each group. To compensate for dropouts, at least 30 patients were planned to be enrolled in each group.</p>
                <p>Statistical analysis was conducted using the programming language ‘R’ (v 3.60) (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). For descriptive statistics, means and standard deviations were calculated. A Shapiro–Wilk test was used for normality testing. Homogeneity of variance was tested with Levene’s modified test. Hypothesis testing was conducted with <italic>t</italic>-test for independent variables with a normal distribution. Independent variables that were not normally distributed were evaluated with the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test. Correlations between post-treatment increase of irregularity and possible predictors were assessed with scatterplots and Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s12">
                <title>Method error analysis</title>
                <p>Forty-five randomly selected study casts were repeatedly measured on two separate occasions with at least 2 weeks’ interval by the same examiner. Paired <italic>t</italic>-test revealed no significant mean differences between the two series of record occasions. <italic>The size of the method error was determined using</italic> Dahlberg’s formula (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The mean measurement error for the CPDs was 0.1 mm, for LI 0.2 mm, for intercanine and intermolar width 0.2 mm each, and 2.6 degrees for tooth rotations.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s13">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s14">
                <title>Sample characteristics</title>
                <p>Seventy patients matching the inclusion criteria were asked to participate in this trial and, of these, 63 patients (39 females and 24 males) with a mean age of 12.9 years were accepted for participation. Enrolment commenced in June 2013 and ended in April 2018. The last follow-up (T2) was completed in April 2019. <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the baseline demographic data.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Baseline demographic data. SD, standard deviation.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>n</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years Mean (SD)</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impacted palatal canines, <italic>n</italic></th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impacted buccal canines, <italic>n</italic></th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retention</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 (1.7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (1.4)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 (1.7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No retention</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 (1.1)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0 (1.4)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 (1.2)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both groups</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 (1.5)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>The mean duration of treatment was 29.7 (SD = 7.0) months in the retention group and 30.1 (SD = 9.1) months in the non-retention group. No significant differences in treatment duration were found between the groups or between the genders. Surgical exposure was carried out in 15 patients in the retention group and 19 patients in the non-retention group. Extraction of maxillary first premolar teeth was necessary for three patients before referral to the orthodontist in the retention group and one patient in the non-retention group. No significant differences were found between the two groups considering buccally or palatally impacted canines, angulation of canines as well as in surgical exposure of canines (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
                <p>In the retention group, 28 patients received a removable vacuum-formed retainer, and four patients received bonded retainers to all teeth canine-to-canine due to pre-treatment spacing.</p>
                <p>In the non-retention group, one patient showed a CPD of 2 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) during the 10-week interim period. According to the stopping guideline criteria, the observation period was discontinued, and the teeth were realigned. The patient received a retention appliance to avoid further relapse. Another patient in the non-retention group moved away. These two patients were considered as treatment failures in the final analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>A patient who met the stopping guideline criteria during the 10-week interim period.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjaa010f0002"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>CONSORT flow chart.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjaa010f0003"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s15">
                <title>Changes in irregularity index</title>
                <p>The difference in irregularity change between the retention and non-retention groups was statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, 0.4 versus 1.3 mm). The maximum increase in irregularity was 2.5 mm in the retention and 3.2 mm in the non-retention group (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Moreover, the mean maximum single CPD was lower in the retention group compared to the non-retention group, but not significant (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Mean changes in mm CPD (contact point discrepancy) during the retention period (T1 = post-treatment, to T2 = 1-year follow-up) in retention group and in non-retention group. CI, confidence interval; ITT, intention-to-treat.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Retention group (<italic>n</italic> = 32)</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Non-retention group (<italic>n</italic> = 31)</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">←<italic>P</italic>→</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change T2 − T1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Little’s index </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arch length</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.3 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercanine width</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermolar width</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.492</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum CPD T1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.330</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum CPD T2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 mm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum derotation T2 − T1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7°</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4°</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="fn-0100">
                      <p>Results (ITT) represented by means and 95% CIs.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 4.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>The changes in irregularity index in the two groups between T1 and T2 presented as Tukey boxplots.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjaa010f0004"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Small but not statistically significant changes between the groups were found in arch length, intercanine and intermolar width.</p>
                <p>No significant correlations between post-treatment changes in irregularity and duration of treatment, pre-treatment CPDs or tooth derotations were detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). In the non-retention group, including the 10-week interim period, most changes occurred during the 10-week period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 5.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Correlations between changes in irregularity and (A) duration of treatment (rho = 0.28); (B) maximum CPD (rho = 0.15) and (C) maximum derotation (rho = 0.15). CPD, contact point discrepancy.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjaa010f0005"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 6.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Post-treatment changes in irregularity without retention.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjaa010f0006"/>
                </fig>
                <p>In the retention group, 93.5 per cent had a LI less than 3 mm and in the non-retention group 80 per cent had a LI less than 3 mm after the 1-year observation period.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s16">
                <title>Harms</title>
                <p>One patient met the stopping guideline criteria. For this patient, the arch-wire was reinserted and after 2 months of realignment, the patient received a retention appliance.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s17">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <sec id="s18">
                <title>Main findings</title>
                <p>In this unique trial, satisfactory clinical results 1-year post-treatment were found in the group without retention. Even though the average difference in LI, 0.4 versus 1.3 mm, was statistically significant, it is our opinion that this difference was not clinically significant since irregularities of LI between 1 and 3 mm are scored as minimal irregularities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). However, it cannot be overlooked that any individual patient may have been disturbed by an irregularity of 3 mm. Consequently, our initial hypothesis could be partly confirmed and it has to be pointed out that the range of changes in the irregularity index was greater in the non-retention than in the retention group.</p>
                <fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 7.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Case with Little’s index 1.9 mm.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjaa010f0007"/>
                </fig>
                <p>The challenge is to identify the patients with a higher risk for an increase in irregularity index beforehand. Since the parameters for this identification still are not entirely known, the use of the 10-week interim period in the non-retention group was useful in identifying those patients who might have a relapse immediately after treatment. Also, for ethical reasons, this interim method was justified to avoid major relapse or harm to patients. Moreover, from a short-term perspective, this trial also showed that retention with a removable vacuum-formed retainer was successful in patients with impacted maxillary canines and moderate pre-treatment dental irregularities.</p>
                <p>The results of present trial are similar to trials that have investigated post-treatment changes of mandibular anterior teeth. Hence, these trials have reported stable results after IPR and without any retention appliances (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Regardless, it is important to admit that one patient in our trial had to be retreated for 2 months as a significant relapse was detected during the interim period. Studying the characteristics of the outliers and further investigating possible predictors of relapse may help us to identify those patients who might undergo relapse immediately after treatment.</p>
                <p>It can also be pointed out that in the group without retention, the largest irregularity changes occurred during the first 10 weeks. These findings are in line with the results by Reitan <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) who reported changes as early as the first day and a progressive relapse during the following 232 days until the dental fibres were re-arranged.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s19">
                <title>Interpretations</title>
                <p>Assessment of post-treatment changes was carried out by study casts being scanned into digital 3D models. Measuring CPDs can be considered to be a standardized task when measuring both study casts and digital 3D models. Digital 3D models are superior when it comes to measuring rotations, comparison of changes between two models or documentation of the measurements. Nevertheless, if manually placed landmarks are used it is necessary to accept a measurement error that ranges between 0.1 and 0.2 mm even in digital 3D measurements (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Since the LI is a summary score of five contact points, the measurement error can be five times higher. The semi-automatic segmentation in OnyxCeph<sup>3</sup>™ (v3.2) showed a considerable variety in landmark positioning when repeated measurements were conducted, and, therefore, to avoid incorrect and inconsistent measurements the semi-automatic segmentation method was used together with manual corrections.</p>
                <p>Owing to the anatomy of the maxillary anterior teeth the risk of incorrect measurement of CPDs is significant. However, a CPD is not always visible clinically, and a LI of less than 1 mm is often considered to be a perfect alignment. The use of a threshold value might be of interest to reduce the impact of non-visible CPDs, but a threshold value leads to a distinct partitioning of the measurements, thus introducing additional sources of errors. Therefore, in this trial no threshold values were used.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s20">
                <title>Strengths</title>
                <p>The dropout rate was very low in this trial and ensured comparability of both groups and satisfactory power. Moreover, the use of the ITT approach guaranteed that all patients who were randomized remained in their allocated group. Furthermore, patients with discontinued observation or lost to follow-up were regarded as failures, and, thus, the group’s maximum value for change of tooth irregularity (the primary outcome) was recorded. Consequently, the risk of false-positive treatment results was minimal in this trial. In addition, the measurement errors were regarded as small and clinically irrelevant.</p>
                <p>Finally, the RCT methodology reduced the risk of selection bias and confounding variables were avoided by ensuring that both known and unknown determinants of outcome were uniformly allocated between the two patient groups.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s21">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>This trial was a single-centre RCT, and the treatments were conducted by one operator. Therefore, operator-related errors might have influenced the results, but the single-centre design has the advantage of clear communication and less variance of trial conduct.</p>
                <p>Due to the trial’s nature, blinding of the participant or care provider was not possible, which might be considered a source of bias. However, study casts were anonymized before analysis of the changes in the six maxillary anterior teeth and, in addition, the assessor had no prior involvement in the investigation.</p>
                <p>The strength of this trial might have been further enhanced if it had included a long-term follow-up period and collection of patient’s perceptions. The need for a further long-term follow-up trial was identified and has been commenced. Nonetheless, the primary objective of this trial was to short-term assess whether retention is necessary after orthodontic treatment of impacted maxillary canines.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s22">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>Changes between the retention and the non-retention group were statistically but not clinically significant and since satisfactory clinical results 1-year post-treatment were found in the non-retention group retention does not appear to be needed.</p>
              <p>Most of the relapses in the non-retention group occurred during the 10-week post-treatment interim period, and, thus, this period was useful in identifying patients who might have a relapse immediately after treatment.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <sec id="s0108">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This trial was supported by the Public Dental Service, Kronoberg County, Sweden, Department of Research and Development, Region Kronoberg, Sweden, Faculty of Odontology, Malmö University, Sweden, and the Swedish Dental Association.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0109">
              <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
              <p>None declared.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list id="r1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CIT0001">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Trulsson</surname>, <given-names>U.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strandmark</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohlin</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Berggren</surname>, <given-names>U</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A qualitative study of teenagers’ decisions to undergo orthodontic treatment with fixed appliance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>29</volume>, <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>; discussion 195.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12218197</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0002">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shaw</surname>, <given-names>W.C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Factors influencing the desire for orthodontic treatment</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>3</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6943029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0003">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Helm</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kreiborg</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Solow</surname>, <given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Psychosocial implications of malocclusion: a 15-year follow-up study in 30-year-old Danes</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>87</volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3855604</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0004">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Espeland</surname>, <given-names>L.V.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Stenvik</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Perception of personal dental appearance in young adults: relationship between occlusion, awareness, and satisfaction</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>100</volume>, <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1877547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0005">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Al-Moghrabi</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johal</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Fleming</surname>, <given-names>P.S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>What are people tweeting about orthodontic retention? A cross-sectional content analysis</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>152</volume>, <fpage>516</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28962737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0006">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Littlewood</surname>, <given-names>S.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kandasamy</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Retention and relapse in clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Australian Dental Journal,</source><volume>62</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>), <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28297088</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0007">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Renkema</surname>, <given-names>A.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sips</surname>, <given-names>E.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bronkhorst</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Kuijpers-Jagtman</surname>, <given-names>A.M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A survey on orthodontic retention procedures in The Netherlands</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19401355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0008">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Littlewood</surname>, <given-names>S.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Millett</surname>, <given-names>D.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doubleday</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bearn</surname>, <given-names>D.R.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Worthington</surname>, <given-names>H.V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Orthodontic retention: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>33</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16926314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0009">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schütz-Fransson</surname>, <given-names>U.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindsten</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjerklin</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Bondemark</surname>, <given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Twelve-year follow-up of mandibular incisor stability: comparison between two bonded lingual orthodontic retainers</article-title>. <source>The Angle Orthodontist,</source><volume>87</volume>, <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27552722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0010">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pratt</surname>, <given-names>M.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kluemper</surname>, <given-names>G.T.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Lindstrom</surname>, <given-names>A.F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Patient compliance with orthodontic retainers in the postretention phase</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>140</volume>, <fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21803257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0011">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kacer</surname>, <given-names>K.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valiathan</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Narendran</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Hans</surname>, <given-names>M.G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Retainer wear and compliance in the first 2 years after active orthodontic treatment</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>138</volume>, <fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>598</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21055599</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0012">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kocher</surname>, <given-names>K.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gebistorf</surname>, <given-names>M.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandis</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fudalej</surname>, <given-names>P.S.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Katsaros</surname>, <given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Survival of maxillary and mandibular bonded retainers 10 to 15 years after orthodontic treatment: a retrospective observational study</article-title>. <source>Progress in Orthodontics,</source><volume>20</volume>, <fpage>28</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31328248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0013">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Edman Tynelius</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bondemark</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Lilja-Karlander</surname>, <given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of three orthodontic retention methods in Class I four premolar extraction cases – stability after 2 years in retention</article-title>. <source>Orthodontics &amp; Craniofacial Research,</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23324112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0014">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dietrich</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patcas</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandis</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Eliades</surname>, <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Long-term follow-up of maxillary fixed retention: survival rate and periodontal health</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>37</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25086911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0015">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Levin</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samorodnitzky-Naveh</surname>, <given-names>G.R.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Machtei</surname>, <given-names>E.E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The association of orthodontic treatment and fixed retainers with gingival health</article-title>. <source>Journal of Periodontology,</source><volume>79</volume>, <fpage>2087</fpage>–<lpage>2092</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18980517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0016">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Aasen</surname>, <given-names>T.O.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Espeland</surname>, <given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>An approach to maintain orthodontic alignment of lower incisors without the use of retainers</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>27</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15947218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0017">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Edman Tynelius</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bondemark</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Lilja-Karlander</surname>, <given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of orthodontic treatment after 1 year of retention–a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>542</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080961</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0018">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zachrisson</surname>, <given-names>B.U.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nyøygaard</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Mobarak</surname>, <given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Dental health assessed more than 10 years after interproximal enamel reduction of mandibular anterior teeth</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>131</volume>, <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17276856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0019">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Steinnes</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnsen</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Kerosuo</surname>, <given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Stability of orthodontic treatment outcome in relation to retention status: an 8-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>151</volume>, <fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1033</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28554448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0020">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sadowsky</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Sakols</surname>, <given-names>E.I</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Long-term assessment of orthodontic relapse</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>82</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6961816</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0021">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Surbeck</surname>, <given-names>B.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Artun</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hawkins</surname>, <given-names>N.R.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Leroux</surname>, <given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Associations between initial, posttreatment, and postretention alignment of maxillary anterior teeth</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>113</volume>, <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9484210</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0022">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Artun</surname>, <given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Is the postretention relapse of maxillary and mandibular incisor alignment related?</article-title><source>American Journal of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>120</volume>, <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11455371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0023">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Naraghi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andrén</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kjellberg</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Mohlin</surname>, <given-names>B.O</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Relapse tendency after orthodontic correction of upper front teeth retained with a bonded retainer</article-title>. <source>The Angle Orthodontist,</source><volume>76</volume>, <fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16808561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0024">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Andrén</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naraghi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohlin</surname>, <given-names>B.O.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Kjellberg</surname>, <given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pattern and amount of change after orthodontic correction of upper front teeth 7 years postretention</article-title>. <source>The Angle Orthodontist,</source><volume>80</volume>, <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20482345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0025">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thilander</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Myrberg</surname>, <given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>The prevalence of malocclusion in Swedish schoolchildren</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Dental Research,</source><volume>81</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4510864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0026">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shah</surname>, <given-names>R.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boyd</surname>, <given-names>M.A.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Vakil</surname>, <given-names>T.F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Studies of permanent tooth anomalies in 7,886 Canadian individuals. II: congenitally missing, supernumerary and peg teeth</article-title>. <source>Dental Journal,</source><volume>44</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">277400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0027">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Little</surname>, <given-names>R.M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>The irregularity index: a quantitative score of mandibular anterior alignment</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>68</volume>, <fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>563</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1059332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0028">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book">R Core Team. (2019) <italic>A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</italic>. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</uri></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0029">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dahlberg</surname>, <given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1940</year>) <source>Statistical Methods for Medical and Biological Students</source>. <publisher-name>Georg Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>, pp. 
<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0030">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reitan</surname>, <given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Clinical and histologic observations on tooth movement during and after orthodontic treatment</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthodontics,</source><volume>53</volume>, <fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>745</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5233926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0031">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Radeke</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>von der Wense</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Lapatki</surname>, <given-names>B.G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Comparison of orthodontic measurements on dental plaster casts and 3D scans</article-title>. <source>Journal of Orofacial Orthopedics,</source><volume>75</volume>, <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24996855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
