<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10439642" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10439642</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcorhl</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10439642</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10439642</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10439642</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37598194</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37598194</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3269</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-023-03269-4</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Self-assembling peptide and nano-silver fluoride in remineralizing early enamel carious lesions: randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Atteya</surname>
                    <given-names>Sara M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>sara.atteya@alexu.edu.eg</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Amer</surname>
                    <given-names>Hala A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Saleh</surname>
                    <given-names>Susan M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Safwat</surname>
                    <given-names>Yara</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00mzz1w90</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7155.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2260 6941</institution-id><institution>Department of Pediatric Dentistry and Dental Public Health, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Alexandria University, </institution></institution-wrap>Champollion St., Azarita, 21527 Alexandria Egypt </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00mzz1w90</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7155.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2260 6941</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Alexandria University, </institution></institution-wrap>Alexandria, Egypt </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <elocation-id>577</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">Nanoparticles and regenerative biomineralization are new caries prevention technologies. This study assessed the remineralizing effect of self-assembling peptide (P11-4), Nanosilver Fluoride (NSF) and sodium fluoride (NaF) on white spot lesions (WSLs) in permanent teeth.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">Sixty six young adults with WSLs on buccal surfaces in permanent teeth and ICDAS code 1 or 2, were randomly assigned to one of three groups; P11-4, NSF or NaF. Assessment of ICDAS scores, lesion activity (Nyvad scores) and diagnodent readings of lesions were done at baseline and after 1, 3, 6 and 12 months of agents’ application. Comparisons between groups were made using chi squared test and comparison within groups were made using McNemar test. Multilevel binary logistic regression was used to assess the effect of agents on change of ICDAS scores after 3, 6 and 12 months (reduction versus no reduction).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">There were 147 teeth in 66 patients; mean ± SD age = 13.46 ± 4.31 years. There were significant differences in the change of ICDAS scores among the three groups after 3 and 6 months (<italic>p</italic> = 0.005). The reduction in ICDAS score increased steadily in all groups across time with the greatest increase in the P11-4 group: 54.5% after 12 months. Lesion activity (Nyvad scores) showed significant differences among the three groups with the greatest percentage of inactive cases in the P11-4 group. Multilevel binary logistic regression showed non-significant reduction of ICDAS in P11-4 and NSF varnishes compared to NaF varnish (AOR = 2.56, 95% CI: 0.58, 8.77 and AOR = 2.12, 95% CI: 0.59, 7.64 respectively).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">P11-4 and NSF varnish reduced the ICDAS scores, caries activity and diagnodent readings of WSLs in permanent teeth. However, the change in ICDAS scores was not significantly different from NaF.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Trial registration</title>
                  <p id="Par5">This trial was prospectively registered on the clinicaltrials.gov registry with ID: NCT04929509 on 18/6/2021.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Self-assembling peptide</kwd>
                <kwd>P11-4</kwd>
                <kwd>Nano silver fluoride</kwd>
                <kwd>Sodium fluoride</kwd>
                <kwd>White spot lesions</kwd>
                <kwd>ICDAS</kwd>
                <kwd>Diagnodent</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>Alexandria University</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <open-access>
                  <p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p>
                </open-access>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par6">Dental caries is a multifactorial chronic disease and a major public health problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Conventional methods for caries prevention, such as topical fluoride application, decrease demineralization through fluoride deposition in the enamel crystal lattice, reducing its solubility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The effect of fluoride is limited to the outer -30 μm. Consequently, fluoride does not enter deeper than the subsurface demineralized zone; where remineralisation is much needed for the affected enamel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par7">Nanotechnology is an emerging trend in dentistry. Silver nanoparticles (AgNPs) are products with high surface area and a micro- size of atoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Nano-silver fluoride (NSF) varnishes have been developed with high remineralization property and antimicrobial effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Primary teeth treated with fluoride varnish with silver nano particles had better structure than those treated with conventional varnish following remineralization of early WSLs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Nano-silver mouthwash has been proved to be more effective than NaF mouthwash in reducing WSLs in permanent teeth after six months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par8">Self-Assembling Peptide (P11-4) restores hydroxyapatite crystals within the subsurface carious lesion by Guided Enamel Remineralisation (GER). It has hierarchical self-assembly property and forms a fibrillar scaffold with a 3D matrix in the presence of high ionic strength and acidic pH in carious lesions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The safety of P11-4 was demonstrated in a trial for caries arrest in adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Clinical studies of P11-4 showed mixed results. In one study, there was a significant improvement in all outcomes after 6 months of using P11-4 combined with fluoride varnish than fluoride varnish alone in early caries on erupting permanent molars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Also, P11-4 with fluoride varnish significantly decreased the size of early carious lesions in young adults compared to fluoride varnish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. P11-4, applied either with fluoride varnish or alone, was superior in treating early occlusal WSLs in children and adults than fluoride varnish alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Two systematic reviews of seven clinical trials showed that P11-4 improved caries arrest, decreased lesion size and lowered ICDAS scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, P11-4 alone had less remineralization effect than highly concentrated sodium fluoride agent and Remin Pro forte (fluoride, hydroxyapatite and xylitol paste) on WSLs in permanent teeth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. P11-4 induced less lesion regression of white spot buccal lesions in permanent than fluoride varnish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par9">P11-4 and NSF are two novel caries preventive and remineralization agents for early caries lesions. They have limited evidence base to support their relative effects with scarce information from clinical trials comparing both agents directly. Such trials can provide answers to questions about which agent to use in situations where white spot lesions in permanent teeth are present. This study compared P11-4, NSF varnish and NaF varnish in remineralizing WSLs on the buccal surfaces of permanent teeth in young adults after one, three, six and twelve months follow-up. The null hypothesis was that there would be no significant differences in lesion arrest among the three agents.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Material and methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Ethical consideration and study design</title>
                <p id="Par10">This study was a parallel randomized, three arm, clinical trial conducted in the Pediatric Dentistry clinic of the Faculty of Dentistry, Alexandria University. Ethical approval was obtained from the Research Ethics Committee, Faculty of Dentistry, Alexandria University (#0086–11/2019). The trial was prospectively registered on the clinicaltrials.gov registry (NCT04929509). Before the intervention, the study was explained to the participants and they were informed about the etiology of WSLs and the available options for treatment. They were also advised about the importance of oral hygiene and proper diet in preventing WSLs lesions.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Participant eligibility</title>
                <p id="Par11">Participants were recruited randomly from the outpatients clinic of Faculty of Dentistry, Alexandria University if they were aged 10–24 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], with at least one visible WSL in the buccal surface of permanent teeth, with ICDAS II score of 1 or 2, and after signing an informed consent to participate in the study, themselves if they were &gt; 18 years of age or by their guardians/parents if they were younger [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The exclusion criteria were patients receiving tetracyclines, any other medication known to stain teeth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] or had fluoride application less than 3 months before the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Teeth were excluded if they had microcavities or dentinal involvement due to loss of enamel, had a restoration adjacent to the lesion to avoid diagnodent false-positive readings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], had discolouration, enamel hypoplasia or fluorosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Sample size calculation</title>
                <p id="Par12">Sample size was estimated based on assuming 95% confidence level and 80% study power. The percentage of inactive lesions expected after 12 months of applying P11-4 and NaF varnish were estimated to be 68.8% and 25.9% respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. By comparing proportions, sample size was calculated to be 20 patients per group, with each patient having at least one active lesion. This was increased to 22 patients to make up for loss to follow up with total sample of 66 patients.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Randomization, allocation and blinding</title>
                <p id="Par13">Participants were randomly assigned with equal allocation to the three arms, Curodont Repair (P11-4), NSF varnish and NaF varnish, using a computer-generated list of random numbers in blocks of 3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Participants were given serial numbers that was written on identical sheets of paper with the group to which the patient was allocated and placed inside an opaque envelop carrying the patient’s name. A trial independent person kept the envelopes and unfolded them at the time of the intervention. The examiner administering the intervention (NN) was not blinded, since the method of application is different for the three agents. However, the participants were blinded to the agent they received by removing the labels from the bottles. The outcome assessor (SA) was blinded to the intervention type.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Training and calibration</title>
                <p id="Par14">The examiner (S.A.) was trained for ICDAS II and Lesion activity assessment (LAA) criteria by two senior researchers (H.A. and S.S.). Intra examiner reliability was excellent for ICDAS II and LAA examinations (Kappa statistic = 0.92 and 0.90 respectively).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>Intervention</title>
                <p id="Par15">Participants in the first group received P11-4 (Curodont Repair™, Biomedical products for tooth preservation) only at baseline. First, the tooth was completely isolated using rubber dam followed by cleaning of the tooth surface with sodium hypochlorite 2% for 20 s, acid etching with phosphoric acid gel 35–37% for 20 s, rinsing and drying. The agent was applied by removing the safety clip, activating the applicator and squeezing out the sponge above the lesion and the solution was left to diffuse for 5 min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par16">In the second group, each tooth received two drops of NSF only at baseline. NSF was prepared at the Faculty of Pharmacy, Alexandria University according to Wei et al. method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. It was applied with a micro brush, equivalent to a dose of 10 mg and the solution was left in contact with the tooth for 2 min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par17">The third group received 5% NaF varnish (Duraflor®) at baseline and after 6 months. The teeth were dried and a very thin coat of the varnish was applied and allowed to dry for 10 s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par18">All participants were instructed to eat only soft foods and avoid hot liquids for two hours. Oral health instructions were given to all participants.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Outcome assessment</title>
                <p id="Par19">Remineralization was assessed using visual tactile assessment of WSLs based on change in ICDAS II scores (reduction from score 2 to 1, or from score 1 to 0) and LAA (NYVAD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This was the primary outcome. DIAGNOdent score was the secondary outcome. The DIAGNOdent score ranges from 0 to 99 with higher score indicating deeper caries. A decrease in value indicates regression of the carious lesion, whereas an increase indicates progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. A base line zero value for each patient is obtained by choosing a clear non carious patch of enamel, usually the middle third of an anterior tooth. The pen is pointed in perpendicular direction to this area and the set button is touched for 2 s until 0 appears, then the button is released, and zero baseline value is, thus, set. Probe B of laser fluorescence for smooth surface caries was used for lesions examination. Using cotton roll isolation and after air drying with an air syringe, the measurement was performed with the tip making contact at a right angle to the white spot lesion. Measurements were made three times and the values were averaged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Outcome assessment was done at baseline and 1, 3, 6 and 12 months. The flow chart of patients and outcome assessment at each follow-up period is illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Lesion activity assessment (LAA) (NYVAD) criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Clinical parameter 1 (visual appearance: severity score)</td><td align="left">ICDAS score 1,2 (brown lesions)</td><td align="left">1 point</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICDAS score 1,2 (white lesions)</td><td align="left">3 points</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICDAS score 3, 4, 5 or 6</td><td align="left">4 points</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Clinical parameter 2 (gingival inflammation with plaque stagnation)</td><td align="left">Gingival inflammation with plaque stagnation</td><td align="left">3 points</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No gingival inflammation</td><td align="left">1 point</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Clinical parameter 3 (surface texture)</td><td align="left">Rough or soft surface on gentle probing</td><td align="left">4 points</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smooth or hard surface on gentle probing</td><td align="left">2 points</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Final sum</td><td align="left"> ≤ 7</td><td align="left">Inactive caries</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &gt; 7</td><td align="left">Active caries</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Participants flow cart</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_3269_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par20">The World Health Organization questionnaire was used to assess participants’ oral health practices including dental visits, use of fluoridated toothpaste and frequency sugar consumption, and their socioeconomic background (age, sex) as confounders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par21">Normality was checked using Kolmogorov–Smirnov test. Non-normally distributed variables were presented using medians and inter quartile ranges (IQR). Intention to treat analysis was used. Chi squared test was used to compare changes in ICDAS and NYVAD scores among groups and McNemar test was used to compare changes across time within the same group. For LAA, a score of more than 7 was considered active and less than 7 indicated inactive lesion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Multilevel binary logistic regression was used to assess the effect of agents, introduced as fixed effects, on ICDAS score reduction categorized as reduction versus no reduction where reduction was recorded if the score changed from score 2 to score 1 or from score 1 to score 0 and no reduction was recorded if the scores remained unchanged or increased. This was done with and without controlling the confounders (age, sex, brushing with fluoridated toothpaste, dental visits, and sugar consumption, and the number of teeth with white spot lesions in each group). Significance level was set at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05. All tests were two tailed. Data were analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics for Macintosh, Version 28.0. Armonk, NY: IBM Corp.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec11">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="Par22">The study sample included 147 lesions in 66 patients. The mean (± SD) age was 13.46 (± 4.31) with 66.7% females. There were no significant differences among the groups except in the daily frequency of sugar intake and frequency of dental visits last year (<italic>P</italic> = 0.031 and 0.004, respectively, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Demographic description and oral health practices of study participants per group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2"/><th align="left">P11-4 (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, <italic>n</italic> = 44 lesions)</th><th align="left">NSF (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, <italic>n</italic> = 44 lesions)</th><th align="left">NaF (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, <italic>n</italic> = 59 lesions)</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Age: Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">12.55 (3.54)</td><td align="left">11.73 (2.87)</td><td align="left">13.77 (4.6)</td><td align="left">0.196</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Sex n (%)</td><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">9 (40.9%)</td><td align="left">7 (31.8%)</td><td align="left">8 (36.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.822</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">13 (59.1%)</td><td align="left">15 (68.2%)</td><td align="left">14 (63.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Frequency of sugar intake: Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">1.5 (1.01)</td><td align="left">2.45 (1.34)</td><td align="left">2.09 (1.19)</td><td align="left">0.031*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Last dental visit in the last year n (%)</td><td align="left">Never</td><td align="left">2 (9.1%)</td><td align="left">4 (18.2%)</td><td align="left">3 (13.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">0.004*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Once</td><td align="left">7 (31.8%)</td><td align="left">8 (36.4%)</td><td align="left">8 (36.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Twice</td><td align="left">6 (27.3%)</td><td align="left">6 (27.3%)</td><td align="left">9 (40.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3 times</td><td align="left">6 (27.3%)</td><td align="left">4 (18.2%)</td><td align="left">1 (4.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4 times</td><td align="left">1 (4.5%)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1 (4.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Frequency of brushing with fluoridated toothpaste n (%)</td><td align="left">Never</td><td align="left">2 (9.1%)</td><td align="left">5 (22.7%)</td><td align="left">4 (18.2%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">0.196</td></tr><tr><td align="left">More than 1 time per month</td><td align="left">4 (18.2%)</td><td align="left">3 (13.6%)</td><td align="left">7 (31.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Once or twice a week</td><td align="left">8 (36.4%)</td><td align="left">10 (45.5%)</td><td align="left">5 (22.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Once per day</td><td align="left">6 (27.3%)</td><td align="left">2 (9.1%)</td><td align="left">3 (13.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Twice per day</td><td align="left">2 (9.1%)</td><td align="left">2 (9.1%)</td><td align="left">3 (13.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Number of teeth with white spot lesions: Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">2 (1.35)</td><td align="left">2 (1.45)</td><td align="left">2.68 (1.36)</td><td align="left">0.087</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Statistically significant <italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par23">There were significant differences in change of ICDAS scores among the three groups after 3 and 6 months (<italic>p</italic> = 0.005, Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The reduction in ICDAS score increased in all groups in all periods with the greatest being after 12 months in the P11-4 group (54.5%), followed by NSF (47.7%) and the least in the NaF group (30.5%). There was no increase in ICDAS scores in the P11-4 and NSF groups and only 3.4% of lesion had increase in ICDAS scores in the NaF group after 12 months (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Change in ICDAS scores among the groups at different time intervals</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2"/><th align="left">P11-4 (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, n = 44 lesions)</th><th align="left">NSF (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, n = 44 lesions)</th><th align="left">NaF (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, n = 59 lesions)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Chi square (P</italic> value)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="3">N (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">1 Month</td><td align="left">Reduction</td><td align="left">8 (18.2%)</td><td align="left">5 (11.4%)</td><td align="left">4 (6.8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">4,603 (0.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">36 (81.8%)</td><td align="left">39 (88.6%)</td><td align="left">54 (91.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Increase</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1 (1.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">3 Months</td><td align="left">Reduction</td><td align="left">18 (40.9%)</td><td align="left">14 (31.8%)</td><td align="left">6 (10.2%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">14.703 (0.005)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">26 (59.1%)</td><td align="left">30 (68.2%)</td><td align="left">52 (88.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Increase</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1 (1.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">6 Months</td><td align="left">Reduction</td><td align="left">24 (45.5%)</td><td align="left">18 (40.9%)</td><td align="left">9 (15.3)%</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">14.999 (0.005)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">20 (54.5%)</td><td align="left">26 (59.1%)</td><td align="left">48 (81.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Increase</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">2 (3.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">12 Months</td><td align="left">Reduction</td><td align="left">20 (54.5%)</td><td align="left">21 (47.7%)</td><td align="left">18 (30.5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">8.793 (0.066)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">24 (45.5%)</td><td align="left">23 (52.3%)</td><td align="left">39 (66.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Increase</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">2 (3.4%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Statistically significant <italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par24">Between group comparisons of lesion activity showed significant differences after 1 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), 3, 6 and 12 months (<italic>p</italic> = 0.009) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). All groups showed significant reduction in the percentages of active lesions using NYVAD LAA scores across time (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The reduction in lesion activity was observed in all groups till 3 months then became stable after that, with the greatest percentage of inactive lesions in the P11-4 group (100%), followed by NSF and NaF (81.4%) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>NYVAD scores between the groups at different time intervals</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2"/><th align="left">P11-4 (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, n = 44 lesions)</th><th align="left">NSF (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, n = 44 lesions)</th><th align="left">NaF (<italic>N</italic> = 22 patients, n = 59 lesions)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Chi square (P</italic> value)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="3">N (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Baseline</td><td align="left">Inactive</td><td align="left">21 (47.7%)</td><td align="left">19 (43.2%)</td><td align="left">22 (37.3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">1.152 (0.562)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Active</td><td align="left">23 (52.3%)</td><td align="left">25 (56.8%)</td><td align="left">37 (62.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">1 Month</td><td align="left">Inactive</td><td align="left">43 (97.7%)</td><td align="left">33 (75%)</td><td align="left">40 (67.8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">14.145 (&lt; 0.001)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Active</td><td align="left">1 (%)</td><td align="left">11 (25%)</td><td align="left">19 (32.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">3 Months</td><td align="left">Inactive</td><td align="left">44 (100%)</td><td align="left">36 (81.8%)</td><td align="left">48 (81.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">9.326 (0.009)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Active</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td align="left">8 (16.2%)</td><td align="left">11 (18.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">6 Months</td><td align="left">Inactive</td><td align="left">44 (100%)</td><td align="left">36 (81.8%)</td><td align="left">48 (81.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">9.326 (0.009)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Active</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td align="left">8 (16.2%)</td><td align="left">11 (18.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">12 Months</td><td align="left">Inactive</td><td align="left">44 (100%)</td><td align="left">36 (81.8%)</td><td align="left">48 (81.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">9.326 (0.009)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Active</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td align="left">8 (16.2%)</td><td align="left">11 (18.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value</td><td align="left"> &lt; 0.001*</td><td align="left"> &lt; 0.001*</td><td align="left"> &lt; 0.001*</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Statistically significant <italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par25">There were significant differences in Diagnodent readings among the three groups in each follow up period (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and the reduction in median Diagnodent reading in each group across time was also significant (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001) with the lowest Diagnodent median reading observed in the P11-4 group after 12 months, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Diagnodent readings in the three groups at different follow up periods</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_3269_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
              <p id="Par26">The unadjusted multilevel binary logistic regression model showed that P11-4 (UOR = 2.34, 95% CI: 1.05, 5.22) and NSF (UOR = 1.78, 95% CI: 0.80, 3.97) had higher odds of inducing reduction in ICDAS scores than NaF varnish, although the difference was only statistically significant among the P11-4 group (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04). The adjusted multilevel binary logistic regression model showed that P11-4 (AOR = 2.26, 95% CI: 0.58, 8.77) and NSF (AOR = 2.12, 95% CI: 0.59, 7.64) had higher odds of inducing reduction in ICDAS scores than NaF varnish, although these differences were not statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.24 and 0.25, Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Multilevel binary logistic regression assessing the effect of P11-4 and NSF compared to NaF on reduction versus no reduction in ICDAS score after 12 months</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"><bold>UOR</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>95% CI</bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold> value</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>AOR</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>95% CI</bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold> value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>P11-4 vs NaF</bold></td><td align="left">2.34</td><td align="left">(1.05- 5.22)</td><td align="left">0.04*</td><td align="left">2.26</td><td align="left">(0.58, 8.77)</td><td align="left">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>NSF vs NaF</bold></td><td align="left">1.78</td><td align="left">(0.80- 3.97)</td><td align="left">0.16</td><td align="left">2.12</td><td align="left">(0.59, 7.64)</td><td align="left">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">% Correctly classified</td><td align="left" colspan="3">58.5%</td><td align="left" colspan="3">82.3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Model <italic>P</italic> value</td><td align="left" colspan="3">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="3">0.06</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Models are adjusted for age, sex, sugar frequency, number of white spot lesions, frequency of toothbrushing with fluoridated toothpaste and last dental visit</p><p><sup>*</sup>Statistically significant <italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec12">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par27">This study showed that after one application of P11-4, there were no active lesions after 3 months with significantly lower Diagnodent readings than NaF at all follow-up periods. Also, the number of active lesions decreased steadily after one application of NSF and stabilized after 3 months with Diagnodent readings lower than NaF. However, the adjusted analysis showed that the reduction in ICDAS scores in the P11-4 and NSF groups was not significantly different from the NaF group. Thus, there is no support for rejecting the null hypothesis. Our study fills a knowledge gap by providing evidence on whether there are differences between P11-4 and NSF compared to NaF in remineralizing WSLs in permanent teeth. The findings may support the use of two applications of NaF, one application of NSF or P11-4 to control WSLs in permanent teeth depending on availability of agents and patient compliance although longer follow up periods may shed further light on the sustainability of the effects of the three agents.</p>
              <p id="Par28">In the present study, a longer follow up period was used than in most previous studies assessing the remineralization effect of the studied agents and an adjusted analysis was used that also accounted for clustering of teeth within persons. Because of these features, direct comparison with previous studies is difficult. For example, in the present study, there were no differences between the percentage of lesions with reduction of ICDAS scores after P11-4 or NSF compared to NaF after 12 months. This disagrees with Ali et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] who reported significant difference between NSF and NaF in the number of WSLs in permanent teeth of young adults after 3 and 6 months. It also disagrees with Gözetici et.al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], who showed that NaF induced greater regression of white spot buccal lesions than P11-4 after 6 months and Kamh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] who reported greater reduction in ICDAS II scores of WSLs in adults after 3 months when NaF and xylitol paste were used than when P11-4 was used. These differences highlight the need for studies with adequate duration and analysis techniques that take into consideration the differences that may exist among groups to draw valid conclusions about differences in the remineralization potential of caries preventive agents.</p>
              <p id="Par29">The present study showed that there were significantly fewer active lesions in the P11-4 and NSF groups than the NaF. This agrees with Ali et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] who reported that the NSF had significant reduction in lesion activity up to 6 months. Moreover, Alkilzy et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and Doberdoli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] who showed that P11-4 resulted in greater reduction in lesion activity of early occlusal lesions in children and adolescents than NaF after 6 months. Most recently Keeper JH et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] in their systematic review and meta-analysis has shown single application of P11-4 resulted in decreased lesion activity after 24 months. Our study fill a knowledge gap by proving evidence of the effectiveness of NSF in reducing lesion activity up to 12 months.</p>
              <p id="Par30">In the present study, there were significantly lower median Diagnodent readings in the NSF than the NaF group. This agrees with the only published clinical trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] comparing NSF and NaF varnishes in primary teeth that showed significant reduction of diagnodent readings in NSF group than NaF varnish after 3 months. The differences in the present study in Diagnodent readings between P11-4 and NaF also agree with systematic reviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] concluding that up to 12 months, P11-4 showed significantly greater improvement in Diagnodent readings than NaF. The observed differences in the present study in Diagnodent readings among the groups when there were no significant differences in the percentage of lesions with reduction in ICDAS scores highlight the sensitivity of Diagnodent than ICDAS scoring in detecting changes in lesions limited to enamel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par31">Future clinical trials are needed to support the present findings. Further trials are also needed to examine the effects of the studied agents on occlusal and proximal surfaces which are common sites for dental caries in primary and permanent teeth. Studies with longer follow-up periods are also needed.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec13">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="Par32">The findings of this study highlight the remineralizing effect of P11-4 and NSF. After one year, there were no significant differences in the reduction of ICDAS scores among groups in adjusted analysis although P11-4 and NSF showed less caries activity and lower Diagnodent scores than the NaF group. Further studies are needed to guide clinical decision making to select appropriate remineralizing agents for WSLs in smooth surfaces.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>The authors would like to thank Prof. Maha El Tantawi (Professor of Dental Public Health, Faculty of Dentistry, Alexandria University) for her guidance in the statistical analysis. We would like to extend our sincere thanks to Dr. Lobna Mohsen (assistant lecturer at the Faculty of Pharmacy, Alexandria University) for the preparation of the NSF varnish. We also thank Nouran Nabil for helping with patient recruitment and application of the agents.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>SA, HA, SS and YS conceptualized the study and methodology. SA recruited the participants, performed the clinical procedures and statistical analysis. SA, HA and SS interpreted the study results. HA and SS contributed to the review and finalization of the manuscript. All authors approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB). This clinical trial was not funded nor sponsored by any organization. It was self-funded by the authors.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar1">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par33">This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki on medical protocol and ethics and all national ethical standards. Ethical approval was obtained from the Research Ethics Committee, Faculty of Dentistry, Alexandria University (#0086–11/2019). Signed informed consent was obtained from all patients and/ or their guardians before participating in the study. For participants aged 10 to 18 years, informed consent was obtained from parents or guardians. The trial was prospectively registered on the clinicaltrials.gov registry (NCT04929509) on 18/6/2021.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar2">
                <title>Consent for publication</title>
                <p id="Par34">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par35">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lamont</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egland</surname>
                      <given-names>PG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tang</surname>
                      <given-names>Yi-Wei</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sussman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poxton</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schwartzman</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental Caries</article-title>
                  <source>Molecular Medical Microbiology: Second Edition</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>945</fpage>
                  <lpage>955</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fisher</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnston</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hewson</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van Dijk</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reich</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eiselé</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bourgeois</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>FDI Global Caries Initiative; implementing a paradigm shift in dental practice and the global policy context</article-title>
                  <source>Int Dent J</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <lpage>174</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1875-595X.2012.00128.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23016998?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23016998</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schmidlin</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zobrist</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Attin</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wegehaupt</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>In vitro re-hardening of artificial enamel caries lesions using enamel matrix proteins or self-assembling peptides</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-775720150352</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27008255?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27008255</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>García</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Figueroa</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rubalcava</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Perspectives for the use of silver nanoparticles in dental practice</article-title>
                  <source>Int Dent J</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>61</volume>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <lpage>301</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1875-595X.2011.00072.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22117785</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fung</surname>
                      <given-names>MHT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duangthip</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>MCM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lo</surname>
                      <given-names>ECM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chu</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Arresting dentine caries with different concentration and periodicity of silver diamine fluoride</article-title>
                  <source>JDR Clin Transl Res</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <lpage>152</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2380084416649150</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Giron CBT, Mariel-Cardenas J, Pierdant-Perez M, Hernandez-Sierra, Morales-Sanchez JE, Ruiz F. Effectiveness of a combined silver nanoparticles/fluoride varnish in dental remineralization in children: in vivo study. Superficies y Vacio. 2017;30:1–24.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ali</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ismail</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amin</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of nanosilver mouthwash on prevention of white spot lesions in patients undergoing fixed orthodontic treatment-a randomized double-blind clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Dental Sci</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <lpage>255</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jds.2021.03.016</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aggeli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bell</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carrick</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fishwick</surname>
                      <given-names>CW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harding</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mawer</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>pH as a trigger of peptide ẞ-sheet self-assembly and reversible switching between nematic and isotropic phases</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>125</volume>
                  <fpage>9619</fpage>
                  <lpage>9628</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja021047i</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12904028?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12904028</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aggeli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nyrkova</surname>
                      <given-names>IA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bell</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harding</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carrick</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McLeish</surname>
                      <given-names>TC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hierarchical self-assembly of chiral rod-like molecules as a model for peptide ẞ-sheet tapes, ribbons, fibrils, and fibers</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>98</volume>
                  <fpage>11857</fpage>
                  <lpage>11862</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.191250198</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11592996?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11592996</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carrick</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aggeli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boden</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fisher</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ingham</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Waigh</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of ionic strength on the self-assembly, morphology and gelation of pH responsive B- sheet tape-forming peptides</article-title>
                  <source>Tetrahedron</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>63</volume>
                  <fpage>7457</fpage>
                  <lpage>7467</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tet.2007.05.036</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brunton</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davies</surname>
                      <given-names>RPW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burke</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aggeli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brookes</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Treatment of early caries lesions using biomimetic self-assembling peptides-a clinical safety trial</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dent J</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>215</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>E6</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2013.741</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23969679?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23969679</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alkilzy</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tarabaih</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santamaria</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Splieth</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-assembling peptide P11–4 and fluoride for regenerating enamel</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>97</volume>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <lpage>154</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034517730531</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28892645?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28892645</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bröseler F, Tietmann C, Bommer C, Drechsel T, Heinzel-Gutenbrunner M, &amp; Jepsen S. Randomised clinical trial investigating self-assembling peptide P 11–4 in the treatment of early caries. Clin Oral Investig. 2019;1–10.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doberdoli</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bommer</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Begzati</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haliti</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heinzel-Gutenbrunner</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Juric</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Randomized clinical trial investigating self-assembling peptide P11–4 for treatment of early occlusal caries</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Rep</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-60815-8</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31913322</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wierichs</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wolf</surname>
                      <given-names>TG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of a self-assembling peptide to remineralize initial caries lesions-A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>109</volume>
                  <fpage>103652</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2021.103652</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33798639?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33798639</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Keeper JH, Skaret LJ, Thakkar-Samtani M, Heaton LJ, Sutherland C, Vela K, Amaechi BT, Jablonski-Momeni A, Young DA, MacLean JK, Weyant RJ. Systematic review and meta-analysis on the effect of self-assembling peptide P11–4 on initial caries lesions. medRxiv. 2022.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamh</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Niazy</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El-Yasaky</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical Performance and Remineralization Potential of Different Biomimitic Materials on White Spot Lesions</article-title>
                  <source>Al-Azhar Dental J for Girls</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <lpage>358</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21608/adjg.2018.20020</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gözetici</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Öztürk-Bozkurt</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Toz-Akalın</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative Evaluation of Resin Infiltration and Remineralisation of Noncavitated Smooth Surface Caries Lesions: 6-month Results</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Health Prev Dent</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <lpage>106</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30874252?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30874252</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. Child and adolescent health and development. 2019. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.searo.who.int/entity/child_adolescent/topics/adolescent_health/en/">http://www.searo.who.int/entity/child_adolescent/topics/adolescent_health/en/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlee</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schad</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koch</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cattin</surname>
                      <given-names>PC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rathe</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical performance of self-assembling peptide P11–4 in the treatment of initial proximal carious lesions: A practice-based case series</article-title>
                  <source>J Investig Clin Dent</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>e12286</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jicd.12286</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muñoz-Millán</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaror</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Espinoza-Espinoza</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vergara-Gonzalez</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muñoz</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atala-Acevedo</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of fluoride varnish in preventing early childhood caries in rural areas without access to fluoridated drinking water: A randomized control trial</article-title>
                  <source>Commun Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <lpage>69</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cdoe.12330</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saghaei</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Random allocation software for parallel group randomized trials</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2288-4-26</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15535880?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15535880</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Curodont<sup>TM</sup>. Biomedical products for tooth preservation. 2019. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.straumann.com/en/landing/curodont.html">https://www.straumann.com/en/landing/curodont.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qian</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ye</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ma</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The synthesis of chitosan-based silver nanoparticles and their antibacterial activity</article-title>
                  <source>Carbohyd Res</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>344</volume>
                  <issue>17</issue>
                  <fpage>2375</fpage>
                  <lpage>2382</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carres.2009.09.001</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dos Santos Jr</surname>
                      <given-names>VE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vasconcelos Filho</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Targino</surname>
                      <given-names>AGR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flores</surname>
                      <given-names>MAP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Galembeck</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caldas</surname>
                      <given-names>AF</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new “Silver-Bullet” to treat caries in children-Nano Silver Fluoride: a randomised clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>945</fpage>
                  <lpage>951</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2014.05.017</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24930870?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24930870</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cerón-Bastidas</surname>
                      <given-names>XA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The ICDAS system as a complementary method for the diagnosis of dental caries</article-title>
                  <source>CES Odontol</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <lpage>109</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Braga</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benedetto</surname>
                      <given-names>MSD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imparato</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mendes</surname>
                      <given-names>FM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>New methodology to assess activity status of occlusal caries in primary teeth using laser fluorescence device</article-title>
                  <source>J Biomed Opt</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>047005</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1117/1.3463007</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20799836?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20799836</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shinohara</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Takase</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amagai</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haruyama</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Igarashi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kukidome</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Criteria for a diagnosis of caries through the DIAGNOdent</article-title>
                  <source>Photomed Laser Surg</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <lpage>58</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/pho.2006.24.50</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16503789?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16503789</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Oral health surveys: basic methods. World Health Organization. 2013. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241548649">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241548649</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Minuesa-García</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Iranzo-Cortés</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almerich-Torres</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bellot-Arcís</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Montiel-Company</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almerich-Silla</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diagnostic Validity in Occlusal Caries Detection of ICDAS II, DIAGNOdent, Radiography and a Combination of the Three Methods: An In Vitro Study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Med</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>2937</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm11102937</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 35629063?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35629063</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
