<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:42:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8327006" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8327006</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-09</datestamp>
        <setSpec>ijip</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJI</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spiji</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0394-6320</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2058-7384</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8327006</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8327006</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8327006</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34325540</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34325540</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20587384211031107</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_20587384211031107</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>The use of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> DSM 17938 and ATCC
PTA 5289 on oral health indexes in a school population: A pilot randomized
clinical trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9356-4416</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Borrell García</surname>
                    <given-names>Carla</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1-20587384211031107" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="corresp1-20587384211031107" ref-type="corresp"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ribelles Llop</surname>
                    <given-names>Marta</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1-20587384211031107" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>García Esparza</surname>
                    <given-names>Maria Ángeles</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2-20587384211031107" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Flichy-Fernández</surname>
                    <given-names>Antonio Juan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3-20587384211031107" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Marqués Martínez</surname>
                    <given-names>Laura</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1-20587384211031107" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Izquierdo Fort</surname>
                    <given-names>Regina</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4-20587384211031107" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1-20587384211031107"><label>1</label>Department of Dentistry, Faculty of
Health Sciences, CEU Cardenal Herrera University, Valencia, Spain</aff>
              <aff id="aff2-20587384211031107"><label>2</label>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of
Health Sciences, CEU Cardenal Herrera University, Valencia, Spain</aff>
              <aff id="aff3-20587384211031107"><label>3</label>Department of Dentistry, Valencia
University Medical and Dental School, Valencia, Spain</aff>
              <aff id="aff4-20587384211031107"><label>4</label>Department of Periodontics, Valencia
University Medical and Dental School, Valencia, Spain</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="corresp1-20587384211031107">Carla Borrell García, Department of
Dentistry, Faculty of Health Sciences, CEU Cardenal Herrera University, Carrer
Santiago Ramón y Cajal, 20, Alfara del Patriarca, 46115 Valencia, Spain. Email:
<email>carla.borrel@uchceu.es</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <season>Jan-Dec</season>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>35</volume>
              <elocation-id>20587384211031107</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>To assess the effects of a probiotic upon oral health indices in adolescents and
to establish relationships between these indices and dietary habits and oral
hygiene. Twenty-seven adolescents between 12 and 18 years of age were randomized
into two groups. The study group received tablets containing
<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus reuteri DSM 17938</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">ATCC 5289</italic>
for 28 days, while the control group received tablets without any bacteria.
<italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus mutans, Lactobacillus</italic> sp., and salivary pH
were assessed at baseline and at 7, 14, 21, 28, and 45 days. The plaque,
gingivitis, and bleeding indices were recorded at baseline and at 14, 28, and 45
days. Dietary and oral hygiene habits were also evaluated by means of a
questionnaire. A less marked rise in <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic> was recorded in
the study group. Improvements were observed in terms of plaque, gingivitis, and
bleeding, though statistical significance was not reached. Oral pH increased in
the study group, though not to a significant degree. Poorer eating habits were
significantly correlated to increased plaque. The study parameters decreased
with the two strains of <italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri DSM 17938</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ATCC
PTA 5289</italic>, though the results failed to reach statistical.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>dental caries</kwd>
                <kwd>lactobacilli</kwd>
                <kwd>oral health</kwd>
                <kwd>probiotics</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>January-December 2021</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>typesetter</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>ts1</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-20587384211031107">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>In 2002, the World Health Organization (WHO) and the Food and Agriculture
Organization (FAO) of the United Nations defined probiotics as “live microorganisms
which, when administered in adequate amounts, confer a health benefit on the
host.”<sup><xref rid="bibr1-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Although the mechanisms of action of probiotics are not fully known, it has been
suggested that they are able to maintain their viability after coming into contact
with gastric acids—reaching and adhering to the intestinal mucosa to prevent
cellular adhesion and invasion of pathogenic microorganisms, with modulation of the
immune response.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr3-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Probiotics are potentially useful in the management of multifactorial diseases such
as periodontal disease and caries. Dental caries and periodontal disease are
disorders that can be reverted by eliminating the underlying causal factors. The
adoption of preventive measures plays a crucial role in combating these two
diseases. Research in recent years has focused on controlling pathogenic oral
microorganisms through bacteriotherapy with the use of probiotics.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="bibr5-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr6-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Dental caries is a multifactorial disease involving the interaction of four main
factors: the bacterial flora (composed mainly of microorganisms that produce organic
acids), the host (the quality and shape of the tooth, characteristics of saliva,
oral hygiene, type of diet, and ability to develop an immune response at both
systemic and local level), substrates for microorganisms (such as carbohydrates
contained in secretions and foods), and time (relatively long for decalcification
and short for the remineralization of hard tissues). For this reason, dentists
should seek to promote good eating and hygiene habits from an early age.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="bibr8-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr9-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr10-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The role of probiotics in the prevention of dental caries was first suggested in
1985, and the recommendations for using them are strain-specific and mostly comprise
<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium
spp.</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr11-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr12-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p>
              <p>In the last decade, further experimental studies have been carried out on the use of
probiotic strains for the prevention of dental caries and periodontal
diseases.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Ten years ago the role played by probiotics in periodontal disease was not known.
Efforts have primarily focused on the effect of probiotics upon clinical parameters
(plaque, gingival, and bleeding indices) and their interference with the periodontal
microbiota.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bibr14-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup></p>
              <p>In this regard, the use of probiotics has been postulated to play an important
preventive and/or therapeutic role, and may constitute a nonsurgical alternative in
the management of caries and periodontal disease.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bibr16-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The present study was carried out to evaluate the effects of a probiotic upon oral
health indices in a population of adolescents and to establish possible
relationships between these indices and dietary habits and oral hygiene.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-20587384211031107">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="section3-20587384211031107">
                <title>Study population</title>
                <p>A double-blind, placebo-controlled randomized design was used. Adolescents
belonged to Escolapias school in Gandía (Spain) between 12 and 18 years of age
were enrolled for 45 days. In the reviewed bibliography it has been seen that
after 3 months the probiotic appears to no longer remain in the oral cavity.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> We wanted to limit the time further and evaluate if there were probiotic
traces after 45 days, that was the reason why the study lasted 45 days.</p>
                <p>The exclusion criteria were: (i) subjects under 12 years of age or over 18 years
of age; (ii) the use of drugs capable of causing salivary alterations; (iii)
subjects with braces; (iv) topical fluoride treatment in the last month; (v)
regular consumption of probiotics or xylitol chewing gum; (vi) systemic
antibiotic medication in the last 4 weeks; (vii) active or untreated dental
caries; and (viii) subjects with gait disturbances and/or unidentified
syndromes.</p>
                <p>The study was conducted in accordance with the recommendations of the Declaration
of Helsinki, and was approved by the local Ethics Committee (registration
number: CEI18/067). The adolescents’ legal guardians signed written informed
consent form to participation in the study. Before the study, the subjects had
their teeth cleaned by a dentist and were given detailed instructions concerning
oral hygiene and the need to brush their teeth twice a day throughout the study.
They also received a questionnaire addressing issues related to dietary and oral
hygiene habits.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section4-20587384211031107">
                <title>Sample calculation</title>
                <p>In relation to the plaque index, a beneficial change associated with the
probiotic of at least 0.33 points was expected (equivalent to 20% of the
observed range). A variability in the scale of 0.43 points (estimated standard
deviation in a pilot group of 10 children) was assumed, with a power of 80%
(beta error 20%) and a confidence level of 95% (alpha error 5%). In relation to
<italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic> levels a beneficial change associated with the
probiotic of at least half a point on the logarithmic scale was expected
(equivalent to a change in the linear scale of between 10,000 and 100,000 or
between 100,000 and 10,000) with a variability of 0.6 points (standard deviation
on the logarithmic scale), with a power of 80% (beta error 20%) and a confidence
level of 95% (alpha error 5%). Adopting a conservative approach, it therefore
would suffice to recruit 27 patients in order to detect relevant changes in both
indicators.</p>
                <p>The participants were chosen randomly, dividing them into two groups:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet" id="list1-20587384211031107">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>A: Experimental group. Each study participant was given a bottle of 28
probiotic tablets.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>B: Control group. Each study participant was given a bottle of 28 placebo
tablets.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
                <p>Each child entered into each group randomly.</p>
                <list list-type="bullet" id="list2-20587384211031107">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Group of children belonging to the study group: red color.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Group of children belonging to the control group: blue color.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
                <p>Randomization was performed following the two basic principles of
equiprobabilistic allocation of each subject to one of the two treatments and
concealment of random allocation.</p>
                <p>The equiprobabilistic allocation of each unit of analysis is assigned using an
allocation method based on the alphabetical order of the children’s surnames
(from A to M one group and from N to Z the other). Both groups were created and
drawn by an external researcher through a random process (generation of an
odd/even number to assign to one of the two groups).</p>
                <p>The researcher did not know to which group each subject would be assigned when
asked for informed consent, thus ensuring the concealment of the assignment
sequence.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section5-20587384211031107">
                <title>Intervention</title>
                <p>The probiotic tablets (BioGaia AB, Lund, Sweden) contained two strains <italic toggle="yes">of
Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">DSM 17938</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ATCC
PTA 5289</italic>) at a dose of 1 × 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/tablet, respectively.
The placebo tablet was identical in size and composition but contained no
probiotic strains. Both types of tablets were provided by BioGaia AB (Lund,
Sweden). The two groups were differentiated by a color code. All clinical
recordings, as well as the laboratory tests, were carried out without knowledge
of the group to which the subjects were assigned. The tablets were packed in
identical containers carrying the name of the subject. The tutors of each course
were responsible for safekeeping the containers in the staff room of the school.
In the morning, the tutor delivered a tablet to each student before the break
(11:00 a.m.). On Friday the tutor gave each participant a bag with two tablets
for the weekend. This procedure was repeated during the 28 days of the study.
Participants failing to take a tablet were withdrawn from the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section6-20587384211031107">
                <title>Evaluation of microbial, salivary pH, and periodontal indices</title>
                <p>Samples of paraffin-stimulated whole saliva were obtained immediately before
(baseline) and at 14, 28 and 45 days (follow-up) to assess salivary pH,
<italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> sp.,
<italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus mutans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus sp.</italic>
were evaluated using Dentocult<sup>®</sup> SM (Orion<sup>®</sup>) and
Dentocult<sup>®</sup> LB (Orion<sup>®</sup>), in accordance with the
instructions of the manufacturer.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p>
                <p>The collection of saliva samples and the measurement of the indices and salivary
pH were carried out between 9 and 11 a.m. in classrooms prepared previously with
the material on the table. A single operator was responsible for analyzing all
the samples obtained, with the collaboration of the students of the Master in
Pediatric Dentistry of Universidad Cardenal Herrera-CEU (Valencia, Spain) and
duly trained school staff—controlling that the process was carried in the most
exact way possible.</p>
                <p>The plaque, gingivitis, and bleeding indices were assessed under baseline
conditions and at 7, 14, 21, 28, and 45 days. Dietary and oral hygiene habits
were also evaluated by means of a questionnaire. For its validation, the
questionnaire was handed to five pediatric dentistry professors at CEU-Cardenal
Herrera University. They were asked to complete it and indicate whether they
considered if any of the proposed questions were difficult to understand,
inappropriate, ambiguous, or inadequate. Finally, they were asked to make any
suggestions they might have in order to improve the questionnaire.</p>
                <p>Once the questionnaire had been corrected with the contributions of the
specialists, it was examined by a statistician in order to achieve an optimal
data collection that would allow a correct statistical analysis of the data.</p>
                <p>After the modifications of the statistician, a pilot test was carried out by
giving the questionnaire to five parents, who subsequently did not participate
in the study, to check that the questions were properly understood and could be
answered appropriately. At the end of the pilot test, the final changes were
made to the wording of the questionnaire, thus concluding its validation.</p>
                <p>For measurement of the plaque index, we chose the qualitative Silness and Löe index,<sup><xref rid="bibr18-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> which allows recording of the different degrees of intensity of bacterial
plaque accumulation. The Ramfjord index teeth was considered for the
measurements: 16–21–24–36–41–44. A periodontal probe was passed over these
teeth, on the four faces of each tooth (buccal, lingual/palatine, mesial, and
distal), with evaluation according to the amount of plaque present.</p>
                <p>The Silness and Löe index<sup><xref rid="bibr18-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> was also used to measure the gingival index, likewise based on the
Ramfjord index teeth: 16–21–24–36–41–44. The procedure was the same as in the
case of the plaque index, and the values were recorded according to the degree
of inflammation observed.</p>
                <p>Lastly, we evaluated the simplified bleeding rate,<sup><xref rid="bibr18-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> likewise based on the Ramfjord index teeth.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section7-20587384211031107">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The data were processed with the SPSS<sup>®</sup> version 18.0 statistical
package (Chicago, IL, USA) and subjected to one-way analysis of covariance
(ANCOVA). Comparisons of qualitative variables were made using a two-tailed
chi-squared test. Statistical significance was considered for <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
&lt; 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="section8-20587384211031107">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>A total of 12 participants in the experimental group and 15 in the control group
participants completed the entire study period because 3 children did not attend any
of the scheduled checkups (<xref rid="fig1-20587384211031107" ref-type="fig">Figure
1</xref>).</p>
              <fig position="float" id="fig1-20587384211031107">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Flowchart of the study, indicating the methodological stages (left) and
characteristics of the study groups and their follow-up (right).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_20587384211031107-fig1" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <sec id="section9-20587384211031107">
                <title>Microbial evaluation</title>
                <p>The baseline and follow-up levels of salivary <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans and Lactobacillus
sp.</italic> are reported in <xref rid="table1-20587384211031107" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. A beneficial effect of the
probiotic upon <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic> collected in saliva was observed. The
probiotic was associated with maintenance of the levels of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus
sp</italic>., though no statistically significant results were observed on
comparing the two groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="table1-20587384211031107">
                  <label>Table 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Analysis of the longitudinal effect of the use of probiotics upon the
levels of <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans, Lactobacillus sp</italic>., and salivary
pH.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_20587384211031107-table1" position="float"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Day of study</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus sp.</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Salivary pH</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probiotic</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect (SEM)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probiotic</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect (SEM)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probiotic</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect (SEM)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 ± 0.064</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 ± 0.80</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70 ± 0.48</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38 ± 0.47</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.23 ± 0.17</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25 ± 0.21</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 ± 1.18</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 ± 0.91</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20 (0.291)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48 ± 0.95</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36 ± 0.66</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013 (0.237)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.27 ± 0.23</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35 ± 0.25</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.040 (0.038)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 ± 0.65</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 ± 0.81</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.059 (0.239)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29 ± 0.47</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19 ± 0.40</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091 (0.162)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.39 ± 0.14</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.39 ± 0.14</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.026 (0.056)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 ± 0.75</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 ± 0.93</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.188 (0.309)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17 ± 0.39</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07 ± 0.26</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099 (0.127)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28 ± 0.16</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28 ± 0.16</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061 (0.060)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="table-fn1-20587384211031107">
                      <p>Effect: difference between both groups estimated on the baseline
level of the indicator; SEM: standard error of the mean.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section10-20587384211031107">
                <title>Salivary pH and periodontal indices</title>
                <p>An increase in salivary pH was observed in the probiotic group, though with no
statistically significant difference between the two groups (<xref rid="table1-20587384211031107" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The data
corresponding to the plaque, gingival, and bleeding indices are reported in
<xref rid="table2-20587384211031107" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The
effect of probiotic use upon the plaque and gingival indices was found to be
beneficial in comparison with the group of adolescents administered placebo
tablets—though statistical significance was not reached (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt;
0.05). With regard to the bleeding index, the results were nonsignificant, since
the effect of probiotic use upon this index was variable. As in the case of the
gingival index, there was a clearly significant rebound effect.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="table2-20587384211031107">
                  <label>Table 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Analysis of the longitudinal effect of the use of probiotics upon the
plaque, gingivitis, and bleeding indices.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_20587384211031107-table2" position="float"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Day of study</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Plaque index</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gingivitis index</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Bleeding index</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probiotic</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect (SEM)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probiotic</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect (SEM)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probiotic</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect (SEM)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 ± 0.44</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 ± 0.43</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 ± 0.36</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ± 0.33</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 ± 0.05</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 ± 0.07</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 ± 0.29</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.30</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.035 (0.071)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 ± 0.33</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.40</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.046 (0.084)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068 ± 0.088</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087 ± 0.12</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.013 (0.025)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 ± 0.39</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 ± 0.35</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114 (0.096)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 ± 0.34</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 ± 0.32</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058 (0.100)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102 ± 0.096</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091 ± 0.99</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022 (0.027)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 ± 0.35</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 ± 0.34</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.070 (0.100)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 ± 0.31</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 ± 0.31</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.026 (0.111)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067 ± 0.089</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085 ± 0.091</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.011 (0.032)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 ± 0.36</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 ± 0.26</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035 (0.106)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 ± 0.29</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 ± 0.26</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.061 (0.099)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085 ± 0.099</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063 ± 0.077</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028 (0.032)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 ± 0.32</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 ± 0.27</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067 (0.103)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 ± 0.26</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 ± 0.39</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065 (0.139)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.255 ± 0.149</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157 ± 0.126</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105 (0.54)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="table-fn2-20587384211031107">
                      <p>Effect: difference between both groups estimated on the baseline
level of the indicator; SEM: standard error of the mean.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section11-20587384211031107">
                <title>Oral health indices</title>
                <p>The relationship between the oral health indices and dietary and oral hygiene
habits is presented in <xref rid="table3-20587384211031107" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Poorer eating habits and oral hygiene were significantly
correlated to increased plaque (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). There were no
significant differences in the age of the subjects with regard to eating and
hygiene habits, except in the frequency of brushing after meals. In effect,
those under 14 years of age brushed their teeth less frequently than those over
14 years of age, with higher levels of bleeding gums.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="table3-20587384211031107">
                  <label>Table 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Nonparametric correlations between the scores obtained in the study and
the oral health indicators.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_20587384211031107-table3" position="float"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total score</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diet score</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hygiene score</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plaque index</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.384<xref rid="table-fn3-20587384211031107" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gingivitis index</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.260</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bleeding index</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.061</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.061</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.165</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salivary pH</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic>
                          </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.200</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus sp.</italic> log10</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.261</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.287</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.036</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="table-fn3-20587384211031107">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p>
                        <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                        <italic toggle="yes">&lt;</italic>
                        <italic toggle="yes">0.05.</italic>
                      </p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="section12-20587384211031107">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In recent years, research on the use of probiotics for the prevention of dental and
periodontal diseases has progressed considerably, with advances in the
characterization of specific probiotic strains, and of the quantities and frequency
of administration needed to secure beneficial effects in certain oral
disorders.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bibr14-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> In our series no statistically significant variations were
found in the gingival parameters between the study group and the control group, in
coincidence with the observations of Sinkiewicz et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr19-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> and Iniesta et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> It should be noted that the combination of strains used differed between our
study and that of Sinkiewicz et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In effect, Sinkiewicz et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr19-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> used <italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri ATCC 55730</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ATCC PTA
5289</italic>. Iniesta et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr20-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> in turn used the same strains as in our study (<italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri ATCC PTA
5289</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">DSM 17938</italic>), though with methodological
differences versus our own series. Shimauchi et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr21-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> and Mayanagi et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr22-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> studied the effects of <italic toggle="yes">L. salivarius</italic> on periodontal
parameters such as probing depth, gingival index, bleeding index, and plaque index.
In both studies, improvement in periodontal health was observed among smokers.
Similar results have been reported by Krasse et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr23-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> and Vivekananda et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr24-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> where the use of <italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri</italic> also resulted in improvement of
the aforementioned parameters in a population of smokers. However, it must be noted
that these studies differed from our own in terms of the age of the subjects.</p>
              <p>It is not clear how long probiotics remain in saliva once their administration
ceases.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr25-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Yli-Knuuttila et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr26-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> observed that after administering the probiotic <italic toggle="yes">LGG</italic> for 14
days, the counts in the oral cavity gradually decreased—indicating that there is no
permanent colonization, and that the oral persistence of <italic toggle="yes">LGG</italic> is
only temporary. Caglar et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr25-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> likewise showed that the presence of <italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri</italic> in saliva is
only temporary and disappears once administration of the probiotic is suspended. In
our series, a probiotic tablet prepared with a combination of strains of <italic toggle="yes">L.
reuteri DSM 17936</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ATCC PTA 5289</italic> was used in the
study group. Caglar et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> used the probiotic <italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri ATCC 55730</italic> in
some of their investigations. In one of these studies,<sup><xref rid="bibr28-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> they evaluated the effect of chewing gum containing xylitol and probiotic on
the salivary counts of <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus
sp</italic>. A statistically significant decrease in <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic>
levels was recorded. However, there were no changes in the salivary counts of
<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus sp.</italic> In another study by these same authors,<sup><xref rid="bibr27-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> the probiotics were administered in two different vehicles: one consisted of
a straw containing the probiotic while the other was a tablet containing the
probiotic. In this study a statistically significant decrease in <italic toggle="yes">S.
mutans</italic> levels was likewise observed. A similar but nonsignificant trend
was observed for <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus sp.</italic> In coincidence with our own
findings, it can be concluded from these studies<sup><xref rid="bibr27-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> that probiotic use results in
a beneficial effect in terms of the salivary counts of <italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic>,
though in the case of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus sp.</italic> the results vary, and the
levels did not always tend to decrease as they did in our series.</p>
              <p>Finally, we analyzed the relationship between the oral health indexes and dietary and
oral hygiene habits recorded by means of a questionnaire, as well as the
relationship between dietary and oral hygiene habits and subject age and sex. Poorer
eating habits and oral hygiene were significantly correlated to increased plaque, in
coincidence with the observations of Tinanoff et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bibr30-20587384211031107" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> In conclusion, the study
parameters were seen to decrease with the two strains of <italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri DSM
17938</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ATCC PTA 5289</italic>, though the results failed to
reach statistical significance- possibly because of the small sample size
involved.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section13-20587384211031107">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>The administration of a daily tablet of two strains of <italic toggle="yes">L. reuteri (DSM
17938</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ATCC PTA 5289)</italic> for 28 days had an effect on
the decrease of the study parameters. Further studies must be carried out to learn
more about the sustained action of probiotic bacteria upon the oral cavity, as well
as their colonization and biofilm formation capacity, in order to elucidate how they
affect the resident flora.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="section14-20587384211031107" specific-use="figshare">
              <title>Supplemental Material</title>
              <supplementary-material id="suppl1-20587384211031107" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <caption>
                  <title>sj-pdf-1-iji-10.1177_20587384211031107 – Supplemental material for The
use of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> DSM 17938 and ATCC PTA 5289 on
oral health indexes in a school population: A pilot randomized clinical
trial</title>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="sj-pdf-1-iji-10.1177_20587384211031107.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
                <p>Supplemental material, sj-pdf-1-iji-10.1177_20587384211031107 for The use of
<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> DSM 17938 and ATCC PTA 5289 on oral
health indexes in a school population: A pilot randomized clinical trial by
Carla Borrell García, Marta Ribelles Llop, Maria Ángeles García Esparza, Antonio
Juan Flichy-Fernández, Laura Marqués Martínez and Regina Izquierdo Fort in
International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</p>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>The skilful help of all volunteers who worked in the study was greatly aprreciated.
The study was supported by the material provided by BioGaia AB, Sweden, and the
installations of the University Cardenal Herrera-CEU and Escolapias School,
Spain.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or
publication of this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Ethical approval:</bold> The study was conducted in accordance with the recommendations of the Declaration
of Helsinki, and was approved by the local Ethics Committee (registration
number: CEI18/067).</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Informed consent:</bold> Written informed consent was obtained from legally authorized representatives
before the study.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Trial registration:</bold> This randomized clinical trial was not registered because being a pilot study
this research reported on feasibility of a larger study.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Carla Borrell García <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_20587384211031107-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9356-4416" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9356-4416</ext-link></p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> Supplemental material for this article is available online.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bibr1-20587384211031107">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>FAO/WHO J</collab> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Report of a joint
FAO/WHO expert consultation on guidelines for the evaluation of probiotics
in food</article-title>. <publisher-name>World Health Organization and Food
and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Ontario, Canada</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr2-20587384211031107">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flichy-Fernández</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alegre-Domingo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Peñarrocha-Oltra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peñarrocha-Diago</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Probiotic treatment in the
oral cavity: An update</article-title>. <source>Medicina Oral, Patología
Oral y Cirugía Bucal</source>
<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>677</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr3-20587384211031107">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Floch</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>)
<article-title>Recomendations for probiotic use-2011 update</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Clinical Gastroenterology</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr4-20587384211031107">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twetman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecksén-Blicks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Probiotics and oral health
effects in children</article-title>. <source>International Journal of
Paediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18086020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr5-20587384211031107">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twetman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Are we ready for caries
prevention through bacteriotherapy?</article-title>
<source>Brazilian Oral Research</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr6-20587384211031107">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cortés-Dorantes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Rodríguez</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Karakowsky-Kleiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2019</year>)
<article-title>Probiotics and their effect on oral bacteria count in
children: A pilot study</article-title>. <source>European Journal of
Paediatric Dentistry</source><volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30919640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr7-20587384211031107">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceyhan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirzioglu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>An educational programme
designed for the evaluation of effectiveness of two tooth brushing
techniques in preschool children</article-title>. <source>European Journal
of Paediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30063148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr8-20587384211031107">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giugliano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>d’Apuzzo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Majorana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2018</year>)
<article-title>Influence of occlusal characteristics food intake and oral
hygiene habits on dental caries in adolescents: A cross-sectional
study</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Paediatric
Dentistry</source><volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29790772</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr9-20587384211031107">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paglia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>WHO healthy diet to prevent
chronic diseases and caries</article-title>. <source>European Journal of
Paediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29569446</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr10-20587384211031107">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libonati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Taranto</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mea</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Clinical
antibacterial effectiveness Healozone Technology after incomplete caries
removal</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Paediatric
Dentistry</source><volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30919649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr11-20587384211031107">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Probiotics in human
medicine</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>
<volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1902810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr12-20587384211031107">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Çaglar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kargul</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanboga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Bacteriotherapy and
probiotics’ role on oral health</article-title>. <source>Oral
Diseases</source>
<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15888102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr13-20587384211031107">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Meurman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Probiotics and periodontal
disease</article-title>. <source>Periodontology 2000</source>
<volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19878473</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr14-20587384211031107">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alkaya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Laleman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Keceli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Clinical
effects of probiotics containing Bacillus species on gingivitis: A pilot
randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Periodontal
Research</source><volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27859252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr15-20587384211031107">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flichy-Fernández</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ata-Ali</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alegre-Domingo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The
effect of orally administered probiotic Lactobacillus reuteri-containing
tablets in peri-implant mucositis: A double-blind randomized controlled
trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Periodontal Research</source><volume>50</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>775</fpage>–<lpage>785</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25712760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr16-20587384211031107">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahasneh</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecksén-Blicks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Probiotics and oral health
effects in children</article-title>. <source>International Journal of
Paediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18086020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr17-20587384211031107">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>A
comparison between comercial kits and conventional methods for enumeration
of salivary mutans streptococci and lactobacilli</article-title>.
<source>Community Dental Health</source><volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1450999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr18-20587384211031107">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agulló</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Loscos</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchís</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>)
<article-title>Importancia del uso de índices en la práctica periodontal
diaria del higienista dental</article-title>. <source>Periodoncia: Sociedad
Española de Periodoncia</source><volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr19-20587384211031107">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinkiewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronholm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljunggren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>)
<article-title>Influence of dietary supplementation with Lactobacillus
reuteri on the oral flora of healthy subjects</article-title>.
<source>Swedish Dental Journal</source><volume>34</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21306085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr20-20587384211031107">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iniesta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>)
<article-title>Probiotic effects of orally administered Lactobacillus
reuteri-containing tablets on the subgingival and salivary microbiota in
patients with gingivitis. A randomized clinical trial</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Clinical Periodontology</source><volume>39</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):
<fpage>736</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22694350</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr21-20587384211031107">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimauchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayanagi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>)
<article-title>Improvement of periodontal condition by probiotics with
Lactobacillus salivarius WB21: A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical
Periodontology</source><volume>35</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):
<fpage>897</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18727656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr22-20587384211031107">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayanagi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>)
<article-title>Probiotic effects of orally administered Lactobacillus
salivarius WB21-containing tablets on periodontopathic bacteria: A
double-blinded, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical
trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Periodontology</source><volume>36</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>506</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19453574</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr23-20587384211031107">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krasse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>)
<article-title>Decreased gum bleeding and reduced gingivitis by the
probiotic Lactobacillus reuteri</article-title>. <source>Swedish Dental
Journal</source><volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16878680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr24-20587384211031107">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vivekananda</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandana</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Effect of the probiotic
Lactobacilli reuteri (Prodentis) in the management of periodontal disease: A
preliminary randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Oral Microbiology</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>5344</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr25-20587384211031107">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Topcuoglu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cildir</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Oral
colonization by Lactobacillus reuteri ATCC 55730 after exposure to
probiotics</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Paediatric
Dentistry</source><volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19486373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr26-20587384211031107">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yli-Knuuttila</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Snäll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kari</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>)
<article-title>Colonization of Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG in the oral
cavity</article-title>. <source>Oral Microbiology and Immunology</source><volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr27-20587384211031107">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavaloglu Cildir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ergeneli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Salivary
mutans streptococci and lactobacilli levels after ingestion of the probiotic
bacterium Lactobacillus reuteri ATCC 55730 by straws or
tablets</article-title>. <source>Acta Odontologica Scandinavica</source><volume>64</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16945898</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr28-20587384211031107">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavaloglu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuscu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Effect
of chewing gums containing xylitol or probiotic bacteria on salivary mutans
streptococci and lactobacilli</article-title>. <source>Clinical Oral
Investigations</source><volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17574481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr29-20587384211031107">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tinanoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Dietary determinants of
dental caries and dietary recommendations for preschool
children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Health
Dentistry</source>
<volume>60</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11109219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr30-20587384211031107">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tinanoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanellis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Current understanding of the
epidemiology, mechanisms, and prevention of dental caries in preschool
children</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>551</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12528947</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
