<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:39:05Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9645180" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9645180</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-11-14</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bdj</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz Dent J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz Dent J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bdj</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Brazilian Dental Journal</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0103-6440</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4760</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Fundação Odontológica de Ribeirão Preto</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9645180</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9645180</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9645180</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36043569</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36043569</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0103-6440202204808</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Development of a sodium fluoride and stannous chloride-containing gel
for treatment of dental erosion </article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0068-8218</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pereira</surname>
                    <given-names>Laís Gatti de Souza</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6273-0426</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bezerra</surname>
                    <given-names>Sávio José Cardoso</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7252-6616</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Viana</surname>
                    <given-names>Ítallo Emídio Lira</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8016-9636</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Lima</surname>
                    <given-names>Leonardo Custódio</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7686-089X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Borges</surname>
                    <given-names>Alessandra Bühler</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4445-6697</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Scaramucci</surname>
                    <given-names>Taís</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Department of Restorative Dentistry, University of São Paulo,
School of Dentistry. Av. Prof. Lineu Prestes 2227, São Paulo, SP, Brazil,
05508-000.</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Department of Restorative Dentistry at Institute of Science and
Technology of São José dos Campos, UNESP, São Paulo State University. Av. Engenheiro
Francisco José Longo 777, São José dos Campos, SP, Brazil, 12245-000.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Correspondence: Taís Scaramucci - Department of Restorative
Dentistry, School of Dentistry; University of São Paulo; Av. Prof. Lineu Prestes
2227, São Paulo, SP, Brazil, 05508-000. Phone: +55 11 26488021 E-mail:
<email>tais.sca@usp.br</email>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <season>Jul-Aug</season>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>33</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>54</fpage>
              <lpage>61</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>06</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>Este é um artigo publicado em acesso aberto sob uma licença Creative
Commons</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract:</title>
                <p>This study synthesized and tested experimental gels containing fluoride
(F<sup>-</sup>) and stannous (Sn<sup>2+</sup>) ions for the control of
dental erosion. Enamel and dentin polished specimens were eroded (1% citric acid
solution, 10 min) and randomly allocated into 5 groups (n=10): Placebo -
Hydroxypropyl Methylcellulose (HMC) gel; F+Sn+HMC - 7,500 ppm F<sup>-</sup> /
15,000 ppm Sn<sup>2+</sup>; F+HMC - 7,500 ppm F<sup>-</sup>; Commercial
acidulated phosphate fluoride gel (12,300 ppm F<sup>-</sup>); and Control - no
treatment. After treatment (applied for 60 s), specimens underwent an
erosion-remineralization cycling (5 min in 0.3% citric acid solution, 60 min in
artificial saliva, 4×/day, 20 days). Surface loss (SL, in µm) was determined
after the 5<sup>th</sup>, 10<sup>th</sup> and 20<sup>th</sup> days of cycling
(α=0.05). For enamel, after 5 and 10 days, F+Sn+HMC presented the lowest SL,
which did not differ from the commercial gel. After 20 days, no differences were
found between commercial, F+HMC, and F+Sn+HMC groups. Placebo did not differ
from the control at any time points, and both groups presented the highest SL
when compared to the other groups. For dentin, on the 5th day, F+Sn+HMC, F+HMC
and commercial did not differ significantly, showing lower SL than the control
and the placebo. On the 10th day, F+Sn+HMC and commercial presented the lowest
SL compared to control and placebo. After 20 days, only the commercial gel
showed lower SL than the control and placebo. Thus, the experimental F+Sn+HMC
gel was able to control the progression of tooth erosion.</p>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <title>Resumo</title>
                <p>Este estudo desenvolveu e testou géis experimentais contendo íons fluoreto
(F<sup>-</sup>) e estanho (Sn<sup>2+</sup>) para o controle da erosão
dentária. Os espécimes polidos, de esmalte e dentina, foram previamente erodidos
(solução de ácido cítrico a 1%, 10 min) e alocados aleatoriamente em 5 grupos (n
= 10): Placebo - gel de hidroxipropilmetilcelulose (HMC); F + Sn + HMC - 7.500
ppm F<sup>-</sup> / 15.000 ppm Sn<sup>2+</sup>; F + HMC - 7.500 ppm
F<sup>-</sup>; Gel de flúor fosfato acidulado comercial (12.300 ppm F-); e
Controle - sem tratamento. Após o tratamento (aplicado por 60 s), os espécimes
foram submetidos a uma ciclagem de erosão-remineralização (5 min em solução de
ácido cítrico a 0,3%, 60 min em saliva artificial, 4 × / dia, 20 dias). A perda
de superfície (SL, em µm) foi determinada após o 5º, 10º e 20º dias de ciclagem
(α = 0,05). Para o esmalte, após 5 e 10 dias, o F + Sn + HMC apresentou a menor
PS, não diferindo do gel comercial. Após 20 dias, não foram encontradas
diferenças entre os grupos comercial, F + HMC e F + Sn + HMC. O placebo não
diferiu do controle em nenhum momento, e ambos os grupos apresentaram a maior
PS, comparado aos demais grupos. Para dentina, no 5º dia , F + Sn + HMC, F + HMC
e comercial não diferiram significativamente, apresentando menor PS que o grupo
controle e placebo. No 10º dia, F+Sn+HMC e comercial apresentaram a menor PS
comparado ao grupo controle e placebo. No 20º dia, apenas o gel comercial
apresentou PS menor que o controle e o placebo. Assim, o gel experimental F + Sn
+ HMC foi capaz de controlar a progressão da erosão dentária.</p>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Key Words:</title>
                <kwd>erosive tooth wear</kwd>
                <kwd>dental erosion</kwd>
                <kwd>fluoride</kwd>
                <kwd>stannous</kwd>
                <kwd>gel</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível
Superior-Brasil (CAPES)</funding-source>
                  <award-id>88887.473434/2020-00</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP)</funding-source>
                  <award-id>2020/07986-2</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <funding-statement>“Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível
Superior-Brasil’’ (CAPES) - Finance Code : 88887.473434/2020-00, for the
scholarship of the first author, and grant #2020/07986-2, São Paulo Research
Foundation (FAPESP)</funding-statement>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="0"/>
                <table-count count="3"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="27"/>
                <page-count count="8"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Dental erosion is a superficial loss of dental hard tissues, which are chemically
etched away by acids of nonbacterial origin <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>. When this process is combined with the mechanical
forces that are commonly present at the oral environment, the term erosive tooth
wear is used, as the dental surfaces that were softened by the erosive acids become
more susceptible to be removed by these mechanical impacts <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>. This condition has a global prevalence estimated
in up to 45% in permanent teeth <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>.
It needs to be taken into account that, although some physiological tooth wear is
common to occur, it may become excessive when the pattern of surface loss is
disproportionate to the age <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>,
indicating the beginning of a pathological condition.</p>
              <p>Over the last decades, there has been a growing concern about the high prevalence of
erosive tooth wear that are found in many populations <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. With the decline in the caries rates, dental erosion
has become a condition of increasing interest <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Changes in dietary, social, and oral hygiene habits
commonly provide important explanations for the increased awareness about this
condition <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>. Considering the
irreversible nature of erosive tooth wear, it is important that the condition is
detected in its early stages, and that the professional investigates all the risk
factors involved, so that educational and preventive measures are undertaken <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>. Fluoride products has been
extensively used to prevent erosion, as it can protect the dental surfaces against
dissolution, although it has a limited effect <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>In this regard, when conventional fluoride products, such as sodium fluoride (NaF)
are used, depending on the concentration of the product and its pH, calcium fluoride
can deposit over the dental surfaces, which can act as a barrier against
demineralization <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. The formation
of CaF<sub>2</sub>-like deposits is optimized with highly concentrated and low pH
formulas, but this not often occurs with over-the-counter products <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. In this context, products meant to
be used professionally stands out as an interesting approach to improve fluoride
exposure in subjects with high risk of erosive tooth wear, and they have been
showing positive results in previous investigations <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>. Moreover, the use of polyvalent metal fluorides, such
as stannous ion-containing fluoride products, may promote greater protection against
erosion than the ones containing fluoride only <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>. This is mainly because of the incorporation of
stannous ions into the dental substrates under cyclic conditions, making it more
resistant to acid dissolution <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>,
and to the formation of a metal-rich surface layer.</p>
              <p>So far, there are a few over-the-counter products containing fluoride and stannous
ions; however, highly concentrated formulas containing these compounds, which are
intended for professional application, would be interesting, since they can also
allow the formation of more acid-resistant deposits at the tooth surfaces. Thus,
they could act as an extra support for high-risk individuals with low compliance to
the treatment. Even though the efficacy of the combination of these ions against
erosive tooth wear was well reported, according to our knowledge, in-office products
containing these agents are scarce. In view of the above-mentioned, the present in
vitro study aimed to develop a highly concentrated formulation containing sodium
fluoride and stannous chloride, to be used as a professional application product
targeting the prevention of erosive tooth wear, and to test the ability of this gel
to control the progression of enamel and dentin erosion. The study hypothesis was
that the experimental gel containing both stannous and fluoride (F<sup>+</sup>Sn)
would show a better ability to control the progression of erosion on enamel and
dentin in different experimental times.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>This study followed a randomized experimental design with one experimental
factor, surface treatment, at 5 levels: 1. HMC (placebo): gel containing
hydroxypropyl methylcellulose (no active ingredients), pH = 4.5; 2.
F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC: experimental gel containing sodium fluoride
- 7,500 ppm F<sup>-</sup>, plus stannous chloride - 15,000 ppm Sn<sup>2+</sup>,
and HMC, pH = 4.5; 3. F + HMC: experimental sodium fluoride gel 7,500 ppm
F<sup>-</sup>, and HMC, pH = 4.5; 4. commercial acidulated phosphate
fluoride - APF Gel (Nova DFL, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brasil): 12,300 ppm
F<sup>-</sup>, pH = 4.61; 5. control: no treatment.</p>
                <p> The anti-erosive effect of the treatments was tested in an
erosion-remineralization cycling model of 20 days, using enamel and dentin
specimens (n = 10) obtained from previously eroded bovine incisors. The response
variable was enamel and dentin surface loss (SL, in μm), measured at 5, 10 and
at the end of cycling with an optical profilometer.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Sample size calculation</title>
                <p>A pilot study (not shown) was performed to determine the concentrations of the
agents tested and the number of specimens per group. Sample size calculation was
made on G*Power 3.1. The difference between two means (paired test) was used,
considering an effect size of 12.41 for enamel and 8.15 for dentin, (=0.05 and a
power of 0.95. A sample size of 3 specimens per group was found, but based on
previous studies with the same methodology, we adopted n = 10.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Specimen preparation</title>
                <p>Bovine incisors from young and male cattle, with similar diet, were obtained from
a slaughterhouse and stored in 0.1% thymol solution under refrigeration at 4 °C
until the beginning of the experiment. After cleaning with periodontal curettes,
they were submitted to prophylaxis with Robinson’s brush coupled in a low-speed
hand piece, pumice powder, and water, and were then stored in distilled water at
4 °C until required. Fifty enamel and dentin slabs (4 mm × 4 mm × 2 mm) were
respectively cut from the crowns and the roots of bovine incisors, using an
automatic cutting machine (Isomet, Buehler, Lake Bluff, IL, EUA) and a saw,
under constant irrigation (4” x 0.012” x ½ - ERIOS, São Paulo, Brazil). The
slabs were embedded in acrylic resin (Varidur, Buehler). The resulting blocks
were flattened and polished, using the following sequence of abrasive papers:
800-, 1200- and 4000-grit (Buehler), under constant water cooling. At the end of
the polishing procedure, the specimens underwent an ultrasonic bath with
deionized water for 3 min. The specimens were submitted to profilometric
analysis to select specimens with surface curvature lower than 0.3 μm, without
fractures or any other visual imperfections. The mean (± standard deviation) of
the baseline values were 0.1908 μm (± 0.0713) for enamel and 0.1012 μm (±
0.0753) for dentin. Unplasticized polyvinyl chloride (UPVC) tapes were then
placed on the selected specimens’ polished surfaces, leaving a central window of
4 mm × 1 mm exposed for subsequent testing.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Specimens initial demineralization</title>
                <p>To simulate a previously eroded surface, specimens were immersed in 5 mL of 1%
citric acid solution (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Missouri, EUA; pH~2.3), for 10
min, at room temperature and without agitation. After, they were rinsed with
deionized water and the tapes were removed. The specimens were submitted to a
second profilometric analysis, in order to check the depth of the lesions
created. For enamel, the mean (± standard deviation) of surface loss was 3.7278
μm (±1.7886), and for dentin, 4.2793 μm (±3.1719). The specimens were then
randomly divided into the 5 experimental groups (n = 10/substrate).
Subsequently, the tapes were repositioned on the surface of the specimens for
the experimental procedures.</p>
                <p>Treatments’ application</p>
                <p>According to <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>, the concentration of
Sn<sup>2+</sup> (as SnCl<sub>2</sub>, Sigma-Aldrich) in the gel was chosen
using the stability of the gel as the main parameter (no sign of precipitation
or pH changes). The concentration of fluoride (as NaF, Sigma-Aldrich) was
determined in order to maintain the Sn/F ratio above 1.8, which had shown better
efficacy in previous investigations <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. In the Sn-containing gels, 2.3 g/L of D-gluconic
sodium salt (Sigma-Aldrich) was added for stability purposes. All the gels were
manipulated with 1.5% of hydroxypropyl methylcellulose (HMC, Embrafarma, São
Paulo, SP, Brasil) and had their pH adjusted to 4.5, with either concentrated
HCl or 1 M KOH solutions. The placebo gel was manipulated with only HMC, without
any active ingredients. The commercial gel had the pH measured in 4.61.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Formula of the gels used in the study.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gel</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manufacturer</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Composition</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo gel (HMC)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5% HMC, pH=4.5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium fluoride plus stannous chloride gel
(F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7500 ppm F<sup>-</sup> ;15000 ppm
Sn<sup>2+</sup>, 1.5% HMC, pH=4.5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium fluoride gel (F+HMC)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,500 ppm F<sup>-</sup>, 1.5% HMC,
pH=4.5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidulated phosphate fluor gel-APF
(Commercial)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NOVA DFL (Rio de Janeiro, Brasil)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,300 ppm F<sup>-</sup>, pH=4.5. Acidulated
Phosphate Fluoride Gel 1.23%; pH=4.61</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>The gels were applied in the exposed area of the specimens with a disposable
applicator, for 60 s, following the manufacturer’s recommendations of the
commercial gel. The excess of the gel was removed with cotton rolls and the
specimens were immersed for 30 min in artificial saliva (0.213 g/L
CaCl<sub>2</sub>*2H<sub>2</sub>O; 0.738 g/L KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>;
1.114 g/L KCl; 0.381 g/L NaCl; 12 g/L Tris Buffer, pH adjusted to 7.0 with
concentrated HCl solution).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Erosive cycling</title>
                <p>The specimens were subjected to an erosion-remineralization cycling model, which
consisted of 5-min immersion in 0.3% citric acid solution (natural pH of 2.6),
followed by 60-min exposure to artificial saliva <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. This procedure was repeated four times a day, for
20 days. For the first cycle of the first day (post gel application), the
erosive challenge was performed 30 min after saliva immersion. All the
experiment was conducted at room temperature (~22 °C) and under static
conditions. Overnight, the specimens were stored in humid environment, at 4
°C.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Surface Loss Determination</title>
                <p>After five, ten and twenty days of cycling, the tapes were removed from the
surface of the specimens and the profilometric analysis was conducted with an
optical profilometer (Proscan 2100). A central area of 2 mm long (X) × 1 mm wide
(Y) was scanned with the optical profilometer. The length covered both the
treated area and reference surfaces. The step size was set at 0.01 mm and the
number of steps at 200 in the (X) axle; and at 0.05 mm and 20, respectively, in
the (Y) axle. The depth of the treated area was calculated based on the
subtraction of the average height of the test area from the average height of
the two reference surfaces by using Proscan Application software v. 2.0.17. A
3-point height tool was applied. The calculated depth was considered as the
total surface loss. The dentin specimens were scanned moist to avoid retraction
of the eroded dentin collagen matrix.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Data of enamel and dentin were analyzed independently. For both substrates, data
were transformed to log, to satisfy the premises of normality and homogeneity,
analyzed by Shapiro-Wilk and Brown Forsythe tests, respectively. Data were then
evaluated with two-way repeated measures ANOVA and Tukey tests, considering a
level of significance of 5%. The SigmaPlot 13 software (Systat Software Inc.)
was used for the calculations. </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Enamel</title>
                <p>The means (SD) of surface loss (SL) on days 5, 10 and 20 are presented in <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Significant differences
(p&lt;0.001) were observed between the levels of the factor groups, experimental
times and in the interaction between groups and time. For all groups, SL
occurred gradually, with 20 days showing the greatest loss, followed by 10 days
and 5 days.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Means and standard deviations of enamel surface loss (in
μm).</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="10"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" colspan="10" rowspan="1">Experimental time </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Treatments</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 days </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">10 days </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">20 days </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Means</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Means</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Means</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.68</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.07</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.79</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2.15</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.36</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±4.79</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.21</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.99</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.65</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.17</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.86</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±4.78</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F + HMC</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.35</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.88</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.07</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.24</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.25</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3.94</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Commercial</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.49</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.26</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.92</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2.09</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.72</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3.85</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F+Sn+HMC</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.55</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.86</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.90</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.74</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.45</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2.77</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN1">
                        <p>*Different letters show statistically significant difference
between treatments at each time (p&lt;0.05).</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p> After 5 days of cycling, the F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC gel showed the
lowest SL (p&lt;0.001), not differing significantly only from the commercial gel
(p=0.125). The commercial gel also did not differ from the F<sup>+</sup>HMC gel
(p=0.199). The control and placebo groups showed significantly the highest SL,
with no significant difference between them (p=0.948).</p>
                <p>After 10 days of cycling, the results were maintained, with
F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC presenting the lowest SL (p&lt;0.001), not
differing significantly only from the commercial gel group (p=0.051). The
commercial gel group did not differ significantly from the F+HMC group
(p=0.522). The control and placebo groups maintained the highest SL, not
differing from each other (p=1).</p>
                <p>After 20 days, control and placebo maintained the highest SL, and did not differ
from each other (p=0.999). The other groups had lower SL values but did not
differ significantly (p&gt;0.05).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Dentin</title>
                <p>The means (SD) of surface loss on days 5, 10 and 20 are presented in <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Significant differences were
observed (p&lt;0.001) among the levels of the factor groups and times
(p&lt;0.001); however there was no significant difference in the interaction
(p=0.076). Similarly, to enamel, all groups showed progressive surface loss with
time, which was higher after 20 days, followed by 10 and 5 days.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t3">
                    <label>Table 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Means and standard deviations of dentin surface loss (in
µm)</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="10"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" colspan="10" rowspan="1">Experimental time </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Treatments</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 days </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">10 days </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">20 days </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Means</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Means</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Means</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.39</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.72</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.87</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">± 6.02</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.40</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±13.19</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.06</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±6.14</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.77</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±10.64</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.90</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±11.25</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F + HMC</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.15</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2.70</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.70</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">± 5.27</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.36</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">± 9.14</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Commercial</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.84</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2.37</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.47</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">± 3.53</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.01</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">± 7.30</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F+Sn+HMC</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.91</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3.61</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.25</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">± 3.22</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.29</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">± 1.43</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>After 5 days of cycling, the control and placebo showed significantly the highest
SL, with no significant difference between them (p&gt;0.05). The other groups
presented significantly lower SL, without significant difference among them
(p&lt;0.05).</p>
                <p>After 10 days of cycling, the commercial and F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC
groups showed significantly lower SL when compared to control and placebo
(p&lt;0.05), but they did not differ significantly from the F+HMC gel (p=0.921
and p=0.894, respectively). The placebo and the control were the groups that had
the highest SL, without differing significantly from each other (p=0.999) and
from the F+HMC gel group (p&gt;0.05).</p>
                <p>After 20 days of cycling, the control and the placebo showed the highest SL, not
differing significantly from F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC (p=0.278 and
p=0.408, respectively), which in turn did not differ significantly from the
other groups (p&gt;0.05). The other groups showed no significantly different SL
(p&gt;0.05).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Our study hypothesis was accepted for enamel, since the
F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC gel reduced the progression of erosion on this
substrate at all periods evaluated. Until the tenth day of cycling, the experimental
fluoride and stannous gel (F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC) showed higher protection
than the experimental gel containing fluoride only (F<sup>+</sup>HMC). This result
could be explained by the presence of stannous in the first gel, as the other
components of the formula were the same. Previous investigations have observed that
the combination between fluoride and stannous showed higher protection against
erosion than fluoride alone <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>.
This combination has the ability to form more acid-resistant precipitates on the
enamel surface. In addition, it has been observed that Sn<sup>2+</sup> can be
incorporated into the tooth structure under erosive cycling, making it less soluble
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>. Nevertheless, different from the
solutions, which are repeatly applied during cycling, in the present study, the gels
were applied only once before cycling on previously demineralized enamel. Although a
certain incorporation of stannous cannot be disregarded under such conditions, the
main mechanism of action of stannous was probably related to the formation of
deposits on surface, which may explain the lack of difference between the
F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC and F+HMC gels after twenty days of cycling. It
could be suggested that, after twenty days, the F<sup>-</sup>- and
Sn<sup>2+</sup>-containing deposits were removed by the several acid challenges.
This indicates that a combination of treatments would be preferable for high risk
individuals, where the protective effect of the gel would be complemented by the
daily use of over-the-counter products, such as the mouthrinses, which will also
allow the incorporation of stannous at depth.</p>
              <p>Interestingly, at all experimental times, the commercial gel (12,300 ppm
F<sup>-</sup>) did not differ significantly from the experimental gel
F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC, which has 4,800 ppm less F<sup>-</sup>. Although
one may wonder whether this is due to the higher fluoride concentration of the
commercial gel, which may have compensated for the absence of stannous, it was also
found that the commercial gel did not differ significantly from the F<sup>+</sup>HMC
gel (7,500 ppm F<sup>-</sup>). These results lead us to believe that there might be
a saturation point for the interaction between fluoride and enamel, from which no
greater protective effect can be observed, even with increasing concentrations <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. Hence, in the presence of
Sn<sup>2+</sup>, the fluoride concentration seems to play a secondary role, at
least in the range of the concentrations investigated.</p>
              <p>Subjects with high risk of erosive tooth wear might require the use of more
concentrated fluoride and stannous-containing products to achieve improved
protection. In fact, a previous study showed that a solution with 500 ppm
F<sup>-</sup> and 2,800 ppm Sn<sup>2+</sup> showed lower enamel surface loss due
to erosion than one with 500 ppm F<sup>-</sup> and 1,400 ppm Sn<sup>2+ (</sup><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>. However, to the best of our
knowledge, there are not many products containing higher concentrations of fluoride
and stannous commercially available. These products would be suitable to be used in
the dental offices, complementing the effect of daily use products, such as
toothpastes and mouthrinses. Nevertheless, it was found that not only the
concentration of these actives is important, but also the stannous/fluoride ratio of
the formulation. It was shown that a better efficacy is obtained with ratios of 1.8
and above <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. In line with this
result, for the F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC gel, we have adopted a ratio of 2.0
(15,000 ppm Sn<sup>2+</sup> and 7,500 ppm F<sup>-</sup>), aiming to achieve
optimized results. A lower concentration was also tested in a preliminary study, but
a lower protective effect was observed.</p>
              <p>For dentin, the experimental gel showed a superior protective effect than the placebo
only until the tenth day of cycling, thus our study hypothesis was only partially
accepted. This could be related to the lower protection provided by the combination
of fluoride and stannous on dentin, which may not have the same efficacy of enamel,
as it was also previously observed <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>. When in contact to erosive acids, dentin is
demineralized, exposing the collagen fibers. As the amount of degradable collagen
increases, the rate of demineralization decreases, once the demineralized organic
matrix serves as a barrier to ionic diffusion. Due to this, after an initial
demineralization, mineral loss can be almost completely inhibited, even under severe
erosive conditions <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>.
Nonetheless, the organic matrix of dentin acts as a diffusion barrier not only for
the acids, but also for the active ingredients. The negative charge of the matrix
reacts with positively charged cations such as stannous. Therefore, only unreacted
ions would protect the mineral content against demineralization <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. This could explain why the
presence of stannous has shown significant differences in effectiveness between
enamel and dentin. Additionally, it has been observed that in the presence of large
amounts of fluoride, the progression of dentin erosion can be completely hindered
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>. In fact, in the present
study, the commercial gel, with higher amount of fluoride was the only gel that
maintained the protection of dentin until the 20<sup>th</sup> day. Thus, it can be
suggested that, for this substrate, greater amounts of fluoride are more relevant
than the presence of stannous.</p>
              <p>It should be mentioned, however, that when the organic matrix of the dentin is
removed, the behavior of fluoride and stannous against erosion is similarly to that
observed in enamel <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>, and this is
probably a situation closer to the clinical scenario, as it is likely that the
organic matrix is degraded by enzymes present in the oral environment after its
exposure <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>. Thus, it is possible
to speculate that the F<sup>+</sup>Sn<sup>+</sup>HMC gel would present an
improvement in dentin protection under clinical conditions, justifying further
investigations.</p>
              <p>Although in the literature there is evidence of products with higher concentrations
of stannous in solution than we adopted <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>, our concentration was determined based on previous
studies by our research group and on preliminary studies <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>. We chose to use the highest concentration of
stannous possible, having the stability of the solution as parameter. Possible
adverse effects, such as staining of restorations, burning sensation in the oral
mucosa and toxicity should not be an issue of great importance with the gel, as it
is meant to be used with a lower frequency and under controlled application, where
the possibility of ingestion by the patient should be reduced to a minimal <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>In the present study, it was used bovine instead of human specimens, because as
reported previously <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref>, a higher
number of specimens can be obtained from a single bovine tooth, allowing them to be
allocated into the different experimental groups, increasing their comparability. In
addition, although bovine teeth could show higher susceptibility to erosive wear
than human, this does not jeopardize the relative comparison among groups. Bovine
specimens were already used to evaluate the anti-erosive effect of different agents
on enamel <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> and dentin <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>For both substrates, the control and the placebo groups showed no significant
differences between them. To formulate the experimental gels, we had to use a
thickening polymer, the hydroxypropyl methylcellulose - HMC. Considering that some
polymers may also present an anti-erosive potential <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>, we included a group treated with a placebo gel in our
design, without any actives. This polymer was chosen because of its neutral charge
<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref>, which reduces the
possibility of interaction with the dental substrates.</p>
              <p>It is noteworthy that all the gels tested showed a progressive reduction in their
effectiveness through time, and none of them was able to completely inhibit the loss
of tooth structure. This reinforces the need to evaluate the association of in
office products with those intended for home use. Additionally, it should be taken
into consideration that more clinically relevant designs should be further
considered in future studies, such as assessing the effect of gels when
toothbrushing is present in the model, where there is greater surface loss of the
tooth surfaces and an increase in the concentration of fluoride in the oral
environment, which will be provided by the toothpastes. Considering the limitations
of this in vitro investigation, future in situ studies are needed to confirm the
effectiveness of this preventive measure, especially in combination with products
intended for daily use, and to define the best protocols of use. All in all, the
experimental fluoride and stannous gel can be considered as promising treatment,
because it was able to control the progression of the erosive process in enamel and
dentin similarly to the commercial gel, even with less amount of fluoride. However,
it showed some reduced effect in dentin after 20 days.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>The authors would like to thank the “Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de
Nível Superior-Brasil’’ (CAPES) - Finance Code : 88887.473434/2020-00, for the
scholarship of the first author, and grant #2020/07986-2, São Paulo Research
Foundation (FAPESP).</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlueter</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amaechi</surname>
                      <given-names>BT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bartlett</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buzalaf</surname>
                      <given-names>MAR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Terminology of Erosive Tooth Wear: Consensus Report of a Workshop
Organized by the ORCA and the Cariology Research Group of the
IADR</article-title>
                  <source>Caries Res</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>2</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31610535</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Addy</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shellis</surname>
                      <given-names>RP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Interaction between attrition, abrasion and erosion in tooth
wear</article-title>
                  <source>Monogr Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <lpage>31</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687882</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlueter</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luka</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Erosive tooth wear - a review on global prevalence and on its
prevalence in risk groups</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dent J</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <month>Mar</month>
                  <day>9</day>
                  <volume>224</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>364</fpage>
                  <lpage>370</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29495027</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dugmore</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rock</surname>
                      <given-names>WP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A multifactorial analysis of factors associated with dental
erosion</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dent J</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>196</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <lpage>273</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15017418</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Racki</surname>
                      <given-names>DNO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dalla Nora</surname>
                      <given-names>Â</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Comim</surname>
                      <given-names>LD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zenkner</surname>
                      <given-names>JEDA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alves</surname>
                      <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Erosive tooth wear among South Brazilian adolescents, and its
association with sociodemographic variables</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Oral Res</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>e119</fpage>
                  <lpage>e119</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31939499</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lussi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Erosive tooth wear: a multifactorial condition of growing concern
and increasing knowledge</article-title>
                  <source>Monogr Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>15</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24993253</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zanatta</surname>
                      <given-names>RF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caneppele</surname>
                      <given-names>TMF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scaramucci</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Dib</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maia</surname>
                      <given-names>LC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                      <given-names>DMTP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Protective effect of fluorides on erosion and erosion/abrasion in
enamel: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized in situ
trials</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>120</volume>
                  <fpage>104945</fpage>
                  <lpage>104945</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33113459</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magalhães</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiegand</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rios</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buzalaf</surname>
                      <given-names>MAR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lussi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fluoride in dental erosion</article-title>
                  <source>Monogr Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <lpage>170</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21701198</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petzold</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The influence of different fluoride compounds and treatment
conditions on dental enamel: a descriptive in vitro study of the CaF(2)
precipitation and microstructure</article-title>
                  <source>Caries Res</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <lpage>51</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11359058</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saunders</surname>
                      <given-names>JG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McIntyre</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The ability of 1.23% acidulated phosphate fluoride gel to inhibit
simulated endogenous erosion in tooth roots</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <lpage>266</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17016893</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soares</surname>
                      <given-names>LE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Protective effect of fluoride varnish and fluoride gel on enamel
erosion: roughness, SEM-EDS, and µ-EDXRF studies</article-title>
                  <source>Microsc Res Tech</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <lpage>248</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25626779</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sakae</surname>
                      <given-names>LO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bezerra</surname>
                      <given-names>SJC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>João-Souza</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borges</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aoki</surname>
                      <given-names>IV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aranha</surname>
                      <given-names>ACC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An in vitro study on the influence of viscosity and frequency of
application of fluoride/tin solutions on the progression of erosion of
bovine enamel</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <month>May</month>
                  <volume>89</volume>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <lpage>30</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29425811</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hardt</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lussi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cocks</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klimek</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlueter</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mechanism of action of tin-containing fluoride solutions as
anti-erosive agents in dentine - an in vitro tin-uptake, tissue loss, and
scanning electron microscopy study</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>118</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>376</fpage>
                  <lpage>384</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20662911</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlueter</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klimek</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of stannous and fluoride concentration in a mouth rinse on
erosive tissue loss in enamel in vitro</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>432</fpage>
                  <lpage>436</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19278669</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pereira</surname>
                      <given-names>LGS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joao-Souza</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bezerra</surname>
                      <given-names>SJC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borges</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aranha</surname>
                      <given-names>ACC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scaramucci</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Erratum to: Nd: YAG laser irradiation associated with fluoridated
gels containing photo absorbers in the prevention of enamel
erosion</article-title>
                  <source>Lasers Med Sci</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1461</fpage>
                  <lpage>1461</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28634633</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlueter</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neutard</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>von Hinckeldey</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klimek</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tin and fluoride as anti-erosive agents in enamel and dentine in
vitro</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Odontol Scand</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <lpage>184</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20095948</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>White</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>SB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barbour</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Churchley</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gracia</surname>
                      <given-names>LH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rees</surname>
                      <given-names>GD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inhibition of erosive dissolution by sodium fluoride: evidence
for a dose-response</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>654</fpage>
                  <lpage>660</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546265</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlueter</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klimek</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>In vitro efficacy of experimental tin- and fluoride-containing
mouth rinses as anti-erosive agents in enamel</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>944</fpage>
                  <lpage>948</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19660515</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scaramucci</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borges</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lippert</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zero</surname>
                      <given-names>DT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aoki</surname>
                      <given-names>IV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hara</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Anti-erosive properties of solutions containing fluoride and
different film-forming agents</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>458</fpage>
                  <lpage>465</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25625672</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klimek</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Starck</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Quantitative analysis of the impact of the organic matrix on the
fluoride effect on erosion progression in human dentine using longitudinal
microradiography</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>931</fpage>
                  <lpage>935</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15353250</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klimek</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brune</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schürmann</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of two fluoridation measures on erosion progression in
human enamel and dentine in situ</article-title>
                  <source>Caries Res</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>561</fpage>
                  <lpage>566</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528912</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lussi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sommer</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klimek</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlueter</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of fluoride compounds and stannous chloride as erosion
inhibitors in dentine</article-title>
                  <source>Caries Res</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <lpage>252</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20516684</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pai</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McIntyre</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tadic</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laparidis</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative uptake of fluoride ion into enamel from various
topical fluorides in vitro</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <month>Mar</month>
                  <volume>52</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17500163</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bezerra</surname>
                      <given-names>SJC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viana</surname>
                      <given-names>ÍEL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aoki</surname>
                      <given-names>IV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sobral</surname>
                      <given-names>MAP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borges</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hara</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Erosive tooth wear inhibition by hybrid coatings with
encapsulated fluoride and stannous ions</article-title>
                  <source>J Mater Sci Mater Med</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <lpage>83</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34212232</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boehncke</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koennecker</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mangelsdorf</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wibbertmann</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Concise international chemical assessment document
6</article-title>
                  <source>IPCS Concise Int Chem Assess Doc</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>37</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiegand</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Attin</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Design of erosion/abrasion studies--insights and rational
concepts</article-title>
                  <source>Caries Res</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <lpage>59</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21625133</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>CL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martini</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ford</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The use of hypromellose in oral drug delivery</article-title>
                  <source>J Pharm Pharmacol</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>533</fpage>
                  <lpage>546</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15901342</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
