<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10627419" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10627419</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-11-07</datestamp>
        <setSpec>dpjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dpjo</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2176-9451</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2177-6709</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dental Press International</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10627419</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10627419</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10627419</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37937683</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2177-6709.28.5.e232388.oar</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">00302</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Does leukocyte-platelet-rich fibrin (L-PRF) cause long term
acceleration in the rate of canine retraction? A split-mouth, two-arm parallel
group, randomized control trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3525-6618</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>GUPTA</surname>
                    <given-names>Seema</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Conception or design of the study</role>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                  <role>Overall responsibility</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4237-5113</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>BHAMBRI</surname>
                    <given-names>Eenal</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Conception or design of the study</role>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6711-1552</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>SHARMA</surname>
                    <given-names>Manish</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9693-0549</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>SHAIKH</surname>
                    <given-names>Mubasshir Ahmed</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7126-7373</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>ZOPE</surname>
                    <given-names>Amit</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0009-3010-0364</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>THOKE</surname>
                    <given-names>Bhushan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5381-1753</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>SOROKHAIBAM</surname>
                    <given-names>Monika</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                  <role>Overall responsibility</role>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>PM Dental College, Department of Orthodontics (Dhule, Maharashtra,
India).</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Surendera Dental College and Research Institute, Department of
Orthodontics (Sriganganagar, Rajasthan, India).</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>ACPM Dental College, Department of Oral Pathology (Dhule,
Maharashtra, India).</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">
                  <email>dreenal700@gmail.com</email>
                </corresp>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2">
                  <label>»</label>
                  <p> The authors report no commercial, proprietary or financial interest in the
products or companies described in this article.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>28</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <elocation-id>e232388</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>26</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>ABSTRACT</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective: </title>
                  <p>The present study was conducted to investigate the effects of
leukocyte-platelet-rich fibrin (L-PRF) on the rate of maxillary canine
retraction for a period of 5 months. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods: </title>
                  <p>A split-mouth study was conducted on 16 subjects (9 males and 7 females; age
range 17-25 years; mean age, 21.85±2.45 years) who required therapeutic
extraction of bilateral maxillary first premolars. After the initial
leveling and alignment, L-PRF plugs were placed in a randomly selected
extraction socket (Experimental Group), and the other side served as a
control (Control Group). Canine retraction was carried out by the activation
of nickel-titanium (NiTi) closed-coil springs delivering 150 g of force. The
rates of canine movement, canine rotation, tipping, root resorption, and
molar movement were assessed at monthly intervals for five months (T0-T5).
Pain, swelling and discomfort accompanying the procedure were assessed using
a Likert scale. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results: </title>
                  <p>The study revealed a significant increase in the rate of canine movement on
the experimental side in the first two months, and significant molar
anchorage loss was observed only in the first month for control side. There
were no statistically significant differences between the groups regarding
canine rotation, tipping, probing depth, root resorption, and pain
perception.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions: </title>
                  <p>The use of L-PRF plugs in extraction sockets considerably enhanced the rate
of canine movement only in the first two months, and long-term efficacy was
not observed in this study.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <title>RESUMO</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objetivo: </title>
                  <p>O presente estudo foi realizado para investigar os efeitos da fibrina rica em
leucócitos e plaquetas (L-PRF) na taxa de retração do canino superior,
durante um período de cinco meses. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Métodos: </title>
                  <p>Um estudo de boca dividida foi realizado em 16 indivíduos (9 homens e 7
mulheres; faixa etária de 17 a 25 anos; idade média de 21,85 ± 2,45 anos)
que precisavam de extração terapêutica dos primeiros pré-molares superiores
de ambos os lados. Após o nivelamento e o alinhamento iniciais, os
<italic>plugs</italic> de L-PRF foram colocados em um alvéolo
pós-extração, selecionado aleatoriamente (Grupo Experimental), e o outro
lado serviu como controle (Grupo Controle). A retração do canino foi
realizada pela ativação de molas fechadas de níquel-titânio (NiTi) com 150 g
de força. As taxas de movimentação do canino, rotação, inclinação e
reabsorção radicular do canino e movimentação do molar foram avaliadas em
intervalos mensais durante cinco meses (T0-T5). A dor, o inchaço e o
desconforto após o procedimento foram avaliados por meio de uma escala de
Likert. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Resultados: </title>
                  <p>O estudo revelou um aumento significativo na taxa de movimentação do canino
no lado experimental nos dois primeiros meses, e uma perda significativa de
ancoragem do molar foi observada apenas no primeiro mês no lado controle.
Não houve diferenças estatisticamente significativas entre os grupos, com
relação à percepção da dor e rotação, inclinação, profundidade de sondagem e
reabsorção radicular do canino.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusões: </title>
                  <p>O uso de <italic>plugs</italic> de L-PRF em alvéolos pós-extração aumentou
consideravelmente a taxa de movimentação do canino apenas nos dois primeiros
meses, não sendo observada uma eficácia em longo prazo.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords:</title>
                <kwd>L-PRF plugs</kwd>
                <kwd>Platelet concentrate</kwd>
                <kwd>Anchorage</kwd>
                <kwd>Orthodontic treatment</kwd>
                <kwd>Canine retraction</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="5"/>
                <table-count count="5"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="34"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>The duration of orthodontic treatment is an important concern for adult patients who
want their treatment to be completed as quickly as possible. Due to their busy
schedules, they desire a shorter course and less chair-side time.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Therefore, attempts have been made to accelerate orthodontic tooth movement
(OTM). Various surgically-assisted procedures, such as corticotomy, piezocision, and
micro-osteoperforation, have been used, but they are invasive in nature.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> On the other hand, non-surgical approaches<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> show conflicting results regarding side effects such as systemic
complications. </p>
              <p>One of the many strategies believed to be helpful in increasing OTM by enhancing the
production of a variety of growth factors<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> and effectively shortening the treatment duration is platelet-rich fibrin
(PRF), which was first explored in France by Choukroun et al.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Platelet concentrates are divided into two major categories depending on the
presence of leukocytes and fibrin: platelet-rich plasma [Pure form (P-PRP), and
leukocyte form (L-PRP)] and platelet-rich fibrin [pure form (P-PRF), and
leukocyte-platelet-rich fibrin (L-PRF)].<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> L-PRF has demonstrated more regular growth factor release from the delicate
and flexible fibrin matrix, cost effectiveness, easier preparation, and longer
effects than PRP.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>There are currently fewer human and animal studies on canine retraction using L-PRF
plugs. Only four studies have been found in the literature on the effects of L-PRF
plugs on OTM, and out of them, three studies were conducted for a period of two
months.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> The disparities in the results of the studies may be due to the assessment
techniques used to measure canine retraction. Two studies have used the distance
between the distal marginal ridge of the canine and the mesial marginal ridge of the
second premolar to assess the rate of canine movement. This led to confounding bias
in the studies, as reduction of this distance might be due to anchorage loss, which
was not assessed in the studies.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> The differences in the L-PRF preparation methods, platelet concentrates, and
observation periods also led to the controversial results found in these studies.
None of the studies evaluated anchorage loss and pain assessment in the patients.
Therefore, the present study aimed to determine the effects of L-PRF on the rate of
canine movement, anchorage loss, and pain perception, over a period of five
months.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>STUDY DESIGN</title>
                <p>A single-center, two-arm, randomized control trial with split-mouth design was
conducted on subjects recruited from the Department of Orthodontics at Surendera
Dental College and Research Institute (January 2021-July 2021). The split-mouth
design was chosen to avoid interpersonal variations in the study. Ethical
clearance was obtained from the Institutional Ethical Committee
(SDCRI/IEC/2020/012), and the trial was registered in the Clinical Trials
Registry of India (CTRI) (REF/2022/02/051837). Informed consent was obtained
from patients and/or legal guardians, prior to recruitment. The CONSORT
statement was followed as a guide for this study (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). </p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f1">
                    <label>Figure 1:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) flow
diagram.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-05-e232388-gf1" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>SAMPLE SIZE CALCULATION</title>
                <p>In this study, GPOWER statistical software (v. 3.1, Franz Faul, Universität Kiel,
Kiel, Germany) was used to evaluate the sample size, assuming a mean difference
and standard deviation (SD) of 0.55, type 1 error (α) of 0.05, and type 2 error
(β) of 0.1 to achieve a statistical power of 90%<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>. The resultant sample size was 15, but considering sample attrition, it
was decided to increase the sample size to 20. There was a sample attrition of 4
patients, due to changes in their residence; hence, the study was completed on
16 subjects. </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>RANDOMIZATION, ALLOCATION AND PATIENT SELECTION</title>
                <p>A 1:1 allocation and simple randomization procedure of drawing lots by one
investigator were used to allocate the side of the maxilla for placement of
L-PRF plugs (Experimental Group, n=16), while the opposing side served as the
split-mouth control, inducing secondary healing (Control Group; n=16). </p>
                <sec>
                  <title> PICOS criteria </title>
                  <p>
                    <list list-type="simple">
                      <list-item>
                        <p>» Population: Class II division 1 or Class I bimaxillary
protrusion patients requiring fixed mechanotherapy with first
premolar extractions.</p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>» Intervention: L-PRF plugs on the experimental side. </p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>» Comparison: Control side with no L-PRF plug placement. </p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>» Outcome: Primary outcome: Assessment of canine movement rate.
Secondary outcome: rate of molar movement, assessment of canine
angulation, root resorption, and pain perception. </p>
                      </list-item>
                    </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Study design: Randomized controlled trial. </p>
                  <p>The inclusion criteria were as follows: Subjects with Class II division 1
malocclusion or Class I bimaxillary protrusion, with relatively well-aligned
arches, normodivergent growth pattern (FMA = 25 ± 5°), postpubertal as
assessed by CVMI stage &gt; 5, requiring therapeutic bilateral first
premolar extractions with subsequent retraction of the canine, healthy oral
and systemic conditions (probing depth &lt;3 mm, plaque index &lt;1 mm, no
bleeding on probing), and no previous history of orthodontic treatment.
Patients taking medications that could interfere with orthodontic tooth
movement (NSAIDs, cortisone, hormones, anticoagulants), smoking, pregnancy,
restorations, or endodontic treatments on maxillary canines, and patients
with platelet disorders were excluded from the study.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>INTERVENTION</title>
                <p>After obtaining complete pretreatment records and thorough oral prophylaxis, all
patients started an orthodontic treatment procedure by one orthodontist, to
prevent operator bias, using pre-adjusted Edgewise brackets (MBT 0.022-in slot).
A soldered transpalatal arch (TPA), fabricated with 0.9mm stainless steel (SS)
wire was used for anchorage reinforcement and maintenance of the transverse
dimension. Leveling and alignment was started with a 0.014-in NiTi archwire, and
completed when a 0.016×0.022-in SS archwire was placed for one month. Following,
atraumatic extractions of maxillary first premolars and placement of L-PRF plugs
were performed. NiTi closed-coil springs (Ormco<sup>®</sup>, Orange,California,
USA) with a constant force of 150 g were used to retract the canines on both
sides (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). </p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f2">
                    <label>Figure 2:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Retraction of maxillary canine with NiTi closed coil
springs.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-05-e232388-gf2" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <sec>
                  <title> L-PRF preparation and placement </title>
                  <p>Using a 10-ml syringe, 9 ml whole venous blood sample was drawn quickly from
the brachial vein and placed into two sterile tubes without the use of an
anticoagulant (20-22 seconds on average). These tubes were then immediately
centrifuged (in less than a minute) at 2,700 rpm (about 400-g centrifugation
force, based on our estimations) for 12 minutes<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> in IntraSpin centrifuge system (Intra-Lock International Boca,
Raton, Fla). This caused a three-layer structure to form, with red blood
cells at the bottom, cellular plasma with a straw color at the top, and
platelets and a fibrin clot in the middle (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig
3</xref>A). The middle portion (L-PRF) was collected, 2mm below the
lower dividing line, after the upper straw-colored layer was removed, L-PRF
plugs (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>B) were placed in the
socket using sterile tweezers, and compressed with amalgam condenser. The
sockets were sutured using 4-0 vicryl sutures. Adhering to the protocols,
with proper management of time period, is very critical and therefore, were
carefully followed in the present study, to prevent dose- or
procedure-dependent errors.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p>
                  <p>
                    <fig position="float" id="f3">
                      <label>Figure 3:</label>
                      <caption>
                        <title>L-PRF preparation (A) and L-PRF plugs (B).</title>
                      </caption>
                      <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-05-e232388-gf3" position="float"/>
                    </fig>
                  </p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>OUTCOME ASSESSMENT</title>
                <p>All the required records, such as orthopantomograms (OPGs), intraoral periapical
radiographs (IOPARs), and probing depths for maxillary canines, were taken prior
to retraction (T0) and after 5 months (T5). Questionnaires for pain assessment
were given to each patient to complete at home and return on the next
appointment. Patients were discouraged from taking painkillers and when they
did, in the event of severe pain, they were advised to write it down. Patients
were recalled at intervals of 21 days for 5 months (T1-T5). Measurements were
made on dental casts according to the procedure described in a previous
study<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>, and presented bellow.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>MEASURING PROCEDURE</title>
                <sec>
                  <title> Evaluation of canine and first molar anteroposterior movement </title>
                  <p>The amount of canine and molar movement, and of canine rotation were assessed
using the method described by Zeigler and Ingervall<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). Photographs of the
study models were taken by placing them vertically on a glass plate at a
distance of 30 cm from the lens of the digital camera, as described by
Azevedo et al.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Before taking the photographs of the study model, the cusp tip of
the canine, median palatal raphae, and third rugae were marked with a
pencil. A perpendicular projection of the cusp tip of the canine and the
central fossae of the first molar was drawn on the median line. The distance
was measured from the medial rugae point of the third palatal rugae to
assess movements of the canine and first molar monthly, for five months. All
measurements were made using sliding digital calipers to the nearest 0.1 mm.
Angles were measured using a protractor to the nearest 0.5°. </p>
                  <p>
                    <fig position="float" id="f4">
                      <label>Figure 4:</label>
                      <caption>
                        <title>Schematic diagram depicting measurement of canine rotation
(a), canine movement (b) and molar movement (c).</title>
                      </caption>
                      <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-05-e232388-gf4" position="float"/>
                    </fig>
                  </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title> Evaluation of root resorption and periodontal health of the canine </title>
                  <p>Root resorption of the maxillary canine was assessed at T0 and T5 using
IOPARs, taking index scores from 0-4, as described by Levander and
Malmgren.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Probing depth and attachment loss were assessed using an UNC #15
periodontal probe.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title> Evaluation of rotation and mesiodistal tipping of canine </title>
                  <p>On the standardized photographs of the study models, the angle between the
median raphae and the line through the mesial and distal edges of the canine
was measured to assess canine rotation (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig
4</xref>). Canine angulation was assessed using an OPG with a line
through the orbital plane as a reference plane, as described by Ursi et
al.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title> Assessment of patient’s perception of pain, discomfort and satisfaction
towards the procedure </title>
                  <p>Following surgery, the patients received a questionnaire to complete, in
order to determine their level of pain and discomfort. The questionnaire
consisted of six items, five of which used a Likert scale with a four-point
response range, and one with a three-point range. Participants were
questioned about their subjective experiences with discomfort while eating,
pain, and their perception of swelling on the surgical side at two different
time points, T1 and T2, where T1 was 24 h following the surgical procedure
and T2 was three days later.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>ERROR OF METHOD</title>
                <p>To determine the errors associated with measurements, the measurements were
repeated two weeks apart, by the same investigator, on 10 subjects. The
intraclass correlation coefficient using Dahlberg formula, and paired
<italic>t</italic>-tests were used to assess random and systematic errors in
the study, respectively. </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>BLINDING</title>
                <p>This was a single-blind study, in which the statistician was blinded with regard
to the origin and grouping of data.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</title>
                <p>The measurements were analyzed statistically using SPSS v. 23 software (SPSS for
Windows, release 7.51 Chicago, USA). The Shapiro-Wilk normality test was applied
to assess the normality of the data. All variables except pain were found to be
normally distributed; therefore, independent <italic>t</italic>-test was used to
compare the mean differences of the two groups for monthly and overall canine
and molar movements, as well as overall changes in canine rotation, angulation,
root resorption and probing depths at the end of five months. The chi-square
test was applied to compare the pain, swelling and discomfort scores across the
two groups. Statistical significance was set at <italic>p</italic>≤ 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>The moderate to high reliability was observed with intraclass correlation
coefficients between 0.88- 0.93 for all measurements. No statistically significant
differences were found between the repeated measurements for any variable. The mean
age of the subjects at the start of the treatment was 21.85±2.45 years. The rates of
canine movement, molar movement, canine tipping and rotations, probing depth of
canines, and root resorption of the canines were assessed at an interval of 21 days
from T1 to T5 in 16 orthodontic patients. </p>
              <sec>
                <title>PRIMARY OUTCOME</title>
                <p>There was a statistically significant greater rate of canine movement in the
first two months (T0-T1 and T1-T2) in the experimental group [1.806 ± 0.404mm in
the first month; 2.184 ± 0.297mm in the second month] than in the control group
[1.294 ± 0.297mm in the first month; 1.875 ± 0.331mm in the second month]. The
difference in the tooth movements on both sides is depicted in <xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>. The total amount of canine
retraction was 6.407 ± 0.336 mm on the experimental side and 5.546 ± 0.663 mm on
the control side, and the difference between both was statistically significant
(<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
                    <label>Table 1:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of the rate of canine movement (mm) between the
experimental and control groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of canine retraction</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental Group Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T Value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0-T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.806 ± 0.404</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.294 ± 0.297</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.084</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1-T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.184 ± 0.297</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.875 ± 0.331</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.779</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2-T3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.147 ± 0.442</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.906 ± 0.441</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.543</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.133</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3-T4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.531 ± 0.329</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.528 ± 0.413</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.982</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4-T5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739 ± 0.303</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943 ± 0.424</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.566</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOTAL</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.407 ± 0.336</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.546 ± 0.663</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.633</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN1">
                        <p> SD = Standard Deviation; NS = Not Significant; * significant at
p ≤ 0.05.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f5">
                    <label>Figure 5:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Difference in tooth movement of maxillary canine on experimental
(right) and control (left) sides at T2.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-05-e232388-gf5" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>SECONDARY OUTCOME</title>
                <p>On the comparison of both groups, it was noticed that control group displayed
more anchorage loss (0.473 ± 0.0705 mm), compared to experimental group (0.407 ±
0 .0719 mm), which was statistically significant only in the first month of
treatment (T0-T1) and thereafter; being non-significant for the remaining time
period (p ≥ 0.05) (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
                    <label>Table 2:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of molar movement (mm) rate between the experimental
and control groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of molar movement (mm)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental Group Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0-T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407 ± 0 .0719</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473 ± 0.0705</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.6217</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0136*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1-T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306 ± 0.0609</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.321 ± 0.0802</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.5496</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5797</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2-T3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359 ± 0.2017</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399 ± 0.2334</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0318</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4660</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3-T4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.500 ± 0.1204</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.486 ± 0.1250</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.4048</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3531</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4-T5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.239 ± 0.3371</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243 ± 0.3230</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3733</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6613</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOTAL</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.811 ± 0.3819</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.922 ± 0.3824</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.8216</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4178</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN2">
                        <p>SD = Standard Deviation. NS = Not Significant. * Significant at p
≤ 0.05.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>The study revealed non-significant changes in the amount of root resorption, mean
probing depth, amount of canine rotation, and tipping in both groups during
canine retraction (p ≥0.05) (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref>,
<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t3">
                    <label>Table 3:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of the canine root resorption index and mean probing
depths between the experimental and control groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Root resorption index </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Probing Depth </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental Group<break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group<break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental Group<break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group<break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRE</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 ± 0.433</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.188 ± 0.390</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.219±0.655</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.328 ± 0.629</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POST</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.375 ± 0.484</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.313 ± 0.464</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.721</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.234±0.664</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.375 ± 0.619</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN3">
                        <p>SD = Standard Deviation. Significant at p ≤ 0.05.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t4">
                    <label>Table 4:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of the mean differences in the canine rotation and
canine tipping between the experimental and control groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="2"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Canine rotation (degrees) </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Canine Tipping (degrees) </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental Group<break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group<break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental Group<break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group <break/> Mean ± SD</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.063 ± 3.614</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.938 ± 3.733</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.926</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.969 ± 0.760</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.000 ± 2.179</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.959</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN4">
                        <p>SD = Standard Deviation. Significant at p ≤ 0.05.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>Assessment of pain, swelling, and discomfort following surgical intervention and
the overall perception of discomfort showed non-significant differences. None of
the patients reported using analgesics (<xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">Table
5</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t5">
                    <label>Table 5:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Assessment of pain, swelling, and discomfort following surgical
intervention, using a four-point Likert scale, and overall
perception of discomfort for the experimental and control
groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="3"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Question</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Group</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Time</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Scores </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chi value </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Q1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">4.3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.222</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control </td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.57</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.664</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Q2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">5.38</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.981</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Q3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.88</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.641</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.54</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.765</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Q4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.54</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.76</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 11</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.133</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.98</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Q5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2.39</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.301</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.376</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.828</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Q6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.47</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.478</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">3.31</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.067</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN5">
                        <p>SD = Standard Deviation. NS = Not Significant. Significant at p ≤
0.05.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Due to the lack of sufficient data on the long-term influence of L-PRF on the rate of
canine movement,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> the present study was conducted to determine the effects of L-PRF on the
rate of canine movement. Most of studies on platelet concentrates were conducted
using PRP and injectable-PRF (i-PRF). PRP has the highest autologous platelet
concentration in a small amount of plasma. Different doses of PRP promote
orthodontic tooth movement, according to animal studies.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Submucosal injection of PRP or i-PRF have disadvantages related to pain,
discomfort and swelling of the mucosa after injection, as well as the possibility of
leakage during injection.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> In contrast, L-PRF has the advantages of simpler preparation and prolonged
effects.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> In the present study, L-PRF plugs were used, as they behave as true fibrin
tissue, maintain their fibrin structure even after seven days of placement, and
slowly release more growth factors, mainly TGF-β, which has been shown to have
anti-inflammatory properties, stimulate neoangiogenesis, increase proliferation of
osteoblasts, and collagen synthesis, which triggers bone regeneration and
accelerates tooth movement. Additionally, protease enzymes, other growth factors
such as vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF); platelet derived growth factor AB
(PDGF AB), and matrix proteins such as fibronectin are also released by L-PRF
plugs.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> As stated in PRP studies, the effects of L-PRF can also be related to the
timing of release, concentration, and content of its growth factors. As the
preparation of L-PRF plugs is very technique-sensitive and their acceleration
effects are directly related to their dosage and method of preparation, a precise
method, as suggested by Dohan et al,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> was used in the present study. After coming into contact with the glass, the
blood sample without an anticoagulant almost instantly began to coagulate, which cut
down on the amount of time needed to centrifuge fibrinogen. To get therapeutically
useful L-PRF plugs charged with serum and platelets, the proper preparation
technique must be followed, and quick handling is essential.</p>
              <p>Immediately after careful extraction of first premolars, L-PRF plugs were inserted
into the extraction socket to trigger regional acceleratory phenomenon (RAP). The
experimental side of the trial, where the L-PRF plugs were inserted, displayed a
higher rate of canine retraction than the control side, which was temporary only for
the first two months. The findings of the present study are in accordance with
previous studies.<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> The 150-g of retraction force from the NiTi closed coil springs led to an
increased rate of tooth movement even in the control group, which was in agreement
with studies conducted by Bokas and Woods<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> (1.85 mm) and Khanmasjedi et al<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> (1.67 ± 0.39 mm). This was mainly a tipping movement, which was also noticed
by Reyes Pacheco et al<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> in their study, and might be due to constant and continuous force delivery
by NiTi springs. The acceleration of canine movement was seen more in the second
month, compared to the first month, which was similar to previous studies.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> This may be due to the slow release of BMP2 and TGF-β after a period of 7
days. The original L-PRF clots remained in good shape for a longer period of
time.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> However, the present findings were in disagreement with the findings of
Reyes Pacheco et al<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> and Zeitounlouian et al.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> Reyes Pacheco et al<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> found a decreased rate of retraction in 15 out of 17 patients. The disparity
in the results might be due to the fact that they conducted the study on adults with
a mean age of 33 years, who presented less periodontal response, compared to young
adults in the present study.<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Moreover, they used the maxillary dental midline as reference landmark for
assessment of canine movement, which itself is not a stable landmark, and this would
be highly influenced by forces acting on the entire arch. They prepared L-PRF at
2700rpm for 14 min in 10ml of blood, and did not use the standardized procedure for
preparing L-PRF; Xpression Box was also not used for compression of plug, which
could have led to the methodological errors in the study, affecting the
results.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Zeitounlouian et al<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> also did not find any acceleration effects of PRF in their study. They used
i-PRF in their study and these conflicting results may be related to the different
centrifugation protocols and methodology (700 rpm for 3 min). The centrifuge
characteristics have a direct impact on the architecture and cell content of L-PRF
clots. The different centrifugation speeds could result in a considerable flaw in
all PRP/PRF studies.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Other studies<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> have found accelerated tooth movement in the L-PRF group, compared to the
control group, at all time intervals. However, two<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> of these studies were conducted for a period of 2-3 months and also had
confounding bias in the method of assessment of canine movement, which might have
affected the outcome. </p>
              <p>In the present study, all measurements were taken from the third palatal rugae, which
is considered as stable structure.<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> The reason for the short-term increase in OTM might be due to the short-term
increase in the number of cells and production of cytokines, enhancing bone
remodeling immediately following PRF application.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> However, the actual effects and mechanism of PRF need to be elucidated in
further well-designed studies using standard protocols. Similar to PRP, L-PRF can
also have dose-dependent effects; therefore, it is highly recommended to determine
the concentrations of platelets and leukocytes in whole blood and L-PRF samples
using ELISA before their application. </p>
              <p>During tooth movement, force application away from the center of resistance results
in unwanted tipping and rotation. There were no appreciable differences between
groups regarding canine rotation or inclination. These findings are consistent with
those from other studies.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> On the other hand, Reyes Pacheco et al<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> showed a larger canine rotation on the control side than on the experimental
side. These conflicting results may be due to differences in methodology and
platelet concentration. Comparing the probing depth and root resorption before and
after the investigation, there were no discernible differences between the
experimental and control groups. This is in accordance with previous studies.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Assessment of perception of pain, swelling and discomfort showed
non-significant results in the present study, corroborating the findings of previous
studies.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> This was due to the anti-inflammatory effects of PRF.<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> The primary limitation of this study was lack of evaluation of gender
differences. </p>
              <sec>
                <title>CLINICAL IMPLICATIONS</title>
                <p>The results of this study support the short-term acceleration and
anti-inflammatory effects of L-PRF on the rate of canine retraction, with less
anchorage loss and no deleterious effects on the periodontium. However,
long-term effects on the acceleration of canine retraction were not observed in
this study; therefore, based on the findings of this study, further well
designed randomized control studies in this regard are recommended. </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>The movement of the canines and molars, tipping, rotation, anchorage loss, and
probing depth were evaluated, and it was concluded that the rate of canine
retraction was statistically greater on the experimental side only in the first two
months with the use of L-PRF. Anchorage loss was greater in the control group only
in the first month of treatment. Canine tipping, rotation, root resorption, probing
depth, and pain perception were statistically insignificant in both groups. </p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other" id="fn1">
                <label>»</label>
                <p>
                  <bold>Patients displayed in this article previously approved the use of their
facial and intraoral photographs.</bold>
                </p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ong</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>HL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Periodontic and orthodontic treatment in adults</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>122</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>420</fpage>
                  <lpage>428</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12411890</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miles</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Accelerated orthodontic treatment - what's the
evidence</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <lpage>70</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28297096</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buschang</surname>
                      <given-names>PH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campbell</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ruso</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Accelerating tooth movement with corticotomies is it possible and
desirable?</article-title>
                  <source>Semin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
                  <lpage>294</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tehranchi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Behnia</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pourdanesh</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Behnia</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Younessian</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of autologous leukocyte platelet rich fibrin on the
rate of orthodontic tooth movement A prospective randomized clinical
trial</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Dent</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <lpage>357</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30147398</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choukroun</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adda</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schoeffler</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vervelle</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Une opportunit ? en paro-implantologie: Le PRF</article-title>
                  <source>Implantodontie</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <lpage>62</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marenzi</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riccitiello</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tia</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>di Lauro</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sammartino</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of leukocyte- and platelet-rich fibrin (L-PRF) in the
healing of simple postextraction sockets a split-mouth study</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed Res Int</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>2015</volume>
                  <fpage>369273</fpage>
                  <lpage>369273</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26273612</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flückiger</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fujioka-Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sawada</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sculean</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schaller</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative release of growth factors from PRP, PRF, and
advanced-PRF</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Oral Investig</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>2353</fpage>
                  <lpage>2360</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farshidfar</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amiri</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Firoozi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamedani</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ajami</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tayebi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The adjunctive effect of autologous platelet concentrates on
orthodontic tooth movement a systematic review and meta-analysis of current
randomized controlled trials</article-title>
                  <source>Int Orthod</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>100596</fpage>
                  <lpage>100596</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34866025</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nemtoi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sirghe</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nemtoi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haba</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of a plasma with platelet-rich fibrin in bone
regeneration and on rate of orthodontic tooth movement in
adolescents</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Chim</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>3727</fpage>
                  <lpage>3730</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dohan Ehrenfest</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>NR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pereda</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jiménez</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Corso</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kang</surname>
                      <given-names>BS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of the centrifuge characteristics and centrifugation
protocols on the cells, growth factors, and fibrin architecture of a
leukocyte- and platelet-rich fibrin (L-PRF) clot and
membrane</article-title>
                  <source>Platelets</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <lpage>184</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28437133</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahuja</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bhambri</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohini</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Does corticotomy accelerate canine retraction with adequate
anchorage control A split mouth randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Orthod Waves</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>79</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <lpage>21</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ziegler</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ingervall</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A clinical study of maxillary canine retraction with a retraction
spring and with sliding mechanics</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>95</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <lpage>106</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2916474</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azevedo</surname>
                      <given-names>LR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torres</surname>
                      <given-names>TB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Normando</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Canine angulation in individuals with Class I and Class III
malocclusion comparative analysis through a new method using digitized
images</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Press J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <lpage>117</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Levander</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malmgren</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the risk of root resorption during orthodontic
treatment a study of upper incisors</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <lpage>38</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3162877</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ursi</surname>
                      <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tavano</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriques</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of mesiodistal axial inclination through panoramic
radiography</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Orthod</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <lpage>173</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2387903</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rashid</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>ElSharaby</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nassef</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mehanni</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mostafa</surname>
                      <given-names>YA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of platelet-rich plasma on orthodontic tooth movement in
dogs</article-title>
                  <source>Orthod Craniofac Res</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <lpage>110</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28414871</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liou</surname>
                      <given-names>EJW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The development of submucosal injection of platelet rich plasma
for accelerating orthodontic tooth movement and preserving pressure side
alveolar bone</article-title>
                  <source>APOS Trends Orthod</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castro</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortellini</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Temmerman</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teughels</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characterization of the leukocyte- and platelet-rich fibrin block
release of growth factors, cellular content, and structure</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>855</fpage>
                  <lpage>864</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30742137</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dohan Ehrenfest</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bielecki</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jimbo</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barbé</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Del Corso</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Inchingolo</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Do the fibrin architecture and leukocyte content influence the
growth factor release of platelet concentrates An evidence-based answer
comparing a pure platelet-rich plasma (P-PRP) gel and a leukocyte- and
platelet-rich fibrin (L-PRF)</article-title>
                  <source>Curr Pharm Biotechnol</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1145</fpage>
                  <lpage>1152</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21740377</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Erdur</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karakasli</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oncu</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ozturk</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hakki</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of injectable platelet-rich fibrin (i-PRF) on the rate of
tooth movement</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <lpage>292</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33459765</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>El-Timamy</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Sharaby</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eid</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Dakroury</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mostafa</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaker</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of platelet-rich plasma on the rate of orthodontic tooth
movement</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>90</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <lpage>361</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33378433</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bokas</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Woods</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A clinical comparison between nickel titanium springs and
elastomeric chains</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Orthod J</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16792244</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khanemasjedi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moradinejad</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Javidi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Niknam</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jahromi</surname>
                      <given-names>NH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rakhshan</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of elastic memory chains versus nickel-titanium coil
springs in canine retraction a two-center split-mouth randomized clinical
trial</article-title>
                  <source>Int Orthod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>561</fpage>
                  <lpage>574</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reyes Pacheco</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Collins</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Contreras</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lantigua</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pithon</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                      <given-names>OM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Distalization rate of maxillary canines in an alveolus filled
with leukocyte-platelet-rich fibrin in adults a randomized controlled
clinical split-mouth trial</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>158</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <lpage>191</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32591274</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeitounlouian</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeno</surname>
                      <given-names>KG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brad</surname>
                      <given-names>BA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haddad</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Three-dimensional evaluation of the effects of injectable
platelet rich fibrin (i-PRF) on alveolar bone and root length during
orthodontic treatment a randomized split mouth trial</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <lpage>92</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33653326</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schubert</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jäger</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maltha</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bartzela</surname>
                      <given-names>TN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Age effect on orthodontic tooth movement rate and the composition
of gingival crevicular fluid a literature review</article-title>
                  <source>J Orofac Orthop</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>125</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31919542</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barhate</surname>
                      <given-names>UH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duggal</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mangaraj</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharan</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duggal</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jena</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of autologous leukocyte-platelet rich fibrin (L-PRF) on
the rate of maxillary canine retraction and various biomarkers in gingival
crevicular fluid (GCF) a split mouth randomized controlled
trial</article-title>
                  <source>Int Orthod</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>100681</fpage>
                  <lpage>100681</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36151016</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jang</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koga</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Iijima</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yozgatian</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cha</surname>
                      <given-names>BK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A novel method for the assessment of three-dimensional tooth
movement during orthodontic treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>79</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>447</fpage>
                  <lpage>453</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19413387</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Çagli Karci</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baka</surname>
                      <given-names>ZM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of the effects of local platelet-rich fibrin injection
and piezocision on orthodontic tooth movement during canine
distalization</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>160</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <lpage>40</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33962809</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naji</surname>
                      <given-names>RE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeitounlouian</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alomari</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Youssef</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the efficacy of platelet-rich plasma (PRP) and
injectable platelet-rich fibrin (i-PRF) in the acceleration of canine
retraction a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Int Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <lpage>253</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mheissen</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daraqel</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alzoubi</surname>
                      <given-names>EE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of platelet-rich concentrates on the rate of
orthodontic tooth movement a systematic review and
meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <lpage>207</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36056906</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rokia</surname>
                      <given-names>AG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kheirallah</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hassan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khalil</surname>
                      <given-names>FH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kheirallah</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The preliminary outcomes of platelet-rich fibrin injection on
pain perception following insertion of archwire A randomized controlled
clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>APOS Trends Orthod</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reyes Pacheco</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Collins</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Contreras</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lantigua</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pithon</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                      <given-names>OM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Distalization rate of maxillary canines in an alveolus filled
with leukocyte-platelet-rich fibrin in adults A randomized controlled
clinical split-mouth trial</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>158</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <lpage>191</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32591274</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Francisco</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vale</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Platelet-rich fibrin in bone regenerative strategies in
orthodontics a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>Materials</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>1866</fpage>
                  <lpage>1866</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32316144</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
