<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:36:21Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10728541" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10728541</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-12-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>cedr</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" id="cre2790" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2057-4347</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRE2</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2057-4347</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10728541</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10728541</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10728541</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37787028</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37787028</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.790</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CRE2790</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="overline">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A 3‐year controlled clinical trial comparing high‐translucency zirconia (cubic zirconia) with lithium disilicate glass ceramic (e.max)</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">FAWAKHIRI <sc>et al.</sc>
</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="cre2790-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fawakhiri</surname>
                    <given-names>Hiba A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-3353-7996</contrib-id>
                  <xref rid="cre2790-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <address>
                    <email>alfawaheba@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="cre2790-cr-0002" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Abboud</surname>
                    <given-names>Souad</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cre2790-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="cre2790-cr-0003" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kanout</surname>
                    <given-names>Shaza</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cre2790-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="cre2790-aff-0001">
                <label>
                  <sup>1</sup>
                </label>
                <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Operative Dentistry</named-content>
                <institution>Damascus University</institution>
                <city>Damascus</city>
                <country country="SY">Syria</country>
              </aff>
              <aff id="cre2790-aff-0002">
                <label>
                  <sup>2</sup>
                </label>
                <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of fixed Prothdontiscs</named-content>
                <institution>Damascus University</institution>
                <city>Damascus</city>
                <country country="SY">Syria</country>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold> Hiba A. Fawakhiri, Department of Operative Dentistry, Damascus University, Al‐Mazzah St, Damascus, Syria.<break/>
Email: <email>alfawaheba@gmail.com</email>
<break/>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>9</volume>
              <issue seq="150">6</issue>
              <issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.v9.6</issue-id>
              <fpage>1078</fpage>
              <lpage>1088</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <!--&#x000a9; 2023 The Authors. Clinical and Experimental Dental Research published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd.-->
                <copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">© 2023 The Authors. <italic toggle="yes">Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</italic> published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CRE2-9-1078.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec id="cre2790-sec-0010">
                  <title>Introduction</title>
                  <p>The rate of clinical success in veneers, under esthetics, has achieved a range of 18 months to 20 years. In a plethora of studies, it registers a success rate reaching 75% and even 100%. The most common type of glass ceramics used in ceramics is the vitreous lithium disilicate crystal‐reinforced material, e.max®. Recent studies focus on “polycrystalline ceramic use” in manufacturing veneers, as it possesses a stronger structure and different enabling manufacturing schemes.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="cre2790-sec-0020">
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>This research aims at comparing e.max and the high‐translucent Cubic Zirconia. Such comparison is administered to veneers manufacturing: esthetic (surface and edge, and staining and color matching), functional (crack and fracture, contact point, and patient satisfaction), and biological (posttreatment vitality and hypersensitivity, and periodontal response).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="cre2790-sec-0030">
                  <title>Materials and Methods</title>
                  <p>The research sample consisted of 60 veneers, divided into two groups: cubic zirconia and e.max. The sample included 2 males (16.6%) and 10 females (83.3%), with age ranging from 25 to 37 years. Patients were thoroughly diagnosed and treated and included in this study based on certain inclusion–exclusion criteria. Hickel's 2010 criteria were utilized to examine and observe the clinical aspect of veneers during intervals of 1 week, 3 months, 1 year, and 3 years.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="cre2790-sec-0040">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>No significant differences were traced across the groups for all the variables, with a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>‐value being greater than 0.05. The <italic toggle="yes">e.max</italic> group revealed better clinical results compared to the <italic toggle="yes">cubic zirconia</italic> one regarding esthetics and tooth translucency. Nonetheless, the results showed a merely slight increase in hypersensitivity in the e.max group.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="cre2790-sec-0050">
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>Within the limitation of an extensive follow‐up period, we can conclude that there is no difference between cubic zirconia and e.max (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05), where e.max and <italic toggle="yes">cubic zirconia</italic> veneers have the same characteristics in terms of the following. The characteristics of the aspects examined were esthetic, functional, and biological.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd id="cre2790-kwd-0001">e‐max</kwd>
                <kwd id="cre2790-kwd-0002">gingivitis</kwd>
                <kwd id="cre2790-kwd-0003">translucent zirconia</kwd>
                <kwd id="cre2790-kwd-0004">veneers</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group id="funding-0001">
                  <funding-source>Damascus University</funding-source>
                  <award-id>501100020595</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="1"/>
                <table-count count="1"/>
                <page-count count="11"/>
                <word-count count="6153"/>
              </counts>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>2.0</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>December 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.3.6 mode:remove_FC converted:19.12.2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
            <notes>
              <p content-type="self-citation">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0034"><string-name><surname>Fawakhiri</surname>, <given-names>H. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abboud</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Kanout</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>A 3‐year controlled clinical trial comparing high‐translucency zirconia (cubic zirconia) with lithium disilicate glass ceramic (e.max)</article-title>. <source>Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1079</fpage>–<lpage>1089</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </p>
            </notes>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="cre2790-sec-0060">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Preservation of tooth structure and prevention of needless tooth structure removal are basic and important principles in prosthodontics. Striving to achieve the cosmetic aspect is also a basic requirement, especially in the modern world. Veneers can satisfy both of the aforementioned requirements, for they are considered conservative, esthetic, and functional prosthetic options (Cardoso &amp; Decurcio, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Veneers provide adequate esthetics, registering a satisfactory clinical survival rate, color stability, vibrant appearance, and high resistance to abrasion and discoloration. A considerable number of studies show a survival rate of up to 20 years and a success level of 75%–100%. Dental ceramics consist of a vitreous phase (75%–80%), containing crystals inside; the presence of the true crystalline state of dental <italic toggle="yes">ceramic</italic> is limited to alumina Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, the hardest and strongest known oxides (Sakaguchi &amp; Powers, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p>
              <p>One of the most widely used types of dental ceramics in manufacturing veneers is glass ceramic (Fu et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Zanotto, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Ivoclar Vivadent introduced this ceramic system in two forms: <italic toggle="yes">IPS e.max CAD</italic>, a block milled in CAD/CAM, and another using press‐lost wax, <italic toggle="yes">IPS e.max Press</italic>. The first generation of lithium disilicate, named <italic toggle="yes">IPS Empress 2</italic>, contained glass ceramic and was filled with glass particles, containing approximately 70% lithium disilicate. This was later presented as <italic toggle="yes">IPS e.max</italic>, where lithium silicate crystals play the role of filler crystals in this system as needle‐shaped crystals: 3–6 µm in length and 0.5–0.8 µm in diameter (Özdemir &amp; Özdoğan, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). These crystals form regularly within the ceramic mold during the melting process; besides, glass‐reinforced lithium silicate is a ceramic that can be etched using hydrofluoric acid (Gresnigt et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p>
              <p>One study indicates that lithium disilicate glass‐reinforced porcelain is less abrasive to opposite natural teeth, but more susceptible to wear than feldspar porcelain and glass reinforced with fluorapatite crystals. It displays higher elasticity compared to glass reinforced with fluorapatite crystals followed by feldspar porcelain and glass‐reinforced porcelain with Lucite crystals (Zhang et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). However, glass reinforced with lithium disilicate is considered highly translucent porcelain regardless of the high volume of crystals within its construction. This is due to the low refractive index of lithium disilicate crystals, reaching 1.55 (McLaren &amp; Cao, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), which makes it indicated in cases of veneers and cosmetic anterior prostheses. It is also recommended for making anterior and posterior crowns and intracoronal fillings, as well as bridges with three dental units, provided that the lateral abutment does not exceed the second premolar (McLaren &amp; Cao, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Miwa et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p>
              <p>As a result of the new development in zirconia and its structure and manufacturing methods, obtaining more translucent zirconia has proven feasible compared to the old generations, with improved phases of cosmetics. Such development made possible the use of zirconia in cosmetic areas with the help of external dyes and colorings to achieve color similarity to the adjacent natural teeth. This type of ceramic provides very acceptable esthetic outcomes in manufacturing veneers; experimentally, it reduces the risk of veneer fracture during clinical functioning (Borba et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Calamia, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>). Likewise, it is less costly compared to other materials. Zirconia structures provide a sufficient amount of shade to hide the discolored supports under them due to their high density (porosity &lt; 0.05) and homogeneity even in limited thicknesses (Souza et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p>
              <p>Our current investigation, henceforth, aims at comparing glass reinforced with crystals of lithium disilicate, <italic toggle="yes">e.max</italic>, to high translucent cer. This is held for manufacturing ceramic veneers, under the grounds of esthetic, functional, and biological aspects.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials-and-methods" id="cre2790-sec-0070">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0080">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>This investigation follows the clinically controlled trials scheme. It was conducted at the Department of Operative Dentistry, the Faculty of Dental Medicine, at Damascus University. Furthermore, our research sample was distributed between the two groups after operationalizing the concept of randomization and blinding the researchers. The study included 12 patients who were divided into two groups:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Group 1: 6 patients with 36 ceramic veneers manufactured from <italic toggle="yes">IPS e.max</italic> and applied on 6 anterior teeth.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Group 2: 6 patients with 36 ceramic veneers manufactured from <italic toggle="yes">high‐translucent zirconia</italic> and applied on 6 anterior teeth.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p>Veneers were applied to 12 patients who complained of cosmetic problems, the age of whom ranged from 25–37 years. As well, each patient was randomly assigned to one of the two groups, <italic toggle="yes">e.max</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">cubic zirconia</italic>. Distribution blinding was done by using sealed envelopes, containing the number to refer to the assigned group. In addition to blinded distribution, two calibrating blinded observers made the assessment during the follow‐up periods: in case of any variation of results between them, a third assessment was sought to reach an accurate judgment.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Inclusion criteria</italic>:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>a.</label><p>age between 20 and 40 years</p></list-item><list-item><label>b.</label><p>absence of abnormal functional habits such as bruxism</p></list-item><list-item><label>c.</label><p>good condition of gingival and periodontal tissues</p></list-item><list-item><label>d.</label><p>good oral health</p></list-item><list-item><label>e.</label><p>a clear indication for patients for treatment with veneers: presence of diastema, poor dental restorations, slight modification of color in the discolored teeth, and modification of shape and sizes of the teeth</p></list-item><list-item><label>f.</label><p>patient's written consent to enroll in the study and adherence to a follow‐up session</p></list-item></list></p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Exclusion criteria</italic>:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>a.</label><p>age under 18 years</p></list-item><list-item><label>b.</label><p>bad oral hygiene</p></list-item><list-item><label>c.</label><p>dysfunctional habits and bruxism</p></list-item><list-item><label>d.</label><p>periodontal diseases</p></list-item><list-item><label>e.</label><p>high risk of caries</p></list-item><list-item><label>f.</label><p>inadequate enamel for bonding</p></list-item><list-item><label>g.</label><p>extreme stinging and color change in tooth</p></list-item></list></p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Research materials</italic>:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1.</label><p>Examination tools: periodontal probe with explorer, mouth mirror, and tweezer (Medesy)</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.</label><p>Preparation: depth Marker diamond burs, diamond Taper round‐ended burs, finishing diamond burs (Komet) and Rubber Point kit, gingival retraction cord size (00–000) from (Ultradent), and impression materials (condensational silicon and additional silicon) (Zhermack)</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.</label><p>Temporary crown and bridge material (ExperTemp; Ultradent)</p></list-item><list-item><label>4.</label><p>Phosphoric Acid 37% and hydrofluoric acid 9% (Bisco)</p></list-item><list-item><label>5.</label><p>MonoBond‐S (silane coupling agent) and light‐cured resin Cement—Milky Opaque, along with methacryloyloxydecyl dihydrogen‐phosphate (MDP) (Bisco).</p></list-item><list-item><label>6.</label><p>Bonding agent (Ivoclar Vivadent)</p></list-item><list-item><label>7.</label><p>Veneers manufacturing tools: CAD/CAM scanner from Zircodenta, tempering device, and Ivoclar Vivadent lithium disilicate glass‐reinforced ceramic heat injection furnace</p></list-item></list></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0090">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Research procedure</title>
                <p>To confirm that the patient meets the necessary criteria, a tissue examination was conducted. In addition, digital photographs and initial impressions were taken for the patient to review each clinical case and the cosmetic expectations for the treatment.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0100">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Preparation</title>
                <p>Once the case was enrolled based on the inclusion criteria mentioned above, the treatment teeth were prepared to receive ceramic veneers. Loupes magnifiers were used under chair lighting to ensure a suitable probing depth for preparation and to standardize preparation criteria as much as possible. Minimal preparation was resorted to by adopting the butt joint pattern that guarantees shortening the cutting edge to obtain the required translucent and esthetic aspect. The incisal edge was prepared by depth guide bur; this was followed by preparing the cervical region 0.1–0.3 mm and the mid‐region 0.3–0.5 mm. The cutting edge was also reduced by 1.0–1.5 mm. After removing the enamel via a cone round‐end bur to reach the required depth, the finishing lines were put under the gingival area to guarantee the esthetic aspect and the emanating appearance, adopting the light chamfer scheme. Moreover, the preparation was extended to a completely labial surface without exceeding the interproximal contact, rounding all the edges and linear angles. Later, manufacturing the veneers was achieved following the exact laboratory steps for both the zirconia group and the e.max group (Baldissara et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Daniele et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0110">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Impression</title>
                <p>Following that stage, the impressions were made. First, a second gingival retraction was applied in the sulcular gingiva to provide an accurate thickness of the impression material. Appropriate impression trays for each patient were meticulously chosen, and additional silicon was used to make the impressions using the putty wash technique while taking an impression of the opposite side with alginate and a wax bite of the prepared teeth in a centric occlusion position. The selection of color was performed by a shade guide, and then the provisional restoration was made with the help of a silicone guide that was prepared before starting the whole process. The self‐cured intraoral acryl was injected into the silicone guide, then the provisional restoration was trimmed: the margins were well finished using the finishing burs. The impression was sent to the laboratory with information about the color and age of the patient and notes if that was necessary.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0120">
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Bonding</title>
                <p>This stage was divided into three phases.
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1.</label><p>Tooth‐related phase was commonly shared for the two groups. It included removing the provisional restoration and cleaning the surfaces of the teeth, after isolating the area by a rubber dam. The veneer parts were tried in the patient's mouth to ensure an appropriate fit. The final step was cleaning and etching the teeth surfaces by using 37% phosphoric acid, drying them thoroughly, and applying the bonding agent.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.</label><p>E.max‐related phase comprised treating the e.max's internal surface by etching it with 9% hydrofluoric acid, after which a silane layer was applied and yet another one to achieve shiny surfaces.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.</label><p>High‐translucent zirconia‐related phase encompassed sandblasting with particles of aluminum oxide coated with silica of the internal surfaces for the zirconia for 20 s (2.8 bar, 10 mm standoff distance). After drying, the application of a double bonding agent containing MDP for both types of restoration was done.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p>Finally, we put light‐cured resin cement for both types. A light cure was selected because it possesses more color stability than dual cure cement. The suggestion of utilizing light curing was introduced by Wassell et al. (<xref rid="cre2790-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>); we applied it for only 4–5 s, but we eliminated the excessive cement with the help of a probe, using dental floss in approximal areas. Finally, the veneers were light‐cured from multiple angles to ensure complete polymerization. Following cementation procedures, the patients were instructed on oral hygiene measures.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0130">
                <label>2.6</label>
                <title>Research indices</title>
                <p>The following indices were used to evaluate the veneers according to predefined intervals of 1 week, 3 months, 1 year, and 3 years. The assessment was carried out according to Hickel. Indices contained surface and margin staining, color matching and translucency, presence of fracture or crack, contact points, patient's satisfaction, tooth vitality and hypersensitivity, and finally gingival response.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0140">
                <label>2.7</label>
                <title>Clinical evaluation</title>
                <p>Patients were assessed during the follow‐up sessions, and photographs were taken to document the condition at each follow‐up session. As for patients' satisfaction, a questionnaire was used to be filled out by the patients in each follow‐up session.</p>
                <p>Surface and margin staining involved the evaluated surface and margin staining and color matching that were verified by the visual method comparing the shade taken immediately after the adhesive veneers and the shade during the follow‐up sessions. Fracture or crack was verified by a visual exam by mirror and illumination at the chairside. The contact points were investigated by the difficulty of passing a coated dental floss through the interdental contact points. Additionally, patients' satisfaction was measured by asking patients to fill out a questionnaire as mentioned previously. Tooth vitality was monitored by examining the vitality of abutment and pulp sensitivity by a pulp‐vitality spray tester and comparing it with adjacent teeth. Lastly, the gingival response was traced by measuring the periodontal sulcus in the follow‐up session and comparing it to the initial state.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2790-sec-0150">
                <label>2.8</label>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The collected data were analyzed using SPSS at the level of significance that was set to <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. Other statistical tests, such as Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> and Kruskal–Wallis, were used to compare the research groups and variables.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="cre2790-sec-0160">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>A total of 16 participants were examined, but the final sample size consisted of 12 patients and included 72 samples as seen in Figure <xref rid="cre2790-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The sample included 2 males (16.6%) and 10 females (83.3%) whose ages ranged between 25 and 37 years, with a mean of age of 28.8 and a standard deviation of 4.2 years.</p>
              <fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre2790-fig-0001">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Consort diagram of the study sample.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="CRE2-9-1078-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Table <xref rid="cre2790-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows descriptive and inferential statistics for the research indices to determine if there is a significant difference between the two groups, zirconia, and e.max, after 1 week, 3 months, 1 year, and 3 years. The results showed that there was no staining on the surface for the two groups, except for 2 cases from the e.max group (6.25%) after 3 months, 12 cases (37.5%) after 3 years, and 6 cases (18.75%) from the zirconia group. There exists no significant difference between the two groups. In addition, there is no marginal staining for the two groups.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="cre2790-tbl-0001" content-type="Table">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Descriptive and inferential statistical analysis for the research indices during measurement times.</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                  <thead valign="bottom">
                    <tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
                      <th colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1"/>
                      <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</th>
                      <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</th>
                      <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th>
                      <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="11" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Surface staining index</td>
                      <td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface staining after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                      <td rowspan="11" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
                        <p>1.000 After a week, 1 year</p>
                        <p>0.29 After 3 months</p>
                        <p>0.1 After 3 years</p>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="11" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface staining after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface staining after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Surface staining after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.75%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface staining after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Surface staining after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.75%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface staining after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Surface staining after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple surface staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Edges staining</td>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">1.0000 All timeframe</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edges staining after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No edges staining</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Color matching</td>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">1.000 All timeframe</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color matching is good</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Crack or fracture</td>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                      <td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">1.000 All timeframe</td>
                      <td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crack or fracture after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No crack or fracture</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Contact points</td>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">1.000 All timeframe</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contact points are normal</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction</td>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">1.000 All timeframe</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after a year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after a year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient is completely satisfied</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="10" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Vitality and hypersensitivity</td>
                      <td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5%</td>
                      <td rowspan="10" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
                        <p>0.61 After a week</p>
                        <p>1.000 After 3 months, after 1 year, after 3 years</p>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="10" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple hypersensitivity</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after a week</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.25%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple hypersensitivity</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.75%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after 1 year</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth vitality after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal vitality</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Gingival inflammation</td>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Zirconia</td>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after a week</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">1.000 All timeframe</td>
                      <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">No significant difference</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after a year</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">E.max</td>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after a week</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after 3 months</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after a year</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Gingival inflammation after 3 years</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <permissions>
                  <copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder>
                </permissions>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>With respect to de‐bonding occurrences, the result of our study showed that there were no de‐bonding events in both groups at all subsequent sessions.</p>
              <p>A good color match was observed for both of the groups during all measurement intervals, and there was no significant difference between the two groups. There was no fracture or crack in the edges during the measurement times for the two groups, and there was no significant difference between them. Furthermore, it was detected that there were normal contact points during the measurement times for both groups, and there was no significant difference between them. Patients were completely satisfied with the prostheses in both research groups, and there was no statistically significant difference between the two groups.</p>
              <p>With regard to tooth vitality, a minor hypersensitivity was observed in 37.5% of the cases in the zirconia group after a week, in comparison to 43.75% of the cases in the e.max group after a week. However, the vitality was normal for both groups after 3 months, with no significant difference between the two groups during the measurement times. Finally, no periodontal inflammation was detected across the research participants during the measurement times.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="cre2790-sec-0170">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Ceramic with high crystal content, such as yttria‐stabilized tetragonal zirconia polycrystal (TZP‐Y), is primarily engaged in manufacturing structures of fixed crowns and bridges because of its high fracture toughness properties. Recently, conversely, zirconia has witnessed a plethora of changes to its microstructure, which increased its translucency without losing its fracture resistance. Henceforth, its clinical utilizations are expanded. Consequently, translucent zirconia is widely considered to be an esthetic material, particularly in making anterior and posterior crowns and bridges, along with veneers.</p>
              <p>This type of ceramic has been found to offer incredibly satisfactory esthetic outcomes when used in veneers; it reduces the risk of layered porcelain fracture throughout clinical applications and experimentation. TZP‐Y affords lower cost compared to other used materials; zirconia structures provide sufficient areas of shading to hide the underlying discolored abutment due to its high density and homogeneity even when the region thicknesses are scarce. Hence, the idea of research revolved originally around evaluating the clinical performance of veneers manufactured from both e.max and high‐translucency zirconia. The investigators of this current study faced limited clinical research in the medical literature addressing the use of zirconia in veneer manufacture. Such a shortcoming was accompanied by another lack of clinical research that studied the clinical evaluation of the esthetic, functional, and biological aspects of veneers also manufactured from these two materials, namely the <italic toggle="yes">e.max</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">highly translucent zirconia</italic>. The clinical performance of veneers was evaluated according to the International Dental Federation (FDI) criteria. This is due to the fact that these criteria are comprehensive and cover all the esthetic, functional, and biological aspects. Our present study included three esthetic criteria (surface discoloration, margins discoloration, and color matching), three functional criteria (veneers' fracture or crack, anatomical shape of contact points, and patient's satisfaction), and biological criteria (tooth vitality, posttreatment hypersensitivity, and gingival response). Each of these criteria has been expressed on a scale of 5 degrees.</p>
              <p>Ceramic veneer failure can be categorized as either absolute or relative. Absolute failure is when there are irreparable cracks that make the veneer unacceptable and require a complete remake. Relative failure, on the other hand, is when there are cracks that are still clinically acceptable or when the ceramic attachment fails but can be rebonded (Guess &amp; Stappert, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p>
              <p>One common issue in dentistry is bonding failure when using resin cement to attach ceramic veneers, regardless of whether the veneers are made of e‐max ceramic or cubic zirconia. This can be caused by various factors, such as microleakage, secondary carriers resulting from the dissolution of resin cement, and the dissolution of bonding agents due to chemical and mechanical factors within the oral cavity (Huang et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Additionally, bonding failure can occur when there are errors in handling the dental or prosthesis surface (Morita et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p>
              <p>On the other hand, the effectiveness and polymerization time of a light cure device has a significant impact on the curing process of resin cement (Rasetto et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Additionally, the fillers present in the resin cement play a crucial role in determining the efficacy of the light‐curing device. Fine fillers, in particular, are more adept at scattering light as compared to hybrid fillers (Rueggeberg et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). Finally, de‐bonding also occurs when a ceramic piece breaks off due to high occlusion forces and nonfunctional habits (Radz, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p>
              <p>In our research, we noted that there were no de‐bonding occurrences in either group. This could be attributed to following an accurate cementation protocol, and case selection which had a good occlusion and a precise fit of the ceramic veneers onto the enamel surfaces, which exhibited a comparable elastic modulus to the veneers. Moreover, the exceptional robustness and mechanical precision of the glass ceramics, fortified with lithium disilicate crystals and zirconia porcelain, further amplified these outcomes.</p>
              <p>When evaluating the surface discoloration criteria in this study, no discoloration was observed in the veneers' surface in both study groups (e.max and zirconia), except for two veneers in the (e.max) group after 3 months of observation. The discoloration was simple and could easily be removed by polishing: the surface of e.max veneers was more discolored compared with the zirconia surface.</p>
              <p>No discoloration was observed in the veneers' margins in both study groups through the observation periods. This agrees with Ozel and Aykor's study, in which it was found that there was no marginal discoloration of lithium disilicate crystal (e.max) veneers (Nejatidanesh et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In addition, it agrees with Ahn et al. (<xref rid="cre2790-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) who observed six anterior veneers for 6 months, and no deboning or staining was observed (Ahn et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Contrastively, this study disagreed with Aslan's long‐term study, which traced 11.7% of marginal discoloration in lithium disilicate glass‐ceramic veneers (Aslan et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The difference in these percentages is perhaps due to the difference in the observation period between these studies; it might also be ascribed to the marginal fit quality, use of light‐cured resin cement in the adhesion, marginal finishing quality, and patient adequate oral hygiene. Nonetheless, only one case of marginal discoloration was observed in another study (Peláez et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), which employed translucent zirconia bridges to replace the second premolar or the first molar.</p>
              <p>Color matching and translucency were good in both of the study groups, namely e.max and zirconia. The results of our study disagreed with Nejatidanesh et al., who found that a large percentage of the veneers (IPS e.max) had discoloration over time. The reason was attributed to the fact that the discoloration occurred on the adjacent natural teeth, not on the veneers (Nejatidanesh et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Another study comparing <italic toggle="yes">IPS e.max Press</italic> to <italic toggle="yes">monolithic zirconia</italic>, in the form of discs, concluded that lithium disilicate claims more color stability over monolithic zirconia (Kurt &amp; Turhan Bal, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p>
              <p>The bonding to zirconia has been a focus of scientific research during the past period. Various treatment methods have been used: sandblasting using aluminum oxide, nanostructured alumina coating, tribochemical silica coating followed by silanization, and application of resin cement containing 10‐MDP monomer, among others. In this current study, there were no cases in which fracture or loss of veneer bonding was verified in either of the study groups. The results of this study come in accordance with Nejatidanesh et al. They did not record any fracture or cracking in the e.max veneers; this was ascribed to the high flexural strength of the material used, which can reach up to 420 MPa (Nejatidanesh et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) and does not have any problem in adhesion and no accident trauma was recorded. In addition, this finding agrees with other studies that reported a high success rate when they used dense zirconia (Klink &amp; Hüttig, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Sailer &amp; Hämmerle, <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Also, this agrees with Matthias Kern's study, which found there were no fracture events in cases of zirconia ceramic; this is due to the fact that zirconia has twice the flexural strength than glass infiltrated alumina (Kern et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). What's more, the contact points were normal in all veneers in the two groups during each observation interval. This is perhaps linked to two factors: the expertise of the dental technician and the accuracy of the sculpting devices in forming natural, esthetic, and anatomical proximal areas. Nevertheless, the patients expressed their satisfaction with the shape, color, and verbal function in both study groups (e.max and zirconia) during the observation periods. Diagnostic waxing and obtaining the patient's consent before starting the process might have contributed to this outstanding acceptance. In addition to that, the prompt manufacture of prostheses, with the help of the diagnostic waxing, allowed the patient to test pronunciation, as well as the shape before the final prosthesis was made. Hence, our study agrees with Aslan et al. (<xref rid="cre2790-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), which achieved esthetic satisfaction with 98% for glass ceramic reinforced with lithium disilicate crystals (e.max) veneers. It also agrees with Liu et al. who conducted their investigation on glass ceramic reinforced with lithium disilicate crystals (e.max) veneers. Their patients' satisfaction with esthetic aspects was evaluated using the VAS scale; it showed the mean of patients' satisfaction with the esthetic aspect to be 9.2 during the 2‐year span of observation (Liu et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p>
              <p>Our results also agreed with Nejatidanesh et al. (<xref rid="cre2790-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), indicating that dental sensitivity following the cementation of veneers gradually disappeared over time, whereas this study differed from other studies that did not record any sensitivity after adhering veneers (Sun et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Yuce et al., <xref rid="cre2790-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). This finding may be attributed to the fact that cementation and preparation produce subjective sensations of pain related to the patient. However, no gingival inflammation was observed in the study groups during all the observation intervals. The results of our study agreed with Nejatidanesh et al. (<xref rid="cre2790-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), for they did not observe an increase in the gingival index over time. It also agreed with D'Arcangelo et al. (<xref rid="cre2790-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), which did not show an increase in the gingival index when using veneers. The reason is mainly ascribed to the persistence of preparation in the cervical area, quality of adhesion and marginal finishing, good marginal fitting of the prostheses, as well as the patients' commitment to oral care and follow‐up sessions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="cre2790-sec-0180">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>Within the limitation of an extensive follow‐up period, we can conclude the following:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1.</label><p>Zero de‐bonding event occurred at 3 years follow‐up in the cubic zirconia group and e.max group.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.</label><p>There was a simple hypersensitivity after a week of adhesion in both comparison groups, but it disappeared in follow‐up sessions.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.</label><p>There is a simple surface staining after 3 years follow‐up in the test and control groups.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="cre2790-sec-0190">
              <title>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</title>
              <p>Hiba A. Fawakhiri developed the idea, designed the research, wrote the manuscript, analyzed the data, and finalized the manuscript. Shaza Kanout and Souad Abboud supervised the research and helped in writing the manuscript.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="cre2790-sec-0210">
              <title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title>
              <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="cre2790-sec-0240">
              <title>ETHICS STATEMENT</title>
              <p>Approval and consent to participate were meticulously met. Ethical approvals were obtained from both the Higher Committee for Medical Research at Damascus University and from the Scientific Research Committee at the Faculty of Dental Medicine, Damascus University (N: 1059 t/m date: 15‐12‐2018). Moreover, all methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations. Informed consent was obtained from all participants before participating in the research.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack id="cre2790-sec-0200">
              <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
              <p>This study was supported by Damascus University in order to get a master's degree in prosthodontic dentistry.</p>
            </ack>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="cre2790-sec-0230">
              <title>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</title>
              <p>Data underlying this manuscript will be shared on reasonable request to the corresponding author.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="cre2790-bibl-0001">
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0001">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0001"><string-name><surname>Ahn</surname>, <given-names>M.‐Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahn</surname>, <given-names>D. G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pyo</surname>, <given-names>S. W.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>, <given-names>H. K.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>A noninvasive esthetic treatment of isolated microdontia using new high‐translucent cubic‐phase zirconia (5Y‐PSZ) laminate veneers: A case report</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Korean Academy of Prosthodontics</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0002">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0002"><string-name><surname>Aslan</surname>, <given-names>Y. U.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uludamar</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Özkan</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Clinical performance of pressable glass‐ceramic veneers after 5, 10, 15, and 20 years: A retrospective case series study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Esthetic and Restorative Dentistry</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31168916</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0003">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0003"><string-name><surname>Baldissara</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wandscher</surname>, <given-names>V. F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marchionatti</surname>, <given-names>A. M. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parisi</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monaco</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Ciocca</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Translucency of IPS e.max and cubic zirconia monolithic crowns</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry</source>, <volume>120</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29475752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0004">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0004"><string-name><surname>Borba</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Araújo</surname>, <given-names>M. D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Lima</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshimura</surname>, <given-names>H. N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cesar</surname>, <given-names>P. F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griggs</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Della Bona</surname>, <given-names>Á.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Flexural strength and failure modes of layered ceramic structures</article-title>. <source>Dental Materials</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1259</fpage>–<lpage>1266</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21982199</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0005">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0005"><string-name><surname>Calamia</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The current status of etched porcelain veneer restorations</article-title>. <source>The Journal of the Philippine Dental Association</source>, <volume>47</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9462055</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0006">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cre2790-cit-0006"><string-name><surname>Cardoso</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Decurcio</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <source>Ceramic veneers contact lenses and fragments</source>. <publisher-name>Paula de Carvalho</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0007">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0007"><string-name><surname>Daniele</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rondoni</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rossi</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Grappoli</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>A single veneer made with a new multi‐layer cubic zirconia disc: Clinical case report</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cosmetic Dentistry</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0008">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0008"><string-name><surname>D'Arcangelo</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Angelis</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vadini</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>D'Amario</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Clinical evaluation on porcelain laminate veneers bonded with light‐cured composite: Results up to 7 years</article-title>. <source>Clinical Oral Investigations</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1071</fpage>–<lpage>1079</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21773711</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0009">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0009"><string-name><surname>Fu</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engqvist</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Xia</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Glass‐ceramics in dentistry: A review</article-title>. <source>Materials (Basel)</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1049</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32110874</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0010">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0010"><string-name><surname>Gresnigt</surname>, <given-names>M. M. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Özcan</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carvalho</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazari</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cune</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Razavi</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Magne</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Effect of luting agent on the load to failure and accelerated‐fatigue resistance of lithium disilicate laminate veneers</article-title>. <source>Dental Materials</source>, <volume>33</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1392</fpage>–<lpage>1401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29079354</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0011">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0011"><string-name><surname>Guess</surname>, <given-names>P. C.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Stappert</surname>, <given-names>C. F. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Midterm results of a 5‐year prospective clinical investigation of extended ceramic veneers</article-title>. <source>Dental Materials</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>804</fpage>–<lpage>813</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18006051</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0012">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0012"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname>, <given-names>D. G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santerre</surname>, <given-names>J. P.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Finer</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Biodegradation of resin–dentin interfaces is dependent on the restorative material, mode of adhesion, esterase or MMP inhibition</article-title>. <source>Dental Materials</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>1262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29789163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0013">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0013"><string-name><surname>Kern</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Passia</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sasse</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Yazigi</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Ten‐year outcome of zirconia ceramic cantilever resin‐bonded fixed dental prostheses and the influence of the reasons for missing incisors</article-title>. <source>Journal of Dentistry</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28688950</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0014">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0014"><string-name><surname>Klink</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Hüttig</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Zirconia‐based anterior resin‐bonded single‐retainer cantilever fixed dental prostheses: A 15‐ to 61‐month follow‐up</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Prosthodontics</source>, <volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>286</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148991</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0015">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0015"><string-name><surname>Kurt</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Turhan Bal</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Effects of accelerated artificial aging on the translucency and color stability of monolithic ceramics with different surface treatments</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry</source>, <volume>121</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>712.e1</fpage>–<lpage>712.e8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0016">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0016"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>, <given-names>X. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>, <given-names>M. M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The primary evaluation of minimal prepared ceramic veneer in anterior teeth for clinical application</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua kou qiang yi xue za zhi—Zhonghua kouqiang yixue zazhi—Chinese Journal of Stomatology</source>, <volume>47</volume>(<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>617</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23302385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0017">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0017"><string-name><surname>McLaren</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>, <given-names>P. T.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Ceramic in dentistry, part I: Classes of materials</article-title>. <source>Inside Dentistry</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>9</issue>).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0018">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0018"><string-name><surname>Miwa</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kori</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tuskiyama</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuwatsuru</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsushita</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Koano</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Fit of e.max crowns fabricated using conventional and CAD/CAM technology: A comparative study</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Prosthodontics, December</source>, <volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>607</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0019">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0019"><string-name><surname>Morita</surname>, <given-names>R. K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayashida</surname>, <given-names>M. F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pupo</surname>, <given-names>Y. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berger</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reggiani</surname>, <given-names>R. D.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Betiol</surname>, <given-names>E. A. G.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Minimally invasive laminate veneers: Clinical aspects in treatment planning and cementation procedures</article-title>. <source>Case Reports in Dentistry</source>, <volume>2016</volume>, <elocation-id>1839793</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28070427</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0020">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0020"><string-name><surname>Nejatidanesh</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savabi</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amjadi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbasi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Savabi</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Five year clinical outcomes and survival of chairside CAD/CAM ceramic laminate veneers—A retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Prosthodontic Research</source>, <volume>62</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29936052</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0021">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0021"><string-name><surname>Özdemir</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Özdoğan</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The effect of heat treatments applied to superstructure porcelain on the mechanical properties and microstructure of lithium disilicate glass ceramics</article-title>. <source>Dental Materials Journal</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28450675</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0022">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0022"><string-name><surname>Peláez</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cogolludo</surname>, <given-names>P. G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serrano</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lozano</surname>, <given-names>J. F. L.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Suárez</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A prospective evaluation of zirconia posterior fixed dental prostheses: Three‐year clinical results</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry</source>, <volume>107</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22633593</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0023">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0023"><string-name><surname>Radz</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Minimum thickness anterior porcelain restorations</article-title>. <source>Dental Clinics of North America</source>, <volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21473998</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0024">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0024"><string-name><surname>Rasetto</surname>, <given-names>F. H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Driscoll</surname>, <given-names>C. F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prestipino</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masri</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>von Fraunhofer</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Light transmission through all‐ceramic dental materials: A pilot study</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry</source>, <volume>91</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15153851</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0025">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0025"><string-name><surname>Rueggeberg</surname>, <given-names>F. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caughman</surname>, <given-names>W. F.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Curtis</surname>, <suffix>Jr.</suffix>, <given-names>J. W.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Effect of light intensity and exposure duration on cure of resin composite</article-title>. <source>Operative Dentistry</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8183730</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0026">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0026"><string-name><surname>Sailer</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Hämmerle</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Zirconia ceramic single‐retainer resin‐bonded fixed dental prostheses (RBFDPs) after 4 years of clinical service: A retrospective clinical and volumetric study</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Periodontics &amp; Restorative Dentistry</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24804284</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0027">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cre2790-cit-0027"><string-name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname>, <given-names>R. L.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Powers</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Craig's Restorative Dental Materials</source> (Vol. <volume>213</volume>). <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0028">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0028"><string-name><surname>Souza</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbosa</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Araújo</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyashita</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bottino</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melo</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Ultrathin monolithic zirconia veneers: Reality or future? Report of a clinical case and one‐year follow‐up</article-title>. <source>Operative Dentistry</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29284106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0029">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0029"><string-name><surname>Sun</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Single‐tooth replacement in the anterior arch by means of a cantilevered IPS e.max press veneer‐retained fixed partial denture: Case series of 35 patients</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Prosthodontics</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23476915</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0030">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0030"><string-name><surname>Wassell</surname>, <given-names>R. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St. George</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ingledew</surname>, <given-names>R. P.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Steele</surname>, <given-names>J. G.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Crowns and other extra‐coronal restorations: Provisional restorations</article-title>. <source>British Dental Journal</source>, <volume>192</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>619</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12108942</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0031">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0031"><string-name><surname>Yuce</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ulusoy</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Turk</surname>, <given-names>A. G.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Comparison of marginal and internal adaptation of heat‐pressed and CAD/CAM porcelain laminate veneers and a 2‐year follow‐up</article-title>. <source>Journal of Prosthodontics</source>, <volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29271526</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0032">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0032"><string-name><surname>Zanotto</surname>, <given-names>E. D.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Bright future for glass‐ceramics</article-title>. <source>American Ceramic Society Bulletin</source>, <volume>89</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2790-bib-0033">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2790-cit-0033"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yi</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>A comparative study of progressive wear of four dental monolithic, veneered glass‐ceramics</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Mechanical Behavior of Biomedical Materials</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28595102</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
