<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10896781" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10896781</identifier>
        <datestamp>2024-02-28</datestamp>
        <setSpec>springeropen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Oral Investig</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Oral Investig</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Clinical Oral Investigations</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1432-6981</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1436-3771</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10896781</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10896781</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10896781</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38407635</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38407635</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5565</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00784-024-05565-x</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Is it possible to extract primary maxillary molars without palatal injection?: a controlled clinical trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8241-1310</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>TUĞUTLU</surname>
                    <given-names>Esra Ceren</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>cerentatli88@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0828-4533</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>SANCAK</surname>
                    <given-names>Kevser</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ryemn72</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449874.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0454 9762</institution-id><institution>Department of Pedodontics, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Ankara Yıldırım Beyazıt University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ankara, Türkiye </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ryemn72</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449874.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0454 9762</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Ankara Yıldırım Beyazıt University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ankara, Türkiye </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>28</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <elocation-id>174</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2024</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p id="Par1">The absolute necessity of a palatal injection for the extraction of primary maxillary molars has never been explored, despite the fact that it is widely known that children do not tolerate local anesthetic injections into the palatal tissue well. The aim of this study was to compare separately the perception of pain in the absence of palatal injection after anesthesia and maxillary primary molar tooth extraction using different anesthetic solutions and different post-anesthetic waiting times.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Materials and methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">A single-blinded randomized controlled study was conducted in 78 participants (26 patients with palatal anesthesia (the control groups), and 26 patients with 5 min and 26 patients with 8 min post-anesthetic waiting time without palatal anesthesia (the study groups)). Subjective experiences of pain were evaluated separately after anesthesia and tooth extraction using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) and the Wong-Baker Faces Pain Rating Scale (WBS).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">In terms of VAS scores obtained following administration of anesthesia, there was a statistically significant difference between the groups (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). VAS pain scores were reported to be lower in the groups without palatal anesthesia than in the groups with palatal anesthesia. No statistically significant difference was observed in VAS and Wong-Baker scores after tooth extraction between the groups with and without palatal anesthesia (<italic>P</italic>&gt;0.05).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p id="Par4">While the pain reported following administration of anesthesia was found to be higher in the groups receiving palatal anesthesia, no difference was found between the groups in the pain reported after tooth extraction.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Clinical relevance</title>
                  <p id="Par5">Extraction of maxillary primary molars is possible without palatal injection by injecting 4% articaine or 2% lidocaine into the buccal vestibule of the tooth with a waiting time of 5 or 8 min.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Local anesthesia</kwd>
                <kwd>Pain perception</kwd>
                <kwd>Tooth extraction</kwd>
                <kwd>Injections</kwd>
                <kwd>Articaine</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>Ankara Yıldırım Beyazıt University</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <open-access>
                  <p>Open access funding provided by the Scientific and Technological Research Council of Türkiye (TÜBİTAK).</p>
                </open-access>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par6">The American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry (AAPD) recognizes that the pain experienced by children and adolescents due to inadequate pain management during dental procedures can have significant physical and psychological consequences for the patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Tooth extraction is an invasive procedure in which pain control is critical for reducing anxiety and improving children’s cooperation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The key to avoiding pain during this procedure is the use of local anesthesia. Yet the local anesthetic injection itself can also trigger anxiety, which causes pain and leads to difficulties in behavior management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Palatal injections in particular are known to be poorly tolerated by the majority of both adults and pediatric patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. For this reason, many studies have investigated whether maxillary teeth extraction can be performed without palatal anesthesia in the adult patient group, and it has been concluded that buccal infiltration anesthesia is sufficient for permanent maxillary permanent teeth extraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. However, this issue has never to our knowledge been investigated in the pediatric patient group.</p>
              <p id="Par7">Furthermore, in several studies, various different waiting times have been investigated when performing maxillary molar tooth extraction without palatal anesthesia. In many studies, it was reported that a 5-minute waiting time was sufficient for the anesthetic agent to spread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Sharma et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] reported that a waiting period of 6–7 min eliminated the need for palatal injection of articaine and lidocaine infiltration, while Sekhar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] found that this required a period of 8 min. Lima-Júnior et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] suggested that with a 10-minute waiting time, a painless extraction could be performed with only buccal anesthesia.</p>
              <p id="Par8">In the last century, local anesthetics formed the basis of pain control in dentistry and various solutions were used. Lidocaine, which was first used in 1948, is considered the gold standard of local anesthetics and is the most widely used injectable amide local anesthetic agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Articaine hydrochloride is an anesthetic solution first produced by H. Rusching et al. in 1969; it acts similarly to other amide anesthetics but has several advantages over them due to differences in chemical conformation, including higher intraneural concentrations, greater longitudinal diffusion, and better conduction blockading [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par9">Assessing children’s pain is important both for planning and determining the effectiveness of dental treatments. The assessment of pain, whether acute or chronic, should be simple, practical and as objective as possible. Because pain is a subjective experience, self-report of the intensity of pain is the preferred method of assessment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. A wide variety of pain rating scales are used to assess acute pain, including the Visual Analog Scale (VAS), the Descriptive Pain Scale, the Faces Pain Scale, the Numerical Pain Scale and the Analog Chromatic Scale. One of these scales, the Wong-Baker Faces Pain Rating Scale (WBS), has undergone extensive psychometric evaluation and is currently considered suitable for use in children aged three to eighteen years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Another frequently used scale is the VAS, which is also known to give reliable results in the assessment of acute pain in children over eight years of age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par10">The hypothesis of this study was that painless extraction can be performed using only buccal infiltration anesthesia via both articaine and lidocaine. The patient’s perception of pain may not change or decrease in primary maxillary molar extractions without palatal anesthesia. The aim of this study was thus (1) to evaluate the level of anesthesia administered and the post-extraction perception of pain, and (2) to determine which local anesthetic solution and post-anesthetic waiting time were more successful in maxillary primary teeth extraction in children who did not undergo palatal anesthesia.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Ethics and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par11">Ethics committee approval was obtained from the Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, at Ankara Yıldırım Beyazıt University (Date: 27.04.2022, No: 06). The study was registered retrospectively at ClinicalTrials.gov (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier, NCT06025825). The Declaration of Helsinki and good clinical practices were followed during the study. Before starting the study, the patients and their families were informed about its content, and written informed consent was obtained from the parents. This prospective, randomized controlled, single-blind trial was conducted in accordance with the CONSORT (Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials) statement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Patient selection</title>
                <p id="Par12">To estimate the sample size, power analysis was performed with the G*Power 3.1 program, with reference to study of Bataneih et al., and with a 0.52 effect size, 95% power and 5% error level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Patients aged 8–12 years, of both genders, who attended the Faculty of Dentistry Hospital at Ankara Yıldırım Beyazıt University for a routine dental examination and treatment, and who had at least one maxillary molar tooth extraction indication, were included in the study. Children with any chronic/systemic disease, acute toothache, history of tooth extraction, allergy to benzocaine, lidocaine or articaine, and Frankl’s 1 or Frankl’s 2 behavior ratings were excluded from the study. The CONSORT flow diagram (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) depicts the enrollment, randomization, allocation, and completion of patients in groups. Patients who had at least one-third of the tooth root for which extraction was indicated were included in the study.</p>
                <p id="Par13">The groups were determined as follows:</p>
                <p id="Par14">Group 1. Buccal infiltration anesthesia + palatal infiltration anesthesia (with articaine HCl) (Control group).</p>
                <p id="Par15">Group 2. Buccal infiltration anesthesia (5 minutes’ waiting time after anesthesia with articaine HCl).</p>
                <p id="Par16">Group 3. Buccal infiltration anesthesia (8 minutes’ waiting time after anesthesia with articaine HCl).</p>
                <p id="Par17">Group 4. Buccal infiltration anesthesia + palatal infiltration anesthesia (with lidocaine HCl) (Control group).</p>
                <p id="Par18">Group 5. Buccal infiltration anesthesia (5 minutes’ waiting time after anesthesia with lidocaine HCl).</p>
                <p id="Par19">Group 6. Buccal infiltration anesthesia (8 minutes’ waiting time after anesthesia with lidocaine HCl).</p>
                <p id="Par20">
                  <fig id="Fig1">
                    <label>Fig. 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Flow diagram</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="784_2024_5565_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e285"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Study procedures</title>
                <p id="Par21">All anesthesia administration and tooth extractions were performed by the same pediatric dentist, who had 10 years of clinical experience. Before the solution was administered, the injection site was dried with a cotton and Ultracare 20% benzocaine gel (Ultradent Products Inc., South Jordan, UT, USA) was applied to the prepared injection site for 1 min. Following this, lidocaine hydrochloride 2% containing 0.0125 mg/ml epinephrine with Jetocain (Adeka İlaç Sanayi ve Ticaret A.Ş, İstanbul, Türkiye) or articaine hydrochloride 4% containing 0.012 mg epinephrine hydrochloride with Ultracaine D-S (Sanofi Aventis Deutschland GmbH, Frankfurt, Germany) (0.8 cc for buccal and 0.2 cc for palatal infiltration anesthesia) was injected through a Morita 30G dental needle using a Paroject intraligamental syringe in the mucobuccal fold area closest to the extracted tooth. After the local anesthesia applications, tooth extractions were performed after waiting 5 min for groups 1, 2, 4 and 5, and after 8 min for groups 3 and 6.</p>
                <p id="Par22">The VAS and Wong-Baker scores of the participants were recorded separately following the administration of local anesthesia and tooth extractions. In order to determine the scores, the participants were asked the following questions:</p>
                <p id="Par23">
                  <list list-type="order">
                    <list-item>
                      <p id="Par24">“‘0’ represents no pain and ‘100’ represents the worst possible pain. Can you give a score for the pain you feel?” (for the VAS) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p id="Par25">“These faces are ranked from ‘happy’ to ‘unhappy’ and show how much it hurts. Can you point to the face that shows how much pain you are feeling?” (for the WBS) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p id="Par26">All questions were asked by a single, non-operator evaluator (KS) who was blinded to the study groups.</p>
                <p id="Par27">
                  <fig id="Fig2">
                    <label>Fig. 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="784_2024_5565_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e323"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p id="Par28">
                  <fig id="Fig3">
                    <label>Fig. 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Wong-Baker Faces Pain Rating Scale (WBS)</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="784_2024_5565_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e333"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par29">The analysis of the data was performed with the IBM SPSS 26.0 program (IBM Corporations, Armonk, New York, USA). Descriptive statistics were used for discrete numerical variables and were expressed as mean ± standard deviation or median (minimum-maximum), while categorical variables were expressed as number of cases and percentage (%). Whether the distribution of discrete numerical variables was close to normal was investigated using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. The significance of the difference between the groups in terms of mean values was evaluated with the Kruskal-Wallis H test. If the Kruskal-Wallis H test results were found to be significant, the group(s) causing the difference was/were determined using the Mann-Whitney U test. In addition, comparisons between groups using articaine and lidocaine were made with the Mann-Whitney U test. The statistical significance level was accepted as <italic>P</italic> = 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="Par30">The overall study sample consisted of 78 patients, 40 (51.3%) females and 38 (48.7%) males, and their ages ranged from 8 to 12 years with a mean of 9.34 (± 1.20) years. The differences in gender and age distribution between the six groups were statistically insignificant (<italic>p</italic> = 0.71 and <italic>p</italic> = 0.82). Also, there were no statistically significant differences between the six groups in terms of Frankl scores (<italic>p</italic> = 0.93) and the distribution of extracted teeth (<italic>p</italic> = 0.09).</p>
              <p id="Par31">The distribution of Wong-Baker scores after local anesthesia according to groups are given in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. In terms of post-anesthesia Wong-Baker scores, there was no statistically significant difference between the groups (<italic>p</italic> = 0.10).</p>
              <p id="Par32">
                <table-wrap id="Tab1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Distribution of Wong-Baker scores according to groups after local anesthesia</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left">Wong-Baker Scores</th>
                        <th align="left">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th align="left">P Value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 1 (control group with articaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.92 ± 1.44</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="6">0.10</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 2 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">2.15 ± 1.06</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 3 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/8-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.76 ± 1.30</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 4 (control group with lidocaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">2.53 ± 1.39</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 5 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with lidocaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.15 ± 0.98</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 6 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with lidocaine/8-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">2.15 ± 0.89</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>Data are expressed as mean ± SD (standard deviation). Comparison between groups was made using the Kruskal-Wallis H test</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p id="Par33">A statistically significant difference was detected between the groups in terms of VAS scores measured after anesthesia (<italic>p</italic> = 0.019). As a result of the pairwise comparisons, there was statistically significant difference in VAS scores between the first and third groups (<italic>p</italic> = 0.023). The mean VAS scores in the third group were found to be statistically significantly lower than those of the first group. Additionally, there was a statistically significant difference between the fifth group and the first, second, fourth and sixth groups (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03, <italic>p</italic> = 0.015, <italic>p</italic> = 0.012, <italic>p</italic> = 0.035). The mean VAS scores in the fifth group were found to be statistically significantly lower than the first, second, fourth and sixth groups (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p>
              <p id="Par34">
                <table-wrap id="Tab2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Distribution of VAS scores according to groups after local anesthesia</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left">VAS Scores</th>
                        <th align="left">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th align="left">P Value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 1 (control group with articaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">40.00 ± 23.89</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="6">0.019*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 2 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">33.07 ± 20.56</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 3 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/8-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">22.30 ± 26.50</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 4 (control group with lidocaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">37.15 ± 28.98</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 5 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with lidocaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">13.53 ± 12.68</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 6 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with lidocaine/8-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">33.23 ± 24.32</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>Data are expressed as mean ± SD (standard deviation). Comparison between groups was made using the Kruskal-Wallis H test. VAS = Visual Analog Scale. *Statistically significant difference</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p id="Par35">There were no differences between the groups in terms of post-extraction Wong-Baker and VAS scores (<italic>p</italic> = 0.44 and <italic>p</italic> = 0.09) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p>
              <p id="Par36">
                <table-wrap id="Tab3">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Distribution of Wong-Baker and VAS scores according to groups after tooth-extractions</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left">Wong-Baker Scores</th>
                        <th align="left">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th align="left">P Value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 1 (control group with articaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">2.00 ± 1.08</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="6">0.44</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 2 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">2.61 ± 1.19</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 3 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/8-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.76 ± 1.58</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 4 (control group with lidocaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.76 ± 1.23</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 5 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with lidocaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.61 ± 1.38</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 6 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with lidocaine/8-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">2.30 ± 2.09</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">VAS Scores</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 1 (control group with articaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">36.15 ± 23.19</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="6">0.09</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 2 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">46.15 ± 25.26</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 3 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with articaine/8-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">21.76 ± 29.47</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 4 (control group with lidocaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">27.61 ± 24.02</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 5 (buccal infiltration anesthesia with lidocaine/5-min. waiting time)</td>
                        <td align="left">24.00 ± 30.29</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Group 6 (buccal infiltration anesthesia + 8-min. waiting time with lidocaine)</td>
                        <td align="left">40.38 ± 36.08</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>Data are expressed as mean ± SD (standard deviation). Comparison between groups was made using the Kruskal-Wallis H test. VAS = Visual Analog Scale</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p id="Par37">Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> shows the distribution of Wong-Baker and VAS scores obtained after anesthesia and after tooth extraction in the groups that employed articaine and lidocaine as local anesthetics. There were no differences between the articaine and lidocaine groups in terms of post-anesthesia and post-extraction Wong-Baker and VAS scores.</p>
              <p id="Par38">
                <table-wrap id="Tab4">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Distribution of Wong-Baker and VAS scores according to articaine and lidocaine groups after local anesthesia and tooth extractions</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left">Wong-Baker Scores</th>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left">Mean±SD</th>
                        <th align="left">P Value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">Post-anesthesia</td>
                        <td align="left">Articaine</td>
                        <td align="left">1.94 ± 1.25</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">0.984</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Lidocaine</td>
                        <td align="left">1.94 ± 1.23</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">Post-extraction</td>
                        <td align="left">Articaine</td>
                        <td align="left">2.12 ± 1.32</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">0.312</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Lidocaine</td>
                        <td align="left">1.89 ± 1.60</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">VAS Scores</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">Mean±SD</td>
                        <td align="left">P Value</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">Post-anesthesia</td>
                        <td align="left">Articaine</td>
                        <td align="left">31.79 ± 24.29</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">0.381</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Lidocaine</td>
                        <td align="left">27.97 ± 24.74</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">Post-extraction</td>
                        <td align="left">Articaine</td>
                        <td align="left">34.69 ± 27.36</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2">0.384</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Lidocaine</td>
                        <td align="left">30.66 ± 30.56</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>Data are expressed as mean ± SD (standard deviation). Comparison between groups was made using the Mann-Whitney U test. VAS = Visual Analog Scale</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par39">The aim of the study was to evaluate the pain experienced after anesthesia administration and in the post-extraction period in groups which had had buccal infiltration anesthesia with and without palatal anesthesia. The study’s hypothesis was accepted since there was no difference between the groups regarding post-anesthesia and post-extraction pain. This hypothesis was based on the claim that a buccally-administered local anesthetic agent may spread to the soft and hard tissues around the tooth and could eliminate the need for palatal injection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par40">Injection of local anesthesia in pediatric patients is a serious challenge and palatal injections are considered one of the most traumatic procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The palatal mucosa is tightly connected to the underlying periosteum and has an abundant nerve supply underneath. For this reason, palatal anesthesia is more painful than anesthesia applied to other areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In palatal injection, pain occurs due to the accumulation of the anesthetic in a narrow area and the displacement of the mucoperiosteum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. A child who experiences this kind of pain may become uncooperative and exhibit extreme dental anxiety or fear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par41">Many techniques can be used to reduce the discomfort of intraoral injections, including topical anesthetic application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], topical cold application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], computerized injection systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], pressure application, eutectic mixture of local anesthetics (EMLA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and transcutaneous electronic nerve stimulation (TENS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Although different injection and auxiliary techniques have been developed, palatal injection is still a discomforting and painful procedure for patients and is not universally accepted. The literature suggests that bypassing palatal injection makes the anesthesia procedure significantly more comfortable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Providing palatal anesthesia through buccal infiltration is a more feasible method than others. There are studies showing the effectiveness of this method in permanent and deciduous teeth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. To our knowledge, there is no study comparing the perception of anesthesia and post-extraction pain after maxillary primary molar tooth extraction in children in terms of the type of anesthesia and waiting time.</p>
              <p id="Par42">The current study found that there was no difference related to pain after anesthesia and primary molar tooth extraction between groups to which buccal anesthesia with palatal anesthesia was applied and groups to which buccal anesthesia without palatal anesthesia was applied. Uçkan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] showed in their study that painless tooth extraction can be performed in permanent maxillary cases via buccal infiltration anesthesia without palatal injection. Kolli et al. demonstrated that palatal injection could be left out in the extraction of primary maxillary molar teeth, in parallel with the results of the current study. Nevertheless they found that articaine was more effective than lidocaine during extraction with buccal infiltration anesthesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] stated in their review that a single buccal injection for primary molar extractions eliminates painful palatal injections and provides a potential advantage during treatment in pediatric patients.</p>
              <p id="Par43">The secondary aim of this study was to compare the efficacy of anesthesia with 4% articaine versus 2% lidocaine after anesthesia and tooth extraction in providing adequate palatal anesthesia with buccal injections. The present study found no difference between the efficacy of articaine and lidocaine during anesthesia and extraction. Many authors have reported that extraction of maxillary teeth is possible with buccal infiltration anesthesia without palatal injection alone, as articaine has superior anesthetic and diffusion properties, and some authors have reported similar results for lidocaine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Bataneih et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] concluded that the type of anesthetic solution did not make a difference in the perception of the pain of the injection. This may be explained by the fact that the maxilla has a porous bone structure and is thinner in children, which facilitates the diffusion of local anesthetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. According to research by Bahrololoomi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], there is no difference between lidocaine and articaine when it comes to the removal of primary maxillary molar teeth, and their study attributed this outcome to the increased binding affinity of articaine to plasma proteins and the higher partition coefficient of lidocaine. Massignan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] reported no difference between articaine and lidocaine on primary maxillary molar teeth for which extraction was planned and buccal anesthesia was applied; however, they found that articaine caused more injection pain. Contrary to this study, according to research by Mittal et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], articaine was insufficient for palatal anesthesia during the extraction of maxillary primary molars.</p>
              <p id="Par44">Additionally, the present study aimed to evaluate the effect of waiting time after anesthesia in terms of anesthetic agents and pain perception. It was found that a waiting period of both 5 and 8 min after buccal infiltration anesthesia was effective in anesthesia and post-extraction pain control. Also, no difference was observed in patients who were given articaine or lidocaine in terms of waiting time. This suggests that the diffusion properties of articaine and lidocaine are similar. Lima-Júnior et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] suggested that with a 10-minute waiting period, a painless extraction can be performed with only buccal anesthesia. However, Uçkan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] reported that a 5-minute waiting time is sufficient for the anesthetic agent to spread. Sekhar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] reported that a waiting period of 8 min eliminated the need for palatal injection of lidocaine infiltration.</p>
              <p id="Par45">The basic factor in treating children is to manage their fear, anxiety and pain, so it is important to assess and record these conditions, using reliable and valid methods to help them communicate the level of pain they are experiencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Pain can be measured using techniques such as self-report, biomarkers, and behavioral assessment, because pain is itself subjective. Self-report assessment is, however, most commonly recommended in the literature for the evaluation of pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Since perception of pain is complex and multidimensional, studies have suggested the use of more than one scale to evaluate children’s experience of pain, and have reported that both the VAS and WBS are appropriate subjective pain assessment tools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. It is widely accepted that the WBS is suitable for assessing acute pain in children aged 3 to 18 years and the VAS in children over 8 years of age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Therefore, in the current study, the VAS and WBS were used together to evaluate the perception of pain after anesthesia and extraction in children between the ages of 8 and 12.</p>
              <p id="Par46">This study has some limitations. One of these is that the primary fourth and fifth teeth could have been evaluated separately. Further studies on this topic could do this. A second limitation is that objective evaluations (systolic pressure, heart rate measurement etc.) were not carried out. A third limitation is that the outcomes could be different from those of the current study in patients of different ages, particularly in young children who are uncooperative during anesthetic procedures. Consequently, including participants with a wider age range could have given us more information about the exact age limit for the application of this technique. Randomized and single or double-blinded clinical studies with larger sample populations should be conducted in future.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="conclusion">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="Par47">Discomfort caused by palatal injection may preclude treating children; the authors therefore recommend that clinicians administer a single buccal infiltration of articaine or lidocaine and avoid palatal infiltration. According to the findings of the present study, extraction of primary maxillary molars without palatal anesthesia is possible with buccal infiltration of articaine or lidocaine with a waiting time of 5 or 8 min. Performing primary molar extractions with only buccal anesthesia reduces the number of injections and eliminates painful palatal injections, thus increasing the treatment compliance of pediatric patients.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>E.C.T. and K.S. conceived the ideas; E.C.T. and K.S. collected the data; E.C.T. analysed the data; E.C.T. and K.S. led the writing of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.’</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>No funding was obtained for this study.</p>
              <p>Open access funding provided by the Scientific and Technological Research Council of Türkiye (TÜBİTAK).</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data availability</title>
              <p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar3">
                <title>Ethical approval</title>
                <p id="Par50">This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, at Ankara Yıldırım Beyazıt University (Date: 27.04.2022, No: 06).</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar4">
                <title>Informed consent</title>
                <p id="Par51">Written informed consent was obtained from the parents of all participants included in the study.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par48">The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain management in infants, children, adolescents and individuals with special health care needs</article-title>
                  <source>The reference Manual of Pediatric Dentistry</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Chicago, Ill</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>American Academy</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bahrololoomi</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rezaei</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Anesthetic efficacy of single buccal infiltration of 4% articaine compared to routine inferior alveolar nerve block with 2% lidocaine during bilateral extraction of mandibular primary molars: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Anesth Pain Med</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <lpage>69</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17245/jdapm.2021.21.1.61</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33585685?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33585685</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smail-Faugeron</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muller-Bolla, Sixou</surname>
                      <given-names>MJL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Courson</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Split-mouth and parallel-arm trials to compare pain with intraosseous anaesthesia delivered by the computerised quicksleeper system and conventional infiltration anaesthesia in paediatric oral healthcare: protocol for a randomised controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ open</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>e007724</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-007724</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26163031?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26163031</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aminabadi</surname>
                      <given-names>NA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farahani</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oskouei</surname>
                      <given-names>SG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Site-specificity of pain sensitivity to intraoral anesthetic injections in children</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <lpage>243</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2334/josnusd.51.239</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19550092?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19550092</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bataineh</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nusair</surname>
                      <given-names>YM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Rahahleh</surname>
                      <given-names>RQ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative study of articaine and lidocaine without palatal injection for maxillary teeth extraction</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Oral Invest</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>3239</fpage>
                  <lpage>3248</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00784-018-2738-x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uckan</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dayangac</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Araz</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is permanent maxillary tooth removal without palatal injection possible?</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endodontology</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>102</volume>
                  <fpage>733</fpage>
                  <lpage>735</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tripleo.2005.12.005</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aseri</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batta</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singh</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pilania</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>YK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Maxillary posterior teeth removal without palatal injection–truth or myth: a dilemma for oral surgeons</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Diagn Research: JCDR</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>ZC01</fpage>
                  <lpage>ZC04</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7860/JCDR/2014/10378.5092</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Badcock</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McCullough</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Palatal anaesthesia for the removal of maxillary third molars as practised by oral and maxillofacial surgeons in Australia and New Zealand</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>52</volume>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <lpage>332</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1834-7819.2007.tb00510.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18265690?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18265690</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rathi</surname>
                      <given-names>NV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khatri</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Agrawal</surname>
                      <given-names>AG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thosar</surname>
                      <given-names>NR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deolia</surname>
                      <given-names>SG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Anesthetic efficacy of buccal infiltration articaine versus lidocaine for extraction of primary molar teeth</article-title>
                  <source>Anesth Prog</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>66</volume>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2344/anpr-65-04-02</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30883236?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30883236</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sekhar</surname>
                      <given-names>GR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nagaraju</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nandagopal</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sudheer</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is palatal injection mandatory prior to extraction of permanent maxillary tooth: a preliminary study</article-title>
                  <source>Indian J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <lpage>102</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0970-9290.80006</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21525686?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21525686</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima Júnior</surname>
                      <given-names>JLD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dias-Ribeiro</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Araújo</surname>
                      <given-names>TN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferreira Rocha</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Honfi Júnior</surname>
                      <given-names>ES</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarmento</surname>
                      <given-names>CFDM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seabra</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sousa</surname>
                      <given-names>MDSCD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the buccal vestibule-palatal diffusion of 4% articaine hydrochloride in impacted maxillary third molar extractions</article-title>
                  <source>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <lpage>132</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Malamed S (2004) Clinical action of specific agents. Mosby-Year Book Inc. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://rlmc.edu.pk/themes/images/gallery/library/books/dental/%5BStanley_F._Malamed%5D_Handbook_of_Local_Anesthesia,(BookFi).pdf">https://rlmc.edu.pk/themes/images/gallery/library/books/dental/%5BStanley_F._Malamed%5D_Handbook_of_Local_Anesthesia,(BookFi).pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 20 November 2023</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ortel</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rahn</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kirch</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics of articaine</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
                  <lpage>425</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003088-199733060-00002</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9435991</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garra</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singer</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taira</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chohan</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cardoz</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chisena</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thode</surname>
                      <given-names>HC</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validation of the Wong-Baker FACES pain rating scale in pediatric emergency department patients</article-title>
                  <source>Acad Emerg Med</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <lpage>54</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1553-2712.2009.00620.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20003121?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003121</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chandran</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain assessment in children using a modified wong baker faces pain rating scale</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Clin Prev Dentistry</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <lpage>205</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15236/ijcpd.2019.15.4.202</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Powell</surname>
                      <given-names>CV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelly</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williams</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determining the minimum clinically significant difference in visual analog pain score for children</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <lpage>31</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mem.2001.111517</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11145767?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11145767</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schulz</surname>
                      <given-names>KF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Altman</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moher</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>CONSORT 2010 statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.c332</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bahrololoomi</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maghsoudi</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Articaine use does not routinely eliminate the need for palatal injections for primary maxillary molar extractions: a randomized cross-over clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Maxillofacial Surg</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>603</fpage>
                  <lpage>611</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10006-021-01021-2</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ram</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peretz</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Administering local anaesthesia to paediatric dental patients–current status and prospects for the future</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Pediatr Dent</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <lpage>89</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-263X.2002.00343.x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meechan</surname>
                      <given-names>JG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effective topical anesthetic agents and techniques</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Clin</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <fpage>759</fpage>
                  <lpage>766</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harbert</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Topical ice: a precursor to palatal injections</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <lpage>28</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0099-2399(89)80094-9</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 2607263?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2607263</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Friedman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hochman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A 21st century computerized injection system for local pain control</article-title>
                  <source>Compendium Continuing Educ Dentistry</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>995</fpage>
                  <lpage>1000</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meechan</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winter</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of topical anaesthesia and electronic nerve stimulation for reducing the pain of intra-oral injections</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dent J</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>181</volume>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
                  <lpage>335</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.4809252</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8972953?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8972953</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumaresan</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Srinivasan</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pendayala</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of the effectiveness of lidocaine in permanent maxillary teeth removal performed with single buccal infiltration versus routine buccal and palatal injection</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
                  <lpage>257</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12663-014-0624-x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kolli</surname>
                      <given-names>NKR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nirmala</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nuvvula</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effectiveness of articaine and lidocaine single buccal infiltration versus conventional buccal and palatal injection using lidocaine during primary maxillary molar extraction: a randomized control trial</article-title>
                  <source>Anesth Essays Researches</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>160164</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0259-1162.186589</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiang</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ji</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of Articaine vs Lignocaine for infiltration anaesthesia during primary molar extractions</article-title>
                  <source>Pakistan J Med Sci</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>1048</fpage>
                  <lpage>1055</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12669/pjms.38.4.5343</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fan</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>WL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>ZH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>ZQ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of the efficiencies of permanent maxillary tooth removal performed with single buccal infiltration versus routine buccal and palatal injection. Oral surgery, oral medicine, oral Pathology</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Radiol Endodontology</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>107</volume>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
                  <lpage>363</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tripleo.2008.08.025</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Massignan</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silveira Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cardoso</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bolan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy and adverse events of 4% articaine compared with 2% lidocaine on primary molar extraction: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>1031</fpage>
                  <lpage>1040</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joor.12989</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mittal</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chopra</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Srivastava</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of anesthetic efficacy of articaine and lidocaine during primary maxillary molar extractions in children</article-title>
                  <source>Pediatr Dent</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>520</fpage>
                  <lpage>524</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26883609?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26883609</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rathnam</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Madan</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Madan</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The language of pain: a short study</article-title>
                  <source>Contemp Clin Dent</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <lpage>145</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0976-237X.72778</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22114404?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114404</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Briggs</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Closs</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A descriptive study of the use of visual analogue scales and verbal rating scales for the assessment of postoperative pain in orthopedic patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Pain Symptom Manag</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>438</fpage>
                  <lpage>446</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0885-3924(99)00092-5</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khatri</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kalra</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of two pain scales in the assessment of dental pain in East Delhi children</article-title>
                  <source>Int Sch Res Notices</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>2012</volume>
                  <fpage>247351</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5402/2012/247351</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
