<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:49:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4243744" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4243744</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-11-26</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jaos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de São
Paulo</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4243744</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4243744</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4243744</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21552707</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21552707</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-77572011000200002</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Saliva and tongue coating pH before and after use of mouthwashes and
relationship with parameters of halitosis</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>TOLENTINO</surname>
                    <given-names>Elen de Souza</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>CHINELLATO</surname>
                    <given-names>Luiz Eduardo Montenegro</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>TARZIA</surname>
                    <given-names>Olinda</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> DDS, MSc, PhD student, Department of Stomatology, Bauru School of
Dentistry, University of São Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil. </aff>
              <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> PhD, Professor, Department of Stomatology, Bauru School of Dentistry,
University of São Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil. </aff>
              <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> PhD, Assistant Professor, Department of Biological Sciences, Bauru
School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil. </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Elen de Souza Tolentino - Rua:
Campos Sales, nº 255 - apto 602 - Zona 07 - 87020-080 - Maringá - PR - Brasil -
e-mail: <email>elen_tolentino@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>Mar-Apr</season>
                <year>2011</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Mar-Apr</season>
                <year>2011</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>19</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <fpage>90</fpage>
              <lpage>94</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>07</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>The aim of this work was to evaluate saliva and tongue coating pH in oral healthy
patients with morning bad breath before and after use of different oral
mouthrinses.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Material and Methods</title>
                  <p>aliva and tongue coating pH of 50 patients allocated in 5 groups were measured
respectively by a digital pHmeter and color pH indicators, before, immediately
after and 30 min after rinsing 5 different mouthrinses: cetilpiridine chloride
associated with sodium chloride, triclosan, enzymatic solution, essential oil and
distilled water.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Only triclosan and essential oil increased salivary pH immediately after rising.
The enzymatic solution decreased salivary and tongue coating pH immediately after
rinsing.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>Salivary pH tended to be acidic while tongue coating pH tended to be alkaline,
even after rising. Triclosan and essential oil mouthrinses increased salivary pH
immediately after rinsing. Enzymatic solution decreased saliva and tongue coating
pH immediately after rising.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Halitosis</kwd>
                <kwd>Saliva</kwd>
                <kwd>Tongue</kwd>
                <kwd>Mouthwashes</kwd>
                <kwd>pH</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>The existence of an association between tongue microorganisms and those present in
saliva has been reported<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. The
anaerobic microbiota of the tongue biofilm is one of the main responsible for the
release of sulfur-containing compounds (VSC), which are directly involved in the
occurrence of halitosis. The origin of halitosis has been localized in the oral cavity
in up to 85% of people suffering from this condition. In most cases, it is produced in
the mouth by the action of Gram-negative anaerobic bacteria on sulfur-containing
proteinaceous substrates in the saliva, such as debris and plaque<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The most common source of bad breath in individuals with good oral hygiene and healthy
periodontal tissues is from the posterior dorsum of the tongue<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>, where the crypts are the favored sites for growth of
the anaerobic bacteria responsible for halitosis. Several studies have implicated the
dorsum of the tongue as the primary site of microflora putrefaction and the production
of VSC<sup><xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The importance of halitosis has led to the formulation of different commercial products
that are claimed to have anti-halitosis effect. The mechanisms of action of these
solutions are in general due to their antimicrobial or oxidizing properties or their
capacity to inhibit the formation of VSC, even in the presence of oral bacteria.
Antibacterial components such as chlorhexidine, cetylpyridinium chloride, triclosan,
essential oils, chlorine dioxide, zinc salts, benzalkonium chloride, hydrogen peroxide
and sodium bicarbonate have been used in the treatment of halitosis, either alone or in
combination, and either as a single mode of therapy or together with the mechanical
treatment of tongue coating.</p>
              <p>pH is the major regulating factor in the formation of bad breath<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> and the chemical control of biofilm with
antimicrobial solutions may reduce the levels of microorganisms and VSC in patients with
halitosis complaint. It is thus important to carry out new studies with these products
and their actual influence on salivary and tongue coating pH, as well as investigate the
feasibility of the association of these aspects and the development of halitosis. The
aim of this work was to evaluate saliva and tongue coating pH in oral healthy patients
with physiological halitosis before and after use of different mouthrinses.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <p>This study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee of Bauru School of
Dentistry, University of São Paulo (Process nº 008/2008). Fifty oral and systemic
healthy dental students, aged over 18 years, from Bauru Dental School volunteered to
participate in this study.</p>
              <p>The exclusion criteria were subjects with medical disorders, such as diabetes mellitus,
renal disease, gastrointestinal disorders, respiratory diseases<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>, evidence of recent bronchitis,
sinusitis or tonsillitis<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, pregnant
women<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, patients undergoing
antibiotic or other antimicrobial therapy, smokers and those who, on pre-study clinical
screening, presented a probing depth ≥4 mm, cavitated caries lesion, naso-pharyngeal
alterations, mouth breathers and patients with prostheses, orthodontic or dental
appliances.</p>
              <p>Before examination, the patients received the following guidelines to improve
standardization of data collection: avoid, 24 h before the second consultation, spicy
and flavored food, coffee, tea or alcoholic beverage; the night before perform oral
hygiene as usual; be fasting for 8 h at the time of consultation; do not perform oral
hygiene, use any kind of mint flavoring or rinse solution or drink water before the
consultation.</p>
              <p>All patients attended two consultations, which were conducted by the same examiner. In
the first consultation, prior to the clinical examination, all subjects were asked to
fill out a questionnaire<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. Next,
clinical examination was performed, mainly aiming the analysis of oral and systemic
health of the patients. In the second consultation, all patients were seen in the
morning, at 7 a.m., fasting for at least 8 h and without having performed any oral
hygiene procedures on the day of consultation<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>, but having performed oral hygiene as usual the previous night at
bedtime, with brushing and dental floss.</p>
              <p>Each patient underwent three collections of saliva samples: at the beginning of the
consultation, immediately after rising a specific solution, and 30 min after rising
(phases <italic>before</italic>, <italic>after</italic>, and <italic>30 min</italic>,
respectively). Each volunteer was submitted to a type of rinse with a specific oral
mouthrinse solution.</p>
              <p>The patients were randomly assigned to 5 groups of 10 volunteers each, distributed as
follows:</p>
              <p>- <italic>SC</italic> Group: rinses with sodium chlorite combined with cetylpyridinium
chloride - chlorine dioxide (Saúde Bucal<sup>®</sup>; Embatek Technology in Cosmetics
Ltd., São Paulo, SP, Brazil);</p>
              <p>-<italic>TS</italic> Group: rinses with combined solution of triclosan (0.03%), sodium
fluoride (225 ppm of fluorine) and copolymer PVM/MA (0.20%) <italic>Gantrez</italic>
(Colgate Total Plax Classic<sup>®</sup> 250 mL; Colgate-Palmolive and Industry Trade
Ltd., São Bernardo do Campo, SP, Brazil); </p>
              <p>-<italic>ES</italic> Group: rinses with enzyme solution – Lysozyme, Lactoferrin, Glucose
Oxidase and Lactoperoxidase (Biotène Mouthwash<sup>®</sup> 240 mL; Laclede, East
University Drive, Rancho Dominguez, CA, USA);</p>
              <p>-<italic>EO</italic> Group: rinses with essential oil (Listerine Cool Mint<sup>®</sup>
Oral antiseptic 1.5 L; Warner-Lambert Co., Morris Plains, NJ, USA);</p>
              <p>-<italic>CTRL</italic> Group (control): rinses with distilled water (placebo).</p>
              <p>Each volunteer rinsed with 20 mL of the solution for 30 s followed by gargling for 10
s.</p>
              <p>Before saliva collection, patients were kept seated for 5 min, relaxed and without
talking<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. Unstimulated saliva
was collected over a period of 5 min. Before collection, the mouth was emptied by an
initial swallow<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. The examinator asked
the subjects to spit out the produced saliva each 30 s in a plastic container (J-10;
Injeplast<sup>®</sup>, São Paulo, SP, Brazil)<sup><xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. This procedure was performed before and after rising, and after
30 min. </p>
              <p>Salivary pH was measured by a digital pH meter (Sentron Model 1001 pH System; Sentron
Incorporated, 33320, USA), calibrated with standard solutions of pH 4.0 and 7.0. The
electrode was washed with distilled water and dried with absorbent paper after each
analysis<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>In the same consultation, tongue coating pH was measured using pH indicator strips (pH
0-14; Merck, Darmstadt, Germany). One strip was placed on posterior tongue region, with
the patient with the mouth opened, for 1 min. The color change in the strip indicated
tongue coating pH. The measurements were performed before, immediately and 30 min after
rising.</p>
              <p>Data were analyzed statistically by two-way ANOVA and Tukey’s test. A significance level
of 5% was set for all analyses.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>The measurements of salivary and tongue coating pH in the 5 groups are presented in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">2</xref>. There was no statistically significant difference (p&gt;0.05) in the
salivary pH between the groups in the <italic>before</italic> and <italic>30
min</italic> phases. In the <italic>after</italic> phase, the <italic>ES</italic>
group presented mean values smaller than the <italic>EO</italic> and <italic>TS</italic>
groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>). In the groups
<italic>CTRL</italic> and <italic>SC</italic> there was no statistically significant
difference (p&gt;0.05) in salivary pH between the 3 phases. In the <italic>TS</italic>
and <italic>EO</italic> groups, the mean pH values in the <italic>after</italic> phase
were higher than the mean values obtained in the <italic>before</italic> and <italic>30
min</italic> phases. In the <italic>ES</italic> group, the mean pH values in the
<italic>before</italic> phase were higher than in the <italic>after</italic> phase
(<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table 4</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Mean and standard deviation (mean±sd) of saliva pH in the studied groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>n</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Phase</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>before</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>after</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>30min</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63±0.44</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.76±0.51</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82±0.43</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.58±0.36</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.87±0.43</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.74±0.26</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.80±0.27</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.59±0.35</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70±0.37</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EO</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.62±0.41</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.01±0.32</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.73±0.31</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTRL</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46±0.48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70±0.50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.74±0.33</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.62±0.40</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.79±0.44</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75±0.33</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Mean and standard deviation (mean±sd) of the tongue coating pH in the studied
groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>n</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Phase</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>before</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>after</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>30min</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50±0.53</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±0.48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50±0.53</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90±0.74</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EO</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±0.48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTRL</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±0.46</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.02±0.77</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28±0.45</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Multiple comparisons of pH in saliva between groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Phase</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>before</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>after</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>30min</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53±0.32<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.54±0.33<sup>ab</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57±0.36<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48±0.23<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71±0.27<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51±0.21<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57±0.28<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.33±0.16<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47±0.18<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52±0.19<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.78±0.17<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44±0.27<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48±0.25<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52±0.30<sup>ab</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52±0.21<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Groups with same letter at each stage have no statistically significant
difference between themselves (Tukey's test, p&gt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Multiple comparisons of pH in saliva between phases</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Phase</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group SC</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group TS</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group ES</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group EO</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group CTRL</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53±0.32<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48±0.23<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57±0.28<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52±0.19<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48±0.25<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">After</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.54±0.33<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71±0.27<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.33±0.16<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.78±0.17<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52±0.30<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30min</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57±0.36<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51±0.21<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47±0.18<sup>ab</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44±0.27<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52±0.21<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Phases with same letter at each stage have no statistically significant
difference between themselves (Tukey's test, p&gt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>In the tongue coating pH analysis, there was no statistically significant difference
(p&gt;0.05) between groups in the <italic>before</italic> and <italic>30 min</italic>
phases. In the <italic>after</italic> phase, the <italic>ES</italic> group presented
smaller mean values than all other groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t05">Table
5</xref>). In the <italic>SC, TS, EO </italic>and<italic> CTRL</italic> groups, there
were no statistically significant difference (p&gt;0.05) between the 3 phases. In the
<italic>ES</italic> group, average values in the <italic>after </italic>phase were
smaller than the average in the phases <italic>before</italic> and <italic>30
min</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t06">Table 6</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Multiple comparisons of pH in tongue coating between groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Phase</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>before</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>after</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>30min</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50±0.53<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±0.48<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50±0.53<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90±0.74<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EO</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±0.48<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTRL</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Groups with same letter at each stage have no statistically significant
difference between themselves (Tukey's test, p&gt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 6</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Multiple comparisons of pH in tongue coating between phases</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Phase</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group SC</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group TS</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group ES</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group EO</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group CTRL</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±0.48<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±0.48<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">After</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50±0.53<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90±0.74<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40±0.52<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30min</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50±0.53<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10±0.32<sup>b</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.42<sup>a</sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4.0±0.52<sup>a</sup></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Phases with same letter at each stage have no statistically significant
difference between themselves (Tukey's test, p&gt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>The reduction in salivary flow during sleep and consequent increase in the number of
epithelial cells scaled from oral mucosa lead to tongue coating formation and therefore
in halitosis, even in healthy pacients<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. Several masking and antimicrobial agents have been proposed to
control both physiological and pathological halitosis. Their clinical efficacy has often
been tested on morning breath<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> rather than in real clinical situations
for evident ethical reasons. It has been postulated that a decrease in salivation during
sleep promotes proliferation of the oral bacteria responsible for the release of the
offending gases in morning bad breath<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Strong evidence that morning breath
odor can be used as a model for investigation of other offensive odors is still lacking
but universally accepted<sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. This fact
justifies the use of oral healthy patients with morning breath odor in this
research.</p>
              <p>Saliva of individuals with "dry mouth" (common situation after a night of sleep) often
presents acidic pH<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. However, there is a tendency that salivary pH becomes
more alkaline during the day, by the act of talking or chewing. Salivary pH is slightly
acidic before its secretion in oral cavity. It becomes alkaline at the time of gland’s
secretion due to loss of carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) and increase of saliva’s
bicarbonate concentration when salivary flow is increased<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. Hypothetically, body fluid pHs remain relatively
constant because of buffering systems, fact that is not different in the saliva, which,
many times, keeps its pH constant, even after rising with acidic solutions, for example.
In the present study, the most notable changes in pH were observed immediately after
rising, but were stabilized after 30 min. Moreover, salivary pH remained slightly acidic
in all stages in all groups, possibly due to the effect of mouthrinses or the buffer
capacity of saliva.</p>
              <p>To discuss these findings of this study, we put in question whether salivary pH,
considered acidic after sleeping, would have a direct influence in halitosis or whether
morning breath odor is only due to increased mucosa desquamation and formation of tongue
coating. According to McNamara, et al.<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> (1972), pH is the major regulating factor in the formation of bad
breath and is clearly established that acidity inhibits the production of odors while
neutrality and alkalinity favor it<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.
The same context is applied to tongue coating pH, which has alkaline pH due to the
production of odorivetores during proteolysis<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. Among the final products of proteolysis are amines, ammonia and
urea, which have alkaline pH, characteristic of physiological or pathological
halitosis<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. It is also
questioned whether the use of mouthrinses could change these pH values and thus
influence, in the reduction of halitosis after their use. For that reason, it would be
logical that mouthrinses provide reduction of saliva and tongue coating pH in order to
reduce halitosis.</p>
              <p>In the present study, there was no statistically significant difference in salivary pH
between the groups, in the phases before and after 30 min of rinsing. In the
<italic>after</italic> phase, the <italic>ES</italic> group presented smaller mean
values than the <italic>TS</italic> and <italic>EO</italic> groups. In the
<italic>CTRL</italic> and <italic>SC</italic> groups, there was no statistically
significant difference in salivary pH between the 3 phases. In the <italic>TS</italic>
and <italic>EO</italic> groups, the mean pH values in the phase <italic>after</italic>
were higher than those recorded before and after 30 min of rinsing. In the
<italic>ES</italic> group, the mean pH values before rinsing was higher than
immediately after rinsing. According to the present research, rinsing with mouthwashes
based on triclosan and essential oils lead to an increase in salivary pH, both lasting
for 30 min. This can be explained by the fact that mouthrinses that cause mouth burning
(fact reported by the volunteers of the groups <italic>TS</italic> and
<italic>EO</italic>) stimulate salivation and thus increase salivary pH<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. For the <italic>ES</italic> group,
there was a pH decrease immediately after its use; however, there was no information in
literature about pH decreasing caused by enzymatic solutions.</p>
              <p>In the control group, in which the volunteers rinsed with distilled water, there was an
increase in salivary pH during the measurements. It can be explained because of the
increase in the saliva’s bicarbonate concentration when salivary flow is increased, a
condition that is common over time: salivary pH increases with the increase of
flow<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. In the study of Suarez,
et al.<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> (2000), patients with
complete oral health were submitted to measurements of bad breath after any kind of oral
hygiene and water only when necessary. The authors observed that the concentrations of
each gas tended to decrease in the first hour after waking. After this period the
concentration tended to remain stable or increase in the next 7 h.</p>
              <p>In our research, the analysis of tongue coating pH showed no statistically significant
difference between the groups, in the phases before and after 30 min of rising. In the
<italic>after</italic> phase, the <italic>ES</italic> group presented smaller mean
values than all other groups. In the <italic>SC, TS, EO</italic> and
<italic>CTRL</italic> groups, there was no significant difference between the three
phases. In the <italic>ES</italic> group, the mean values of the <italic>after</italic>
phase were lower than those obtained before and after 30 min of rinsing. It is known
that tongue coating is the main cause of oral halitosis<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>-<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> and that its
pH tends to be alkaline. Only risings with enzymatic solution (<italic>ES</italic>
group) provided pH decrease immediately after its use; however, the mechanism of action
is not clearly described in the literature. The beneficial impact of oral mouthrinses on
the bacterial load on the dorsum tongue is clearly demonstrated in the study of
Steenberghe, et al.<sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> (2001).</p>
              <p>This study was conducted in oral healthy patients, which is a factor of extreme
importance to avoid the development of chronic halitosis, since bad breath is closely
associated to poor oral hygiene. The measurements of saliva and tongue coating pH in
healthy patients with physiological halitosis homogenized the method. Patients should be
aware that some bacteria are inevitably left behind after mechanical plaque control,
even with an optimal technique. If the oral hygiene is not performed properly,
gingivitis, caries, periodontitis and eventually halitosis may develop. The dental
professional could explain that antiseptic rinsing kills additional bacteria and helps
controlling plaque. For absolute clarity, rinsing should be described as an adjunct to
an established daily oral-care routine, rather than a substitute for brushing and
interdental cleaning<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>According to the methodology applied in this study, it may be concluded that:</p>
              <p>-In a situation of physiological halitosis, salivary pH tended to be acidic while tongue
coating pH tended to be alkaline, even after the use of mouthrinses;</p>
              <p>-Only triclosan and essential oil mouthrinses increased salivary pH immediately after
rising;</p>
              <p>-The enzymatic solution was able to decrease saliva and tongue coating pH immediately
after rising.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
              <p>The authors would like to thank Ovídio dos Santos Sobrinho, Thelma Lopes Silva and José
Roberto Lauris for the support of this study. This investigation was supported by
CAPES.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="r01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anusavice</surname>
                      <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Degradability of dental ceramics</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Dent Res</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <lpage>89</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1292468</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clayton</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Green</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Roughness of pontic materials and dental
plaque</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1970</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
                  <lpage>411</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5264825</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Jager</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feilzer</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davidson</surname>
                      <given-names>CL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The influence of surface roughness on porcelain
strength</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Mater</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
                  <lpage>388</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10967186</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Demirhanoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>ST</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahin</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of topical fluorides and citric acid on
overglazed and autoglazed porcelain surfaces</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>434</fpage>
                  <lpage>440</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1290572</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fairhurst</surname>
                      <given-names>CW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anusavice</surname>
                      <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hashinger</surname>
                      <given-names>DT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ringle</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Twiggs</surname>
                      <given-names>SW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Thermal expansion of dental alloys and
porcelains</article-title>
                  <source>J Biomed Mater Res</source>
                  <year>1980</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>435</fpage>
                  <lpage>446</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6995461</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fischer</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schäfer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marx</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of surface roughness on flexural strength of
veneer ceramics</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>972</fpage>
                  <lpage>975</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630897</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodacre</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bernal</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rungcharassaeng</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kan</surname>
                      <given-names>JY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical complications in fixed
prosthodontics</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>90</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12869972</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Griggs</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>JY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anusavice</surname>
                      <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of flaw size and autoglaze treatment on
porcelain strength</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1414</fpage>
                  <lpage>1417</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8831637</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haselton</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diaz-Arnold</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hillis</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical assessment of highstrength all-ceramic
crowns</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>396</fpage>
                  <lpage>401</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10756288</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Höland</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rheinberger</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Apel</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van 't Hoen</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Höland</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dommann</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical applications of glass-ceramics in
dentistry</article-title>
                  <source>J Mater Sci Mater Med</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>1037</fpage>
                  <lpage>1042</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17122916</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Höland</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rheinberger</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wegner</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frank</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Needle-like apatite- leucite glass-ceramic as a base
material for the veneering of metal restorations in dentistry</article-title>
                  <source>J Mater Sci Mater Med</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <lpage>17</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15348093</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imfeld</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental erosion: definition, classification and
links</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>104</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <lpage>155</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8804882</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>International Organization for Standartization</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>ISO 6872: Dental ceramic</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>The Organization</publisher-name>
                  <year>1995</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jaeggi</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lussi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence, incidence and distribution of
erosion</article-title>
                  <source>Monogr Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <lpage>65</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687884</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelly</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giordano</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pober</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cima</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fracture surface analysis of dental ceramics: clinically
failed restorations</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>430</fpage>
                  <lpage>440</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2088380</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Young</surname>
                      <given-names>WG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Law</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Priest</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daley</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cupped lesions of early onset dental erosion in young
southeast Queensland adults</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <lpage>107</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11491225</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kukiattrakoon</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hengtrakool</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kedjarune-Leggat</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Chemical durability and microhardness of dental ceramics
immersed in acidic agents</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Odontol Scand</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19878041</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kukiattrakoon</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hengtrakool</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kedjarune-Leggat</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of acidic agents on surface ion leaching and
surface characteristics of dental porcelains</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>103</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <lpage>162</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20188237</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kukiattrakoon</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Junpoom</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hengtrakool</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vicker's microhardness and energy dispersive x-ray
analysis of fluorapatite-leucite and fluorapatite ceramics cyclically immersed in
acidic agents</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>443</fpage>
                  <lpage>450</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19776513</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Machado</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lacefield</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Catledge</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Human enamel nanohardness, elastic modulus and surface
integrity after beverage contact</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Dent J</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <lpage>72</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438563</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mackert</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Evans</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of cooling rate on leucite volume fraction in
dental porcelains</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <volume>70</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <lpage>139</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1991871</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mackert</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rueggeberg</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lockwood</surname>
                      <given-names>PE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Evans</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>WO</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Isothermal anneal effect on microcrack density around
leucite particles in dental porcelain</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1221</fpage>
                  <lpage>1227</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8046112</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magalhães</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiegand</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rios</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Honório</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buzalaf</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Insights into preventive measures for dental
erosion</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <lpage>86</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19274390</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Milleding</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wennerberg</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alaeddin</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karlsson</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simon</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Surface corrosion of dental ceramics in
vitro</article-title>
                  <source>Biomaterials</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>733</fpage>
                  <lpage>746</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10353656</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Piangprach</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hengtrakool</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kukiattrakoon</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kedjarune-Leggat</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of salivary factors on dental erosion in
various age groups and tooth surfaces</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>140</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1137</fpage>
                  <lpage>1143</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19723947</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raptis</surname>
                      <given-names>NV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Michalakis</surname>
                      <given-names>KX</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hirayama</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Optical behavior of current ceramic
systems</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16515094</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Serra</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Messias</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Turssi</surname>
                      <given-names>CP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Control of erosive tooth wear: possibilities and
rationale</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Oral Res</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <lpage>55</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19838558</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinmazisik</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oveçoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Physical properties and microstructural characterization
of dental porcelains mixed with distilled water and modeling
liquid</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Mater</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>735</fpage>
                  <lpage>745</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16324737</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
