<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:50:02Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5349026" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5349026</identifier>
        <datestamp>2017-03-17</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jaos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de São
Paulo</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC5349026</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5349026</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">5349026</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20379676</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20379676</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-77572010000100004</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effects of different polishing techniques on the surface roughness of
dental porcelains</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>SARIKAYA</surname>
                    <given-names>Işil</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>GÜLER</surname>
                    <given-names>Ahmet Umut</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> DDS, PhD, Research Assistant, Department of Prosthodontics, Faculty of
Dentistry, Ondokuz Mayis University, Samsun, Turkey.</aff>
              <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> DDS, PhD, Associate Professor, Department of Prosthodontics, Faculty of
Dentistry, Ondokuz Mayis University, Samsun, Turkey.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Dr. Isil SARIKAYA - Ondokuz Mayis
Üniversitesi - Dis Hekimligi Fakültesi - Protetik Dis Tedavisi Anabilim
Dali - Kurupelit - SAMSUN, TÜRKEY - Fax: +90-362-457-6032. E-mail:
<email>sarikaya.i@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>Jan-Feb</season>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Jan-Feb</season>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>18</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>10</fpage>
              <lpage>16</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>04</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2008</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>08</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>The purpose of this study was to evaluate the effects of different polishing
techniques on the surface roughness of dental porcelains.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Material and Methods</title>
                  <p>Fifty-five cylindirical specimens (15x2 mm) were prepared for each feldspathic
(Vita VMK 95, Ceramco III) and low-fusing dental porcelain (Matchmaker).
Fifty-five specimens of machinable feldspathic porcelain blocks (Vitablocs Mark
II), (12x14x18 mm) were cut into 2-mm-thick slices (12x14 mm) with low speed saw.
The prepared specimens were divided into 11 groups (n=5) representing different
polishing techniques including control ((C) no surface treatment), glaze (G) and
other 9 groups that were finished and polished with polishing discs (Sof-Lex)
(Sl), two porcelain polishing kits (NTI (Pk), Dialite II (Di)), a diamond
polishing paste (Sparkle) (Sp), a zirconium silicate based cleaning and polishing
prophy paste (Zircate) (Zr), an aluminum oxide polishing paste (Prisma Gloss)
(Pg), and combinations of them. The surface roughness of all groups was measured
with a profilometer. The data were analyzed with a 2-way analysis of variance, and
the mean values were compared by the Tukey Honestly Significant Difference test
(α=0.05).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>For all porcelain material groups, the lowest Ra values were observed in Group Gl,
Group Sl, Group Pk, and Group Di, which were not significantly different from each
other (p&gt;0.05).When comparing the 4 different porcelain materials, the
machinable feldspathic porcelain block group (Mark II) demonstrated statistically
significantly less Ra values than the other porcelain materials tested
(p&lt;0.05). No significant difference was observed between the VMK 95 and Ceramco
III porcelain groups (p=0.919), also these groups demonstrated the highest Ra
values.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>Subjected to surface roughness, the surfaces obtained with polishing and/or
cleaning-prophy paste materials used alone were rougher compared to the surfaces
finished using Sof-lex, Dialite, and NTI polishing kit. Polishing kits and discs
were found more effective than the polishing pastes used alone or combined use
with Sof-lex discs, thus improving surface smoothness.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Dental porcelain</kwd>
                <kwd>Polishing techniques</kwd>
                <kwd>Surface roughness</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>In addition to the improved esthetic properties, such as translucency, color and
intensity, the main advantages of dental porcelain materials are excellent
biocompatibility and durability<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Although occlusal adjustment of porcelain restorations may be necessary for correction
of inadequate contours or improved esthetics, roughened ceramic surface creating with
this procedure, which may cause an increased rate of plaque accumulation, gingival
inflammation and adverse soft tissue reaction<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. In addition
porcelain reduction with grinding may also cause decrease the strength of the ceramic
restoration<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Since the final occlusal adjustments of a ceramic restoration has to be made after
cementation, there is always need for a careful intraoral polishing of the surfaces.
Exposed porcelain surfaces should be smoothed to prevent excessive wear of the opposing
dentition and to minimize plaque retention<sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Highly polished porcelain surfaces have strength values comparable
to those of specimens that were polished and glazed<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. However, chairside porcelain polishing is efficient and easy for
the clinician. Intraoral polishing also provides infection control by eliminating
repeated laboratory procedures.</p>
              <p>Surface roughness (Ra) refers to the finer irregularities of the surface texture that
usually result from the action of the production process or material condition and is
measured in micrometers (µm)<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>.
Generally, a smooth surface is desirable to reduce retention of bacteria and to have a
shiny appearance<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Various studies are
available to support using different polishing techniques on porcelain surface instead
of glazing<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The purpose of this study was to evaluate the effects of different polishing techniques
on the surface roughness of different dental porcelains. The hypothesis for this study
was that the different polishing techniques would have different effects on the surface
roughness of dental porcelains.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <p>In the present study, four commonly used and commercially available dental porcelains
and different polishing systems were investigated in this study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Figure 1</xref>). Fifty-five cylindrical specimens (15x2mm) were prepared
for each of feldspathic and low-fusing dental porcelains by one investigator who
condensed the porcelains into a polyvinylsiloxane mold in a standardized
manner<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. After each specimen was
mixed using the same amount of porcelain and liquid, placed into the mold and compressed
with a plastic plunger. The excess moisture was absorbed by using a tissue (Selpak;
Eczaclbasl Group, Kocaeli, Turkey). After removal from the mold, the specimens were
fired in one furnace (Programat P80; Ivoclar-Vivadent, Liechtenstein) according to the
manufacturer’s directions (approximately 920-960°C).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Materials used in this study</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="box" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Material Type</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Product</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Manufacturer</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feldspathic porcelain</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VMK
95</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vita Zahnfabrik, Germany</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feldspathic porcelain</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceramco III</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degudent GmbH, USA</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-fusing porcelain</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matchmaker MC</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schottlander, UK</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feldspathic porcelain blocks</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitablocs Mark II</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vita Zahnfabrik, Germany</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finishing and polishing disc</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sof- Lex</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M ESPE, USA</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porcelain polishing kit</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NTI
CeraGlaze</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NTI- Kahla GmbH, Germany</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porcelain polishing kit</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dialite II</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brasseler, USA</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diamond polishing paste</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sparkle</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulpdent, USA</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zirconium silicate cleaning- polishing prophy paste</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zircate</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dentsply Int. Inc., USA</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aluminum oxide polishing paste</td>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prisma Gloss</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dentsply Int. Inc., USA</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Fifty-five specimens of machinable ceramic blocks (12x14x18mm) were cut into 2-mm-thick
slices (2x14 mm) with a low-speed saw (Isomet Low Speed Saw, Buehler, Lake Bluff, IL,
USA). All ceramic discs were wet-ground with 600-grit silicon carbide paper during 10 s
on a 300-rpm grinding machine (Buehler Metaserv, Buehler, Germany).</p>
              <p>The prepared specimens were randomly divided into 11 groups of 5 specimens each
according to the polishing techniques. The polishing procedure was done by a single
investigator and different polishing groups are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Figure 2</xref>. Group C - specimens served as the control group with no
polishing procedure applied. Group Gl - specimens were glazed using the specific glaze
medium for each case. Group Sl - specimens were polished with a series of
12.7-mm-diameter polishing discs (Sof-Lex; 3M/ ESPE, St. Paul, MN, USA) mounted on an
electric handpiece set at a speed of 10,000 rpm during 10 s for coarse and medium discs,
and 30,000 rpm during 10 s for fine and superfine discs, according to the manufacturer’s
instructions. Group Pk - specimens were polished with NTI Cera Glaze polishing kit on an
electric handpiece at 15,000 rpm for 10 s with pre-polishing wheel, at 10,000 rpm during
10 s with refined finishing wheel and at 5,000 rpm for 10 s with high-shine polishing
wheel according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Group Di - specimens were polished
with Dialite II porcelain polishing kit including pre, fine and high-shine wheels on an
electric handpiece at 10,000 rpm for 10 s following the manufacturer’s instructions.
Groups Sp, Zr and Pg - Sparkle diamond polishing paste, Zircate zirconium silicate
cleaning-prophy paste and Prisma Gloss aluminum oxide polishing paste, respectively,
were applied for 10 s to the specimens with a prophylaxis rubber cup (Kenda Polishers,
Kenda AG, Liechtenstein) mounted on an electric handpiece at 15,000 rpm. Group specimens
were applied with a prophylaxis rubber cup on an electric handpiece at 15,000 rpm for 10
s. Group SlSp - specimens were polished as in Group Sl and diamond polishing paste was
applied as described for Group Sp. Group SlZr specimens were polished as in Group Sl and
zirconium silicate cleaning-prophy paste was applied as described for Group Zr. Group
SlPg specimens were polished as in Group Sl and aluminum oxide polishing paste was
applied as described for Group Pg. The specimens were then ultrasonically cleaned
(Eurosonic Energy, Euronda, Italy) with deionized water for 10 min and dried.</p>
              <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Polishing methods</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="box" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Polishing techniques</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- C</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (no surface treatment)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- Gl</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glaze</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- Sl</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sof- Lex</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- Pk</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NTI CeraGlaze Polishing kit</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- Di</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dialite II</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- Sp</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sparkle</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- Zr</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zircate</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- Pg</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prisma Gloss</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- SlSp</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sof- Lex+ Sparkle</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- SlZr</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sof- Lex+ Zircate</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" style="border-right-style:solid;border-right-width:thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group- SlPg</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sof- Lex+ Prisma Gloss</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The specimens were stabilized with silicone impression material into a brass mold and
three roughness measurements (Ra, µm) were performed on each sample using a
profilometer (Perthometer M2, Mahr GmbH, Germany). A cutoff value of 0.25 mm allowed
detecting those irregularities<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. A diamond stylus (NHT-6) of 2 µm
radius and 90° stylus angle was traversed at a constant speed across each of the
finished samples of ceramic sample with a force of 0.7 N. Before measurements of each
group, the profilometer was calibrated. All profilometer records were made as close as
possible to the sample center<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. For
each specimen, 3 measurements were made and the mean was calculated to obtain the
general surface characteristics of the specimens. The Ra value describes the mean value
for a surface that has been traced by the profilometer<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. A lower Ra
value indicates a smoother surface.</p>
              <p>The effect of porcelain type and polishing procedure as well as their interactions on
the surface roughness was evaluated by two-way ANOVA tests using SPSS for Windows
statistical software version (12.0.1; SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL, USA). The mean values were
than compared by the Tukey honestly significant difference test (α=0.05).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>According to the two-way ANOVA results, porcelain materials, polishing techniques, and
their interaction were statistically significant (p&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 1</xref>). Mean surface roughness values (and standard deviation) and
group differences (Ra) of the feldspathic porcelain materials (Vita VMK 95, Ceramco
III), low-fusing porcelain material (Matchmaker MC), and machinable feldspathic
porcelain block (Vitablocs Mark II) are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Tables 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t05">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t06">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t07">5</xref>, respectively.</p>
              <table-wrap id="t03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Two-way ANOVA for porcelain materials and different polishing
techniques</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Variable (source)</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>
                          <italic>df</italic>
                        </bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Sum of squares</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Mean squares</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>F</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>P</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polishing technique</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.328</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.533</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.107</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porcelain</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.779</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.593</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.830</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interaction</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.431</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.581</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.054</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN01">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Error</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.698</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.072</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN01">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Significant difference at p&lt;.05.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Mean (SD) of surface roughness and differences between groups for Vita VMK 95
porcelain</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Ra</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Difference<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN02">*</xref></bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.134 (0.64)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.724 (0.19)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729 (0.17)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pk</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.640 (0.15)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.700 (0.23)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.639 (0.26)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.241 (0.41)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.728 (0.47)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlSp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.929 (0.76)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlZr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.731 (0.48)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlPg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.122 (0.24)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN02">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Different letters indicate statistically significant difference between the
groups (p&lt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Mean (SD) of surface roughness and differences between groups for Ceramco III
porcelain</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Ra</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Difference<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN03">*</xref></bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.667 (0.21)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c,d</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.609 (0.23)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617 (0.10)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pk</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.639 (0.10)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999 (0.26)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.824 (0.39)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c,d</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.974 (0.12)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.872 (0.18)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c,d</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlSp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.400 (0.19)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlZr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.481 (0.22)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlPg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.595 (0.29)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c,d</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN03">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Different letters indicate statistically significant difference between the
groups (p&lt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Mean (SD) of surface roughness and differences between groups for Matchmaker
MC porcelain</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Ra</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Difference<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN04">*</xref></bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.015 (0.23)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b,c,d</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.456 (0.11)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.757 (0.11)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pk</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.691 (0.16)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366 (0.08)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.746 (0.26</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b,c</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.728 (0.20)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.700 (0.10)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SISp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.262 (0.32)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d,e,f</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIZr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.652 (0.17)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e,f</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIPg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.175 (0.41)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c,d,e</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN04">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Different letters indicate statistically significant difference between the
groups (p&lt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t07" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Mean (SD) of surface roughness and differences between groups for Mark II
porcelain</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Ra</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Difference<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN05">*</xref></bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314(0.12)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406(0.18)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sl</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431(0.09)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pk</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.584(0.04)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.434(0.04)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.380(0.12)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312(0.11)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342(0.07)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlSp</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.386(0.06)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlZr</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.321(0.12)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlPg</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.364(0.13)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a,b</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN05">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Different letters indicate statistically significant difference between the
groups (p&lt;0.05).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>For the VMK 95 feldspathic porcelain material, the lowest Ra values were observed in
Group Gl (0.724), Group Sl (0.729), Group Pk (0.640), Group Di (0.700), Group C (1.134)
and Group SlPg (1.122), which were not significantly different from each other
(p=0.732). The highest Ra value in the VMK 95 porcelain material was observed in Group
Zr (2.241), which were not significantly different from Group Sp (1.639), Group Pg
(1.728), Group SlSp (1.929) and Group SlZr (1.731) (p=0.466). The differences between
VMK 95 feldspathic porcelain material group are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table 2</xref>. For the Ceramco III feldspathic porcelain material, the
lowest Ra values were observed in Group Gl (0.609), Group Sl (0.617), Group Pk (0.639)
and Group Di (0.999), which were not significantly different from each other (p=0.230).
The highest Ra value in the Ceramco III feldspathic porcelain material was observed in
Group Zr (1.974) which were not significantly different from Group C (1.667), Group Sp
(1.824), Group Pg (1.872) and Group SlPg (1.595) (p=0.265) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t05">Table 3</xref>).</p>
              <p>For the low-fusing porcelain material, the lowest Ra values were observed in Group Di
(0.366), which were not significantly different from Group Gl (0.456), Group Sl (0.757),
Group Pk (0.691) and Group Sp (0.746) (p=0.203). No significant difference was observed
among Group SlZr (1.652), Group SlPg (1.175), Group SlSp (1.262), Group Pg (1.700) and
Group Zr (1.728), also these groups demonstrated the highest Ra values for the
low-fusing porcelain material tested (p=0.063) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t06">Table
4</xref>).</p>
              <p>For the machinable feldspathic porcelain block, the lowest Ra values were observed in
Group C (0.314), Group Gl (0.406), Group Sl (0.431), Group Di (0.434), Group Sp (0.380),
Group Zr (0.312), Group Pg (0.342), Group SlSp (0.386), Group SlZr (0.321) and Group
SlPg (0.364), which were not significantly different from each other (p=0.816). Group Pk
(0.584) differed significantly from these groups (p&lt;0.05). No significant difference
was observed among Group Pk (0.584), Group Gl (0.406), Group Sl (0.431), Group Di
(0.434), Group Sp (0.380), Group SlSp (0.386) and Group SlPg (0.364) (p=0.100) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t05">Table 5</xref>).</p>
              <p>When comparing the 4 different porcelain materials, the machinable feldspathic porcelain
block (Mark II) demonstrated significantly lower Ra values than the other porcelain
materials tested (p&lt;0.05). No significant difference was observed between the VMK 95
and Ceramco III porcelains (p=0.919), which presented the highest Ra values.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>The hypothesis set as the premise of this study was accepted, since different polishing
techniques affected the surface roughness of the evaluated dental porcelains. In the
present study the efficiency of different porcelain polishing kits, polishing discs,
cleaning-prophy paste materials and their combinations were compared. These materials
were selected among frequently used dental porcelain systems as being fast and effective
on creating smoothed porcelain surfaces.</p>
              <p>The Ra parameter obtained with a profilometer is used to describe the surface texture of
the porcelain specimens. This parameter describes the overall roughness of a surface and
can be defined as the arithmetical average value of all absolute distances of the
roughness profile from the center line within the measuring length<sup><xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Various finishing and polishing techniques can use on porcelain surface to preserve its
structural resistance and obtain a clinically acceptable smoothness comparing with
glazing<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. Previous studies on surface roughness
of dental porcelains demonstrated that very smooth surfaces were obtained when
restorations were polished with rubber wheel, Sof-lex discs, porcelain polishing kit,
diamond paste and aluminum oxide paste<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>-<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. In this
study, it was observed that using porcelain polishing disc or polishing kits, diamond
pastes or alumina pastes alone created surfaces as smooth as glazed specimens as similar
studies. This result indicates that polishing kits and disc systems had a similar effect
on ceramic surface roughness compared to glazing.</p>
              <p>According to Al Wahadni, et al.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>(1998), polishing of a ceramic restoration by diamond paste at the final
stage after clinical adjustment was equivalent to reglazing. Hulterstrom, et
al.<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>(1993) found that Sof-lex
system produced the best results for Mark I porcelain when no polishing paste was used.
In the present study, the Soflex system produced the lowest Ra values for all
porcelains. Final polishing with a diamond-containing polishing paste after polishing
with the Sof-lex system produced no significant decrease in the Ra value for Mark II
ceramics. Hulterstrom, et al<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> (1993)
recommended that final polishing with the fairly expensive diamond paste did not
significantly improve the smoothness of the ceramic surface polished with the Sof-lex
system. Furthermore several studies have shown that final polishing with a diamond paste
did not improve the surface smoothness of ceramic restorations<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Due to the difficult in reaching intraoral access, occlusal corrections may result in
insufficient polishing and the formed microcracks may be susceptible to later
catastrophic fractures. Therefore, much care must be taken in order to make a careful
polishing of inlay areas that had been previously subjected to rotary occlusal
corrections to prevent from this particular problem<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>In the present study, the surfaces obtained with polishing and/or cleaning-prophy paste
materials were rougher when used alone compared with the surfaces finished through using
Sof-lex, Dialite, and NTI polishing kit. This finding is in agreement with previous
reports investigating the effects of different polishing systems on the surface
roughness of ceramics<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>According to the results of present study, the machinable feldspathic porcelain block
group (Mark II) demonstrated significantly lower Ra values than the other porcelain
materials. No significant difference was observed between the VMK 95 and Ceramco III
porcelains, which presented the highest Ra values. Several studies on finishing and
polishing of dental ceramics have been published, but there is a lack of studies
investigating the effectiveness of different polishing techniques for the newer types of
dental porcelain, such as Mark II porcelain blocks. There were not significant
differences among the various polishing techniques for Mark II porcelains, and this is
thought to be due to the extreme hardness of Mark II feldspathic blocs.</p>
              <p>The present study has some limitations. Although intraoral polishing systems have been
used, this is an in vitro study and so the efficiency of polishing systems might be
different under clinical conditions. Furthermore, different results might be expected
with different types of porcelain and polishing protocols. Further investigations are
necessary to evaluate the surface roughness of other porcelain systems after polishing
with different polishing protocols.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>Within the limitation of this study, glazing and polishing discs and kits have shown
lower Ra values than those obtained using polishing pastes. Polishing kits and discs
were found more effective than the polishing pastes used alone or combined with Sof-lex
discs, resulting in improved surface smoothness. If occlusal adjustment of a ceramic
restoration has to be made after cementation there is always need for a careful
intraoral polishing with polishing kits and discs.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="r01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al Wahadni</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Glazing and finishing dental porcelain: a literature
review</article-title>
                  <source>J Can Dent Assoc</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>64</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>580</fpage>
                  <lpage>583</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9785688</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ancowitz</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torres</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rostami</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Texturing and polishing: The final attempt at value
control</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Clin North Am</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>607</fpage>
                  <lpage>612</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891643</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anusavice</surname>
                      <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phillips' science of dental materials</source>
                  <edition>10th ed</edition>
                  <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>WB Saunders Company</publisher-name>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <fpage>598</fpage>
                  <lpage>600</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bessing</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiktorsson</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of two different methods of polishing
porcelain</article-title>
                  <source>Scand J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>1983</year>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>482</fpage>
                  <lpage>487</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6581525</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Camacho</surname>
                      <given-names>GB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vinha</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Panzeri</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nonaka</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goncalves</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Surface roughness of a dental ceramic after polishing with different
vehicles and diamond pastes</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Dent J</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <lpage>194</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17262123</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clelland</surname>
                      <given-names>NL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Agarwala</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Knobloch</surname>
                      <given-names>LA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seghi</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Wear of enamel opposing low-fusing and conventional ceramic
restorative materials</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <lpage>15</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11406790</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Craig</surname>
                      <given-names>RG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Powers</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wataha</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Dental Materials: properties and manipulation</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Saint Louis</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>113</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fuzzi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaccheroni</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vallania</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Scanning electron microscopy and profilometer evaluation of glazed and
polished dental porcelain</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>452</fpage>
                  <lpage>458</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9108746</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hulterstrom</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bergman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Polishing systems for dental ceramics</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Odontol Scand</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <lpage>234</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8237306</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jagger</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harrison</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An in-vitro investigation into the wear effects of unglazed, glazed,
and polished porcelain on human enamel</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>320</fpage>
                  <lpage>323</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7965907</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jefferies</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The art and science of abrasive finishing and polishing in restorative
dentistry</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Clin North Am</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>613</fpage>
                  <lpage>627</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891644</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lawn</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pajares</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polack</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lloyd</surname>
                      <given-names>IK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Materials design in the performance of all-ceramic
crowns</article-title>
                  <source>Biomaterials</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>14</issue>
                  <fpage>2885</fpage>
                  <lpage>2892</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14962567</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lohbauer</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krämer</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petschelt</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frankenberger</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Correlation of in vitro fatigue data and in vivo clinical performance
of a glassceramic material</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Mater</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467049</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lohbauer</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Müller</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petschelt</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of surface roughness on mechanical strength of resin
composite versus glass ceramic materials</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Mater</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>250</fpage>
                  <lpage>256</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17628659</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martinez-Gomis</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bizar</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anglada</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samso</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peraire</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative evaluation of four finishing systems on one ceramic
surface</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <lpage>77</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paravina</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Powers</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Esthetic color training in dentistry</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Saint Louis</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Patterson</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McLundie</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stirrups</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taylor</surname>
                      <given-names>WG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of a porcelain refinishing system in restoring surface finish
after grinding with fine and extra fine diamond burs</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>402</fpage>
                  <lpage>406</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1331431</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raimondo</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Richardson</surname>
                      <given-names>JT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiedner</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Polished versus autoglazed dental porcelain</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>64</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>553</fpage>
                  <lpage>557</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2090814</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarac</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarac</surname>
                      <given-names>YS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yüzbasioglu</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bal</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of porcelain polishing systems on the color and surface
texture of feldspathic porcelain</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <lpage>128</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911889</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schlissel</surname>
                      <given-names>ER</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Newitter</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Renner</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gwinnett</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An evaluation of postadjustment polishing techniques for porcelain
denture teeth</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1980</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <lpage>265</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6928194</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scurria</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Powers</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Surface roughness of two polished ceramic materials</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>71</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <lpage>177</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8126673</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tholt de Vasconcelos</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miranda</surname>
                      <given-names>WG Jr</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prioli</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oda</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Surface roughness in ceramics with different finishing techniques
using atomic force microscope and profilometer</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>442</fpage>
                  <lpage>449</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16924984</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whitehead</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shearer</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watts</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>NHF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of methods for measuring surface roughness of
ceramic</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
                  <lpage>427</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7636611</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wright</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Masri</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Driscoll</surname>
                      <given-names>CF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Romberg</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>GA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Runyan</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of three systems for the polishing of an ultra-low-fusing
dental porcelain</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>92</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>486</fpage>
                  <lpage>490</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15523338</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
