<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:40:37Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8884354" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8884354</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-01-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jips</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Indian Prosthodont Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Indian Prosthodont Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIPS</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>The Journal of the Indian Prosthodontic Society</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0972-4052</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1998-4057</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer - Medknow</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8884354</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8884354</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8884354</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36510951</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JIPS-22-82</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jips.jips_336_21</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Comparison of patient satisfaction between complete dentures fabricated using “conventional” and “cephalometric angular reconstruction” vertical dimension procedures: A multicenter randomized clinical trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Vinnakota</surname>
                    <given-names>Dileep Nag</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Edamadaka</surname>
                    <given-names>Nagaraj</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Reddy</surname>
                    <given-names>P Sesha</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Duggineni</surname>
                    <given-names>Chalapathi Rao</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1">Department of Prosthodontics, Narayana Dental College and Hospital, Nellore, Andhra Pradesh, India</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Prosthodontics, PMNM Dental College and Hospital, Bagalkot, Karnataka, India</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Department of Prosthodontics, Government Dental College and Hospital, RIMS, Kadapa, Andhra Pradesh, India</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>3</label>Department of Prosthodontics, Mamatha Dental College, Khammam, Telangana, India</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Dileep Nag Vinnakota, Department of Prosthodontics, Narayana Dental College and Hospital, Nellore, Andhra Pradesh, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="dileepnagmds@gmail.com">dileepnagmds@gmail.com</email>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Jan-Mar</season>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>27</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>22</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>82</fpage>
              <lpage>91</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>01</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>07</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>01</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2022 The Journal of Indian Prosthodontic Society</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="st1">
                  <title>Aim:</title>
                  <p>In Prosthodontics, during complete denture fabrication, conventional methods employed to determine occlusal vertical dimension require patient co-operation. Hence, the aim of the present study is to evaluate the clinical effectiveness of the 'cephalometric angular reconstruction' procedure in the calculation of these lost dimensions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st2">
                  <title>Settings and Design:</title>
                  <p>Multicentric randomised clinical trial conducted in four dental hospitals.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st3">
                  <title>Materials and Methods:</title>
                  <p>Fully edentulous people who came to the hospitals for complete denture treatment were recruited into the study. Those who fulfilled the inclusion criteria were randomly assigned to two groups; Group 1: Dentures fabricated using a 'conventional' procedure and Group 2: Dentures fabricated using 'cephalometric angular reconstruction'. The patient's level of satisfaction was assessed on a scale of 1 to 5; 1-dissatisfaction to 5-excellent. The confounding factors that can influence the satisfaction were also recorded.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st4">
                  <title>Statistical Analysis Used:</title>
                  <p>The distribution of patient's satisfaction was assessed using Chi-square test, whereas the difference between the two groups was evaluated using Mann–Whitney test.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st5">
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>There was no significant difference either in the vertical dimension determined (<italic>P</italic> = 0.465) or the patient's level of satisfaction (<italic>P</italic> = 0.943) between the two groups. There was no influence of confounding factors considered in the present study on the satisfaction levels. There was no difference in the distribution of satisfaction levels based on the dentist's quality assessment (<italic>P</italic> = 0.243).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st6">
                  <title>Conclusion:</title>
                  <p>Complete dentures fabricated using cephalometric angular reconstruction procedure of vertical dimension determination were equivalent with respect to patient satisfaction, compared to those made using a conventional method. Hence, the new method can be clinically recommended during denture fabrication.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Cephalometrics</kwd>
                <kwd>complete dentures</kwd>
                <kwd>occlusion</kwd>
                <kwd>vertical dimension</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>The vertical dimension of occlusion (VDO) refers to the measurement in the vertical plane that establishes the relation between the maxilla and mandible when occluded.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] It is of great biological importance as it plays a vital role in mastication, speech, appearance, and functioning of surrounding tissues.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] In completely edentulous individuals, VDO is lost, and reconstituting the occlusal support is essential during prosthodontic rehabilitation. As the association between morphology and function is inseparable, an increase in this dimension prevents muscular relaxation, whereas a decrease causes over-relaxed musculature.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Hence, to avoid the disturbance in neuromuscular tone, precise measurement of VDO is essential. Many methods based on preextraction data, intra-oral measurements, profile tracing, rest position, swallowing, phonetic, neuromuscular perception, and craniometrics values are described in the literature.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Although there are many advances, clinical judgment based on experience alone is considered to play a significant role in the assessment of this important component during the construction of dentures. In routine clinical practice, the conventional technique of determining the vertical dimension at rest and positioning VDO to establish 2–3 mm of interocclusal rest space is employed. Another traditional technique based on anatomical landmarks and facial proportions is also used clinically. All these techniques require patient co-operation, and additionally, are extremely subjective. Hence, attempts were made to implement other standardized methods of calculating the lost facial dimensions.</p>
              <p>In recent times, cephalometric analysis has gained much popularity in this field. Information pertinent to the role of cephalometrics in prosthodontic diagnosis, treatment planning, and prognosis is evident in the literature.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] Many software programs are also being developed to calculate VDO using computer-assisted cephalometrics.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] These methods are based on the skeletal landmarks that are not affected by edentulism.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] The accuracy, and the reliability of angular and linear measurements and correlations, led to the development of regression equations.[<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] In a study, based on multiple regressions, five angular and two linear cephalometric landmarks with weak to moderate positive and negative correlations were observed, yielding satisfactory results.[<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] However, complexity is the major barrier to apply this technique clinically because most prosthodontists seldom use cephalometric techniques and analysis. To overcome this, an easy and simple method of cephalometric angular reconstruction that combines both the concepts of facial proportions and cephalometrics has been tested in contemporary dentulous individuals.[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] The positive results led to the framing of simple linear regression formulae. Thus, cephalometrics showed a lot of scope in this arena because of the positive observations in the preliminary studies.</p>
              <p>The reconstructed VDO, in people with lost facial dimensions, influences the success of the prosthesis. This is because the tolerance, stability, esthetics, function, and phonetics of any prosthesis change based on the determined maxillomandibular relations. Hence, any deviation of the VDO affects all these aspects, in turn impacting the satisfaction of persons wearing these dentures. As there is no clinical trial that has compared the clinical effectiveness of determining VDO using cephalometric approach, the present multicentre randomised trial has been planned to determine the difference in the overall satisfaction of persons wearing complete dentures fabricated using “conventional” and “cephalometric angular reconstruction procedures.”</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2">
              <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
              <sec id="sec2-1">
                <title>Ethical clearance</title>
                <p>The present clinical trial is registered at the Clinical Trials Registry, India, with the registration number CTRI/2021/05/033585. A total of four dental institutes participated in the clinical trial. The institutional ethical committees of all the participating institutes approved the study protocol. The ethical approval number of the primary and leading center is IEC/NDCH/2020/P-48. Ethical approval numbers of other centers are PMNMDCH/1968/2020–21; Rc. No. 99/Academic/GDCH/Kadapa/2020; MDC_R_088429. Informed written consent was obtained from all the participants prior to screening for possible inclusion. All the participating investigators took part in an online meeting before the inclusion of the first patient to predefine and standardize the methodology and ensure uniform treatment outcome.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-2">
                <title>Trial design</title>
                <p>This was a multicentre, parallel-group, equivalence, triple-blind trial with restricted randomization and an allocation ratio of 1:1 conducted in India (four centers).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-3">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>All the participants attending the outpatient department of the four dental institutes (centers) were recruited based on the following eligibility criteria.</p>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Completely edentulous persons with Class I skeletal pattern (The Class I skeletal pattern was determined using the YEN angle, [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>], which is based on the landmarks midpoint of sella, the midpoint of premaxilla, and center of the largest circle that is tangent to the internal inferior, anterior and posterior surfaces of the mandibular symphysis, measured at the midpoint of the premaxilla. If this angle was between 117 and 123 degrees, it was considered as Class I skeletal pattern)</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Age range of 50–80 years</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Who gave their written informed consent to participate in the study.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Yenn angle considered in the present study</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Those with craniofacial malformations, facial asymmetries, or cleft palate were excluded from the study.</p>
                <p>The study took place in the Departments of Prosthodontics in four dental institutions of India from December 2020 to June 2021.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-4">
                <title>Interventions</title>
                <p>All the standard steps involved in the fabrication of complete dentures were followed for every participant, irrespective of the group. One postgraduate student in each center performed all the clinical procedures. In addition, they were trained and calibrated to determine the vertical dimension using either conventional or angular reconstruction procedures. That trained student recorded the vertical dimensions of all the participants in a centre. The details of the interventions for each group are mentioned below.</p>
                <p>Group 1: The anatomical landmarks method was considered for determining the vertical dimension at rest. The Willis guide was used to measure the distance from the pupils of the eye to the rimaoris and the distance from the columella to the lower border of the mandible. When these measurements are equal, the jaws were considered at rest. Then, by establishing 2–3 mm of interocclusal rest space, the VDO was calculated.</p>
                <p>Group 2: The cephalogram was obtained and placed on the view box with the patient's image facing the right. The four corners of the radiograph were taped to the view box. The matte acetate film was placed over the radiograph and taped securely to the radiograph and the view box. With a sharp 3H drawing pencil, the required reference landmarks, Nasion (N), Anterior Nasal Spine (ANS), Porion (P), and Gonion (G) were marked, as represented in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. These points were joined as shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> to form angles; N-ANS-G (by joining the landmarks N, ANS, and G) and P-G-ANS (by joining the landmarks P, G, and ANS). Then, using the formulae “N-ANS-Gnathion (Gn) (in degrees) =1.271 N-ANS-G (in degrees) +24.83” and “P-G-Gn (in degrees) = 0.987 P-G-ANS (in degrees) +35.93,” the two angles were determined (where Gn is point Gn) and reconstructed on the tracing[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] [<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>]. The intersection of the two angles was marked as Gn [<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>]. The distance between ANS and the reconstructed point Gn was considered as the VDO in cephalogram [<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>]. The distance between N and ANS (<italic>x̍</italic>); as well as ANS and reconstructed Gn (<italic>y̍</italic>) was measured on the tracing [<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>]. The clinical distance between N and columella (<italic>x̍</italic>) of the patient was measured, and using the formula <italic>x̍/y̍=</italic> x/y, the clinical distance between columella and Gn (<italic>y</italic>) was determined and considered VDO [<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>].</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Landmarks considered in the present study; (1) Nasion; (2) Anterior Nasal Spine; (3) Porion; (4) Gonion; (5) Gnathion</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F3">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>N-ANS-G and P-G-ANS (1) Angle formed between Nasion, Anterior Nasal Spine, Gonion (2) Angle formed between Porion, Gonion, Anterior Nasal Spine</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F4">
                  <label>Figure 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Determined angles N-ANS-Gn and P-G-Gn (1) Angle formed between Nasion, Anterior Nasal Spine, Gonion (2) Angle formed between Porion, Gonion, Anterior Nasal Spine (3) Angle determined between Nasion, Anterior Nasal Spine, Gnathion (4) Angle determined between Porion, Gonion, Gnathion</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g004" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F5">
                  <label>Figure 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Reconstruction of point Gnathion</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g005" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F6">
                  <label>Figure 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Reconstructed vertical dimension of occlusion in cephalogram</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g006" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="F7">
                  <label>Figure 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Clinical determination of vertical dimension of occlusion</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g007" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Immediately after insertion of fabricated complete dentures, all the participants were evaluated by respective investigators in each center. A questionnaire, which was divided into three parts, was used for assessing the outcome. In the first part, the dentist assessed the quality of the dentures; a rating scale of 1–5 was used, where 1-poor quality and 5-excellent quality. In the second part, the patients answered the questions regarding gender, age, level of education, marital status (married, divorced, single, or widowed), self-supporting lifestyle (1-ability to live by themselves, 2-supported by their families, and 3-able to live alone), smoking habits, period of tooth loss, and the number of previous complete dentures worn. In the third part of the questionnaire, patients rated their complete dentures, depending on the level of satisfaction. The patients rated using a scale ranging from 1 to 5 (where 1 – dissatisfaction and 5 – excellent).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-5">
                <title>Outcomes</title>
                <p>The patient satisfaction on a scale ranging from 1 to 5 (1 – dissatisfaction to 5 – excellent) was considered the primary outcome measure. On the other hand, the dentist rating the denture quality from 1 to 5 (1 – poor quality and 5 – excellent quality) was considered the secondary outcome. There were no changes in the outcomes after the trial commenced.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-6">
                <title>Sample size</title>
                <p>Based on the pilot study findings done on 12 participants (6 for each group), with 5% significance level and a power of 90%, considering patient satisfaction scale as the primary outcome measure, a sample size of 236 (118 in each group) was necessary. So, a final sample of 240 (120 in each group) was determined. To recruit this number of patients, a 6-month inclusion period was anticipated. No interim analysis was performed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-7">
                <title>Randomization</title>
                <p>The randomization was stratified by centers (four dental institutions) with a 1:1 allocation. Restricted randomization, i.e., block randomization was employed in the present study with multiple block sizes of 4 and 6. The table of random numbers was used to generate the random allocation sequence. Sequentially numbered opaque-sealed envelopes were used as mechanism for the allocation concealment. Determination of whether the participant should be given dentures using the conventional method or angular reconstruction procedure was done after enrolment, and initials steps of primary and secondary impressions, and fabrication of occlusal rims was completed. The appropriate numbered envelope was opened at the main center, and information given to other centers, during the jaw relation procedure. A professor in the main center (unrelated to the study) generated random allocation sequence, and assignment of participants to interventions. The enrollment of participants was done by the four investigators individually in their respective centers. The participants, the outcome assessors, and data analysts were blinded to the allocation.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-8">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The statistical analysis was carried out using SPSS 17.0 version for Windows (Chicago, III, USA). The level of significance was set at 0.05 level. Descriptive statistics regarding confounding factors like age, gender, level of education, marital status, self-supporting life style, smoking, period of tooth loss, and number of previous dentures worn was represented in number and percentage. The difference in the distribution of patient's satisfaction based on the various confounding factors considered was determined using Chi-square test. The difference in the distribution of patient's satisfaction based on center and dentist's assessment was tested using Chi-square test. The difference in the patient satisfaction scale between the two groups was assessed using Mann–Whitney test. The difference in the VDO between the two groups was assessed using unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>The details of the enrolment, number of participants who were randomly assigned to two groups, who received the intended treatment, and who were analyzed for the primary outcome is represented as a participant flow diagram [<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>]. The required number of participants could be recruited in the specified period of 6 months. The demographic characteristics of the participants are represented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The mean age of the participants was 63.87 (range: 50–80), and among them, 136 were male and 104 females. The patient's level of satisfaction ranged from 3 to 5 (median: 4). The mean N-ANS-G obtained in the angular reconstruction group was 92.19 ± 3.54, whereas mean P-G-ANS was 89.53 ± 4.54. There was no significant influence of confounding factors on the level of satisfaction reported by complete denture wears [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>]. There was no difference (<italic>P</italic> = 0.943) in the patient's level of satisfaction between the conventional and angular reconstruction groups [<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>]. Even, there was no influence of center on the difference in the level of satisfaction between the groups [<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>]. The distribution of satisfaction levels based on dentist assessment also showed no significant difference (<italic>P</italic> = 0.243), which is depicted in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The VDO determined based on the two considered methods also showed no significant difference (<italic>P</italic> = 0.465), the details of which are represented in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>.</p>
              <fig position="float" id="F8">
                <label>Figure 8</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Participant flow diagram</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-22-82-g008" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Demographic characteristics of the participants <italic>n</italic>=240</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (65.83)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (34.17)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 (56.67)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (43.33)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level of education</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Illiterate</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (30.83)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary school</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (25.42)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle school</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (20.00)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High school</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (11.25)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intermediate/diploma</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (9.17)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Graduate</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2.50)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Professional degree</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.83)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221 (92.08)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Divorced</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.83)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.08)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Widowed</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (5.00)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-supporting life style</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ability to live by themselves</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221 (92.08)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Supported by their families</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (5.83)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Able to live alone</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.08)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking habit</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (38.33)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (61.67)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Period of tooth loss (months)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (52.08)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (47.92)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of previous dentures worn</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (73.33)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (26.67)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Represented as number (Percentage)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Effect of confounding factors on complete denture wearer’s level of satisfaction</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 3</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 4</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 5</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>P</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (19)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (38.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (42.4)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.349 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (20.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (46.4)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (32.9)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (17.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (41.9)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (40.5)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.682 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (22.1)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (40.4)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (37.5)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Illiterate</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (16.2)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (43.2)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (40.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.589 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary school</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (37.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (41.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle school</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (25.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (43.8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (31.2)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High school</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (22.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (37.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (40.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intermediate/diploma</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (13.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (50.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (36.4)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Graduate</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (83.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Professional degree</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (18.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (42.5)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (38.9)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Divorced</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (60.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (40.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Widowed</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-supported life style</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ability to live by themselves</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (19.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (41.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (39.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Supported by their families</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (14.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (50.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (35.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Able to live alone</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (60.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (40.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoking habit</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (19.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (38.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (42.4)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (19.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (43.2)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (37.2)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Period of tooth loss (months)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (20.8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (36.8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (42.4)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (18.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (46.1)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (35.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of previous dentures worn</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (18.8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (40.9)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (40.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.785 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (21.9)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (42.2)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (35.9)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Represented as number (Percentage). NS: Nonsignificant</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Complete denture wearer’s satisfaction based on centre</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Centre</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 3</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 4</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 5</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>P</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (20.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (35.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (45.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.423 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (15.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (38.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (46.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (41.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (36.6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (50.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (28.3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Mean±SD</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Median</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Range</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>
                          <italic>P</italic>
                        </bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Centre 1 (<italic>n</italic>=60)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.23±0.77</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.854 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26±0.78</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Centre 2 (<italic>n</italic>=60)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30±0.75</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.904 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33±0.71</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Centre 3 (<italic>n</italic>=60)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13±0.78</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.886 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17±0.75</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Centre 4 (n=60)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1±0.71</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.723 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.03±0.72</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Total sample (<italic>n</italic>=240)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19±0.79</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20±0.78</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Represented as Number (Percentage). NS: Nonsignificant, SD: Standard deviation</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Cross tabulation of dentist assessment and wearer’s level of satisfaction</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dentist/wearer</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 3</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 4</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 5</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>P</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Represented as Number (Percentage). NS: Nonsignificant</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T5">
                <label>Table 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Outcome measures considered in the present study</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Level</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 3</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 4</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level 5</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Group 1</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weare’s satisfaction</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dentist assessment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Group 2</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wearer’s satisfaction</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dentist assessment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Vertical dimension of occlusion determined</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Groups</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Mean±SD</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Range</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>
                          <italic>P</italic>
                        </bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <hr/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.52±4.22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1-73.4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.465 (NS)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.91±4.11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1-73.1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Represented as number. NS: Nonsignificant, SD: Standard deviation</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>In recent times, prosthodontics has advancements in techniques and materials, but clinical steps for the determination of VDO could not evolve for preciseness. In edentulous people, because of the absence of posterior teeth, there will be a loss of VDO. The restored dimensions should be the same as probably what existed before the edentulous situation, as correct registration of VDO has biological importance.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] However, the major problem with the existing methods is that the muscles controlling the mandible become tense when the mechanical recording devices are placed in the mouth. In addition, the physiological methods employed show variation in measurements between sittings and within the same sitting. Thus, failure in determining the VDO might cause many kinds of problems such as temporomandibular joint disorders, muscular dysfunction, atrophy, alveolar bone resorption, a trauma of soft tissue, disturbance in phonetics, esthetics, swallowing, and chewing.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Specifically, the VDO, if it is greater, causes trauma to supporting tissues, phonetic problems, disturbance in temporomandibular joint and esthetics, whereas low VDO decreases the masticatory efficiency and esthetics. So, proper establishment of VDO is important to improve the function and esthetics, and thus the patient's quality of life.[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] Measures to avoid indiscriminate increase or decrease in this value are important.</p>
              <p>Standard measurement established through radiographic techniques and cephalometric analyses, which are easy, accurate, convenient, economical, and individualized, can be a useful additional tool in prosthodontics, if proved to be effective. A study reported maximum correlation between VDO inferior (lower facial angle from the G point to the ANS and the chin point) and the gonial angle.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] The regression formulae derived in that study were encouraging in the field of Prosthodontics. Still, the major drawback was that the formulae proposed were based on a single cephalometric dimension that can influence the accuracy of the measurement. To surpass this, multiple regression equations derived by considering six angular and four linear cephalometric measurements were proposed.[<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] However, for this, the dentist needs to invest more time in completing the analysis. Later, a simple cephalometric angular reconstruction method was tested on dentulous people and proved to be accurate.[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] The reconstruction of the facial dimensions through angles reported statistically significant positive correlations, which can be due to the fact that the human face follows precise dimensions. Hence, the present study was planned to determine the clinical effectiveness of the angular reconstruction method in edentulous people by comparing the satisfaction levels of people wearing complete dentures fabricated using the vertical dimensions predicted by cephalometrics to those with the conventional method. There was no difference either in the vertical dimension values determined as well as the in the satisfaction levels between the two groups. This shows that the angular reconstruction method can be employed clinically.</p>
              <p>The famous artist Leonardo Da Vinci gave simple ratios for drawing the face, which was applied to complete denture construction by Ivy.[<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] The facial dimensions follow simple proportions, and this concept of harmonic faces can be utilized for the rehabilitation of lost dimensions. Research and clinical experience have revealed a close interdependence of facial proportions.[<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref><xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] In the early stages of research, it has been observed that nasal height (N to ANS) accounts for 43% of the total facial height (N to Gn). In another study done on harmonious individuals, total facial height has been divided into 45% and 55% of nasal height and dental height, respectively. Later, in another study, the population has been divided into three facial types based on the growth pattern; normal, retrognathic, and prognathic. It has been observed that the upper facial height varied very little between the three facial patterns, whereas on the other hand, lower facial height has been found to be 56%, 59.5%, and 54.1% of total facial height in normal growth pattern, retrognathic and prognathic groups respectively. The proportion of middle and lower third the proportion of middle and lower third was proposed to be 0.8. Thus, the literature has proved a definite correlation between various facial dimensions, which led to the development of an instrument called a golden ruler. In another study, the face has been divided into four proportions and the ratio used for prosthesis construction. In the present study, for the conventional method of denture preparation, Willi's gauge was employed. The Pupil-rima oris distance has been considered to be equal to chin-nose distance, which is also based on facial proportions. That might be the reason for the similar vertical dimensions obtained in both methods. In almost all the cases, the level of patient comfort was satisfactory. This is the “comfort zone concept” that emphasizes VDO to be in a range instead of a fixed point.[<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] Because of this adaptive capacity, small dispersions were acceptable and did not influence muscle activity. A study observed that the increase in VDO could change the extent of mandibular trajectory during swallowing only if the increase was more than 3 mm.[<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</p>
              <p>The major drawback/limitation of cephalometrics is the need for a radiographic setup, which might not be available in all dental clinics, and additionally, the radiation exposure. Another drawback is the influence of racial differences[<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and the need to frame separate formulae for other populations based on the same theoretical principle. Thus, generalizabilty is a significant issue. However, there are many advantages of the angular reconstruction procedure considered in the present study. The landmarks selected were simple and could be marked easily. Using four cephalometric points, reconstruction of another point, Gn was done efficiently; there was ease in calculation, construction, and application. Angular variables were minimally affected due to problems of magnification and distortion when compared with the linear measurements. The patient's acceptability is another crucial factor in the success of this technique. Further studies on the clinical application of angular reconstruction procedure for partially edentulous people requiring removable partial dentures and dentate individuals undergoing orthodontic treatment are indicated. In addition, usage of radiographic markers for increasing the accuracy of transferring the cephalometric measurements to actual measurements is also indicated.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>Based on the limitations of the present study, the cephalometric angular reconstruction procedure has been proved to be successful and can be suggested as an equivalent to standard methods of recording the VDO. It can be suggested as an alternative to patients with neuromuscular problems, those unable to co-operate for the conventional methods of recording the vertical dimension and in scenarios, which demand reduction of the time spent in contact with patients.</p>
              <sec id="sec2-9">
                <title>Registration</title>
                <p>The study is registered at the Clinical Trials Registry, India, with the registration number CTRI/2021/05/033585.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-10">
                <title>Protocol</title>
                <p>The full detailed protocol can be downloaded from the Clinical Trial Registry.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-11">
                <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
                <p>Nil.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec2-12">
                <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
                <p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgment</title>
              <p>We would like to acknowledge all the participants for their voluntariness, and cooperation.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="ref1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <collab>The glossary of prosthodontic terms: Ninth edition</collab>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <fpage>e1</fpage>
                  <lpage>105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28418832</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alhajj</surname>
                      <given-names>MN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khalifa</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abduo</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amran</surname>
                      <given-names>AG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Isamail</surname>
                      <given-names>IA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determination of occlusal vertical dimension for complete dentures patients: An updated review</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>896</fpage>
                  <lpage>907</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28600914</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fayz</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eslami</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determination of occlusal vertical dimension: A literature review</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>59</volume>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3279190</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koka</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vertical dimension of occlusion</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>342</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17695854</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Turrell</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical assessment of vertical dimension</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1972</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4558967</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kois</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Phillips</surname>
                      <given-names>KM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Occlusal vertical dimension: Alteration concerns</article-title>
                  <source>Compend Contin Educ Dent</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>1176</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheppard</surname>
                      <given-names>IM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheppard</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vertical dimension measurements</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>95</volume>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <lpage>80</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16543012</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abduo</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lyons</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical considerations for increasing occlusal vertical dimension: A review</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <fpage>2</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burnett</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clifford</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Closest speaking space during the production of sibilant sounds and its value in establishing the vertical dimension of occlusion</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <fpage>964</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8496479</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silverman</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The speaking method in measuring vertical dimension</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1953</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bissasu</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pre-extraction records for complete denture fabrication: A literature review</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739894</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Millet</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeannin</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vincent</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malquarti</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Report on the determination of occlusal vertical dimension and centric relation using swallowing in edentulous patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>1118</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14641678</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loschiavo</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Madhav</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whyman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determination of vertical dimension by hydraulic intraoral jack</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3050000</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vinnakota</surname>
                      <given-names>DN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kanneganti</surname>
                      <given-names>KC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pulagam</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keerthi</surname>
                      <given-names>GK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determination of vertical dimension of occlusion using lateral profile photographs: A pilot study</article-title>
                  <source>J Indian Prosthodont Soc</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27746594</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chaconas</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gonidis</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A cephalometric technique for prosthodontic diagnosis and treatment planning</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthodont Dent</source>
                  <year>1986</year>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <fpage>567</fpage>
                  <lpage>73</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Basler</surname>
                      <given-names>FL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Douglas</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moulton</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cephalometric analysis of the vertical dimension of occlusion</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1961</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>831</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qamar</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Munir</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naeem</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Role of cephalometery in evaluation of vertical dimension</article-title>
                  <source>Pak Oral Dent J</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zielak</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neto</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>da Cunha</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deliberador</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giovanini</surname>
                      <given-names>AF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cephalometric approach to the occlusal vertical dimension reestablishment</article-title>
                  <source>Case Rep Dent</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>2014</volume>
                  <fpage>920840</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25105032</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Edwards</surname>
                      <given-names>CL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Richards</surname>
                      <given-names>MW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Billy</surname>
                      <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neilans</surname>
                      <given-names>LC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using computerized cephalometrics to analyze the vertical dimension of occlusion</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8240648</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sudhir</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chittaranjan</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arun Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taruna</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pavan Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramu Reddy</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Digital cephalometric tracings by PRO-CEPH V3 software for comparative analyses of vertical dimension in edentulous patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Diagn</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brzoza</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barrera</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Contasti</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hernandez</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Predicting vertical dimension with cephalograms, for edentulous patients</article-title>
                  <source>Gerodontology</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <lpage>103</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15934351</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Robert</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Facially generated occlusal vertical dimension</article-title>
                  <source>Compendium</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>1183</fpage>
                  <lpage>93</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9656843</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koller</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Merlini</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spandre</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palla</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparative study of two methods for the orientation of the occlusal plane and the determination of the vertical dimension of occlusion in edentulous patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>413</fpage>
                  <lpage>25</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1432356</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bassi</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deregibus</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Previgliano</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bracco</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Preti</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the utility of cephalometric parameters in constructing complete dentures. Part I: Placement of posterior teeth</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11350578</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bassi</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rizzatti</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schierano</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Preti</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the utility of cephalometric parameters in constructing complete denture. Part II: Placement of anterior teeth</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11350588</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tavano</surname>
                      <given-names>KT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seraidarian</surname>
                      <given-names>PI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>DD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jansen</surname>
                      <given-names>WC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determination of vertical dimension of occlusion in dentate patients by cephalometric analysis – Pilot study</article-title>
                  <source>Gerodontology</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>e297</fpage>
                  <lpage>305</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21323984</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Orthlieb</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laurent</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laplanche</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cephalometric estimation of vertical dimension of occlusion</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>802</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11012856</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Strajnić</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stanisić-Sinobad</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marković</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stojanović</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cephalometric indicators of the vertical dimension of occlusion</article-title>
                  <source>Coll Antropol</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>535</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18756907</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morais</surname>
                      <given-names>EC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ornaghi</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sponchiado</surname>
                      <given-names>AP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zielak</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determination of final occlusal vertical dimension by cephalometric analysis</article-title>
                  <source>RSBO</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <lpage>50</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yamashita</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shimizu</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katada</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A newly proposed method to predict optimum occlusal vertical dimension</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
                  <lpage>90</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25251764</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vinnakota</surname>
                      <given-names>DN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamatham</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of occlusal vertical dimension using cephalometric angular reconstruction</article-title>
                  <source>Indian J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34269233</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ivy</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental and facial types. The American system of dentistry</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1887</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <fpage>1030</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ricketts</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Divine proportion in facial esthetics</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Plast Surg</source>
                  <year>1982</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7172592</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref34">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peck</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peck</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A concept of facial esthetics</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>1970</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
                  <lpage>318</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4917993</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sakar</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sülün</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kurt</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gençel</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reliability and comparison of two facial measurements to detect changes of occlusal vertical dimension in complete denture wearers</article-title>
                  <source>Gerodontology</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20455954</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref36">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bhat</surname>
                      <given-names>VS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gopinathan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reliability of determining vertical dimension of occlusion in complete dentures: A clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>J Indian Prosthodont Soc</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref37">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barbosa</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bittencourt</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of facial proportions in the vertical plane to investigate the relationship between skeletal and soft tissue dimensions</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Press J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <lpage>106</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref38">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rivera-Morales</surname>
                      <given-names>WC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mohl</surname>
                      <given-names>ND</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Relationship of occlusal vertical dimension to the health of the masticatory system</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <fpage>547</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2066895</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref39">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shen</surname>
                      <given-names>YF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>HP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pan</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hong</surname>
                      <given-names>HH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vertical dimension of occlusion related to mandibular movement during swallowing</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed J</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33863681</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref40">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuroe</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosas</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Molleson</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Variation in the cranial base orientation and facial skeleton in dry skulls sampled from three major populations</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15130044</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
