<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:49:42Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3881827" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3881827</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-01-08</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jaos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J. Appl. Oral. Sci.</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de São
Paulo</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3881827</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3881827</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3881827</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23032205</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23032205</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-77572012000400008</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Comparative clinical study of the effectiveness of different dental
bleaching methods - two year follow-up</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>MONDELLI</surname>
                    <given-names>Rafael Francisco Lia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de AZEVEDO</surname>
                    <given-names>Juliana Felipi David e Góes</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>FRANCISCONI</surname>
                    <given-names>Ana Carolina</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de ALMEIDA</surname>
                    <given-names>Cristiane Machado</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>ISHIKIRIAMA</surname>
                    <given-names>Sérgio Kiyoshi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff05">5</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff01"><label>1 </label> DDS, MS, PhD, Associate Professor, Department of Restorative
Dentistry, Endodontics and Dental Materials, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of
São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> PhD student, Department of Restorative Dentistry, Endodontics and
Dental Materials, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> DDS, PhD, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, São
Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> DDS, PhD, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, São
Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff05"> DDS, MS, PhD, Assistant Professor, Department of Restorative Dentistry,
Endodontics and Dental Materials, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo,
São Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Rafael Francisco Lia Mondelli - Al. Dr. Octávio
Pinheiro Brisolla, 9-75 - Bauru - SP - 17012-901 - C.P. 73 - Departamento de
Dentística, Endodontia e Materiais Dentários - Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru,
Universidade de São Paulo - Phone: 55 14 3235-8265 - e-mail:
<email>rafamond@fob.usp.br</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Jul-Aug</season>
                <year>2012</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>20</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>435</fpage>
              <lpage>443</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>12</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>08</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2011</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>This study evaluated color change, stability, and tooth sensitivity in patients
submitted to different bleaching techniques.</p>
                <sec>
                  <title>Material and methods</title>
                  <p>In this study, 48 patients were divided into five groups. A half-mouth design was
conducted to compare two in-office bleaching techniques (with and without light
activation): G1: 35% hydrogen peroxide (HP) (Lase Peroxide - DMC Equipments, São
Carlos, SP, Brazil) + hybrid light (HL) (LED/Diode Laser, Whitening Lase II DMC
Equipments, São Carlos, SP, Brazil); G2: 35% HP; G3: 38% HP (X-traBoost -
Ultradent, South Jordan UT, USA) + HL; G4: 38% HP; and G5: 15% carbamide peroxide
(CP) (Opalescence PF - Ultradent, South Jordan UT, USA). For G1 and G3, HP was
applied on the enamel surface for 3 consecutive applications activated by HL. Each
application included 3x3' HL activations with 1' between each interval; for G2 and
G4, HP was applied 3x15' with 15' between intervals; and for G5, 15% CP was
applied for 120'/10 days at home. A spectrophotometer was used to measure color
change before the treatment and after 24 h, 1 week, 1, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months. A
VAS questionnaire was used to evaluate tooth sensitivity before the treatment,
immediately following treatment, 24 h after and finally 1 week after. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Statistical analysis did not reveal any significant differences between in-office
bleaching with or without HL activation related to effectiveness; nevertheless the
time required was less with HL. Statistical differences were observed between the
results after 24 h, 1 week and 1, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months (intergroup).
Immediately, in-office bleaching increased tooth sensitivity. The groups activated
with HL required less application time with gel. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>All techniques and bleaching agents used were effective and demonstrated similar
behaviors.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Dental bleaching</kwd>
                <kwd>Dentin sensitivity</kwd>
                <kwd>Hydrogen peroxide</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>State of São Paulo Research Foundation/FAPESP</funding-source>
                  <award-id>2006/02540-9</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>Cordination of Higher Education and Graduate Training -
Capes</funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec>
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Tooth color is determined by a combination of the different optical properties of
enamel, dentin and pulp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref></sup>. Tooth
discolorations vary in etiology, appearance, localization, severity and adherence to
tooth structure, and they are categorized as intrinsic or extrinsic. Although extrinsic
discoloration can be removed with a prophylactic cleaning procedure, intrinsic staining
necessitates chemical bleaching. Bleaching has been accepted as the least aggressive
method for treating discolored teeth.</p>
              <p>Until recently, the most commonly used method for vital teeth was home bleaching,
originally proposed by Haywood and Heymann<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref></sup> (1989), in which an individual tray that contained 10% carbamide
peroxide was used by the patient during the night for approximately 2 to 5 weeks. This
technique presents a number of advantages such as easy application, less peroxide
concentration, lower cost and less time in the dental office<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref></sup>. However, it
also presents some disadvantages, especially because of the professional's lack of
control over monitoring the use of the bleaching agents and trays by the patients. In
addition, some patients did not adjust to the trays, a weekly visit is necessary to
observe any initial bleaching results, and 2 to 5 weeks are required to obtain the
desired results.</p>
              <p>With the hope of obtaining more control, color stability, and effectiveness, as well as
to save time, in-office bleaching was proposed. This technique utilizes high
concentrations of hydrogen peroxide (between 15% and 38%) that can be activated by light
sources or heat. The equipment can use different light sources, such as halogen, Plasma
arc, light emitting diode (LED), ultraviolet lamp, laser (Argon, Diode, Neodymium-YAG or
CO<sub>2</sub>) and hybrid light<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r30">30</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Tooth discoloration and bleaching assessments/measurements can range from subjective
comparison methods to the use of objective instrumentation. There are limitations to the
use of subjective measurement methods using porcelain or acrylic resin shade guides;
these include the effectiveness of variables such as light conditions, experiences, age,
fatigue of the human eye, and conditions such as color blindness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r28">28</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>This CIELAB system was defined in 1967 by the International Commission on
Illumination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup>. This is a
three-dimensional uniform color space with equal distances corresponding to equally
perceived color differences. This system has three axes: the L* axis represents
lightness and extends from 0 (black) to 100 (white); and a* and b* represent the
redness-greenness and yellowness-blueness axis, respectively. When a* and b* coordinates
approach zero, the colors become neutral. A color difference (ΔE) between two objects
can be calculated within the CIELAB color system. The spectrophotometer was considered
more reliable by Matis, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r19">19</xref></sup>
(2002) because this method is more objective and sensible than a visual scale and
photos. Many authors have used this evaluation system as it allows for a better
comparison of the results obtained<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r29">29</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Tooth sensitivity during the bleaching period, at home or in office, is described as the
biggest problem for some authors, but sensitivity can disappear before bleaching
ends<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref></sup>. Other effects, such as small changes in
the enamel structure after bleaching treatments, have also raised concerns for some
researchers. These alterations can be easily restored by polishing, and enamel contact
with calcium and phosphate present in the saliva<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref></sup>, as well as the application of fluoride<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup>. Changes in the micro-hardness, morphology, roughness,
and wear are considered insignificant to many authors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Many studies have evaluated the effectiveness and security of some new products and
techniques. However, there is no consensus in relation to the effectiveness of at-home
or in-office bleaching, nor about their effects on the dental tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">25</xref></sup>. The activation of a bleaching agent by the thermocatalytic technique
has been questioned due to its deleterious effects on the structure. The objective of
this randomized clinical study was to evaluate tooth sensitivity, the degree of the
color alteration (ΔE) and bleaching maintenance after 2 years, and to compare the
effectiveness of the at-home and in-office bleaching techniques, with and without the
use of hybrid light source for gel activation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Patient inclusion and exclusion criteria</title>
                <p>This research was approved by the Ethics Committee in Research of the Bauru School of
Dentistry, University of São Paulo (process: 29/2006). Forty-eight patients were
selected using the following inclusion criteria: needed to have all anterior teeth
(superior and inferior) without restorations or caries; to agree to sign the consent
form; 18 to 30 years old; in good health; color A3 in at least four teeth; and to
agree to return for scheduled visits and follow-up examinations. The exclusion
criteria were: any disease that can interfere in the research; gingivitis or
periodontitis; those who smoke; any reaction to peroxides; any family history of
neoplasia in the oropharinge and adjacency; use of any bleaching agents within the
last year; tooth sensitivity of less than 1 on the VAS questioner scale; pregnant or
lactating women; and tetracycline stained teeth.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>The 48 patients selected were randomly divided into 5 groups (n=16), and all
bleaching gels were used according to the manufacturer's instructions and are
described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>. For a direct
comparison between bleaching protocols employed, a split-mouth design was used, where
the same patients were submitted to two bleaching treatments, one on the right
superior and inferior arcs and the other in the left superior and inferior arcs (G1
and G2; G3 and G4). The hybrid light (HL), Whitening Laser II (LED/therapeutic diode
laser) - (DMC Equipments, São Carlos, SP, Brazil), was used and employed 6 LEDs each
with a wavelength of 470 nm and irradiance of 350 mW/cm<sup>2</sup>, and 3 infrared
diode laser points each with a wavelength of 810 nm and 200 mW/cm<sup>2</sup>.</p>
                <table-wrap id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Bleaching gels used</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="border" rules="all">
                    <thead>
                      <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Comercial brands</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Bleaching gels</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Manufacturer</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Clinical use</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opalescence PF(CP 15%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbamine Peroxide15%</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> UltradentProducts Inc.</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Home bleaching</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OpalescenceXtra Boost (HP 38%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrogen Peroxide38%</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UltradentProducts Inc.</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> In office with chemical and/or physical activation</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laser Peroxide(HP 35%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrogen Peroxide35%</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DMC EquipamentsLtda</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In office with chemicaland/or physical activation</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>For Groups 1, 2, 3 and 4, the clinical steps were done in office, with and without
light activation:</p>
                <p>Supra-gingival prophylaxis using pumice stone and a "Robson" brush was performed,
followed by color measurement (canines, central and lateral incisors, superior and
inferior arcs) with a spectrophotometer and the initial photo using a digital camera
(D-70, Nikon) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>(A) Initial photo and (B) spectrophotometer color measurement</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jaos-20-04-0435-g01"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Application in the superior and inferior arcs of a gingival barrier (Lase-Protect,
DMC Equipments, São Carlos, SP, Brazil) in Groups 1 and 2 and an OpalDam (Ultradent
Products Inc., South Jordan UT, USA) in Groups 3 and 4 was followed by
photoactivation.</p>
                <p>In Group 1, the superior and inferior teeth on the right side received an application
of a 1 mm thick bleaching gel composed of 35% HP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3A</xref>), and the left side was protected with gauze. Next, the
bleaching gel was activated with HL for 3' in both arcs simultaneously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3B</xref>), followed by a 1' wait to allow the
temperature to fall. This step was performed twice more consecutively. After the
removal of the gel and teeth cleansing, the procedure was repeated two more times in
the same appointment for a total 33' of gel action. After the completion of the right
side arcs, the bleaching gel (HP 35%) without HL activation (Group 2) was applied to
the left side arcs for 3 consecutive 15' periods<italic>,</italic> with 15' intervals
between each application, totaling 45' of gel action. In Groups 3 and 4, the
bleaching gel (HP 38%) was applied and followed the same activation protocols as
Groups 1 and 2 (right side activated with HL and left side without),
respectively.</p>
                <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Clinical bleaching procedure in groups 1 and 2: A- bleaching gel application in
the right side arcs; B- activation of the gel with hibrid light (HL) in the
right side arcs and protection of the left side arcs</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jaos-20-04-0435-g02"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Polishing of the teeth in the vestibular faces was performed on all groups with a
felt disc impregnated with abrasives (Laser Peroxide, DMC Equipments, São Carlos, SP,
Brazil) to reestablish the enamel smoothness. After polishing, a desensitizing gel
(Lase Sensy, DMC Equipments, São Carlos, SP, Brazil) composed of 2% sodium fluoride
and 5% potassium nitrate was applied for 4'. For the groups activated with HL, laser
therapy was performed (25 J for 30") on all patients, regardless of tooth
sensitivity, in order to avoid and control postoperative sensitivity.</p>
                <p>For Group 5 (home bleaching), after initial photos were taken and color measurements
were done, the individual trays for the superior and inferior arcs were given to each
patient, as well as four gel-filled syringes (CP 15%) and instructions for use. The
gel was to be used 2 hours <italic>per</italic> day over a period of 10 days. During
this period, patients were not to use any products that could compromise the
bleaching.</p>
                <p>In the present study, Group 5 (home bleaching) was employed only to compare with the
results of in-office bleaching, with and without light activation. It is important to
know that in all groups, the control was obtained in the baseline color measurement
of each tooth that was evaluated from each patient.</p>
                <p>All patients received instructions to avoid any substance that could stain teeth in
the first 48 hours following the treatment, e.g., coffee, black tea, cola, mustard,
ketchup, red wine, soy sauce, chocolate, red fruits, tomato sauce, beets, etc. Beyond
these, patients were instructed to avoid other substances that could stain teeth such
as red lipstick, consumption of tobacco products, and food and beverages with acidic
pH levels. For patients who experienced exacerbated tooth sensitivity (Groups 1, 2, 3
and 4), an anti-inflammatory (Nimesulida 100 mg EMS, Eurofarma, Medley, Novartis) was
prescribed for one or two days.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Instrumental method for color measurement</title>
                <p>Digital photos were taken and instrumental color monitoring was performed before
bleaching and 24 hours, 1 week, 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months and 24 months
after (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>), using a contact-type
intra-oral spectrophotometer (Vita Easyshade, Vita-Zanhnfabrik, Bad Säckingen,
Germany). Color differences were calculated using the following equation:
ΔE=[(ΔL*)<sup>2</sup>+(Δa*)<sup>2</sup>+(Δb*)<sup>2</sup>]<sup>1/2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup>.</p>
                <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Control after: (A) 24 hours; (B) 1 month; (C) 12 months; (D) 24 months</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jaos-20-04-0435-g03"/>
                </fig>
                <p>The measurements to obtain tooth color were done using a spectrophotometer following
the manufacturer's instructions and in agreement with Kim-Pusateri, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16 </xref></sup>(2009); these measurements were taken
from the same area of each tooth (middle of the tooth) two times consecutively. When
these values were equal, they were registered. When the values were not equal,
additional measurements were taken until equal measurements were obtained, and only
one measurement for each tooth was recorded.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Tooth sensitivity assessment</title>
                <p>Before bleaching, the patients were submitted to the VAS questionnaire to measure
tooth sensitivity (baseline), as well as immediately after bleaching, 24 hours and 1
week. This evaluation determined the differences between the evaluation periods and
the bleaching gels tested. The patient was to indicate any tooth or oral sensitivity
by marking the level of sensitivity on the horizontal line, which ranges from 0 to
10, with 10 being the most sensitive.</p>
                <p>Range of sensitivity scores used:</p>
                <p>0-1: No pain</p>
                <p>2-3: Mild pain</p>
                <p>4-6: Moderate pain</p>
                <p>7-8: Severe pain</p>
                <p>9-10: Intolerable pain</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>All groups were submitted to histogram and Kolmogerov-Smirnov tests, and all data
presented normal distribution criteria. As a result of this normal distribution, the
results were submitted to ANOVA tests to identify any differences between groups
(p≤0.05%) and Tukey tests for individual comparisons between all groups with a level
of significance of p≤0.05%.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>The number of subjects who returned for each evaluation period for all groups evaluated
(n=16) can be observed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="f05">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
              <table-wrap id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Distribution of the number of subjects that returned for each evaluation period
for all groups evaluated (n=16)</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="box" rules="all">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Groups</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold> Initial</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>24 hours</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>1 week</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>1 month</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>6 months</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>12 months</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>18 months</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>24 months</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The values of the degree of change and color maintenance (ΔE) in the in-office and
at-home bleaching techniques over 24 months were submitted to ANOVA testing by three-way
ANOVA (bleaching agents, photoactivation and time), and Group 5 was submitted to two-way
ANOVA (time and bleaching gel). No statistically significant differences were observed
between in-office bleaching treatments (G1, G2, G3, and G4). The home bleaching group
(G5) presented statistically higher values of ΔE in comparison to the other two
bleaching agents used in office with or without HL (G1, G2, G3 and G4) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Figure
6</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Mean and standart deviation of ΔE for bleaching groups evaluated during 24
months</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Groups</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>24 hours</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>1 week</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>1 month</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>6 month</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>12 months</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>18 months</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>24 months</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G1:</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.80+1.42<sup>Ba</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45+1.40<sup>Bb</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64+1.45<sup>Bc</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49+1.45<sup>Bd</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99+1.45<sup>Be</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87+0,67<sup>Bf</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23+0.61<sup>Bg</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HP 35% + HL</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2:</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.49+1.45<sup>Ba</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.54+1.37<sup>Bb</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.43+1.47<sup>Bc</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33+1.39<sup>Bd</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85+1.41<sup>Be</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94+0.68<sup>Bf</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09+0.69<sup>Bg</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HP 35%</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G3:</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.83+1.39<sup>Ba</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.77+1.32<sup>Bb</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78+1.37<sup>Bc</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64+1.26<sup>Bd</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75+1.15<sup>Be</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77+0.60<sup>Bf</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85+0.56<sup>Bg</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HP 38% + HL</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G4:</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.76+1.50<sup>Ba</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67+1.56<sup>Bb</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64+1.38<sup>Bc</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42+1.47<sup>Bd</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75+1.26<sup>Be</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63+0.64<sup>Bf</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87+0.60<sup>Bg</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HP 38%</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G5:</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.80+1.75<sup>Aa</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.70+1.64<sup>Ab</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.67+1.57<sup>Ac</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52+1.62<sup>Ad</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.07+1.63<sup>Ae</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27+0.98<sup>Bf</sup>
</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29+0.78<sup>Bg</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr align="center">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CP 15% + HL</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>* Lower case letters: analysis between columns in the same line</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn>
                    <p>* Capital letters: analysis between lines in the same column</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn>
                    <p>HL= hibrid light</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 6</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Graph of mean (ΔE) for bleaching groups evaluated during 24 months</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jaos-20-04-0435-g04"/>
              </fig>
              <p>The observation time (intra-groups) presented statistically significant differences in
the five periods for all groups evaluated (Tukey test, p≤0.05).</p>
              <p>The differences in degree of sensitivity were determined using two-way ANOVA testing
(bleaching agent and time evaluation) and the Tukey test for individual comparisons
(<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>). Statistical differences were
observed only in the period immediately after the bleaching between PH 35% and PC 15%.
After 24 hours, there were no differences between in-office bleaching gels, and after 1
week, the sensitivity levels returned to normal.</p>
              <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Description of the sensitivity results based on the bleaching gel used</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Bleaching gels</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Baseline</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Immediately after bleaching</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>24 hours</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>7 days</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>(mean±SD)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HP 35%</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45+0.88<sup>A</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47+3.13<sup>B</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93+0.90<sup>D</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42+0.87<sup>E</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HP 38%</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71+0.83<sup>A</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95+1.78<sup>BC</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89+2.33<sup>D</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69+0.82<sup>E</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP 15%</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65+0.73<sup>A</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54+1.91<sup>C</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72+0.68<sup>E</sup>
</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>*Capital letters: analysis between lines in the same column</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>The purpose of this <italic>in vivo</italic> study about vital tooth bleaching was to
compare the effectiveness and stability in-office (with or without photoactivation) and
at-home bleaching techniques in relation to color change (ΔE) and tooth sensitivity, for
24 months after the treatments. CP 15% gel was used at home and in office, two bleaching
agents with high concentrations (HP 35 and 38%) were used for chemical and physical
activation.</p>
              <p>Tooth color alteration can be determined by means of a visual evaluation using a color
shade, which is a subjective method, very functional, easy and fast to use<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">25</xref></sup>. Objective methods that can be employed
are the use of a spectrophotometer, colorimeters and software images<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref></sup>. The instrumental evaluation has been
preferred over the visual evaluation because it makes the process more practical and
statistically more reliable<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r19">19</xref></sup>. For
Groups 1, 2, 3 and 4 (in-office bleaching), six teeth were evaluated from each patient,
and for Group 5, twelve teeth; this allowed measurements from each patient to become
more precise in obtaining the color alteration (ΔE) in numeric values (CIELAB System)
and provided normal distribution results. This is another advantage of this method
(spectrophotometer) in comparison to a visual scale evaluation by operators. In a study
done by Kim-Pusateri, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16 </xref></sup>(2009),
using the same methods, they confirmed that this method gives more confidence and
standard results, with 96% accuracy.</p>
              <p>Tooth bleaching is directly related to tooth structure and permeability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">25</xref></sup>. The enamel behaves like a
semi-permeable membrane that possibly transmits water and other substances with small
molecular size, such as oxygen ions (O-) present in the HP. These characteristics allow
oxygen diffusion (oxygen reaction) over the organic structure of teeth and permit
reaction to the stained molecules, and this promotes the bleaching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref></sup>. A light source was used with the
objective to accelerate the reaction and become more effective<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r30">30</xref></sup>. The theoretical advantage of the light source is the increase in
the hydrogen peroxide temperature, thus accelerating the reaction and forming hydroxyl
and oxygen free radicals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r30">30</xref></sup>. A temperature rise of 10ºC increases the speed of hydrogen peroxide
decomposition by 2.2 times<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref></sup>. To
increase the interaction of visible light with the bleaching gel, manufacturers
incorporate coloring agents or pigments into their products, which have colors capable
of promoting maximum absorption of this light and subsequent conversion into heat.</p>
              <p>For the present study, one hybrid light source composed of a LED and a therapeutic diode
laser were used to activate the bleaching gel in the in office techniques. In accordance
with Camargo, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> (2009), the use
of a LED or Nd:Yag laser for activation of the HP 35% permitted a higher degree of
penetration in the direction of the chamber pulp (20 minutes after the gel application),
in comparison to the groups without photo activation.</p>
              <p>Post-bleaching sensitivity differs from dentin hypersensitivity because it is related
directly to the penetration of the sub-products of the bleaching gels in the dentin and
pulp tissue, through the enamel, causing reversible pulpit and consequent teeth thermal
sensitivity, but not causing permanent damage to the pulp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r23">23</xref></sup>. These responses are correlated with the peroxide
concentration, time, frequency of gel application and pulp temperature rise with light
activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref></sup>. Carrasco, Carrasco-Guerisoli and
Fröner<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> (2008), in an <italic>in
vitro</italic> study, found low indexes of temperature increases considered
compatible with pulp vitality maintenance, when applying an LED source or HL to the gel
(35% HP). Coutinho, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup> (2008)
evaluated the rise of pulp-chamber temperature induced by different light sources in
in-office bleaching with HP 35%, and they concluded that the specific combination of
color agent + light color determines good dental bleaching with a smaller temperature
increase and, consequently, less sensitivity. In the present study, the lowest dental
sensitive index was observed in the G5 (home bleaching) in the function of low gel
concentration (CP 15%). Groups 1-4 used high concentrations of the bleaching gel (HP 35
and 38%), and all experienced higher levels of sensitivity. After 24 hours, the degree
of sensitivity had lowered considerably and returned to normal levels after one week for
all groups evaluated. Although the groups in office were completed in the same
appointment, to each patient (right and left side), it was not possible to determine
whether the teeth with or without HL activation presented higher or lower degrees of
sensitivity. As a result, sensitivity analysis was determined just by the bleaching
agent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>). Marson, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18</xref></sup> (2008), in an <italic>in vivo</italic>
study, found high levels of sensitivity (92% of patients) in in-office bleaching using
HP 35% with and without any light source, but in all cases, this sensitivity disappeared
24 hours after the treatment.</p>
              <p>The use of HL in one <italic>in vitro</italic> study of rats found a less inflammatory
response in the coronal pulp independent of the bleaching gel concentration used (HP
15%, 25% and 35%), when compared to the in-office bleaching without HL activation. This
indicated that the diode laser present in the HL equipment has a therapeutic effect in
the process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">11</xref></sup>. The initial results
(after 1 month) presented by Rosa and Mondelli<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref></sup> (2009), in a clinical research study comparing the level of
sensitivity in in office bleaching (HP 35%) with and without light activation (HL), were
obtained by performing the procedure at different times (7 days apart) to the same
patient. The group without HL activation (3x15') presented, immediately after the
bleaching, a significant increase in sensitivity compared to the groups with HL
(3x7'30"). These results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>) suggest that
the light activation system (LED/therapeutic laser), with half of the gel action time,
produces the same level of color change, but with less pulp inflammation and,
consequently, lower sensitivity degree, in agreement with Frigo, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">11</xref></sup> (2009). In the present study, all
manufacturers' instructions were followed; it is possible that the diode laser
diminished the effects of sensitivity, though it was impossible for all patients to
identify differences between the right and left side arches. As a result of this
observation, tooth sensitivity was compared between bleaching gels rather than bleaching
protocols.</p>
              <p>Micro-structure alterations, such as microhardness and roughness, which reverted
naturally after 7 to 15 days after bleaching due to the effect of the calcium and
phosphate ions present in the saliva<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">26</xref></sup>, as well as to fluoride
applications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup>, are not
considered significant. One <italic>in vitro</italic> study done by Mondelli, et
al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref></sup> (2009) evaluated roughness
and wear, before and after brushing, of bovine enamel submitted to different bleaching
protocols (CP 16%; HP 35%+HL; HP 35%+halogen light). There were no significant
differences among the groups comparing initial and post-bleaching roughness. After
brushing, there were differences between the control group and experimental groups. The
home bleaching group (CP 16%) showed a significant increase in roughness values compared
to group HP 35%+HL. Wear was significantly less for the control group compared to the
other groups. Bleaching techniques promoted increased bovine enamel surface roughness
and wear when submitted to simulated brushing.</p>
              <p>Cadenaro, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup> (2008), demonstrated
in an <italic>in vivo</italic> study with HP and CP in high concentrations, after
multiple applications, no occurrence of roughness alterations in the enamel superficies.
All bleaching gels evaluated in this study possessed one important characteristic, a
neutral pH level, because gels with acidic pH can promote higher alterations in the
topography of the enamel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref></sup> and have
the potential to induce collateral effects, such as tooth sensitivity and gingival
irritation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The difference in the action time of the bleaching gels (contact with teeth) evaluated
in this study explain the statistical differences in initial ΔE value G5 in relation to
the other groups. These differences disappear after 18 and 24 months of control in
relation to other in-office groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>).
For G1 and G3 (9' HL activation), the total time of gel action was 33', divided into 3
consecutive applications; for G2 and G4, (without light activation), the total time of
gel action was 45', divided into 3 consecutive applications of 15' each with 15' between
each applications; and for G5, the total time of tray use (15% CP) was 1,200'. The rise
in the number of in-office bleaching treatments without HL or the possibility of
applying and activating, with HL, the bleaching gel up to five times in the same
session<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref></sup> will determine the
best results (higher ΔE), in order to compensate for differences in gel action
time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>A new in-office protocol activated with HL (the same light used in this study),
decreased the action time of the gel to 7'30" (30"+2'HL+30"+2'HL+30"+2'HL), possibly to
obtain teeth bleaching in only one session, justifying the use of HL in the in office
bleaching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref></sup>. This protocol enables the bleaching to be obtained in
only one session by performing 5x gel applications. This finding is in agreement with
those of other authors, who observed that the light equipment can be used to shorten the
gel application time, and this accelerates the bleaching process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The efficiency of these lights presented some conflicting results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18</xref></sup>. Marson, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18</xref></sup> (2008) discovered no differences in the
activation or note with a light source (halogen, LED, and LED/Diode laser) in in-office
bleaching, but the authors did not follow the protocols recommended by the manufacturers
and did not state the gel activation time. This information was obtained in the original
PhD thesis, where the activation time for all light sources was only 20" <italic>per
</italic>tooth in each of two bleaching appointments. On another clinical study,
Bernadon, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> (2010), compared the
efficiency of at-home bleaching versus in-office bleaching activated with HL (Whitening
Lase, DMC Equipments, São Carlos, SP, Brazil); in-office bleaching with and without HL
activation; and at-home bleaching, versus a combination of at-home and in-office
bleaching activated with HL. The authors did not observe differences in the bleaching
results, sensitivity and durability in the 6 months between the techniques, and they
concluded that light activation is not recommended. The authors did not follow the
protocol recommended by the manufacturer of the HL, and instead, they performed two
sessions with three gel applications of 15' each and light activation of 4'.</p>
              <p>In the present study, independent of the technique, bleaching gel concentration and
activation with or without HL, all protocols employed were effective in promoting teeth
bleaching. This finding confirms that the results obtained with the bleaching are not
dependent on the technique employed (home bleaching, in-office bleaching with or without
light activation). The color change (color rebound) in the bleaching treatments during
the time evaluated (24 months) was similar among all groups evaluated without
statistically significant differences, a finding that supports the results of a two-year
study by Swift, May and Wilderider<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">27</xref></sup>
(1999). Similar results were found in <italic>in vivo</italic> studies by Bizhang, et
al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup> (2009), Marson, et.
al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18 </xref></sup>(2009) and Bernadon, et
al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> (2010). Bizhang, et
al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup> (2009) utilized a
colorimeter and concluded that at-home bleaching (CP 10%) and in office bleaching (HP
15%) are equally efficient and patients retained the lightness for 3 months.</p>
              <p>Given the results of this study and the literature presented, light activation with HL
can produce effective results with less time for gel action, when compared with at-home
bleaching and in-office bleaching without light activation, and this knowledge can be
useful in many clinical situations.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>Due to the results observed during the evaluated times, we can conclude:</p>
              <p>In-office bleaching presented highest sensitivity initially in comparison to at-home
home bleaching;</p>
              <p>All techniques and bleaching gels used were effective in teeth bleaching;</p>
              <p>The in-office bleaching techniques utilizing two bleaching gels, with or without light
activation (HL), presented similar results; and</p>
              <p>The color change (ΔE) recorded in the bleaching treatments during the time evaluated was
similar among all groups evaluated.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <sec>
                <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                <p>State of São Paulo Research Foundation/FAPESP (2006/02540-9) and Cordination of
Higher Education and Graduate Training - Capes.</p>
              </sec>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="r01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Attin</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manolakis</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buchalla</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hannig</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of tea on intrinsic colour of previously bleached
enamel</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehab</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>488</fpage>
                  <lpage>494</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berga-Caballero</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forner-Navarro</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amengual-Lorenzo</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>At-home vital bleaching: a comparison of hydrogen peroxide and
carbamide peroxide treatments</article-title>
                  <source>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>E94</fpage>
                  <lpage>E99</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16388304</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bernardon</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sartori</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ballarin</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Perdigão</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lopes</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baratieri</surname>
                      <given-names>LN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical performance of vital bleaching techniques</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20166405</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bistey</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nagy</surname>
                      <given-names>IP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simó</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hegedus</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> FT-IR study of the effects of hydrogen peroxide on
superficial tooth enamel</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <lpage>330</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116354</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bizhang</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chun</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Damerau</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shing</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raab</surname>
                      <given-names>WH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zimmer</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative clinical study of the effectiveness of three different
bleaching methods</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <fpage>635</fpage>
                  <lpage>641</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19953771</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cadenaro</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Breschi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nucci</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Antoniolli</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Visintini</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prati</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of two in-office whitening agents on the enamel surface
<italic>in vivo</italic>: a morphological and non-contact profilometric
study</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <lpage>134</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18435185</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Camargo</surname>
                      <given-names>SEA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cardoso</surname>
                      <given-names>PE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Valera</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Araújo</surname>
                      <given-names>MAM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kojima</surname>
                      <given-names>AN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Penetration of 35% hydrogen peroxide into the pulp chamber in bovine
teeth after LED or Nd: YAG laser activation</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Esthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <lpage>88</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19655647</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carrasco</surname>
                      <given-names>TG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carrasco-Guerisoli</surname>
                      <given-names>LD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fröner</surname>
                      <given-names>IC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> study of the pulpchamber temperature rise during
light-actived bleaching </article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <lpage>359</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19089234</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Commission Internationale de L`Eclairage</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Recommendations on uniform colour spaces, colour terms</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Bureau Central de la CIE</publisher-name>
                  <year>1978</year>
                  <comment>Publication 15, supplement 2</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coutinho</surname>
                      <given-names>DS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silveira</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nicolau</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zanin</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brugnera</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of temperature increase <italic>in vitro</italic> human
tooth pulp by light sources in the dental whitening process</article-title>
                  <source>Laser Med Sci</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <lpage>185</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frigo</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pallota</surname>
                      <given-names>RC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meneguzzo</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marcos</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Penna</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lopez-Martins</surname>
                      <given-names>RAB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the photo-activated dental bleaching effect on dental
pulp in an <italic>in vivo</italic> rat experimental model</article-title>
                  <source>R Dental Press Estet</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <lpage>114</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldstein</surname>
                      <given-names>RE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garber</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Complete dental bleaching</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Quintessence Publishing Co.</publisher-name>
                  <year>1995</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haywood</surname>
                      <given-names>VB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>History, safety, and effectiveness of current bleaching techniques and
applications of the nightguard vital bleaching technique</article-title>
                  <source>Quintessence Int</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>471</fpage>
                  <lpage>488</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1410249</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haywood</surname>
                      <given-names>VB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heymann</surname>
                      <given-names>HO</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Nightguard vital bleaching</article-title>
                  <source>Quintessence Int</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <lpage>176</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2762507</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joiner</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The bleaching of teeth: a review of the literature</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <fpage>412</fpage>
                  <lpage>419</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16569473</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim-Pusateri</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brewer</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>EL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wee</surname>
                      <given-names>AG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reliability and accuracy of four dental shade-matching
devices</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>101</volume>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <lpage>199</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19231572</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aguiar</surname>
                      <given-names>FHB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liporoni</surname>
                      <given-names>PCS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Munin</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ambrosano</surname>
                      <given-names>GMB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lovadino</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of the effectiveness of bleaching agents
activated by different light sources</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosth</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <lpage>254</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marson</surname>
                      <given-names>FC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sensi</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vieira</surname>
                      <given-names>LCC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Araújo</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical evaluation of in-office dental bleaching treatments with and
without the use of light activation sources</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18335726</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matis</surname>
                      <given-names>BA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamdan</surname>
                      <given-names>YS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cochran</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eckert</surname>
                      <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stropes</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A clinical evaluation of a bleaching agent used with and without
reservoirs</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11817468</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mondelli</surname>
                      <given-names>RFL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Toledo</surname>
                      <given-names>FL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ishikiriama</surname>
                      <given-names>SK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">Clareação de dentes polpados em consultório com e sem
condicionamento ácido prévio de esmalterelato de caso clínico</article-title>
                  <source>R Dental Press Estet</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <lpage>51</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mondelli</surname>
                      <given-names>RFL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azevedo</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Francisconi</surname>
                      <given-names>PAS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ishikiriama</surname>
                      <given-names>SK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mondelli</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Wear and surface roughness of bovine enamel submitted to
bleaching</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Esthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>396</fpage>
                  <lpage>403</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20111762</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ontiveros</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paravina</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Color change of vital teeth exposed to bleaching perfomed with and
without supplementary light</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>450</fpage>
                  <lpage>457</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>RB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Passive tooth bleaching: the cosmetic revolution</source>
                  <publisher-loc>La Mesa</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>R.B. Roberts</publisher-name>
                  <year>1991</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosa</surname>
                      <given-names>RE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mondelli</surname>
                      <given-names>RFL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title xml:lang="pt">Comparação clínica entre clareamento com e sem
fotoativação</article-title>
                  <source>DMC Journal</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <lpage>17</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sulieman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Addy</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacDonald</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rees</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A safety study <italic>in vitro</italic> for the effects of an
in-office bleaching system on the integrity of enamel</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>581</fpage>
                  <lpage>590</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15386865</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sulieman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacDonald</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rees</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Addy</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of three in-office bleaching systems based on 35% hydrogen
peroxide with different light activators</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Dent</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <lpage>197</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16158812</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Swift</surname>
                      <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>May</surname>
                      <given-names>KN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilder</surname>
                      <given-names>AD</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heymann</surname>
                      <given-names>HO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bayne</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Two-year clinical evaluation of tooth whitening using at-home
bleaching system</article-title>
                  <source>J Esth Dent</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watts</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Addy</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tooth discolouration and staining: a review of the
literature</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dental J</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>190</volume>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <lpage>316</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wetter</surname>
                      <given-names>NU</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barroso</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pelino</surname>
                      <given-names>JEP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental bleaching efficacy with diode laser and LED irradiation: an
<italic>in vitro</italic> study</article-title>
                  <source>Lasers Surg Med</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <lpage>258</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15493033</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiegand</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vollmer</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Foitzik</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Attin</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Attin</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of different whitening modalities on bovine enamel and
dentin</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Oral Investig</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <lpage>97</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
