<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:38:42Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10315020" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10315020</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-07-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcorhl</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10315020</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10315020</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10315020</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37393272</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37393272</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3133</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-023-03133-5</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Periodontitis in obese adults with and without metabolic syndrome: a cross-sectional study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nilsen</surname>
                    <given-names>Astrid</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Thorsnes</surname>
                    <given-names>Anette</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lie</surname>
                    <given-names>Stein Atle</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Methlie</surname>
                    <given-names>Paal</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bunaes</surname>
                    <given-names>Dagmar F.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Reinholtsen</surname>
                    <given-names>Karen K.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Leknes</surname>
                    <given-names>Knut N.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>knut.leknes@uib.no</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7914.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7443</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Dentistry – Periodontics, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Bergen, </institution></institution-wrap>Aarstadveien 19, Bergen, N-5009 Norway </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412008.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9753 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Medicine, </institution><institution>Haukeland University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Bergen, Norway </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7914.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7443</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Science, </institution><institution>University of Bergen, </institution></institution-wrap>Bergen, Norway </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <elocation-id>439</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>23</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">Epidemiological studies support an association between obesity, metabolic syndrome (MetS), and periodontitis. Still, understanding of the effects of low-grade inflammation in obese subjects on periodontitis and influence of MetS remains incomplete. The aims of this cross-sectional study were to explore the association between obesity related variables and periodontitis, and assess if MetS is a risk indicator for periodontitis in a sample of obese adults.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">The study sample comprised 52 adults with a body mass index (BMI) of ≥ 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> referred for obesity therapy at the Obesity Centre at Haukeland University Hospital (HUH), Bergen, Norway. The subjects had prior to enrolment completed a 5-month lifestyle intervention course as part of a 2-year managing program. According to the revised National Cholesterol Education Program Adult Treatment Panel III (NCEP ATP III) classification of MetS, 38 subjects were recruited to the MetS group and 14 subjects to the non-MetS group. Medical data including peripheral blood samples were obtained from records at HUH at the time of enrolment. Probing depth, clinical attachment level, tooth mobility, furcation involvement, bleeding on probing (BoP) were recorded and intraoral bitewings evaluated at a full-mouth periodontal examination. Associations between risk variables for obesity/MetS and periodontitis were explored using linear and logistic regression models.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">In the present sample 79% of the subjects were diagnosed with periodontitis. The prevalence of stage III/IV periodontitis was 42.9% in the non-MetS group vs. 36.8% in the MetS group (p = 0.200). In the non-MetS group 29.8% of the sites displayed BoP vs. 23.5% in the MetS group (p = 0.048). For stage III/IV periodontitis, the effect of age appeared to be significant for obesity related variables and MetS (p = 0.006, p = 0.002, respectively). None of the other analyses showed significant association with the outcome variables.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">In the present sample of obese subjects, periodontitis occurred independently of MetS. Reaching a certain BMI level, suggested association between MetS and periodontitis might be non-significant due to the dominating impact of obesity related variables undermining the effect of other systemic factors.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Trial registration</title>
                  <p id="Par6">The principal clinical trial, entitled “Obesity and Oral Diseases”, was prospectively registered in ClinicalTrials.gov with registration NCT04602572 (20.10.2020).</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Cross-sectional study</kwd>
                <kwd>Periodontitis</kwd>
                <kwd>Obesity</kwd>
                <kwd>Systemic mediators</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>University of Bergen (incl Haukeland University Hospital)</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <open-access>
                  <p>Open access funding provided by University of Bergen.</p>
                </open-access>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par7">Overweight and obesity increasing globally are considered major challenges to human health services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In 2016, 39% of adults were overweight and 13% were obese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Present understanding recognizes adipose tissue as an endocrine organ, adipocytes acting as modulators affecting local and systemic inflammation. This low-grade inflammation may contribute to the occurrence of diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular disease, hypertension, stroke, and cancers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Several oral health concerns including periodontitis, tooth loss, xerostomia, dental erosion, and dental caries have also been linked with obesity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par8">Metabolic syndrome (MetS) represents an assembly of functional disturbances including obesity, increased waist circumference, increased insulin levels/blood glucose, hypertension and/or low high-density lipoprotein (HDL)/high triglycerides (TG) count. Each is considered a risk factor for the development of other diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Co-occurring as a syndrome, these factors significantly increase risk of developing potentially life-threatening diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The prevalence of MetS is estimated to be about 25% of the adult world population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Age, familial history of type 2 diabetes, previous gestational diabetes, gout, and polycystic ovary syndrome are risk factors associated with increased risk of developing MetS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. There are several definitions of MetS, the revised version of the National Cholesterol Education Program Adult Treatment Panel III (NCEP ATP III) definition from 2005 was used in the present study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par9">Periodontitis is a chronic non-communicable, inflammatory disease encompassing tooth supporting gingival tissues and alveolar bone triggered by dysbiosis of oral microbiota and host immune response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Periodontitis affects oral function and aesthetics impacting individual quality of life and well-being. Severe periodontitis is the sixth most prevalent non-communicable condition affecting approximately 10% of the world population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par10">Elevated levels of inflammatory biomarkers including high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (CRP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and proinflammatory cytokines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] have been observed in obese subjects. The association between obesity and periodontitis has been shown in several studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, the understanding of effects of low-grade inflammation in overweight/obese subjects on periodontitis remains incomplete [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. A recent population-based cohort study reported that obese subjects presented a significantly higher risk of tooth loss than normal-weight subjects and that preventive strategies directed to reduce tooth loss should target obese subjects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. An obesity modulated imbalance may result in an increased expression of pro-inflammatory and reduction of anti-inflammatory adipokines, leading to a persistent chronic inflammatory status. The presence of insulin resistance and obesity might have a close relation to the plasma levels of TNF-α, CRP, and IL-6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par11">Periodontitis and MetS share inflammation as a common feature and subjects affected by either disease may display elevated levels of circulatory cytokines. Both TNF-α and IL-6 have been considered important mediators for periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Increased levels of these mediators in MetS subjects, and their association with development of MetS associated morbidities further support theories of a bidirectional relationship between MetS and periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Oxidative stress as a potential link between MetS and periodontitis has also received attention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par12">The aims of the present cross-sectional study were to explore the association between obesity related variables and periodontitis, and assess if MetS is a risk indicator for periodontitis in a sample of obese adults. We hypothesize that MetS deteriorates the periodontal inflammatory status in these subjects.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p id="Par13">The study protocol and informed consent following the Helsinki Declaration of 1975 (version 2008) was approved by the Norwegian Regional Ethics Committee (Reference 152,810–22/02/2021/REK Vest). The principal clinical trial, entitled “Obesity and Oral Diseases”, was prospectively registered in ClinicalTrials.gov with registration NCT04602572 (20.10.2020). Study subjects were informed of the nature, scope, and consequences of participating in the study before signing the informed consent. The present article is written according to Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) guidelines. All methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations.</p>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Study design and setting</title>
                <p id="Par14">The present cross-sectional study enrolled subjects from the Obesity Centre, Section of Endocrinology, Haukeland University Hospital (HUH), Bergen, Norway, January 2021 through September 2021. Medical data and fasting blood samples were collected at enrolment. A clinical periodontal examination was performed at the Department of Clinical Dentistry, University of Bergen, January 2021 through December 2021. Enrolled subjects were informed of any periodontal pathology and recommended to seek dental care from a local dentist or periodontal specialist of choice.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Pre-study calibration and sample size calculation</title>
                <p id="Par15">One examiner (AT) unaware of group assignment performed all clinical examinations. Prior to initiation of the study, two separate calibration exercises were performed: 1: Examiner AT was calibrated with an experienced periodontist (KNL) and 2: Examiner AT performed an exercise to assess intra-examiner reproducibility for the primary outcome variables probing depth (PD) and clinical attachment level (CAL). In a study sample of five subjects (100 teeth/600 sites), PD and CAL were examined twice, 10 min apart, at six sites per tooth. Intraclass correlation coefficients (ICCs) were calculated separately for each site. ICC for repeated measures ranged between 0.84 and 0.93 for PD and between 0.82 and 0.95 for CAL.</p>
                <p id="Par16">The pre-study sample size calculation was based on change in PD. A difference of 0.5 mm was considered clinically relevant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Standard deviation of the difference between repeated PD measurements from the intra-calibration exercise was 0.5 mm. A power analysis based on 50 subjects (25/group) with the level of significance (α) set to 0.05, resulted in 90% power to detect a true difference of 0.5 mm. Drop-outs were not anticipated.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Study subjects</title>
                <p id="Par17">The study included subjects with an initial body mass index (BMI) ≥ 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> having completed a 5-month lifestyle intervention course as part of a 2-year managing program. Consecutive subjects were screened for eligibility according to inclusion/exclusion criteria by a senior consultant. Fifty-two out of 129 screened subjects were enrolled (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p>
                <p id="Par18">Study exclusion criteria included leukaemia/neutropenia, HIV/AIDS, pregnancy, use of immunosuppressive drugs, mental illness (active psychosis, severe depression), Sjögren’s syndrome, obesity caused by endocrine disease (e.g., hypercortisolism, hypothyroidism), bulimia nervosa, and present/past history of head and neck cancer. In addition, subjects treated for periodontitis or used systemic antibiotic/anti-inflammatory medication within the last 6 months were also excluded.</p>
                <p id="Par19">Enrolled subjects were assigned into a non-MetS or a MetS group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) according to the revised NCEP ATP III classification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. MetS was determined when participants met at least three out of five criteria: waist circumference ≥ 102/88 cm, men/women; fasting triglycerides ≥ 1.7 mmol/L or drug treatment for elevated levels; HDL-cholesterol &lt; 1.03/1.30 mmol/L, men/women; systolic blood pressure &gt; 130 mmHg an/or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 85 mmHg or antihypertensive medication; elevated fasting s-glucose ≥ 5.7 or anti-diabetic medication. Data on waist circumstance (WC) were missing, but WC was safely assumed to exceed the revised NCEP ATP III criteria in patients with BMI &gt; 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. The blood sample for testing MetS diagnosis parameters (triglycerides, HDL-cholesterol, and fasting glucose) and CRP were all collected at HUH in the morning after 12 h fasting. Subjects were excluded if group allocation was not possible based on predefined MetS criteria.</p>
                <p id="Par20">
                  <fig id="Fig1">
                    <label>Fig. 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Flowchart of study participants</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_3133_Fig1_HTML" id="d32e437"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Questionnaire</title>
                <p id="Par21">Upon arrival for the clinical examination, study subjects completed a multiple-choice questionnaire including demographic items, general health, medication, smoking, oral health/hygiene, and dietary habits. Questions were repeated orally if there were missing answers resulting in a 100% response rate. The questionnaire, tested internally to ascertain that all items were easily understood, was constructed by the research group experienced in the items selected. Participants were classified as either current smokers (had smoked ≥ 100 cigarettes in their lifetime and currently smoked), former smokers (had smoked ≥ 100 cigarettes in their lifetime, not currently smoking), or never smokers (had not smoked ≥ 100 cigarettes in their lifetime) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Periodontal examination</title>
                <p id="Par22">The following clinical parameters were recorded: PD (distance in mm from the gingival margin to the base of the periodontal pocket); and CAL (distance in mm from the cemento-enamel junction or the margin of a dental restoration to the base of the pocket) using a periodontal probe (PCPUNC 15, Hu-Friedy, Chicago, IL, USA) at six sites per tooth rounded up to the nearest mm (mesio-buccal, buccal, disto-buccal, disto-palatal/lingual, lingual/palatal, mesio-lingual/palatal). Bleeding on probing (BoP), sites showing bleeding on gentle probing was estimated at four sites per tooth (mesial, buccal, distal, lingual) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Furcations were examined using a curved Nabers furcation probe (PQ2N; HU-Friedy, Chicago, IL, USA) and recorded according to horizontal classification criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]: Furcation defects, featuring loss of periodontal support &gt; 3 mm into the furcation but not encompassing the total width of the furcation area were classified as degree II. Physiological tooth mobility was classified as degree 0, horizontally mobility &lt; 1 mm as degree 1, increased mobility &gt; 1 mm horizontally as degree 2, and degree 3 as severe mobility in both horizontal and vertical direction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Two bitewing radiographs were obtained to estimate periodontal bone loss. All teeth but third molars were examined.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>Periodontal diagnosis</title>
                <p id="Par23">Periodontitis was diagnosed and classified using the 2017 World Workshop on the Classification of Periodontal and Peri-implant Diseases and Conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In short, stage I periodontitis was diagnosed in the presence of interdental CAL of 1–2 mm at the site of greatest loss, PD 3–4 mm, radiographic bone loss affecting the cervical third of the roots, and no tooth loss due to periodontitis; stage II as the presence of interdental CAL loss of 3–4 mm, PD 4–5 mm, radiographic bone loss affecting the cervical third of the roots, and no tooth loss due to periodontitis; stage III as the presence of interdental CAL loss of ≥ 5 mm, PD &gt; 5 mm, radiographic bone loss affecting the middle third of the roots, and ≤ 4 teeth lost due to periodontitis; stage IV as the presence of interdental CAL loss of ≥ 5 mm, PD &gt; 5 mm, the radiographic bone loss affecting the middle third or more of the roots, and &gt; 4 teeth lost due to periodontitis and in the absence of 10 or more occluding pairs of teeth. The extension of periodontitis was categorized as localized or generalized. Localized, meaning less than 30% of examined teeth fulfil the minimum criteria for the patients´ acquired stage of periodontitis and generalized, meaning 30% or more of the teeth coincide with the acquired stage of periodontitis. Agreement on case definition of subjects with unclear status was reached by discussion between the examiners and the reference examiner (KNL). Grading of periodontitis was not performed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par24">Mean values and standard deviations were used to describe continuous variables. For categorical variables frequencies and percentages were used. Quantitative variables such as PD and CAL were sectioned into three distinct groups: 0–3 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], 4–5 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and ≥ 6 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The variables associated with MetS; HDL, triglycerides, serum glucose and blood pressure are categorical, and analysed based on the limit value for these variables used in the definition for MetS; NCEP ATP III. Data on furcation, tooth mobility, and radiographic bone loss are not reported due to the low number of positive observations.</p>
                <p id="Par25">For continuous variables at patient level, two-group t-test was used to test statistical differences, while chi-square tests were used for the categorical variables. Continuous variables were analysed using linear regression models reporting beta coefficients with 95% confidence intervals (95% CI). The categorical (dichotomous) outcome variables were analysed using logistic regression models, reporting odds ratios (ORs) with 95% CI. For tooth and site-specific outcomes variables, the regression analyses were performed using cluster robust variance estimates to adjust for multiple measures per individual. Stata version 17 (TX, USA) was used for the statistical analyses. P-values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="Par26">A total of 52 subjects (1456 teeth/8736 sites) meeting study inclusion criteria were examined (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Fourteen were diagnosed as non-MetS (mean age 44.3 years, range 22–73 years) and 38 as MetS (mean age 49.1 years, range 26–66 years).</p>
              <p id="Par27">Characteristics and severity of periodontitis for included subjects are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The non-MetS group included 10 females and 4 males, the MetS group 18 females and 20 males (p = 0.123). Subjects with and without MetS were similar in all characteristics, except elevated serum glucose (p = 0.025) and triglycerides (p = 0.004) mean values.</p>
              <p id="Par28">Total percentage subjects diagnosed with periodontitis was 78.6% in the non-MetS group vs.78.9% in the MetS group (p = 0.20). Five (35.7%) and six (42.9%) subjects in the non-MetS group were classified as stage I/stage II and stage III/stage IV (p = 0.25). In the MetS group the numbers were 16 (42.1%) and 14 (36.8%).</p>
              <p id="Par29">
                <table-wrap id="Tab1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Study sample characteristics on patient level</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left">Variable</th>
                        <th align="left">Non-MetS</th>
                        <th align="left">N</th>
                        <th align="left">MetS</th>
                        <th align="left">N</th>
                        <th align="left">P-value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Age in years</td>
                        <td align="left">44.3 (15.6)*</td>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left">49.1 (11.0)*</td>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.219</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Sex</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.123</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Male</td>
                        <td align="left">4 (28.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">20 (52.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Female</td>
                        <td align="left">10 (71.4%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">18 (47.4%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Ethnicity</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.928</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Norwegian</td>
                        <td align="left">13 (92.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">35 (92.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Other</td>
                        <td align="left">1 (7.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">3 (7.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Smoking</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.753</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Current smoker</td>
                        <td align="left">2 (14.3%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">3 (7.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Former smoker</td>
                        <td align="left">1 (7.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">4 (10.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Never smoker</td>
                        <td align="left">11 (78.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">31 (81.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Snuff</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.748</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Yes</td>
                        <td align="left">2 (14.3%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">3 (7.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Former user</td>
                        <td align="left">1 (7.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">2 (5.3%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> No</td>
                        <td align="left">11 (78.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">33 (86.8%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                        <td align="left">42.4 (4.87)*</td>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left">41.1 (4.02)*</td>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.315</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Brushing teeth ≥ 2 daily</td>
                        <td align="left">8 (57.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left">23 (60.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.825</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Use of interdental cleaning aids (floss, toothpick, ID-brush)</td>
                        <td align="left">10 (71.4%)</td>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left">28 (73.7%)</td>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">HDL, female (mmol/L)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.3 (0.18)*</td>
                        <td align="left">10</td>
                        <td align="left">1.3 (0.40)*</td>
                        <td align="left">18</td>
                        <td align="left">0.980</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">HDL, male (mmol/L)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.2 (0.22)*</td>
                        <td align="left">4</td>
                        <td align="left">1.1 (0.23)*</td>
                        <td align="left">20</td>
                        <td align="left">0.232</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">
                          <p>BP </p>
                          <p>(mm HG)</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">12</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">34</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Systolic</td>
                        <td align="left">123.9 (39.4)*</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">126.6 (47.0)*</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">0.856</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Diastolic</td>
                        <td align="left">78.8 (24.8)*</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">75.4 (29.8)*</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">0.714</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">HbA1c (mmol/mol)</td>
                        <td align="left">34.0 (3.46)*</td>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left">38.8 (10.5)*</td>
                        <td align="left">37</td>
                        <td align="left">0.101</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> S-glucose (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left">5.00 (1.89)*</td>
                        <td align="left">13</td>
                        <td align="left">6.58 (2.26)*</td>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">
                          <bold>0.025</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Triglycerides (mmol/L)</td>
                        <td align="left">1.29 (0.38)*</td>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left">2.27 (1.19)*</td>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">
                          <bold>0.004</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">CRP (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left">3.07 (5.54)*</td>
                        <td align="left">6</td>
                        <td align="left">3.71 (6.31)*</td>
                        <td align="left">25</td>
                        <td align="left">0.740</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Stage of periodontitis</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.200</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> No periodontitis</td>
                        <td align="left">3 (21.4%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">8 (21.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Stage I/Stage II</td>
                        <td align="left">5 (35.7%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">16 (42.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Stage III/Stage IV</td>
                        <td align="left">6 (42.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">14 (36.8%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Extent of periodontitis</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">14</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">38</td>
                        <td align="left">0.252</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Localised</td>
                        <td align="left">6 (54.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">22 (73.3%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> Generalised</td>
                        <td align="left">5 (45.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">8 (26.7%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p><italic>*=Mean (standard deviation)</italic>, non-MetS = non-metabolic syndrome, <italic>MetS = metabolic syndrome, BMI = body mass index, HDL = high density lipoprotein, BP = blood pressure, mm HG = millimetre of mercury, HbA1c = glycated haemoglobin, S-glucose = serum glucose, CRP = C-reactive protein, Smoking: current smoker (yes) former/never smoker (no)</italic></p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p id="Par30">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> presents the distribution of PD, CAL, and BoP. No differences in distribution of PD and CAL categories were observed between subjects with and without MetS (p = 0.94, both). In the non-MetS group, 29.8% of sites showed BoP, whereas the percentage in the MetS group was 23.5 (p = 0.048).</p>
              <p id="Par31">
                <table-wrap id="Tab2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>The distribution of probing depth, clinical attachment level, and bleeding on probing in various categories for the non-metabolic syndrome (non-MetS) and metabolic syndrome (MetS) group at site level</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" colspan="4">Baseline</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left">non-MetS</th>
                        <th align="left">MetS</th>
                        <th align="left">P-value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">PD</td>
                        <td align="left">n = 2352</td>
                        <td align="left">n = 6384</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.942</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">0–3 mm</td>
                        <td align="left">2 060 (87.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left">5 587 (87.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">4–5 mm</td>
                        <td align="left">280 (11.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left">758 (11.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">≥ 6 mm</td>
                        <td align="left">12 (0.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left">39 (0.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">CAL</td>
                        <td align="left">n = 2352</td>
                        <td align="left">n = 6384</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.942</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">0–3 mm</td>
                        <td align="left">1 992 (84.7%)</td>
                        <td align="left">5 397 (84.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">4–5 mm</td>
                        <td align="left">331 (14.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left">917 (14.4%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">≥ 6 mm</td>
                        <td align="left">29 (1.2%)</td>
                        <td align="left">70 (1.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BoP</td>
                        <td align="left">n = 1492</td>
                        <td align="left">n = 4015</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">
                          <bold>0.048</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">No</td>
                        <td align="left">1 049 (70.2%)</td>
                        <td align="left">3 073 (76.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Yes</td>
                        <td align="left">445 (29.8%)</td>
                        <td align="left">942 (23.5%)</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>PD = probing depth, CAL = clinical attachment level, BoP = bleeding on probing</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p id="Par32">The outcomes of unadjusted and adjusted logistic regression analyses for interdental PD (on site level), CAL (on site level), and stage III/stage IV periodontitis (on patient level) are shown in Tables <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, and <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. The unadjusted analyses showed that age had a significant impact on stage III/stage IV periodontitis (p = 0.008; Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p>
              <p id="Par33">
                <table-wrap id="Tab3">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Odds ratio (OR) for having interdental probing depth (PD) ≥ 4 mm, at site level, when adjusted for variables associated with obesity and metabolic syndrome (MetS)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Unadjusted</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Adjusted for obesity related variables</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Adjusted for obesity related variables and MetS</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Smoking vs. never smoking</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.07 (0.31–3.70)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.917</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.05 (0.32–2.41)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.941</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.54 (0.36–6.57)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.556</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Age</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.02 (1.00-1.05)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.113</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.02 (1.00-1-04)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.117</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.02 (0.99–1.04)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.162</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Females vs. males</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.07 (0.57–2.02)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.837</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.10 (0.56–2.14)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.788</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.05 (0.49–2.24)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.901</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BMI</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.97 (0.89–1.06)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.538</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.98 (0.90–1.07)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.724</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.99 (0.91–1.07)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.763</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">CRP</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.01 (0.92–1.10)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.907</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.00 (0.91–1.09)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.997</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.00 (0.92–1.10)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.951</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">HDL</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.77 (0.41–1.43)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.405</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.05 (0.52–2.14)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.890</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Triglycerides</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.10 (0.58–2.08)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.770</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.88 (0.42–1.88)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.749</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> S-glucose</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.23 (0.66–2.29)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.522</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.18 (0.65–2.14)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.591</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BP</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.68 (0.78–3.63)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.187</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.87 (0.78–4.46)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.161</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>BMI = body mass index, CRP = C-reactive protein, HDL = high density lipoprotein, S-glucose = serum glucose, BP = blood pressure</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p id="Par36">
                <table-wrap id="Tab4">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Odds ratio (OR) for clinical attachment level (CAL) ≥ 4 mm at site level when adjusted for variables associated with obesity and metabolic syndrome (MetS)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Unadjusted</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Adjusted for obesity related variables</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Adjusted for obesity related variables and MetS</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Smoking vs. never smoking</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.03 (0.29–3.65)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.963</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.06 (0.32–3.52)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.923</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.48 (0.36–6.19)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.588</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Age</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.02 (1.00-1.05)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.087</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.02 (1.00-1.04)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.088</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.02 (0.99–1.04)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.124</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Females vs. males</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.97 (0.53–1.77)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.913</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.98 (0.52–1.87)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.960</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.93 (0.46–1.91)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.852</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BMI</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.98 (0.90–1.06)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.549</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.99 (0.91–1.07)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.800</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.99 (0.92–1.07)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.833</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">CRP</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.00 (0.92–1.09)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.935</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.00 (0.92–1.08)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.969</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.00 (0.92–1.09)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.976</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">HDL</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.70 (0.38–1.30)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.262</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.91 (0.46–1.81)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.793</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Triglycerides</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.12 (0.61–2.05)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.716</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.89 (0.44–1.83)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.759</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> S-glucose</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.17 (0.64–2.14)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.601</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.14 (0.65–2.02)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.646</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BP</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.65 (0.78–3.46)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.189</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.66 (0.73–3.77)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.231</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>BMI = body mass index, CRP = C-reactive protein, HDL = high density lipoprotein, S-glucose = serum glucose, BP = blood pressure</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p id="Par35">When adjusted for obesity related variables and MetS, the effect of age on stage III/stage IV periodontitis, persisted to be significant (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; p = 0.006 and p = 0.002, respectively). The effect of age on PD and CAL continued to be non-significant (Tables <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p>
              <p id="Par38">
                <table-wrap id="Tab5">
                  <label>Table 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Odds ratio (OR) for having stage III/stage IV periodontitis, at patient level, when adjusted for variables associated with obesity and metabolic syndrome (MetS)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Unadjusted</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Adjusted for obesity related variables</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2">Adjusted for obesity related variables and MetS</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"/>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                        <th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="left">p</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Smoking vs. never smoking</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.07 (0.16–7.19)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.941</td>
                        <td align="left">0.30 (0.00-36.38)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.626</td>
                        <td align="left">0.34 (0.00-63.78)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.687</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Age</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.09 (1.02–1.17)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">
                          <bold>0.008</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left">1.15 (1.04–1.26)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">
                          <bold>0.006</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left">1.15 (1.05–1.26)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">
                          <bold>0.002</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Females vs. males</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.22 (0.39–3.79)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.728</td>
                        <td align="left">4.64 (0.68–31.67)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.117</td>
                        <td align="left">7.34 (0.77-70.00)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.083</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BMI</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.99 (0.87–1.13)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.889</td>
                        <td align="left">1.08 (0.87–1.34)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.489</td>
                        <td align="left">1.04 (0.82–1.32)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.734</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">CRP</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.99 (0.87–1.13)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.889</td>
                        <td align="left">1.04 (0.84–1.29)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.691</td>
                        <td align="left">1.04 (0.85–1.29)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.690</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">HDL</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.01 (0.90–1.14)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.812</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">5.75 (0.36–92.55)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.218</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Triglycerides</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.56 (0.16–1.94)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.357</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">1.17 (0.18–7.78)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.868</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> S-glucose</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">1.86 (0.58–5.94)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.296</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">0.68 (0.12–3.95)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.672</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">BP</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.84 (0.27–2.61)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.758</td>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left"/>
                        <td align="left">9.50 (0.27-339.51)</td>
                        <td char="." align="char">0.217</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>BMI = body mass index, CRP = C-reactive protein, HDL = high density lipoprotein, S-glucose = serum glucose, BP = blood pressure</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Summary and comparison with other studies</title>
                <p id="Par40">In a sample of obese subjects with a mean BMI of 41.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, the occurrence of periodontitis was not found to be associated with MetS. The data analyses revealed a higher percentage cases with severe periodontitis in the non-MetS group (stage III/stage IV: 42.9%) compared with the MetS group (stage III/stage IV: 36.8%). Similar distributions of PD and CAL were observed in the two groups. Interestingly, a significantly higher percentage BoP was observed in the non-MetS compared with the MetS group. For staging of periodontitis, the effect of age appears to be significant both for obesity related variables and MetS.</p>
                <p id="Par41">We hypothesized that MetS would promote a more severe periodontal conditions in obese subjects. However, the prevalence of periodontitis was similar (78.6% in non-MetS vs. 78.9% in MetS), the non-MetS group exhibiting a slightly higher prevalence severe periodontitis (42.9% in non-MetS vs. 36.8% in MetS). Moreover, BoP was more prevalent in the non-MetS group (29.8% in non-MetS vs. 23.5% in MetS; P = 0.048). The questionnaire, however, exploring personal oral hygiene routines disclosed comparable findings (73.7% in the MetS vs. 71.4% in the non-MetS group).</p>
                <p id="Par42">A study on the prevalence and severity of periodontitis in a Tromsø, Norway, normal-weight population (mean age 47.3 years, range 20–79 years), reported a prevalence of 49.5% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Despite similar study mean age and rather high prevalence of periodontitis possibly caused by less frequent use of dental services in the northern regions of Norway, the present findings both in the non-MetS and the MetS group appeared to be substantially higher (&gt; 78%). The production and systemic distribution of the pro-inflammatory cytokines in obese subjects vary depending on the subtype of adipose tissue, with visceral adipose tissue being the subtype most often associated with development of comorbidities and systemic adverse effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Low-grade systemic inflammation is most likely the causal association between obesity and periodontitis and thus, partly explaining the high prevalence of periodontitis in the present study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par43">A study from northern Finland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] investigated the association between periodontal pockets and obesity defined by BMI and WC. The participants were categorised at the age of 31 and 46 years, while periodontal examination was undertaken at the age of 46. This design allowed the authors to investigate the long-term effects of obesity. Both parameters showed an association between periodontitis and long-term obesity, but periodontitis was more strongly associated with WC than with BMI. The article suggests that BMI is an inferior parameter for obesity compared with WC because it does not consider the distribution of fat throughout the body. WC captures central obesity and therefore might be a more appropriate indicator for the low-grade systemic inflammatory effects of visceral body fat. Overall, this indicates that both obesity and central obesity may exert harmful effects on periodontal health beyond what is observed in cross-sectional studies.</p>
                <p id="Par44">The association between prevalence of periodontitis and MetS was investigated in Vietnamese subjects allocated to an MetS (mean age 57.8/mean BMI 28.3 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) or a non-MetS (mean age 58.2/mean BMI 27.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Subjects with more severe periodontitis presented with a higher risk of MetS. A significantly higher percentage severe periodontitis was thus observed in the MetS vs. that in the non-MetS group (37.9% vs. 19.4%). The present study reported high prevalence of severe periodontitis in both groups (42.1% vs. 35.7%), and with non-significant intergroup difference. With a lower mean age (49.1 years in the Mets vs. 44.3 years in the non-Mets) and despite lifestyle differences between western culture Norway and south-eastern culture Vietnam making the comparison difficult, the severity of periodontitis in the present study might be expected to be at the same level or less than in the Vietnamese study.</p>
                <p id="Par45">A Brazilian case-control study also reported a risk association between MetS and periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The prevalence of periodontitis was 54.6% in the MetS group and 35.6% in the control group. Study subjects were categorized based on BMI ≤ 25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and &gt; 25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. However, no information on mean group BMI was available. The overall prevalence of periodontitis in our study groups approximated 79%. This may indicate that exceeding a certain level of overweight/obesity the association between MetS and periodontitis becomes less significant as the dominating impact of obesity relates variables undermines the detrimental effect of other systemic factors.</p>
                <p id="Par46">The regression analysis showed a tendency toward significant impact of gender on the development of stage III/stage IV periodontitis when adjusting for MetS variables (p = 0.083). Age had a significant effect on the prevalence of stage III/stage IV periodontitis. The effect of age might be expected as periodontitis is an irreversible, cumulative disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. As the non-MetS group is rather heterogeneous, including subjects with high BMI who also have other elements of MetS comorbidities, the lack of observed deterioration from the MetS was not unexpected. Higher mean values for triglyceride and serum glucose were measured for the MetS group. For the other criteria defining MetS, the non-MetS group showed relatively high values as well, yet, not meeting the requirements for a MetS diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition, some subjects in the MetS group were medicated for health-related problems such as high blood pressure, and thereby distorting general health parameters. In other words, the combination of a non-MetS group with borderline requirements for MetS and a MetS group receiving medical treatment for comorbidities, may lead to non-significant risk indicator differences between the groups. In addition, a more recent definition of MetS using lower cut-off values for WC and fasting glucose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] may result in a higher MetS prevalence possibly attenuating the association between periodontitis and MetS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec13">
                <title>Methodological challenges and strengths</title>
                <p id="Par47">The unbalanced distribution of subjects within the two groups, with a lower number of subjects included in the non-MetS group, might undermine the statistical power of the study. In the present study, staging and grading were primarily based on clinical measures such as CAL, PD, furcation involvement, and bitewing radiographs. Registration of plaque would give a more nuanced understanding of all clinical parameters and particularly BoP. The rather high mean BMI of our study sample may undermine the likelihood of detecting intergroup differences. Only about 15% of the obese population will not develop obesity related co-morbidities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In addition, a 5-month lifestyle intervention course may affect the interpretation of the study outcomes. The use of calcium channel blockers to treat hypertension, angina pectoris, or cardiac arrhythmias, is a widely known risk factor for development of drug induced gingival overgrowth, which can affect the gingival conditions and influence the development/progression of periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Due to the low number of study subjects, the estimates from the adjusted regression analyses should be interpretated cautiously. The interpretation of study outcomes without a satisfactory matched control group of normal-weight subjects needs to be made with caution. Future studies evaluating the potential association between obesity and periodontitis and the influence of Mets require inclusion of a normal-weight control group and a non-MetS group with comparable levels of obesity and absence of MetS comorbidities.</p>
                <p id="Par48">The strength of this study is the full-mouth periodontal evaluation, and the periodontal examination performed by only one examiner with high ICC values, improving the disease detection accuracy. The sociodemographic, oral hygiene habits, laboratory and clinical data were rather comprehensive and relevant.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec14" sec-type="conclusion">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="Par49">In the current sample of obese subjects, periodontitis occurred independently of MetS. The data analyses showed that a higher percentage cases with severe periodontitis was found in the non-MetS group (stage III/stage IV: 43%) compared with the MetS group (stage III/stage IV: 37%). A significantly higher percentage of BoP was detected in the non-MetS group. For stage III/stage IV periodontitis, the effect of age appears to be significant both for obesity related variables and MetS. Apparently, when a certain BMI level is reached the suggested association between MetS and periodontitis seems to be inferior due to the dominating impact of obesity related variables possibly undermining the significance of other systemic factors.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Drs. Nilsen and Thorsnes are equally contributing authors.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>This study was funded by a grant from Meltzer. Sincere thanks are expressed to Professor Ulf M.E. Wikesjö for reviewing the manuscript.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>All authors made substantial contributions to conception and design of the study. AT, AN and PM collected the data and SAL analyzed the data. AT, AN, KNL, SAL, PM, DFB, and KKR have been involved in data interpretation, drafting the manuscript, and revising it critically and have given final approval of publishing.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>The study was funded by the authors and their institutions.</p>
              <p>Open access funding provided by University of Bergen.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data Availability</title>
              <p>The datasets used and analysed during the current study and coding are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar3">
                <title>Ethics approval, consent to participate, and guidelines</title>
                <p id="Par51">The study protocol and informed consent, following the Helsinki Declaration of 1975, version 2008, have been approved by the Norwegian Regional Ethics Committee (Reference 152810–22/02/2021/REK Vest). The study subjects were informed of the nature, scope, and consequences of participating in the study before signing the informed consent. All methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar4">
                <title>Consent to publish</title>
                <p id="Par52">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par50">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>BMI</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par54">Body mass index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>MetS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par55">Metabolic syndrome</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HUH</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par56">Haukeland University Hospital</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>PD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par57">Probing depth</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>BoP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par58">Bleeding on probing</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CAL</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par59">Clinical attachment level</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HDL</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par60">High-density lipoprotein</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>TG</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par61">High triglyceride</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CRP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par62">C-reactive protein</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ICC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par63">Intraclass correlation coefficients</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>WC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par64">Waist circumstance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>BP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par65">Blood pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Flodgren G, Gonçalves-Bradley DC, Summerbell CD. Interventions to change the behaviour of health professionals and the organisation of care to promote weight reduction in children and adults with overweight or obesity. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2017 (11): CD000984. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD000984.pub3.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Obesity and overweight: World Health Organization; 2021 [updated 2021 Jun 9 cited 2023 Jun 4]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/en/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity-and-overweight">https://www.who.int/en/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity-and-overweight</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vairavamurthy</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheskin</surname>
                      <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kraitchman</surname>
                      <given-names>DL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arepally</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weiss</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Current and cutting-edge interventions for the treatment of obese patients</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Radiol</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>93</volume>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejrad.2017.05.019</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28668407?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28668407</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vinciguerra</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baratta</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farina</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tita</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Padova</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vigneri</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Very severely obese patients have a high prevalence of type 2 diabetes mellitus and cardiovascular disease</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Diabetol</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>443</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00592-013-0460-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23447004?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23447004</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marsicano</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sales-Peres</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ceneviva</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sales-Peres</surname>
                      <given-names>SHdC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of oral health status and salivary flow rate in obese patients after bariatric surgery</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Dent</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0039-1698950</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22509123?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22509123</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alberti KG, Eckel RH, Grundy SM, Zimmet PZ, Cleeman JI, Donato KA et al. Harmonizing the metabolic syndrome: a joint interim statement of the International Diabetes Federation Task Force on Epidemiology and Prevention; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; American Heart Association; World Heart Federation; International Atherosclerosis Society; and International Association for the Study of Obesity. Circulation. 2009;120(16):1640-5.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Norsk Elektronisk Legehåndbok. Metabolsk syndrom: Norsk Helseinformatikk; 2020 [updated 2023 Feb 1; cited 2021 Oct 11]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nhi.no/kosthold/overvektfedme/metabolsk-syndrom/?page=all">https://nhi.no/kosthold/overvektfedme/metabolsk-syndrom/?page=all</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cameron</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaw</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zimmet</surname>
                      <given-names>PZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The metabolic syndrome: prevalence in worldwide populations</article-title>
                  <source>Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
                  <lpage>75</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecl.2004.03.005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15158523?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15158523</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grundy</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cleeman</surname>
                      <given-names>JI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daniels</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donato</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eckel</surname>
                      <given-names>RH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franklin</surname>
                      <given-names>BA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diagnosis and management of the metabolic syndrome: an American Heart Association/National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute scientific statement</article-title>
                  <source>Curr Opin Cardiol</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.hco.0000200416.65370.a0</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16355022?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16355022</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meyle</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chapple</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Molecular aspects of the pathogenesis of periodontitis</article-title>
                  <source>Periodontol 2000</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <lpage>17</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/prd.12104</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26252398?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26252398</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frencken</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stenhouse</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Green</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laverty</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dietrich</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global epidemiology of dental caries and severe periodontitis - a comprehensive review</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 18</issue>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <lpage>s105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12677</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brooks</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blaha</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blumenthal</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Relation of C-Reactive protein to Abdominal Adiposity</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Cardiol</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>106</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <lpage>61</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2010.02.017</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20609648?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20609648</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marques-Vidal</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bochud</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bastardot</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lüscher</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferrero</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gaspoz</surname>
                      <given-names>J-M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between inflammatory and obesity markers in a Swiss Population-Based sample (CoLaus Study)</article-title>
                  <source>Obes Facts</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>734</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000345045</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23108472?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23108472</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nascimento</surname>
                      <given-names>GG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leite</surname>
                      <given-names>FR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Do</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peres</surname>
                      <given-names>KG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Correa</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Demarco</surname>
                      <given-names>FF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is weight gain associated with the incidence of periodontitis? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>495</fpage>
                  <lpage>505</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12417</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25952821?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25952821</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jepsen</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suvan</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deschner</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Genco</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The association of periodontal diseases with metabolic syndrome and obesity</article-title>
                  <source>Periodontol 2000</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/prd.12326</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32385882?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32385882</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kang</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pavitt</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between central obesity and tooth loss in the non-obese people: results from the continuous National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) 1999–2012</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>430</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13091</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30791123?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30791123</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vallim</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gaio</surname>
                      <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oppermann</surname>
                      <given-names>RV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rösing</surname>
                      <given-names>CK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Albandar</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Susin</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Obesity as a risk factor for tooth loss over 5 years: a population-based cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <lpage>23</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13378</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33010056?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33010056</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Makkar</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wadhawan</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dagdag</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Merchant</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Postolache</surname>
                      <given-names>TT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Periodontal, metabolic, and cardiovascular disease: exploring the role of inflammation and mental health</article-title>
                  <source>Pteridines</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <lpage>63</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/pteridines-2018-0013</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30705520?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30705520</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yucel-Lindberg</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Båge</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inflammatory mediators in the pathogenesis of periodontitis</article-title>
                  <source>Expert Rev Mol Med</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>e7</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/erm.2013.8</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23915822?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23915822</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bandiwadekar</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shanbhag</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Madhuniranjanswamy</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khanagar</surname>
                      <given-names>SB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naik</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siddeeqh</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association of Periodontitis with metabolic syndrome: a case-control study</article-title>
                  <source>J Int Soc Prev Community Dent</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>458</fpage>
                  <lpage>65</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jispcd.JISPCD_91_20</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33042888?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33042888</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bullon</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morillo</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramirez-Tortosa</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quiles</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Newman</surname>
                      <given-names>HN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Battino</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Metabolic syndrome and periodontitis: is oxidative stress a common link?</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>88</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>503</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034509337479</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19587154?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19587154</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bunæs</surname>
                      <given-names>DF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lie</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Enersen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aastrøm</surname>
                      <given-names>AN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mustafa</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leknes</surname>
                      <given-names>KN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Site-specific treatment outcome in smokers following non‐surgical and surgical periodontal therapy</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>933</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12462</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26407817?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26407817</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tomar</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asma</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Smoking-attributable periodontitis in the United States: findings from NHANES III. National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>71</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>743</fpage>
                  <lpage>51</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2000.71.5.743</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 10872955?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872955</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mühlemann</surname>
                      <given-names>HR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Son</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gingival sulcus bleeding–a leading symptom in initial gingivitis</article-title>
                  <source>Helv Odontol Acta</source>
                  <year>1971</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <lpage>13</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 5315729?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5315729</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>von Elm</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Altman</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egger</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pocock</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gøtzsche</surname>
                      <given-names>PC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vandenbroucke</surname>
                      <given-names>JP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The strengthening the reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) Statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Surg</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1495</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijsu.2014.07.013</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25046131</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miller</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Textbook of Periodontia (oral medicine)</source>
                  <year>1943</year>
                  <edition>2</edition>
                  <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>The Blakiston Co</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tonetti</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Greenwell</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kornman</surname>
                      <given-names>KS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Staging and grading of periodontitis: Framework and proposal of a new classification and case definition</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <issue>S20</issue>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <lpage>S61</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12945</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holde</surname>
                      <given-names>GE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oscarson</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trovik</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tillberg</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jönsson</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Periodontitis Prevalence and Severity in adults: a cross-sectional study in norwegian Circumpolar Communities</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>88</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1012</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2017.170164</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28671509?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28671509</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ellulu</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Patimah</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khaza’ai</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rahmat</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abed</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Obesity and inflammation: the linking mechanism and the complications</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Med Sci</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>851</fpage>
                  <lpage>63</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/aoms.2016.58928</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28721154?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28721154</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fontana</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eagon</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trujillo</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scherer</surname>
                      <given-names>PE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klein</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Visceral Fat Adipokine Secretion is Associated with systemic inflammation in obese humans</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>1010</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db06-1656</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17287468?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287468</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>He</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The causal effect of life course adiposity on periodontitis: a mendelian randomization study</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>94</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <lpage>62</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/JPER.21-0632</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 37163583?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37163583</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dong</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gong</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chu</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mendelian randomization highlights the causal association of obesity with periodontal diseases</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>662</fpage>
                  <lpage>71</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13640</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 35569024?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35569024</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tegelberg</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saxlin</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tervonen</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Knuuttila</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jokelainen</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Auvinen</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association of long-term obesity and weight gain with periodontal pocketing: results of the Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1966 study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1344</fpage>
                  <lpage>55</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13524</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34288019?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34288019</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pham</surname>
                      <given-names>TAV</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The association between periodontal disease severity and metabolic syndrome in vietnamese patients</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Dent Hyg</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>484</fpage>
                  <lpage>91</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/idh.12350</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29900658?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29900658</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campos</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>FO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cota</surname>
                      <given-names>LOM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between periodontitis and metabolic syndrome: a case-control study</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>784</fpage>
                  <lpage>91</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/JPER.19-0298</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31691971?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31691971</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eke</surname>
                      <given-names>PI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dye</surname>
                      <given-names>BA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thornton-Evans</surname>
                      <given-names>GO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Genco</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence of periodontitis in adults in the United States: 2009 and 2010</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>914</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034512457373</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22935673?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22935673</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gasner NS, Schure RS. Periodontal Disease. StatPearls. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing, Copyright © 2021. StatPearls Publishing LLC.; 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kotin</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walther</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wenzel</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zyriax</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borof</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schnabel</surname>
                      <given-names>RB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between periodontitis and metabolic syndrome in the Hamburg City Health Study</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>93</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>1150</fpage>
                  <lpage>60</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/JPER.21-0464</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34967009?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34967009</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blüher</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Adipose tissue dysfunction in obesity</article-title>
                  <source>Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <lpage>50</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1192044</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19358089?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19358089</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fardal</surname>
                      <given-names>Ø</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lygre</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Management of periodontal disease in patients using calcium channel blockers - gingival overgrowth, prescribed medications, treatment responses and added treatment costs</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>640</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12426</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26076712?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26076712</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lygre</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Legemiddelindusert gingival overvekst (LIGO)</article-title>
                  <source>Nor Tannlegeforen Tid</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>124</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>370</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tungare S, Paranjpe AG. Drug Induced Gingival Overgrowth. StatPearls. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing, Copyright © 2021. StatPearls Publishing LLC.; 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
