<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:50:14Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4246388" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4246388</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-12-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jaos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de São
Paulo</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4246388</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4246388</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4246388</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21085813</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21085813</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-77572010000500018</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Diclofenac in hyaluronic acid gel: an alternative treatment for actinic
cheilitis</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>LIMA</surname>
                    <given-names>Giana da Silveira</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>da SILVA</surname>
                    <given-names>Gabriela Ferrari</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>GOMES</surname>
                    <given-names>Ana Paula Neutzling</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de ARAÚJO</surname>
                    <given-names>Lenita Maria Aver</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>SALUM</surname>
                    <given-names>Fernanda Gonçalves</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> DDS, MSc, PhD student, Department of Operative Dentistry, Federal
University of Pelotas, Pelotas, RS, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> DDS Graduate student, Department of Operative Dentistry, Federal
University of Pelotas, Pelotas, RS, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> DDS, MSc, PhD in Oral Pathology, Associate Professor, Department of
Semiology and Clinic, Center for Diagnosis of Oral Diseases, Federal University of
Pelotas, Pelotas, RS, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> DDS, PhD in Oral Medicine, Oral Medicine and Oral Maxillofacial Cancer
Prevention Unit, São Lucas Hospital, Pontifical Catholic University of Rio Grande
do Sul, Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Fernanda Gonçalves Salum -
Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio Grande do Sul - PUCRS -
Hospital São Lucas - Av. Ipiranga, 6690 - Sala 231 - 2º andar -
90610-000 - Porto Alegre - RS - Brazil - Phone/Fax: +55 51 3320-3254 - e-mail:
<email>fesalum@terra.com.br</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>Sep-Oct</season>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Sep-Oct</season>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>18</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <fpage>533</fpage>
              <lpage>537</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>05</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>07</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>Actinic cheilitis (AC) is a precancerous lesion of the lip vermillion caused by
prolonged exposure to ultraviolet light. The aim of this study was to evaluate the
effect of 3% diclofenac in 2.5% hyaluronic acid gel in the treatment of AC.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>Thirty-four patients with chronic AC were treated twice a day with topical
diclofenac during a period of 30 to 180 days. The individuals were followed up
every 15 days by means of clinical examination and digital photographic
documentation.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Of the 27 patients that completed the study, 12 (44%) showed complete remission of
the whitish plaques and exfoliative areas, and 15 (56%) had partial remission of
the clinical picture of cheilitis. The latter group was submitted to excision of
the leukoplakic areas which diagnosis varied from mild to moderate epithelial
dysplasia.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>The results suggest a promising role for diclofenac in hyaluronic acid gel in the
treatment of AC. This treatment has the advantages of not being invasive and
showing few side effects.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Diclofenac</kwd>
                <kwd>Hyaluronic acid</kwd>
                <kwd>Cheilitis</kwd>
                <kwd>Actinic rays</kwd>
                <kwd>Oral leukoplakia</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Actinic cheilitis (AC), also called actinic cheilosis or solar cheilitis, is a
potentially malignant condition of the lip vermillion caused by long-time exposure to
ultraviolet light. This lesion affects mostly the lower lip and is more frequent in
individuals with fair skin, males and those who are regularly in the sun such as farm
workers and fishermen<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. In the south
region of Brazil, due to the tropical climate and the European descent of large part of
the population, this lesion assumes great importance.</p>
              <p>There are two clinical forms of AC: acute and chronic. The acute form is more common in
young individuals and occurs after excessive exposure to the ultraviolet light, while
the chronic form is a cumulative and irreversible alteration. In chronic AC, the lip
appears parched and atrophic, with dyschromic areas, white or gray plaques and recurrent
erosions<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. The lesion is usually asymptomatic, but can in some
cases be accompanied by a burning sensation, numbness and pain.</p>
              <p> The main objectives of treatment of chronic AC are to prevent the development of
squamous cell carcinoma, improve the aesthetic picture and diminish the inconvenience
caused by lip erosions, crusts and roughness. There are various therapeutic modalities
with the aim of removing the altered epithelium of these lesions such as the topical
application of 5-fluorouracil, trichloroacetic acid, imiquimod and retinoids. Other
treatments include surgical excision with cold scalpel (vermillionectomy), vaporization
with CO<sub>2</sub> or Er:YAG laser, cryosurgery, electrodissection and photodynamic
therapy with aminolevulinic acid<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. These treatments are
very destructive and frequently cause considerable discomfort to the patients, which has
stimulated the development of effective and economically viable alternatives for the
treatment of AC. Diclofenac in hyaluronic acid gel has been employed in the topical
treatment of actinic keratoses with satisfactory results and well-tolerated side effects
by the majority of the patients<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. The present study was conducted with the aim of evaluating by means
of a clinical follow-up the effect of 3% diclofenac in 2.5% hyaluronic acid gel in the
treatment chronic actinic cheilitis.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <p>This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the Dental School of the
Federal University of Pelotas, Brazil. Thirty-four patients who had been diagnosed with
chronic actinic cheilitis, seen at the Center for Diagnosis of Oral Diseases of the
Federal University of Pelotas, Brazil, without noteworthy systemic alterations, were
enrolled for this study. The patients exhibited on physical examination areas of
leukoplakia (whitish plaques), spotting and/or exfoliation of the lip vermillion. The
inclusion criteria were: presence of white plaques, dyschromic and or exfoliative areas
in the lower lip. Patients with erosion, ulcerated areas and plaques with irregular
surface were not included in the study (exclusion criteria). The objectives of the study
were explained to the individuals, and afterwards, they signed an informed consent form.
The patients were then submitted to anamnesis and physical oral examination. Digital
photographic documentation was taken for each case to record the extent of labial
alterations. These alterations were classified as: Grade I: presence of dyschromic
areas; Grade II: presence of exfoliative areas; Grade III: presence of whitish
plaque(s); and Grade IV: combination of two or more of these alterations.</p>
              <p>The treatment protocol consisted of the topical application of 3% diclofenac in 2.5%
hyaluronic acid gel on the lip vermillion, twice a day (morning and night), after oral
hygiene. The patients were instructed to not eat or drink for one hour after the
application and to use lip sunscreen with SPF 15 during all day long. The individuals
were followed up every 15 days, and the period of treatment was determined by the
response and necessity of each case, ranging from 30 to 180 days.</p>
              <p>An image record was taken at the initial visit and each follow-up visit to evaluate the
results. The evaluation was performed by two calibrated examiners on the basis of
information of the patient's chart, physical examination and observation of the
photographic documentation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Twenty-seven patients completed the treatment. All the subjects were Caucasian, with a
predominance of fair skin, and most of them practiced professional activities involving
ultraviolet light exposure. The lesion was more common among men, with a gender ratio of
8:1 and mean age of 58 (SD±12) years old. The patients were asymptomatic,
although seven individuals complained about aesthetic discomfort.</p>
              <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref> presents the result obtained in each
case, the grade of actinic cheilitis of the patients treated and the duration of the
therapy. Approximately 78% of the patients exhibited chronic AC classified as grade IV,
15% grade III and 7% grade II. In 48% of the cases, all of the extent of the lower lip
appeared affected. In the other cases, the areas affected varied in extension and
continuity. The presence of whitish plaques was evident in 25 patients, while 23 showed
exfoliative areas and 24 spotting of the lip.</p>
              <table-wrap id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Gender, age and grade of actinic cheilitis of the 27 patients who completed the
therapy, as well as, period and results obtained with the topical application of
diclofenac</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr align="center" style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">TREATMENT</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#dcdcde">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CASE</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GENDER</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGE</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRADE</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Period (day)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>TOTAL</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>REMISSION</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>PARTIAL</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>REMISSION</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Improvement of the lesions was observed in all the patients, with diminution of the
thickness of the leukoplakic areas, disappearance of scaling areas and greater
hydration, besides more uniform coloration. Of the 27 patients who completed the study,
12 (44%) showed total remission of the plaque and exfoliative areas present at the start
of treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2B</xref>). However, dyschromic regions continued to be present. Fifteen
patients (56%) exhibited significant improvement of AC but without complete resolution
of the condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3B</xref>), with the persistence of whitish plaques, which were later
excised. The diagnosis of these biopsied lesions varied from mild to moderate epithelial
dysplasia.</p>
              <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Actinic cheilitis grade II, lower lip showed exfoliative areas (a), which
exhibited total remission (b) after 60 days of topical application of
diclofenac</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jaos-18-05-0533-g01"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Actinic cheilitis grade IV with leukoplakic and spotting areas (a). Lesion showed
total remission of the leukoplakic area, however, spotting areas continued to be
present (b)</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jaos-18-05-0533-g02"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Actinic cheilitis grade IV, before (a) and after (b) 180 days of diclofenac
topical application. Lip showed partial remission of cheilitis, with decrease of
the thickness of the leukoplakic areas. The whitish plaque (arrow) was later
excised</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jaos-18-05-0533-g03"/>
              </fig>
              <p>The drug utilized was well tolerated by the patients, but in two cases, treatment was
discontinued due to the development of an allergic picture characterized by edema and
intense erythema, associated with a burning sensation at the site of drug application.
Five patients discontinued treatment for personal reasons unrelated to the study. All
the individuals who concluded the study remained on follow-up for at least 1 year and
routinely used lip sunscreen.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Actinic cheilitis is a lesion of the lip vermillion, analogous to actinic keratoses,
which has been treated by surgical procedures and topical drugs, some with a cytotoxic
effect and the potential to cause tissue destruction<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. The topical action of diclofenac in a hyaluronic acid
vehicle has been investigated for the treatment of actinic keratoses, showing promising
results and less intense adverse effects in comparison with other drugs such as
5-fluorouracil<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. In the present
study, the action of diclofenac was investigated in the treatment of chronic actinic
cheilitis, which showed leukoplakic, dyschromic and exfoliative areas. Complete or
partial remission of the clinical picture of the lesions was obtained in all the cases,
a finding that corroborates with the studies of Ulrich, et al.<sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> (2007) and Nelson, et al.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> (2007), who also utilized diclofenac in the treatment of
AC, in samples of six and 19 individuals, respectively. Ulrich, et al.<sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> (2007) utilized this drug for 6 weeks
and Nelson, et al.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> (2007) for 90
days.</p>
              <p>In the present study, the period of treatment was based on the clinical response of each
case, where the maximum period was established as 180 days. The complete resolution of
the clinical presentation determined the suspension of the therapy and was obtained in
as little as 30 days of treatment. The variation in the speed of response to diclofenac
was also observed in the topical treatment of solar keratoses<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> and is
associated mainly with inherent factors of individuals. Additionally, the response to
treatment depends on the disposition and motivation of the patients to achieve a
positive outcome, as well as the amount of medication used in each application. In the
present study, the amount of substance applied varied based on the interpretation by the
individuals of the instructions supplied by the investigator.</p>
              <p>Diclofenac is a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent (NSAID) whose mechanism of action
is not completely understood. Its possible antineoplasic effect is being investigated,
because it induces apoptosis by inhibiting cyclooxygenases (COX-1 and COX-2), which are
involved in the metabolism of arachidonic acid and are superexpressed in various
epithelial tumors<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. The hypothesis
proposed is that NSAIDs, by inhibiting the metabolism of arachidonic acid, impede the
potent tumorigenic effects of its metabolites. Such effects include the conversion of
pro-oncogenes to oncogenes, inhibition of immunologic vigilance, inhibition of
apoptosis, stimulation of angiogenesis and increase in invasiveness of tumor
cells<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Therefore, diclofenac
can be effective in the treatment as well as the prevention of epithelial lesions
related to actinic radiation. </p>
              <p>Hyaluronic acid, the vehicle in which diclofenac is delivered, has been widely utilized
in the cosmetics industry because of its moisturizing properties. This polysaccharide
was chosen primarily with the aim of allowing the accumulation of diclofenac in the
epidermis, prolonging its half-life at the site of action<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. In addition to
these effects, Wolf, et al.<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> (2001)
suggested that the hyaluronic acid gel may have intrinsic activity, increasing the
efficacy of the treatment.</p>
              <p>The lip vermilion is an anatomic site in which treatment can be difficult due to the
risk of permanent scars and susceptibility to irritation<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. However, the application of diclofenac in hyaluronic
acid gel did not cause the development of erosive or ulcerated areas on the lips. Of the
29 patients who effectively underwent treatment, only two showed adverse effects that
determined their exclusion from the study. These local reactions including pruritis,
erythema and/or burning sensation were observed in some cases, and were tolerated by the
patients. These adverse reactions have also been described by other authors who studied
the use of diclofenac for the treatment of keratoses as well as actinic
cheilitis<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The risk of relapse after the treatment instituted is unknown. However, the patients in
this study were followed-up for more than a year and those who had a complete remission
of the clinical picture of cheilitis showed no signs of recurrence. The patients who had
a partial remission were submitted to excisional biopsy of the whitish plaques and
displayed no signs of progression of the lesion. Meanwhile, the majority of the patients
studied continue to be exposed to ultraviolet light, since they maintained their outdoor
occupational activities. The follow-up of these individuals and their awareness with
respect to precautions and preventive measures with the use of sunscreen and hats are
essential.</p>
              <p>The results of the present study are in accordance with the literature regarding the
epidemiologic profile and clinical characteristics of actinic cheilitis<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. For didactic purposes, in this study,
cheilitis were classified according to severity as grade I through grade IV. Twenty-one
out the 27 patients who were treated showed chronic AC grade IV. However, due to the
small number of patients with cheilitis grade II and III, it was not possible to carry
out statistical comparisons of the results obtained for the different lesion grades.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>As with the treatment of actinic keratoses, 3% diclofenac in 2.5% hyaluronic acid gel
showed promising results and good tolerability in the treatment of AC, indicating a
treatment modality adequate for this precursor lesion. In addition, this treatment has
the advantages of not being invasive, having low cost and showing few side effects and
good aesthetic results. There is a need for randomized studies to investigate the action
of this drug; however, as AC is a precancerous lesion, the comparison of the action of
diclofenac in placebo-controlled studies is impracticable. All the other available
treatment modalities that are established for this disease show a high potential for
tissue damage, which makes it difficult to compare their effects with those of
diclofenac in hyaluronic acid gel in randomized clinical trials.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="r01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berking</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herzinger</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flaig</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brenner</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borelli</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Degitz</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The efficacy of photodynamic therapy in actinic cheilitis of the lower
lip: a prospective study of 15 patients</article-title>
                  <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>825</fpage>
                  <lpage>830</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17598848</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brown</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hanpanitcharoen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>GP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An in vitro investigation into the effect of glycosaminoglycans on the
skin partitioning and deposition of NSAIDs</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Pharm</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>225</volume>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>121</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11489559</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fecker</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stockfleth</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nindl</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ulrich</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forschner</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eberle</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of apoptosis in the therapy and prophylaxis of epithelial
tumours by nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)</article-title>
                  <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>156</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 3</issue>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <lpage>33</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488403</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gebauer</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brown</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Varigos</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Topical diclofenac in hyaluronan gel for the treatment of solar
keratoses</article-title>
                  <source>Australas J Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <lpage>43</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12581080</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huber</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Terezhalmy</surname>
                      <given-names>GT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The patient with actinic cheilitis</article-title>
                  <source>Gen Dent</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <fpage>274</fpage>
                  <lpage>282</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16903202</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kaugars</surname>
                      <given-names>GE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pillion</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Svirsky</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Page</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burns</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abbey</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Actinic cheilitis: a review of 152 cases</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>88</volume>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <lpage>186</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10468463</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Markopoulos</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Albanidou-Farmaki</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kayavis</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Actinic cheilitis: clinical and pathologic characteristics in 65
cases</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Dis</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <lpage>216</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15196142</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Masferrer</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leahy</surname>
                      <given-names>KM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koki</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zweifel</surname>
                      <given-names>BS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Settle</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Woerner</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Antiangiogenic and antitumor activities of cyclooxygenase-2
inhibitors</article-title>
                  <source>Cancer Res</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <fpage>1306</fpage>
                  <lpage>1311</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10728691</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moore</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Willoughby</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hyaluronan as a drug delivery system for diclofenac: a hypothesis for
mode of action</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Tissue React</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>156</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8867645</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nelson</surname>
                      <given-names>CG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spencer</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nelson</surname>
                      <given-names>CG</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A single-arm, open-label efficacy and tolerability study of diclofenac
sodium 3% gel for the treatment of actinic keratosis of the upper and lower
lip</article-title>
                  <source>J Drugs Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>712</fpage>
                  <lpage>717</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17763595</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Orenstein</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldan</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weissman</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winkler</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haik</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new modality in the treatment of actinic cheilitis using the Er:YAG
laser</article-title>
                  <source>J Cosmet Laser Ther</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <lpage>25</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17506137</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pirard</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vereecken</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mélot</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heenen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Three percent diclofenac in 2.5% hyaluronan gel in the treatment of
actinic keratoses: a meta-analysis of the recent studies</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Dermatol Res</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>297</volume>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <lpage>189</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16235081</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rivers</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arlette</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shear</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guenther</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carey</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poulin</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Topical treatment of actinic keratoses with 3.0% diclofenac in 2.5%
hyaluronan gel</article-title>
                  <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>146</volume>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <lpage>100</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11841372</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rivers</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McLean</surname>
                      <given-names>DI</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An open study to assess the efficacy and safety of topical 3%
diclofenac in a 2.5% hyaluronic acid gel for the treatment of actinic
keratoses</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>133</volume>
                  <fpage>1239</fpage>
                  <lpage>1242</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9382562</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Robinson</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Actinic cheilitis. A prospective study comparing four treatment
methods</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <fpage>848</fpage>
                  <lpage>852</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2736096</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Germain</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yeager</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Skelton</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Topical 5% imiquimod for the therapy of actinic
cheilitis</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>497</fpage>
                  <lpage>501</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12271290</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morhenn</surname>
                      <given-names>VB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Piacquadio</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bilateral comparison of the efficacy and tolerability of 3% diclofenac
sodium gel and 5% 5-fluorouracil cream in the treatment of actinic keratoses of
the face and scalp</article-title>
                  <source>J Drugs Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <lpage>159</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16485883</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ulrich</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forschner</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ulrich</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stockfleth</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sterry</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Termeer</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Management of actinic cheilitis using diclofenac 3% gel: a report of
six cases</article-title>
                  <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>156</volume>
                  <issue> 3</issue>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488406</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wolf</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taylor</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tschen</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kang</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Topical 3.0% diclofenac in 2.5% hyaluronan gel in the treatment of
actinic keratoses</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>709</fpage>
                  <lpage>713</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737438</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wright</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dufresne</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Actinic cheilitis</article-title>
                  <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>490</fpage>
                  <lpage>491</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9568209</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
