<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:36:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10389564" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10389564</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-08-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>lwwopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Surg</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Surg</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JS9</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>International Journal of Surgery (London, England)</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1743-9191</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1743-9159</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10389564</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10389564</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10389564</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37288546</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37288546</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJS-D-22-01730</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JS9.0000000000000340</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00007</article-id>
              <article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Intranasal esketamine combined with oral midazolam provides adequate sedation for outpatient pediatric dental procedures: a prospective cohort study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Jing</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <email>2021110495@stu.cqmu.edu.cn</email>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zeng</surname>
                    <given-names>Jie</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <email>501332@hospital.cqmu.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>Nan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <email>500586@hospital.cqmu.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5896-7095</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Silu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <email>500159@hospital.cqmu.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Zhong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
                  <email>zer052005@126.com</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Liao</surname>
                    <given-names>Jingrong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <email>500524@hospital.cqmu.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ran</surname>
                    <given-names>Haosong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
                  <email>ranhaosong@gmail.com</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1957-574X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yu</surname>
                    <given-names>Cong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                  <email>500158@hospital.cqmu.edu.cn</email>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Anesthesiology, the Stomatology Hospital Affiliated Chongqing Medical University</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Chongqing Key Laboratory of Oral Diseases and Biomedical Sciences</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Chongqing Municipal Key Laboratory of Oral Biomedical Engineering of Higher Education</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>College of Artificial Intelligent, Chongqing University of Technology, No. 69 Hongguang Rd, Banan, Chongqing</aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Engineering Research Center of Fujian University for Stomatological Biomaterials, Xiamen Medical College, Xiamen, China</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Department of Anesthesiology, the Stomatology Hospital Affiliated Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China. Tel.: +86 139 9620 2110; fax: +86 23 88860222. E-mail: <email>500158@hospital.cqmu.edu.cn</email> (C. Yu).</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>5</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>109</volume>
              <issue>7</issue>
              <fpage>1893</fpage>
              <lpage>1899</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>5</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2023 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbysalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License 4.0</ext-link>, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work, even for commercial purposes, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</ext-link>
</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="js9-109-1893.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Background:</title>
                <p>Severe dental phobia or failure to cooperate with treatment are very common in outpatient pediatric dentistry. Personalized and appropriate noninvasive anesthesia methods can save medical expenses, improve treatment efficiency, reduce the anxiety of children, and improve the satisfaction of nursing staff. Currently, there is little conclusive evidence for noninvasive moderate sedation strategies in pediatric dental surgery.</p>
                <sec>
                  <title>Materials and methods:</title>
                  <p>The trial was conducted from May 2022 to September 2022. Each child was first given midazolam oral solution 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>, and when the Modified Observer’s Assessment of Alertness and Sedation score reached 4, a biased coin design up-down method was used to adjust the dose of esketamine. The primary outcome was the ED<sub>95</sub> and 95% CI of intranasal esketamine hydrochloride with midazolam 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>. Secondary outcomes included the onset time of sedation, treatment and awakening times, and the incidence of adverse events.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>A total of 60 children were enrolled; 53 children were successfully sedated but 7 were not. The ED<sub>95</sub> of intranasal esketamine with 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> midazolam oral liquid for the treatment of dental caries was 1.99 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> (95% CI 1.95–2.01 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>). The mean onset time of sedation for all patients was 43.7±6.9 min. 15.0 (10–24.0) min for examination and 89.4±19.5 min for awakening. The incidence of intraoperative nausea and vomiting was 8.3%. Adverse reactions such as transient hypertension and tachycardia occurred during the operations.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion:</title>
                  <p>The ED<sub>95</sub> of intranasal esketamine with 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> midazolam oral liquid for the outpatient pediatric dentistry procedure under moderate sedation was 1.99 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>. For children aged 2–6 years with dental anxiety who require dental surgery, anesthesiologists may consider using midazolam oral solution combined with esketamine nasal drops for noninvasive sedation after a preoperative anxiety scale evaluation.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords:</title>
                <kwd>dental surgery</kwd>
                <kwd>ED<sub>95</sub>
</kwd>
                <kwd>intranasal esketamine</kwd>
                <kwd>pediatric</kwd>
                <kwd>sedation</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>SDC</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>T</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <boxed-text content-type="shaded" position="anchor">
                <caption>
                  <p>Highlights</p>
                </caption>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Dental anxiety in children is very common and detrimental to surgery.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Esketamine combined with midazolam is an effective tool for sedation in children.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>The incidence of adverse events of esketamine combined with midazolam for sedation is low.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </boxed-text>
              <p>Dental caries is a multifactorial condition involving the colonization of the oral cavity with cariogenic microorganisms, the use of fluoride, diet, oral health, and the interaction of genetic, biochemical, and social factors<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Severe early childhood caries is a major healthcare issue that affects infants and preschool children globally, with its prevalence in China continuing to increase<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. If treatment is delayed, it will cause pain and infection, and even cause alveolar and jaw bone inflammation, leading to tooth loss<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>, eventually causing eating difficulties, language and cosmetic changes in children’s later growth and development. In most cases, a pediatric dental procedure is performed under local anesthesia in a dental surgery setting. Nondrug behavior management, especially tell-show-do are regular methods used to improve the degree of cooperation during dental procedures. However, severely anxious children or special-needs children (more common in preschool children) are fearful and lack cooperation during the dental procedure. Failure to cooperate with dentists and a lack of sufficient treatment time can seriously limit the effects of the dental treatment. Treatment of Severe early childhood caries under general anesthesia is considered to be the best drug behavior management approach for young children and is increasingly recommended by dentists in China, but there are associated medical risks and increased costs. Therefore, we explored an easy approach to implement a moderate sedation scheme suitable for short dental treatment<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. At the present time, sedatives administered to children (such as propofol, etomidate, pentobarbital) require invasive procedures involving intravenous access. About one percent of infants and children are given dexmedetomidine<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> with the possibility of eliciting life-threatening adverse events (AEs). About 5% of patients given intravenous short-acting barbiturates and circa 7% intravenous midazolam experienced AEs, notably respiratory depression, and transient desaturation<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Effective local or regional anesthesia usually reduces the dose of sedative required and improves the safety of the surgical procedure<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Although midazolam oral solution and dexmedetomidine have good sedative effects, they do not have analgesic effects. Esketamine is the dextrorotatory structure of racemic ketamine, and blocks N-methyl-D-aspartic acid activity in the central nerve system, inducing sedation, analgesia, and unconsciousness. Its affinity for the N-methyl-D-aspartic acid receptor is higher, and is 2 times more potent in its anesthesia and analgesia effects compared to ketamine. In addition, the mental symptoms are milder, and it is especially suitable for inducing short-term surgical anesthesia in children without the need for endotracheal intubation<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. Nasal administration is an excellent route for children, is simple and has a high bioavailability<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. However, children treated with esketamine alone have exhibit increases in heart rate and blood pressure, and the rapid heart rate can cause agitation and endanger the child’s life. Therefore, esketamine should not be used alone in pediatric anesthesia<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. As a new generation product, the actions of esketamine need to be further investigated. The ED<sub>95</sub> can reflect the effect of the continuous action of the drug, which is not normally investigated in controlled studies. Our aim was to provide the interested reader with the most effective dose in which the desirable clinical effect elicited will be certain. Midazolam oral liquid is a short-acting benzodiazepine with sedative, amnesic, and anxiolytic effects, usually prescribed as preoperative medication for children<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. In terms of drug interactions, the net effect of intranasal esketamine on midazolam is short-term weak inhibition, with an increase of less than 1.5 times and no clinical significance<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Therefore, we use midazolam oral solution combined with esketamine nasal drops<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. This methodologic improvement study was designed to determine the ED<sub>95</sub> of intranasal esketamine with 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> midazolam oral liquid as a moderate sedation regimen for the treatment of children’s dental caries by the biased coin design up-down method (BCD-UMD).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>The trial was conducted from May 2022 to September 2022. The children underwent pediatric dental surgery including caries treatment and complex supernumerary tooth extraction under moderate sedation induced with midazolam and intranasal esketamine. The study was carried out in strict accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki principles for research on humans and was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Stomatological Hospital Affiliated to Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China April 23, 2022 [No.: CQHS-REC-2022(LSNo.132)]. All children’s legal representatives signed informed consent. The trial was registered at chictr.org.cn before the patients were enrolled (ChiCTR2200058047, registration date: 27 March 2022). This study has been reported in accordance with strengthening the reporting of cohort, cross-sectional and case-control studies in surgery (STROCSS) standards<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. Supplemental Digital Content 1, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A649" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A649</ext-link>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Study population</title>
                <p>The trial inclusion criteria were: children aged 2 to 6 years old who were scheduled to receive sedation for dental surgery; American Society of Anesthesiologists medical status I to II. The exclusion criteria were: nonconsensual; known to be allergic to midazolam oral solution and/or esketamine; hepatic or renal problems; runny nose; serious systemic disease (for example: congenital heart disease; Kawasaki disease; multisystem inflammatory syndrome; primary systemic vasculitis); or a diagnosis of fever.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="methods">
                <title>Study procedures and interventions</title>
                <p>All patients fasted for greater than or equal to 2 h. Oral midazolam solution and the esketamine intranasal instillation were administered by an anesthesiologist who was not involved in collecting trial data. A dose of 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> midazolam oral solution and nasal drops of undiluted esketamine (2 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>) were employed.</p>
                <p>Children who visited the clinic on the same day were evaluated by anesthesiologists, and informed consent was obtained from the children’s guardians. Before patients entered the treatment room, the following vital signs were measured: heart rate; blood pressure; and blood oxygen saturation. Sedation was assessed by a blinded anesthesiologist using the Modified Observer’s Assessment of Alertness and Sedation (MOAA/S)<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> (eAppendix 1, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A650" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A650</ext-link>) scale every 5 min after the administration of midazolam oral solution. After administration, our anesthesiologist stood on the right side of the patient, called out the patient’s name, and judged the depth of sedation based on the patient’s response to their name. When we called a patient’s name in a normal voice, they were unresponsive, and the MOAA/S score was 4 at this time. Until we needed to call out their names loudly and/or repeatedly. Only then could patients respond, at which point the MOAA/S score was 3. Esketamine intranasal instillation was performed when the MOAA/S sedation score reached 4. Immediately after successful sedation, the pediatric dentist infiltrated the surgical area with local anesthetic. If the patient was less than 4 years old they were given an injection of 2% lidocaine (5 ml: 0.1 g, Southwest Pharmaceuticals; SFDA No. H50020038); the maximum total dosage was &lt;4 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>. Patients greater than or equal to 4 years old were given 4% articaine and epinephrine injection (1.7 ml: 68 mg, Products Dentaires Pierre Rolland; SFDA No. H20140732) up to a maximum dosage of 5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>. Five minutes after local anesthetic injection, the treatment procedure was initiated. To prevent aspiration of water ingress and foreign objects, rubber dams were placed for isolation during the surgical procedure. The onset time of sedation was defined as the time when patients had MOAA/S scores less than or equal to 3. The success of sedation was defined as: under the condition of MOAA/S less than or equal to 3, the operation was successfully completed without remedial measures. And the marker of sedation failure were MOAA/S score greater than or equal to 4 points. If the patient failed to be sedated, a salvage ‘sevoflurane inhalation’ remedy were given to complete the dental surgery. Total sevoflurane inhalation induced sedation deep has been widely used in our dental procedures, and our previous clinical trial revealed that solo sevoflurane exposure did not lead to adverse neurocognitive outcomes or neurological deficits in healthy preschool children (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Operation time chart.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="js9-109-1893-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>According to previous relevant literature and our preliminary trials<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>, we choose 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> as constant dose of midazolam oral solution (10 ml: 20 mg, Yichang Humanwell, Inc., YiChang, HuBei; SFDA No. H20213321), the initial dose of intranasal esketamine is 1 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> as followed (2 ml: 50 mg, Jiangsu Hengrui Medicine; SFDA No. H20193336). The next dose was based upon previous patient responses, using the BCD-UMD<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. The dosing interval was 0.25 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>. If sedation failed, the next patient’s dose of esketamine was increased by 0.25 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>, and if sedation was successful, the next patient was randomized to receive the same dose (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.95), or 0.25 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> less (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.05). It is fair to say that the sample size for the BCD-UMD has not been well defined, but anesthesia trials that employ the top-down approach typically have a cohort of 20–40 patients<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. We recruited 60 patients, including 42 for caries treatment and 18 for supernumerary tooth extraction<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. The time to onset of sedation was defined as the time from the initiation of the administration of midazolam oral solution to the successful induction of sedation. The wake-up time was defined as the time from intranasal esketamine titration until patient discharge from the dental office. An aldrete score of 9 or above will allow discharge (eAppendix 2, Supplemental Digital Content 3, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A651" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A651</ext-link>)<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. After the dental surgery was finished, the patient was transferred to a recovery area. Patients were followed up with by an original developed smartphone-based applet WeChat Applet for dental anxiety the next day to record any AEs and intelligent feedback (eFigure 1, Supplemental Digital Content 4, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A652" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A652</ext-link>)<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Outcome measure</title>
                <p>The primary outcome was the dose from the start of administration to the time when the patient fell asleep (MOAA/S ≤ 3 points). Secondary outcomes included the time to onset of sedation, time to treatment, time to awakening, security indicators (e.g., incidence of AEs such as hypotension, hypertension, bradycardia, tachycardia, respiratory depression, oxyhemoglobin desaturation, reflux and vomiting, hypoglycemia), and sex-specific onset and recovery times.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Pace <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> recommended the enrollment of 20–40 patients in BCD-UMD based sequential dose-finding studies, as most practical cases provide a stable estimate of the dose; in our study, 60 patients were included. ED<sub>95</sub> in pediatric patients was estimated using an isotonic regression estimator μ3, and ~95% CIs for ED<sub>95</sub> were calculated using the bias-corrected percentile method derived from bootstrapping, with a resampling size of 60, the number of replicates 2000 and a target Γ of 0.95<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. Adjusted response probabilities were obtained by the Aggregate Neighbor Violator Algorithm. Statistical analysis was performed using Python 3.10 (numpy package: the fundamental package for scientific computing; scipy package: Compute a two-sided bootstrap CIs of a statistic; pandas package: data form management).</p>
                <p>Data with a normal distribution are given as the mean±SD, and non-normally distributed data as [medians (interquartile range)], evaluated using SPSS for Windows (version 22.0).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Patients’ characteristics and operative data</title>
                <p>Sixty patients participated in our prospective study, with 53 successful and 7 unsuccessful sedations (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> provides an overview of the detailed participant demographics, which were similar across groups.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>CONSORT flow diagram.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="js9-109-1893-g002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Characteristics of participants.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Characteristic</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=60)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Success (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=53)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Failure (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=7)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, No. (%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (45)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (45.3)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female, No. (%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (55)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (54.7)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, year, median (IQR)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5 (34.5–64.0)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (32.0–63.5)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (38–74)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, median (IQR)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (16–18)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.17 (16.3–18.0)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.35 (16.3–17.7)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Primary outcome</title>
                <p>The ED<sub>95</sub> of intranasal esketamine after 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> oral midazolam for pediatric dentistry procedure under moderate sedation was 1.99 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> with 95% CI of 1.95–2.01 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>.</p>
                <p>The frequency of treatment and observed pool adjacent violator algorithm adjusted response rates for each specific esketamine dose are shown in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Pool adjacent violator algorithm adjusted response rates were never observed to decrease with increasing dose.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Observed and PAVA adjusted esketamine response rates (isotonic regression).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Assigned dose (μg/kg)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Number sedative</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Number tested</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Observed response rate</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">PAVA adjusted response rate</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9523</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9523</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Secondary outcomes</title>
                <p>
Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref> details the sedation onset time of 43.7±6.9 min for all patients. Onset time of sedation: 44.1±5.8 min for successful sedation, 15.0 (10–24.0) min for examination, 89.4±19.5 min for awakening.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Secondary outcome statistics.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Characteristic</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=60)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Success (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=53)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Failure (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=7)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examination time, median (IQR), min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0 (10–24.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam onset time, median (IQR), min</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6 (15–20)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6 (15–20)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6 (16–24.6)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sedation onset time, Mean±SD, min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7±6.9</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1±5.8</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3±5.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time of wakefulness, Mean±SD, min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.4±19.5</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Security indicators</title>
                <p>
Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref> details the security indicators. The incidence of nausea and vomiting in all children was 8.3%, the sedation success rate was 7.5%, and the sedation failure rate was 14.3%. The incidence of hypoglycemia in all children was 1.6%, the sedation success rate 1.9%, the incidence of intraoperative hypertension in all children 5%, and the sedation success rate 5.7%. The incidence of tachycardia in all children was 8.5%, the sedation success rate was 1.9%, and the sedation failure rate was 57.1%. There were no AEs such as hypotension, bradycardia, respiratory depression, or oxyhemoglobin desaturation. eFigure 2, Supplemental Digital Content 5, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A663" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A663</ext-link> shows the patient’s heart rate, blood pressure, and oxygen saturation at different times.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Security indicators.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Characteristic</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=60)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Success (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=53)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Failure (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=7)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea, vomiting</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.3%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.5%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypoglycemic reaction</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.7%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.9%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraoperative hypertension</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraoperative tachycardia</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.3%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.9%)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxyhemoglobin desaturation</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypotension</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradycardia</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Houpt scale score</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1–3)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOAA/S scale scores</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3–3.8)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3–4)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4–5)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>eAppendix 3, Supplemental Digital Content 6, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A664" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A664</ext-link> shows the onset times of sedation for 53 children who were successfully sedated: 44.0±5.4 min for males and 44.5±6.2 min for females, with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of 0.762. Wake-up time was 84.9±16.8 for males and 92.8± 16.8 for females, with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of 0.146.</p>
                <p>The intranasal esketamine doses in the seven patients with sedation failure were 1 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>, 1.25 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>, 1.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>, 1.75 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>, 2.0 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> and 1.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>, 1.75 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Seven patients with sedation failure, all had MOAA/S score less than or equal to 3 within 30 min of esketamine administration and reached the level of sedation, two patients woke up during local anesthesia and refused treatment (MOAA/S &gt;4), five patients on intraoperative awakening (MOAA/S &gt;3) were administered sevoflurane for inhalation rescue.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F3">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Determination of the ED<sub>95</sub> of intranasal esketamine in infants receiving dental surgery. Patient serial number (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis) and the dosage of esketamine dispensed (<italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis) are shown. Sedation failures (open squares), successful sedations (solid squares).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="js9-109-1893-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Outpatient pediatric dental procedure under anesthesia and sedation, whether in China or other countries, severe hypoxia occurred every few years, mostly due to respiratory-related AEs such as laryngospasm, airway obstruction, and respiratory suppression<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. Therefore, research on the ratio of anesthetics other than general anesthesia and deep sedation is imminent. Several previous studies have found that esketamine 1 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> intranasally is approximately as effective as ketamine 2 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> intranasally<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>, whereas ketamine 3 and 6 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> did not produce sufficient sedation<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>. Preoperative nasal sedation with 3 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> esketamine alone was insufficient for sedation and resulted in a higher incidence of postoperative agitation. Intranasal esketamine can provide adequate sedation for pediatric patients in outpatient care. Higher percentile effective doses provide more clinical guidance, so we explored the ED<sub>95</sub> of esketamine combined with midazolam oral solution. An isotonic regression estimator with exmedetom statistics that measures responses at arbitrary points (quantiles) on the dose-response curve with low bias and variance. The BCD design approach avoided unvalidated extrapolation of the ED<sub>50</sub> because most of the peak distributions of administered doses were around the mean. Therefore, we used the BCD design method and the isotonic regression estimator to study the ED<sub>95</sub> of esketamine combined with midazolam oral solution. In our study, we calculated the ED<sub>95</sub> of esketamine nasal drops combined with 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> midazolam oral solution to be 1.99 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> [95% CI, 1.95–2.01 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>], the results may provide clinical guidance for performing these pediatric surgeries in children 2–6 years of age undergoing dental surgery.</p>
              <p>The combination of esketamine and sedative drugs can be expanded or substituted for other pediatric procedures requiring MOAA/S less than or equal to 3. On the one hand, it is used for pre-examination sedation, such as improving the cooperation of children with inhalation anesthesia masks<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> better sedation in children with tonsillectomy<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. Facilitate pediatric upper gastrointestinal endoscopy<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> and pediatric MRI examination<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. On the other hand, it has been applied to sedation for other pediatric outpatient procedures, such as: hernia in children, circumcision, debridement, and suture.</p>
              <p>It is an important clinical context to provide safe and effective preoperative medication to children, promote their calmness and cooperation, and avoid anxiety and agitation. Although many drugs and methods have been studied worldwide, various details should be highlighted. For example, midazolam oral solution alone is prone to elicit complications such as excitement, hallucinations, behavior changes, and delayed awakening<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. The sedative effect may even be unsatisfactory due to individual differences in the first-pass effect or AEs such as a high incidence of nausea and vomiting. Increased respiratory secretions may occur when intravenous propofol is combined with different doses of ketamine<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. Numerous studies have shown that dexmedetomidine is a good alternative for preoperative sedation or sedation before computed tomograhy and other medical imaging examinations, but it does not have an analgesic action. Dexmedetomidine should be used with caution in patients less than 18 years old<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Based on clinical experience and related studies, we gave a dose of midazolam oral liquid of 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>. Esketamine is extensively metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, mainly 3A4 and 2B6<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>. N-demethylation to norketamine is the main pathway for the metabolism of esketamine<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. Norketamine is further metabolized via a cytochrome P450 enzymes-dependent pathway, with an increase in maximum concentration from zero to infinity (C<sub>max</sub>) and the AUC higher than for esketamine, especially after the oral route of administration, so esketamine effects lasted longer ketamine<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Carlos Perez-Ruixo<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> stated that the absolute bioavailability of 56 mg and 84 mg intranasal esketamine was 54 and 51%, respectively. Yoshitsugu Yanagihara<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> estimated that the bioavailability of ketamine administered by nasal spray to be about 45%, so we specified the initial nasal dose as 1.0 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> based on the above studies.</p>
              <p>In children requiring fractionated diagnosis and treatment, esketamine did not accumulate in the plasma following repeated or infrequent administration after twice weekly intranasal doses<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>. Following intranasal administration, the expected time to reach peak plasma concentrations of esketamine was 20–40 min after the last nasal spray treatment, followed by a rapid decline in the esketamine plasma concentration, with a terminal half-life between 7 and 12 h<sup><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. The onset time of the drug in this study was 44.2±5.8 min. Considering the onset time of midazolam oral liquid, it was basically consistent with this conclusion.</p>
              <p>Combination therapy not only improved patient satisfaction with preanesthetic sedation, but did not increase the wake-up time or the incidence of AEs<sup><xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>In this trial, the incidence of intraoperative hypertension was 5% and the incidence of tachycardia was 8.3%. The next day, by follow-up with an original smartphone-based applet WeChat applet for dental anxiety, postoperative blood pressure, and heart rate had returned to normal, which were consistent with Doherty’s<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> findings that blood pressure increases after esketamine administration are usually transient in nature, asymptomatic, and did not associate with serious cardiovascular safety sequelae. In general, AEs related to blood pressure, abnormal heart rate, and cardiovascular. AEs began shortly after dosing in esketamine-treated patients and resolved within 1.5 h of patient dosing<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Intraoperative hypertension and tachycardia may also be caused by a 4% articaine injection containing 1:100 000 epinephrine. The incidence of drug induced postoperative nausea and vomiting cannot be unequivocally established because of blood or inflammatory stimuli after oral dental<sup><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>, which differ from other operations. One successfully sedated patient developed hypoglycemia 1 h after surgery. The family was informed that it probably developed because she has fasted for more than 12 h. Studies have shown that esketamine has a lower adverse reaction rate, a shorter recovery time, and directional recovery time than racemic ketamine<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>. The results of our study showed that the onset time of sedation for boys and girls were: 43.0±5.8 min and 44.2±6.0, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.762, but statistical significance was not reached; the awakening time was 84.9±16.8 and 92.8±21.2 min, respectively, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.146, which was not statistically different, findings consistent with the result of Jing Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> who reported no sex difference in esketamine efficacy.</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>Our study had several limitations: The heart rate, blood pressure, respiratory rate, and pulse oximeter measured at baseline before dosing may have been inaccurate due to the children’s anxiety and crying; Several factors may have affected the level of sedation, including the duration of fasting before sedation, the child’s sleep quality. It is noteworthy that the seven patients who failed sedation slept well the night before sedation. More data are needed in future studies.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>The ED<sub>95</sub> of intranasal esketamine with 0.5 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup> midazolam oral liquid for the outpatient pediatric dentistry procedure under moderate sedation was 1.99 mg·kg<sup>−1</sup>. Such regimens provide safe and moderate sedation for pediatric dental procedure in an office-based setting.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Ethical approval</title>
              <p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board Stomatological. Hospital Affiliated to Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China 23 April 2022 (No.: CQHS-REC-2022 (LSNo.132)).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Sources of funding</title>
              <p>The authors disclose that they received the following financial support for the research publication of this article. Fujian Oral Biomaterials College (Xiamen Medical College) Engineering Research Center. (Grant No.: XMMC-KQ202102); Intelligent Medicine Project of Chongqing Medical University (Grant No.: ZHYX202116).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Author contribution</title>
              <p>C.Y.: concept and design; J.W., J.Z., N.Z., S.I.C., Z.C., and J.L.: acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data; J.W.: drafting of the manuscript; C.Y.: critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content; J.Z., H.S.R.: statistical analysis.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title>
              <p>None reported.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title>
              <p>1. Name of the registry: Chinese Clinical Trial Registry chictr.org.cn.</p>
              <p>2. Unique Identifying number or registration ID: ChiCTR2200058047.</p>
              <p>3. Hyperlink to your specific registration (must be publicly accessible and will be checked): <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.chictr.org.cn/showprojen.aspx?proj=155738" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.chictr.org.cn/showprojen.aspx?proj=155738</ext-link>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Guarantor</title>
              <p>CongYu, JingWang, JieZeng.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data availability statement</title>
              <p>Informed consent has been signed for this clinical trial, and the original data will not be shared.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Provenance and peer review</title>
              <p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <fig id="s001" position="anchor">
                <media xlink:href="js9-109-1893-s001.docx"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="s002" position="anchor">
                <media xlink:href="js9-109-1893-s002.docx"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="s003" position="anchor">
                <media xlink:href="js9-109-1893-s003.docx"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="s004" position="anchor">
                <media xlink:href="js9-109-1893-s004.tif"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="s005" position="anchor">
                <media xlink:href="js9-109-1893-s005.tiff"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="s006" position="anchor">
                <media xlink:href="js9-109-1893-s006.docx"/>
              </fig>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>The authors thank all the participating children and their families for participating in this study.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>J.W. and J.Z. contributed equally to the work.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. Direct URL citations are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal’s website, <ext-link xlink:href="www.lww.com/international-journal-of-surgery" ext-link-type="uri">www.lww.com/international-journal-of-surgery</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="equal">
                <p>Published online 5 June 2023</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Parental occupations, educational levels, and income and prevalence of dental caries in 3-year-old Japanese children</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Prev Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165111</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wulaerhan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of severe early childhood caries and associated socioeconomic and behavioral factors in Xinjiang, China: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>BMC Oral Health</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Duangthip</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early childhood caries and oral health care of Hong Kong preschool children</article-title>. <source>Clin Cosmet Investig Dent</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duangthip</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Oral health policies to tackle the burden of early childhood caries: a review of 14 countries/regions</article-title>. <source>Front Oral Health</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarumathi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, severity and associated factors of dental caries in 3-6 year old children</article-title>. <source>J Clin Diagn Res</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1789</fpage>–<lpage>1792</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24086915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of dental caries and its treatment under general anaesthetic on children and their families</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33280070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical, individual and environmental factors related to children’s health-related quality of life following treatment under general anaesthetic for dental caries: a path analysis</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35113385</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khurmi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacologic considerations for pediatric sedation and anesthesia outside the operating room: a review for anesthesia and non-anesthesia providers. Pediatric Drugs</article-title>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Spandorfer</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Etomidate versus pentobarbital for computed tomography sedations: report from the Pediatric Sedation Research Consortium</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>690</fpage>–<lpage>695</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18090099</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Prescilla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontaine</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pediatric CT sedation: comparison of dexmedetomidine and pentobarbital</article-title>. <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>W194</fpage>–<lpage>W198</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21257862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison between dexmedetomidine and esketamine in pediatric dentistry surgery</article-title>. <source>Transl Pediatr</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3159</fpage>–<lpage>3165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35070829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblat</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemeroff</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Synthesizing the evidence for ketamine and esketamine in treatment-resistant depression: an international expert opinion on the available evidence and implementation</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>178</volume>:<fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33726522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Türker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Onur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ózer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nasal route and drug delivery systems</article-title>. <source>Pharm World Sci</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15230360</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lofts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Hijleh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Using the intranasal route to administer drugs to treat neurological and psychiatric illnesses: rationale, successes, and future needs</article-title>. <source>CNS Drugs</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35759210</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wajs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Melkote</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cardiac safety of esketamine nasal spray in treatment-resistant depression: results from the clinical development program</article-title>. <source>CNS Drugs</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31994024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathy</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative evaluation of midazolam and clonidine as pediatric oral premedication</article-title>. <source>Anesth Essays Res</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25885837</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willemin</surname><given-names>M-E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zannikos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of drug–drug interactions after esketamine intranasal administration using a physiologically based pharmacokinetic model</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1115</fpage>–<lpage>1128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35579824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manso</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guittet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenhende</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of oral midazolam for minimal and moderate sedation in pediatric patients: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Anaesth</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1094</fpage>–<lpage>1106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31538393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>STROCSS 2021: strengthening the reporting of cohort, cross-sectional and case-control studies in surgery</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg Open</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>100430</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A double-blind, crossover assessment of the sedative and analgesic effects of intranasal dexmedetomidine</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17646493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chernik</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillings</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Validity and reliability of the observer’s: assessment of alertness/sedation scale: study with: intravenous midazolam</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source><year>1990</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2286697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of sevoflurane anesthesia for dental procedure on neurocognition in children: a prospective, equivalence, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beirami</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoshfetrat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Babaiyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of different doses of oral midazolam for pre operation sedation of children</article-title>. <source>Zahedan J Res Med Sci</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stylianou</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Warltier</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in and limitations of up-and-down methodology: a precis of clinical use, study design, and dose estimation in anesthesia research</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17585226</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Determination of the 95% effective dose of remifentanil for the prevention of coughing during extubation in children undergoing tonsillectomy (with or without adenoidectomy)</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Anesthesia</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25559991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intranasal dexmedetomidine following failed chloral hydrate sedation in children</article-title>. <source>Anaesthesia</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24447296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Experience of using a smartphone WeChat applet for dental anxiety assessment and preoperative evaluation: a nationwide multicenter study</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stylianou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flournoy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dose finding using the biased coin up‐and‐down design and isotonic regression</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11890313</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stylianou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Proschan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flournoy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating the probability of toxicity at the target dose following an up‐and‐down design</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12590412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coté</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The single-clinician–operator/anesthetist model for dental deep sedation/anesthesia: a major safety issue for children</article-title>. <source>JAMA Pediatr</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31657849</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A comparison of intranasal dexmedetomidine, esketamine or a dexmedetomidine-esketamine combination for induction of anaesthesia in children: a randomized controlled double-blind trial</article-title>. <source>Front Pharmacol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsze</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Machan</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intranasal ketamine for procedural sedation in pediatric laceration repair: a preliminary report</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>767</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22858745</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ketamine enhances intranasal dexmedetomidine-induced sedation in children: a randomized, double-blind trial</article-title>. <source>Drug Des Devel Ther</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>3559</fpage>–<lpage>3565</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ED50 and ED95 of propofol combined with different doses of esketamine for children undergoing upper gastrointestinal endoscopy: a prospective dose‐finding study using up‐and‐down sequential allocation method</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pharm Ther</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1002</fpage>–<lpage>1009</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35255530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S-x</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>X-s</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J-m</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of esketamine vs dexmedetomidine adjunct to propofol sedation for pediatric 3Tesla magnetic resonance imaging: a randomized, double-blind, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Eur J Med Res</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36411479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of oral triclofos and oral midazolam as premedication in children undergoing elective surgery</article-title>. <source>Anesth Essays Res</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31198261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellenberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sedation for magnetic resonance imaging using propofol with or without ketamine at induction in pediatrics—a prospective randomized double‐blinded study</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Anaesth</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29377404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azizkhani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heydari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazavi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparing sedative effect of dexmedetomidine versus midazolam for sedation of children while undergoing computerized tomography imaging</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Neurosci</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33531939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T-L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of cytochrome P450 gene expression by ketamine: a review</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>720</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29888644</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yanagihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kariya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Involvement of CYP2B6 in n-demethylation of ketamine in human liver microsomes</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>887</fpage>–<lpage>890</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11353758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peltoniemi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saari</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagelberg</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rifampicin has a profound effect on the pharmacokinetics of oral S‐ketamine and less on intravenous S‐ketamine</article-title>. <source>Basic Clin Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676424</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonkman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Donk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ketamine for cancer pain: what is the evidence?</article-title><source>Curr Opin Support Palliat Care</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28306568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R43">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Ruixo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossenu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zannikos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Population pharmacokinetics of esketamine nasal spray and its metabolite noresketamine in healthy subjects and patients with treatment-resistant depression</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>516</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33128208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R44">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yanagihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kariya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Plasma concentration profiles of ketamine and norketamine after administration of various ketamine preparations to healthy Japanese volunteers</article-title>. <source>Biopharm Drug Dispos</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12516077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R45">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kritzer</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pae</surname><given-names>C-U</given-names></name><name><surname>Masand</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Key considerations for the use of ketamine and esketamine in clinical practice: focusing on administration, safety, and tolerability</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Drug Saf</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35475388</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R46">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Loo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdulahad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of intranasal esketamine on on-road driving performance in patients with major depressive disorder or persistent depressive disorder</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>625</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35212235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R47">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Moraes Penna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>APM</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison between oral midazolam versus oral ketamine plus midazolam as preanesthetic medication in autism spectrum disorder: double-blind randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Braz J Anesthesiol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36183860</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R48">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobbeleir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Coster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coucke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Postoperative nausea and vomiting after oral and maxillofacial surgery: a prospective study</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>725</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29301675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R49">
                <label>49</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron-Stefaniak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Krammel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of intravenous S-ketamine on the MAC of sevoflurane: a randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blinded clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>1242</fpage>–<lpage>1248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30442251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R50">
                <label>50</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics and safety of esketamine in Chinese patients undergoing painless gastroscopy in comparison with ketamine: a randomized, open-label clinical study</article-title>. <source>Drug Des Devel Ther</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>4135</fpage>–<lpage>4144</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
