<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:46:09Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6709256" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6709256</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>medicine</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6709256</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6709256</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6709256</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31348316</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31348316</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-19-04983</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000016634</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">16634</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
                  <subject>5900</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Study Protocol Clinical Trial</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Study protocol of the cost-effectiveness comparison of two preventive methods in the incidence of caries</article-title>
                <subtitle>A randomized, controlled clinical trial</subtitle>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fernández-Barrera</surname>
                    <given-names>Miguel Ángel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, MSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lara-Carrillo</surname>
                    <given-names>Edith</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, DSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>c</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
                    <sup>∗</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Scougall-Vilchis</surname>
                    <given-names>Rogelio José</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>c</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pontigo-Loyola</surname>
                    <given-names>América Patricia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, DSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ávila-Burgos</surname>
                    <given-names>Leticia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD, DSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>d</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Casanova-Rosado</surname>
                    <given-names>Juan Fernando</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, MSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                    <sup>e</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Casanova-Rosado</surname>
                    <given-names>Alejandro José</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, MSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                    <sup>e</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Minaya-Sánchez</surname>
                    <given-names>Mirna</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, MSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                    <sup>e</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Medina-Solís</surname>
                    <given-names>Carlo Eduardo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS, MSc</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>c</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
                    <sup>∗</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Program of Doctorate in Health Sciences, Autonomous University State of Mexico, Toluca</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Academic Area of Dentistry of Health Sciences Institute, Autonomous University of Hidalgo State, Pachuca</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Advanced Studies and Research Center in Dentistry “Dr. Keisaburo Miyata” of Faculty of Dentistry, Autonomous University State of Mexico, Toluca</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Health Systems Research Centre, National Institute of Public Health, Cuernavaca</aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Faculty of Dentistry, Autonomous University of Campeche, Campeche, México.</aff>
              <author-notes id="cor1">
                <corresp><label>∗</label>Correspondence: Edith Lara-Carrillo, Advanced Studies and Research Centre in Dentistry “Dr. Keisaburo Miyata” of Faculty of Dentistry, Autonomous University of State of Mexico, Toluca, Mexico, 50130 (e-mail: <email>laracaedith@hotmail.com</email>), Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís, Academic Area of Dentistry of Health Sciences Institute, Autonomous University of Hidalgo State, Pachuca, Mexico, 42160 (e-mail: <email>cemedinas@yahoo.com</email>).</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>98</volume>
              <issue>30</issue>
              <elocation-id>e16634</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>5</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2019 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-98-e16634.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec sec-type="intro">
                  <title>Introduction:</title>
                  <p>Dental caries is the most frequent oral disease worldwide and the main cause of tooth loss in children and young adults. One of the most frequently affected areas is the occlusal surfaces of the first permanent molars (FPM) due to their morphological complexity. At present, several preventive treatments can reduce the incidence of this disease in school populations. In Mexico, the most commonly used technologies are those derived from some presentation of fluoride; on the other hand, research on this topic has been limited.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective:</title>
                  <p>To determine the cost-effectiveness of two different methods for preventing the incidence of caries on the FPM of schoolchildren (6–8 years of age) from public primary schools.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Material and methods:</title>
                  <p>This is a randomized experimental design. Participants will be assigned to two treatment groups of 114 each. In the first group, pit and fissure sealants will be applied, whereas the second group will receive a fluoride varnish. The work will be carried out in schoolchildren that attend public elementary schools in the state of Hidalgo, Mexico. The result variable will be the incidence of caries and the total cost of each of the interventions will be calculated in order to calculate the intervention's cost-effectiveness.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="conclusion">
                  <title>Conclusion:</title>
                  <p>This work will allow us to compare the cost-effectiveness of the pit and fissure sealants and the fluoride varnish in order to determine which offers the best results.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>dental caries</kwd>
                <kwd>Mexico</kwd>
                <kwd>oral health</kwd>
                <kwd>preventive dentistry</kwd>
                <kwd>schoolchildren</kwd>
                <kwd>sealants</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec>
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Dental caries is one of the most frequently encountered oral health problems worldwide. Official figures report that between 60% and 90% of children worldwide suffer from dental caries and that caries occur mainly among the most socioeconomically disadvantaged populations.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> It affects different spheres of people's lives and has a negative impact on people's quality of life, which is why it is considered a public health problem.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Dental caries is a demineralization process of the hard tissues of the tooth, which generates a softening of the surface and subsurface of the enamel that, if it is not stopped, can generate a cavity and even cause the loss of the dental organ.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> One of the areas most affected by dental caries are the pits and fissures of the occlusal surfaces<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>; according to some researchers, these pits and fissures account for about 90% of all caries cases due to the presence of deep and narrow pits and fissures.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Several studies indicate that occlusal surfaces are more susceptible to decay than smooth surfaces due to a lack of post-eruptive maturation and reduced mineral content.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>Concepts on the management of carious lesions have changed during the last few decades.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Increasing knowledge about the importance of preventive dentistry and the management of incipient lesions has modified the dentist's typical protocols, specifically by promoting the current focus on less invasive treatments and trying to preserve the greatest amount of enamel for as long as possible.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Topical fluorides, in their different forms (dentifrices, mouth rinses, gels, and varnishes), allow a local protective effect to be generated on the tooth surface by increasing the exposure time between the fluoride and tooth enamel.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> This increased exposure helps facilitate the remineralization process, which decreases the appearance of new carious lesions in the areas where it is applied. The use of fluorides contributes significantly to the prevention and management of carious lesions.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> Also, the evolution of dental materials enabled the improvement of preventive methods in dentistry, e.g., the changes in and new types of resins and their application, from the technique of acid etching introduced by Buonocore in 1955 and the development of acrylic resins by Bowen in 1953 to the materials that we know today.</p>
              <p>The pit and fissure sealer (PFS) is a low-viscosity resin that penetrates deep pits and fissures. This preventive method reduces the risk that the pits and fissures of the occlusal surfaces become carious by generating a physical barrier that prevents the accumulation of biofilms within these areas.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> The PFS has been modified over time, resulting in improved retention to the dental surface and decreased working time, which facilitated PFS's application along with the change in coloration offered by some brands. Additionally, some of these products even have technology that allows them to release fluoride, thereby improving the resin's cariostatic actions.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>In Mexico, dental caries is a public health problem in schoolchildren<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup>; however, the use of preventive methods other than fluoride in school populations has not been studied in terms of the costs involved in its use nor its results in terms of caries reduction.<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> Almost no clinical trials have been published in this country on this topic, which opens up new research avenues that will, eventually, allow health planners to make decisions based on evidence. The objective of this work will be to determine the cost-effectiveness of two different preventive methods in decreasing the incidence of dental caries on the first permanent molars (FPM) of schoolchildren (from 6 to 8 years of age) from public primary schools.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Methodology</title>
              <sec>
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>This is a randomized experimental design that will be carried out on the FPMs of schoolchildren from public elementary schools in the state of Hidalgo, Mexico. Start date: 2019–03-05.</p>
                <p>Hidalgo is one of the 31 states, which, with Mexico City, comprise the 32 Federal Entities of Mexico. It is divided in 84 municipalities and its capital city is <italic>Pachuca de Soto</italic>. Hidalgo is one of the Mexican states that participated in the fluoridated domestic salt program implemented nationally in 1991. Mexico has no water fluoridation program at the national level; however, some states, including parts of Hidalgo, have water with naturally high levels of fluoride. This is not the case in Pachuca, the capital city of Hidalgo.<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup></p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>The treatments will be carried out within selected public primary schools in selected municipalities of the state of Hidalgo with little access to oral health programs. Participants will be children between 6 and 8 years of age with at least one permanent molar that is healthy and fully erupted with high or moderate risk of caries according to the Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN).<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup></p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Selection criteria</title>
                <p>To be considered to participate in the trial, each potential participant must meet the established inclusion and exclusion criteria. Some of the criteria require oral examination within the baseline measurement, which, may result in some children not participating in the intervention and, therefore, the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Inclusion criteria</title>
                <p>Children must be from 6 to 8 years of age, belong to the selected public elementary schools, and:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Have at least one first molar that is healthy and fully erupted;</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Whose parents sign the informed consent form; and</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Decide to participate in the intervention.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Elimination criteria</title>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Fixed orthodontic appliances;</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Disability;</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Systemic disease; or</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Any alteration of the oral cavity.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.6</label>
                <title>Trial intervention</title>
                <p>The PFSs to be used in this study have been used for years in other populations. Children will be randomly assigned to either the PFS or varnish group and each subject will remain in their assigned group throughout the study.</p>
                <sec>
                  <label>2.6.1</label>
                  <title>Pit and fissure sealant</title>
                  <p>The PFS that will be used for this study is Clinpro3M. This PFS changes color when being light-cured and has a low viscosity, which allows it to have excellent penetration inside the pits and fissures. It has fluoride release capability and is applied through the total enamel etching system.</p>
                  <p>The application of the sealant will be carried out within the public primary schools with the help of a portable tripod and using natural light. Sealers will be reviewed every 3 months for a period of 24 months. In cases of partial or total release, the sealant will be reapplied.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <label>2.6.2</label>
                  <title>Fluoride varnish</title>
                  <p>The varnish used in this study will be DuraphatColgate, which consists of a 5% fluoride varnish containing 22,600 ppm of fluoride suspended in a resin base. It is an easy product to apply since it adheres quickly in the presence of saliva and its color allows good visual control.</p>
                  <p>Once the baseline measurement is obtained, the application will be made within the selected schools with prior prophylaxis and during the first hour of classes to ensure that the children do not consume food until at least 2 h after the treatment, considering the time of the meal recess.</p>
                  <p>The revisions and reapplications will occur every 3 months during the follow-up period of 24 months.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.7</label>
                <title>Risks and adverse effects</title>
                <p>The procedures used in this intervention are currently used as standard treatments for clinical care. The risks for the participants are minimal and basically the same as those of patients that are exposed to these procedures during routine clinical care. Although there are very few reported cases of allergies or hypersensitivity to these products, it will be necessary to question the parents about possible reactions to some of the compounds of the Duraphat varnish or the Clinpro sealer.<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> Adverse events and other unintended effects of trial interventions will be reported to the committee of the university where the protocol was approved. The study will be audited every 6 months, and will be carried out by the IRB.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.8</label>
                <title>Measuring the effectiveness of the intervention</title>
                <p>The primary results for this project are the incidence of caries at 6, 12, 18, and 24 months between the sealant and varnish groups.</p>
                <p>The incidence of dental caries considers the measurement of the existence (or not) of visible changes in the surface of the enamel compared to the basal measurement. In the clinical evaluation, visual caries detection and a standardized and international caries measurement system, known as International Caries Detection and Measurement System (ICDAS), will be used.</p>
                <p>The reviews will occur every 6 months for a 24-month period.</p>
                <sec>
                  <label>2.8.1</label>
                  <title>International caries detection and measurement system (ICDAS)</title>
                  <p>ICDAS is a caries measurement system that uses the visual method to detect caries. It can measure carious lesions at the subclinical stage; ICDAS considers coloration changes sufficient to identify lesions in the incipient stages and does not recommend the use of explorers.</p>
                  <p>This measurement system examines five surfaces and uses codes that range from 0 to 6, depending on the severity of the injury, where 0 indicates a healthy surface.<sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> This system also evaluates the condition of the surface in terms of restorations, where it uses codes that range from 0 to 8, depending on the type of restoration used.<sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> For this study, the examiners will be calibrated and previously standardized (Kappa &gt; 0.80).</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.9</label>
                <title>Estimation of costs</title>
                <p>The estimation of the costs of the interventions will be from the perspective of the service provider, i.e., all the human and material inputs necessary for the implementation of these two interventions will be identified and included. The unit and average cost of each one of the interventions will be estimated in the same evaluation periods; afterward, it will be determined which of the two interventions is more cost-effective for reducing the incidence of caries.</p>
                <p>The cost estimate will include costs related to the training of the personnel that will apply each of the technologies, number of people needed for the application, salaries, and application time, number of control reviews, as well as the costs of purchasing the material and instruments.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.10</label>
                <title>Sample size</title>
                <p>The sample size was calculated using a formula for the difference of proportions. The proportions used in this calculation were the decreases in incidence reported with the use of fluoride varnish (60%) and PFS (40%), a power of 80%, and an α of 95%, which gave a sample size of 97 subjects. In the end, 15% more subjects were added due to the losses to follow-up reported in longitudinal studies, which amounted to 114 subjects for each group.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.11</label>
                <title>Recruitment</title>
                <p>The first thing that will be done in this process will be to obtain permission to conduct the study from the corresponding school authorities. For this, it is necessary to deliver a printed protocol to the school addresses of the area; once the study is authorized by the authorities, the following step will be to obtain permission from each of the schools that will participate in the intervention.</p>
                <p>The next step is to obtain, through meetings with the parents, authorization for their children to participate in the investigation through the signing of informed consent forms.</p>
                <p>Once informed consent has been obtained, the children will be reviewed to identify possible candidates for the study according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Once the established sample size has been reached, the participants will be randomly assigned to one of the intervention groups.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.12</label>
                <title>Assignment for each intervention group</title>
                <p>For the randomization process, the total number of candidates will be included in an Excel database; Excel includes a random number function, which will be used in the randomization process.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.13</label>
                <title>Blinding and masking</title>
                <p>In this study, the type of blinding that will be applied will be simple since the participants will not know what type of technology will be used in each individual. To guarantee this, the subjects will not observe the applications that the other participants will receive. This implies that the subjects will pass individually and be isolated from the other subjects during their participation. In addition, a very similar protocol will be carried out for the application, such as prophylaxis, and therefore the participant will not know what type of treatment will be applied.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.14</label>
                <title>Data collection and analysis</title>
                <p>The information will be collected through primary sources of information, that is, structured odontograms for research. The data will be stored in an Excel database, where the cells will be censored to reduce errors during data capture. For the analysis, the database will be exported to Stata 14.0, where a univariate analysis will be carried out first and followed by a bivariate analysis to find associations between the dependent and independent variables. Non-parametric statistical tests will be used due to the variables’ measurement scale.</p>
                <sec>
                  <label>2.14.1</label>
                  <title>Collection and analysis of the data regarding caries incidence</title>
                  <p>The incidence of dental caries will be analyzed using the ICDAS at 6, 12, 18, and 24 months after the intervention. The data will be collected by a researcher trained in this measurement system.<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> The collected data will be captured according to the codes established in the ICDAS manual.</p>
                  <p>Caries status</p>
                  <p>0 = Sound</p>
                  <p>1 = First visual change in enamel (whitespot seen after 5 s air drying).</p>
                  <p>2 = Distinct visual change in enamel (whitespot seen without air drying).</p>
                  <p>3 = Localized enamel breakdown due to caries with no visible dentin</p>
                  <p>4 = Non-cavitated surface with underlying dark shadow from dentin</p>
                  <p>5 = Distinct cavity with visible dentin</p>
                  <p>6 = Extensive distinct cavity with visible dentin. An extensive cavity involves at least half of a tooth surface and possibly reaching the pulp.</p>
                  <p>7 = Tooth extracted because of caries (tooth surfaces will be coded 97)</p>
                  <p>8 = Tooth extracted for reasons other than caries (tooth surfaces will be coded 98)</p>
                  <p>9 = Unerupted (tooth surfaces coded 99)</p>
                  <p>In each of the measurements, the change occurred in the occlusal surfaces of the first permanent molars between the two preventive treatments used to determine which is more effective in preventing caries in each of the established periods.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <label>2.14.2</label>
                  <title>Analysis of the cost of the intervention</title>
                  <p>Once the direct cost of the interventions is obtained, the cost-effectiveness ratios will be generated as recommended in the literature.<sup>[<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</sup></p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Dental caries is one of the most frequent problems of the oral cavity. It affects more than half of the child population worldwide and is the leading cause of tooth loss in children and young adults.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> At present, there are different preventive methods that allow practitioners reduce the incidence of caries, among which the methods used in this intervention stand out; however, in Mexico, such work is still very scarce. The design of the present study will allow us to compare the effectiveness of both technologies and determine the total cost and cost-effectiveness of each. The information generated by this work can contribute to the decision-making of health planners.</p>
              <p>In Mexico, the use of technologies that prevent oral diseases, other than those derived from fluoride, is limited, e.g., the low rate of use of PFSs reported by the Epidemiological Surveillance System for Oral Pathologies.<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>The benefit of carrying out preventive programs in children is that they improve the subjects’ quality of life, reduce the risks of general disease, and reduce future out-of-pocket expenses for the population and health systems associated with the treatment of this disease.<sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</sup> Results will be disseminated in Mexican and international scientific and professional venues.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Edith Lara-Carrillo, Rogelio José Scougall-Vilchis, América Patricia Pontigo-Loyola, Leticia Ávila-Burgos, Juan Fernando Casanova-Rosado, Alejandro José Casanova-Rosado, Mirna Minaya-Sánchez, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Edith Lara-Carrillo, Rogelio José Scougall-Vilchis, Leticia Ávila-Burgos, Juan Fernando Casanova-Rosado, Alejandro José Casanova-Rosado, Mirna Minaya-Sánchez, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> América Patricia Pontigo-Loyola, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Edith Lara-Carrillo, Rogelio José Scougall-Vilchis, América Patricia Pontigo-Loyola, Leticia Ávila-Burgos, Juan Fernando Casanova-Rosado, Alejandro José Casanova-Rosado, Mirna Minaya-Sánchez, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Edith Lara-Carrillo, Rogelio José Scougall-Vilchis, América Patricia Pontigo-Loyola, Leticia Ávila-Burgos, Juan Fernando Casanova-Rosado, Alejandro José Casanova-Rosado, Mirna Minaya-Sánchez, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Project administration:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera.</p>
              <p><bold>Resources:</bold> Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Edith Lara-Carrillo, Rogelio José Scougall-Vilchis, América Patricia Pontigo-Loyola, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Validation:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Edith Lara-Carrillo, Rogelio José Scougall-Vilchis, América Patricia Pontigo-Loyola, Leticia Ávila-Burgos, Juan Fernando Casanova-Rosado, Alejandro José Casanova-Rosado, Mirna Minaya-Sánchez, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> Miguel Ángel Fernández-Barrera, Edith Lara-Carrillo, Rogelio José Scougall-Vilchis, América Patricia Pontigo-Loyola, Leticia Ávila-Burgos, Juan Fernando Casanova-Rosado, Alejandro José Casanova-Rosado, Mirna Minaya-Sánchez, Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís.</p>
              <p>Carlo Eduardo Medina-Solís orcid: 0000-0002-1410-9491.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="abbr">
                <p>Abbreviations: FPM = first permanent molars, ICDAS = International Caries Detection and Measurement System, SIGN = Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Protocol version: first</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Universal trial number: U1111-1220-3045</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>International registry: Clinical Trial Register Sri Lankan</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Trial Application No: APPL/2018/052</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Registration number: SLCTR/2019/009</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>IRB: Committee of Ethics and Research, Autonomous University of Hidalgo State</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Approval number: Cinv/148/2018</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p>Competing financial interests: This study was supported by a scholarship from the National Council of Science and Technology of Mexico (CONACyT). This research was partially supported by a grant to fieldwork from the Program for Strengthening Quality in Educational Institutions (Programa de Fortalecimiento de la Calidad en Instituciones Educativas—PROFOCIE). Publication supported by the Ministry of Education, Mexican Federal Government, through of The Faculty Development Program (PRODEP).</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Data availability statement: Data is available on request from the authors.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>[1]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Informative note N° 314; April 2012</article-title>. <comment>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs318/es/">https://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs318/es/</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation>[Accessed on 20 March 2019]</date-in-citation></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>[2]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>CVR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Normando</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of oral health on quality life of urban and riverine populations of Amazon: A multilevel analysis</article-title>. <source>PLos One</source><year>2028</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<elocation-id>e0208096</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>[3]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez-Cabezas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chemistry of caries: remineralization and demineralization events with direct clinical relevance</article-title>. <source>Dent Clin North Am</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<elocation-id>469</elocation-id>–<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20630190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>[4]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruzda-Zwiech</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipinska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Borowska-Struginska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Caries experience and distribution by tooth in primary molars in the pre-school child population of Lodz, Poland</article-title>. <source>Oral Health Prev Dent</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<elocation-id>557</elocation-id>–<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26106648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>[5]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chavarría-Bolaños</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinosa-Ramírez</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dental caries prevalence in first permanent molar among patients from the Universidad Cooperativa de Colombia (2006–2011)</article-title>. <source>Univ Odontol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<elocation-id>217</elocation-id>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>[6]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caries process on occlusal surfaces: envolving evidence and understanding</article-title>. <source>Caries Res</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<elocation-id>339</elocation-id>–<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24577073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>[7]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muller-Bolla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Courson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Droz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Definition of at-risk occlusal surfaces of permanent molars: a descriptive study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pediatr Dent</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<elocation-id>35</elocation-id>–<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19953807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>[8]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kotsanos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of posteruptive age of enamel on its susceptibility to artificial caries</article-title>. <source>Caries Res</source><year>1991</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<elocation-id>241</elocation-id>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1913761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>[9]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tassery</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Levallois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Terrer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of new minimum intervention dentistry technologies in caries management</article-title>. <source>Aust Dent J</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<elocation-id>40</elocation-id>–<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23721337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>[10]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yon</surname><given-names>MJY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Medical model in caries management</article-title>. <source>Dent J</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<elocation-id>E37</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>[11]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frencken</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwendicke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contemporary operative caries management: consensus recommendations on minimally invasive caries removal</article-title>. <source>Br Dent J</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>223</volume>:<elocation-id>215</elocation-id>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28798430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>[12]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Mullane</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baez</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fluoride and oral health</article-title>. <source>Community Dent Health</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<elocation-id>69</elocation-id>–<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27352462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>[13]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seppä</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluoride varnishes in caries prevention</article-title>. <source>Med Princ Pract</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<elocation-id>307</elocation-id>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15467304</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>[14]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cvikl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pits and fissure sealants: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>Dent J</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<elocation-id>1</elocation-id>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>[15]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naaman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Housseny</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alamoudi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of pit and fissure sealants-a literature review</article-title>. <source>Dent J</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>E34</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>[16]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernández-Martínez</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles-Bermeo</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lara-Carrillo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with dental caries in primary and permanent dentition in patients aged 2 to 12 years who attended a university clinic</article-title>. <source>West Indian Med J</source>; <comment>In press. DOI: 10.7727/wimj.2017.120</comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>[17]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>García-Cortés</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Loyola-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Loyola-Leyva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Socio-behavioral factors associated to caries prevalence and dmft index in adolescents and young adults in a developing country</article-title>. <source>West Indian Med J</source>; <comment>In press. DOI: 10.7727/wimj.2016.515</comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>[18]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casanova-Rosado</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallejos-Sánchez</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Minaya-Sánchez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toothbrushing frequency and maternal schooling associated with caries in primary dentition in 6- and 7-year-old children</article-title>. <source>West Indian Med J</source>; <comment>In press. DOI: 10.7727/wimj.2016.481</comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>[19]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas-Rincón</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles-Bermeo</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lara-Carrillo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interproximal caries lesions and premature loss of teeth in the primary dentition as risk factors for space loss in the posterior sector: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<elocation-id>e14875</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30882692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>[20]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina-Solís</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallejos-Sánchez</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontigo-Loyola</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Results of a national survey on treatment needs and index of care for dental caries in schoolchildren</article-title>. <source>Impacto Odontológico</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<elocation-id>33</elocation-id>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>[21]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>López-Gomez</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Villalobos-Rodelo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ávila-Burgos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between premature loss of primary teeth with oral hygiene, consumption of soft drinks, dental care and previous caries experience</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<elocation-id>21147</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26916132</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>[22]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallejos-Sánchez</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Minaya-Sánchez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanova-Rosado</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Caries severity using a criterion according to size of lesion among Mexican schoolchildren</article-title>. <source>Rev Univ Ind Santander Salud</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<elocation-id>291</elocation-id>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>[23]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martínez-Pérez</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Monjarás-Ávila</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Patiño-Marín</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiologic study on dental caries and treatment needs in schoolchildren aged six to twelve years from San Luis Potosi</article-title>. <source>Rev Invest Clin</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<elocation-id>206</elocation-id>–<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20815125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>[24]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina-Solis</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Maupomé</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelcastre-Villafuerte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic inequalities in oral health: dental caries in 6 to 12 year-old children</article-title>. <source>Rev Invest Clin</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<elocation-id>296</elocation-id>–<lpage>304</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17146941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>[25]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casanova-Rosado</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina-Solís</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanova-Rosado</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dental caries and associated factor in Mexican schoolchildren aged 6-13 years</article-title>. <source>Acta Odontol Scand</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<elocation-id>245</elocation-id>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>[26]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Ministry of Health</collab>. <article-title>System of Epidemiological Surveillance of Oral Pathologies, 10 years monitoring the oral health of Mexicans</article-title>; <year>2015</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://187.191.75.115/gobmx/salud/documentos/info_sivepab/SIVEPAB_10moaniv.pdf">http://187.191.75.115/gobmx/salud/documentos/info_sivepab/SIVEPAB_10moaniv.pdf</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation>[Accessed 20 March 2019]</date-in-citation></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>[27]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina-Solís</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontigo-Loyola</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Maupomé</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dental fluorosis prevalence and diagnostic test using Dean's index based on 6 teeth, and on 28 teeth</article-title>. <source>Clin Oral Investig</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>197</elocation-id>–<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>[28]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina-Solís</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ávila-Burgos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Márquez-Corona</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Out-of-pocket expenditures on dental care for schoolchildren aged 6 to 12 years: a cross-sectional estimate in a less-developed country setting</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<elocation-id>1997</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>[29]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><comment>Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network: Preventing Dental Caries in Children at High Caries Risk—Targeted prevention of dental caries in the permanent teeth of 6–16 year olds presenting for dental care, Volume 47. Edinburgh: Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network</comment>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>[30]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isaksson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Björkner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contact allergy to Duraphat</article-title>. <source>Scand J Dent Res</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<elocation-id>49</elocation-id>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8441896</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>[31]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allergy contact stomatitis from colophony</article-title>. <source>Dent Update</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<elocation-id>440</elocation-id>–<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17036833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>[32]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallström</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adverse reaction to a fissure sealant: report of case</article-title>. <source>ASDC J Dent Child</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<elocation-id>143</elocation-id>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8486859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>[33]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shivakumar</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandu</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>International Caries Detection and Assessment System: a new paradigm in detection of dental caries</article-title>. <source>J Conserv Dent</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>10</elocation-id>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20379434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>[34]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banting</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggertsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekstrand</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Criteria Manual: International Caries Detection and Assessment System (ICDAS II)</article-title>. <source>International Caries Detection and Assessment System Coordinating Committee</source>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>[35]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dikmen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ICDAS II criteria (international caries detection and assessment system)</article-title>. <source>J Istanb Univ Fac Dent</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<elocation-id>63</elocation-id>–<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28955548</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>[36]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santamaría-Benhumea</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera-Villalobos</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sil-Jaimes</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure, systems, and cost analysis of hospital care</article-title>. <source>Rev Med Inv</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<elocation-id>134</elocation-id>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>[37]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The global burden of oral diseases and risk to oral health</article-title>. <source>Bull World Health Organ</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<elocation-id>661</elocation-id>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16211157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
