<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:37:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10031723" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10031723</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-03-22</datestamp>
        <setSpec>phenaturepg</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Oral Investig</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Oral Investig</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Clinical Oral Investigations</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1432-6981</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1436-3771</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10031723</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10031723</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10031723</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36947263</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36947263</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4940</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00784-023-04940-4</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Microbial adherence on vacuum-formed retainers with different surface roughness as constructed from conventional stone models and 3D printed models: a randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Belayutham</surname>
                    <given-names>Sonia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wan Hassan</surname>
                    <given-names>Wan Nurazreena</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>wannurazreena@um.edu.my</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Razak</surname>
                    <given-names>Fathilah Abdul</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mohd Tahir</surname>
                    <given-names>Norhidayah Nor zahidah</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10347.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2308 5949</institution-id><institution>Department of Paediatric Dentistry and Orthodontics, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Universiti Malaya, </institution></institution-wrap>Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10347.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2308 5949</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral and Craniofacial Sciences, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Universiti Malaya, </institution></institution-wrap>Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>27</volume>
              <issue>6</issue>
              <fpage>3245</fpage>
              <lpage>3259</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2023. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p id="Par1">This single center parallel, randomized controlled trial aimed to determine the propensity of microbial adherence on vacuum-formed retainers (VFRs) with different surface roughness imprints.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Materials and methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">Thirty-six patients debonded from fixed appliances at a teaching institution were allocated by block randomization stratified for gender to three groups [VFRs fabricated on conventional, fused deposition modeling (FDM) or stereolithography apparatus (SLA) working models]. Participants wore the VFRs for three months full-time followed by three months part-time. VFRs were collected after each follow-up for <italic>Streptococcus</italic> and yeast counts. Surface roughness was measured indirectly on the working models using a 3D optical surface texture analyzer. Blinding was not feasible due to appliance appearance. The trial was registered [NCT03844425 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>)] and funded by the Universiti Malaya Dental Postgraduate Research Grant (DPRG/14/19).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">Thirty participants (eleven conventional, ten FDM, and nine SLA) were analyzed after six dropped out. No harms were reported. Microbial counts between the groups were not significantly different. There were more microbes in the lower VFRs than upper VFRs (total count: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05; effect size, 0.5 during full-time wear and 0.4 during part-time wear). SLA had significantly (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) smoother surface than FDM (effect size, 0.3) and conventional models (effect size, 0.5). Microbial adherence was not associated with working model surface roughness.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">Microbial adherence on VFRs was not influenced by degree of surface roughness imprints from working models.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Clinical relevance</title>
                  <p id="Par5">3D printed models can be used to make VFRs. Lower VFRs tended to accumulate oral microbes, potentially increasing the oral health risk in the lower arch.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Vacuum-formed retainers</kwd>
                <kwd>Surface roughness</kwd>
                <kwd>Fused deposition modeling</kwd>
                <kwd>Stereolithography apparatus</kwd>
                <kwd>
                  <italic>Streptococcus</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>
                  <italic>Candida</italic>
                </kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par6">Oral appliances can alter the oral environment and promote changes in the oral microbiota [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The surfaces of orthodontic appliances can harbor microorganisms in the form of biofilm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], leading to the onset of caries and periodontitis. The most common oral bacteria related to caries and periodontal disease such as chronic marginal gingivitis include streptococci, typically the <italic>S. mutans</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], <italic>S. sanguinis</italic>, and <italic>S. milleri</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Other microbes such as <italic>Candida</italic> have also been isolated in children with high caries prevalence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and patients with periodontal disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Adhesion and colonization of <italic>Candida</italic> in the oral cavity under a compromised condition may lead to candidiasis.</p>
              <p id="Par7">Vacuum-formed retainers (VFRs), which are used to maintain the position of corrected dental alignment, are fabricated by heating polyvinyl chloride sheets followed by vacuum- or pressure-formed procedure over the working casts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Its appearance has made it the more accepted type of removable retainer by patients compared to Hawley retainers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Conventionally, the casts are made from stone or plaster, though three-dimensional (3D) printing technology such as fused deposition modeling (FDM) and stereolithography apparatus (SLA) have made it possible to reconstruct 3D image data of study models to 3D replicas from resins with sufficient strength and heat resistance for the vacuum-formed retainer (VFR) fabrication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. VFRs made on 3D printed models are as effective as conventionally made VFRs for retention. However, they are subtly different as the functional dental surfaces appear coarser corresponding to the imprints of striated 3D model surfaces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par8">Salivary bacteria of patients in the retention phase showed a general decrease in patients who wore VFR compared to those using bonded retainer and Hawley retainer, with VFR showing significant reduction after 13 weeks compared to baseline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The design of VFR also makes it a conducive oral environment as it provides additional surface for colonization of microbes especially after prolong use, as early as 60 days after being issued [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. An increased population of the aciduric microbes may increase the risk of decalcification if cariogenic diet is regularly consumed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and periodontal attachment loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], if oral hygiene is neglected. The fabrication of VFR on 3D printed model may produce surfaces with variable dental surface finishing, depending on the type of printing used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. There is possibility that a rough surface finishing of the VFR may support microbial adherence and, thus, lead to increased microbial load in the oral cavity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. An increase in microbial adhesion would potentially impose increased risk on oral health.</p>
              <p id="Par9">In terms of duration for wear, a systematic review found no difference in full-time or part-time wear for VFR to prevent changes in arch width and arch length [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, there is insufficient evidence in the risk of microbial adherence between full-time or part-time wear.</p>
              <p id="Par10">This study aimed to determine the propensity of microbial adherence on VFRs with different surface roughness imprints. The objectives of this study were (1) to investigate the propensity for microbial adherence on VFRs, particularly with increasing surface roughness imprints as made from using different types of working models; (2) to compare microbial adherence between the upper and lower VFRs with different surface roughness; and (3) to compare microbial adherence on VFRs with different surface roughness between full-time and part-time wear.</p>
              <p id="Par11">The null hypotheses were as follows: (1) there was no difference in microbial adherence on VFRs constructed on conventional models and 3D printed models; (2) there was no difference in microbial adherence between the upper and lower VFRs with different surface roughness; (3) there was no difference in microbial adherence on VFRs with different surface roughness between full-time wear and part-time wear.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Trial design</title>
                <p id="Par12">This was a randomized controlled trial with three parallel assignments and allocation ratio of 1:1:1. This single center study was conducted at the Faculty of Dentistry, Universiti Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. The recruitment started from September 2019 until June 2020. The trial began in December 2019 and was completed in April 2021.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Participants, eligibility criteria, and setting</title>
                <p id="Par13">Patients ready for debond after fixed appliance treatment at Faculty of Dentistry, Universiti Malaya, were screened. The inclusion criteria were healthy patients with no systemic disease who were planned for VFRs for retention. The exclusion criteria were those in sectional or single arch fixed appliances treatment, planned for other retention types, smokers, and with systemic disease that may affect salivary flow.</p>
                <p id="Par14">Participants were given the patient information sheet and a detailed explanation of the clinical trial. Participation was voluntary. Recruited participants gave written consent prior to commencement of the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Interventions</title>
                <p id="Par15">Upon debonding, three sets of upper and lower alginate impressions (Hydrogum 5, Zhermack, Italy) were taken to construct the post-treatment study model and two sets of working models. Working models were used to fabricate the standard VFRs and the first set of interventional retainers. In the conventional group, an additional set of alginate impressions was taken to cast another working model for the second interventional retainers. The standard VFRs were issued on the same day of the debonding appointment. Participants were instructed to wear the standard VFRs full-time.</p>
                <sec id="Sec6">
                  <title>Fabrication of the working models</title>
                  <p id="Par16">The alginate impressions were disinfected before casting using green stone (Profilare 100, Dentona, Germany). The stone model contained all involved dentition and the alveolar process. The stone working models were scanned with a structured light scanner (Maestro 3D, Age Solutions, Inc., Italy) using the EasyDentalScan software (Age Solutions, Inc., Italy) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The 3D images of the conventional models were saved as stereolithographic (.stl) files. The FDM working model was made using the Ultimaker S3 machine (Ultimaker, Zaltbommel, Netherlands) at a layer resolution of 60–150 microns, while the SLA working model was made using Formlab Form 3 machine (Formlab, Somerville, Massachusetts) at a layer resolution of 25 microns.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="Sec7">
                  <title>Fabrication of the interventional vacuum-formed retainers</title>
                  <p id="Par17">The interventional VFR was made from a thermoformed material (Erkodur by Erkodent®, Erich Kopp GmbH, Pfalzgrafenweiler, Germany) with 1.0 mm thickness according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The foil was heated and pressed against the upper and lower models individually using an automated pressure-forming unit (Erkopress ES-200E by Erkodent®, Erich Kopp GmbH, Pfalzgrafenweiler, Germany). After it had been left to cool, the foil was removed from the model and trimmed using a straight handpiece and finishing burs. The retainer was trimmed until half of the occlusal surface of the last molar tooth covered and the marginal extension of the retainer was 1–2 mm buccal and 3–4 mm lingual to the gingiva margins. The sharp edges of the retainer were smoothened using sandpaper and cleaned.</p>
                  <p id="Par18">The upper and lower interventional retainers were then placed in a covered plastic container filled with antibacterial mouthwash that contained chlorhexidine digluconate 0.12% (Oradex, Pahang Pharmacy Sdn Bhd, Malaysia). The retainers were left to soak overnight before being issued to the participant the following day to ensure that the retainers were sterile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] at the beginning of each trial stage.</p>
                  <p id="Par19">The same procedure was repeated to construct the second interventional VFRs. The conventional group used the second set working model fabricated at debond. The FDM and SLA groups used the same working models that were used to fabricate the first interventional VFRs. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the different types of working models.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Working models (top) and their respective vacuum-formed retainer (bottom). The working models were made from <bold>A</bold> conventional stone, <bold>B</bold> fused-deposition modeling 3D model, and C stereolithography apparatus 3D model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="784_2023_4940_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="Sec8">
                  <title>Interventional procedure</title>
                  <p id="Par20">Participants were reviewed one-week post-debond (T0). The standard VFRs were returned to the investigator (SB). The first interventional VFRs were issued, and participants were advised to wear the retainers full-time except during meals, brushing and cleaning of the appliance. They were supplied with a new retainer box and a new toothbrush to clean their appliances. Participants were reminded regularly to wear their retainers full-time for three months by SB, who sent reminder mobile messages once a week.</p>
                  <p id="Par21">Participants were reviewed at 3 months post-debond (T1). The first interventional VFRs were removed from participants’ mouth and placed in a covered plastic container filled with phosphate-buffered saline solution (PBS) before being transported to the microbiology laboratory. Participants returned the retainer box and toothbrush provided earlier. The second interventional VFRs were issued, and participants were advised to wear the retainers part-time for 10 h per day. They were given another new retainer box to keep their retainers when they are not used and a new toothbrush to clean their appliances. Participants were reminded regularly to wear their retainers 10 h per day for another 3 months by SB, who sent reminder mobile messages once a week.</p>
                  <p id="Par22">Participants were reviewed again at 6 months post-debond (T2). The appointments were in the morning so that patients were still wearing their retainers within the 10 h per day regime. The second interventional VFRs were removed from the participant’s mouth and placed in a covered plastic container filled with PBS before being transported to the microbiology laboratory. Participants were issued with the previously kept standard VFRs and advised to continue wearing the VFRs part-time.</p>
                  <p id="Par23">The appliance care and hygiene instructions were standardized for all the participants. They were instructed to clean their appliances using the new soft bristle toothbrush given during every review appointment and under running water only. Any type of soap or toothpaste was not allowed for cleansing of the appliances. Participants were informed not to use any type of mouthwash throughout the study period. They were also not allowed to soak their appliances in mouthwash or appliance cleanser. During part-time wear, the participants were asked to clean their appliances first using the soft bristle toothbrush and under running water. Then, the appliances were placed in a covered plastic container which was given during their review appointment and soaked in water only. Participants were also asked to clean the appliances again before wearing.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Outcomes</title>
                <sec id="Sec10">
                  <title>Primary outcome measure</title>
                  <p id="Par24">The primary outcome measure was microbial colony count on the VFRs.</p>
                  <p id="Par25">Clinical specimens and all microbial work were done under the laminar flow cabinet (ERLA CFM Series, Australia) to ensure sterile working environment and to prevent contamination of specimens and procedures. Brain heart infusion (BHI, Difco) agar and broth enriched growth media were used to determine the total microbial count. Mitis Salivarius Agar (MSA, Difco) was used for streptococci count and Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (SDA, Difco) for yeast count.</p>
                  <p id="Par26">All media in powder form was weighed appropriately according to the preparation manual, using an analytical balance (Mettler Toledo AJ100J, USA). The powder was dissolved in distilled water, boiled, and later sterilized at 121 °C for 15 min in an autoclave (HICLA VE HVE-50, Hirayama, Japan). Once cooled, the media were aseptically poured into petri dishes and labeled accordingly. Then, the sterile agar plates and broth media were packed and placed in a chiller (Mutiara, Malaysia) at 4 °C for later use.</p>
                  <p id="Par27">The upper and lower VFRs collected at T1 and T2 were placed into separate plastic containers filled with 150 ml of BHI broth using a sterile tweezer. The retainers were sonicated in a water bath (Grants SS-40-A2, Cambridge, England) and then vortexed for 60 s using a vortex mixer (Snijders Scientific, Holland) to dislodge any attached microorganisms.</p>
                  <p id="Par28">A 100 μl volume of broth from the plastic container containing the dislodged microorganisms was pipetted out and added into three microcentrifuge tubes, each containing 900 μl of BHI broth. Serial dilution was performed on the three microfuge tubes to produce three dilutions — 10<sup>1</sup>, 10<sup>2</sup> and 10<sup>3</sup>. This procedure was performed separately for both the upper and lower retainers.</p>
                  <p id="Par29">Then 50 μl of the suspension from each tube was pipetted out and inoculated on three separate BHI agar plates, three separate MSA agar plates, and three separate SDA agar plates. The plates were incubated in an incubator (Memmert, Germany) at 37 °C for 18 to 24 h. Following incubation, the plates with dilution that gave a colony forming unit (CFU) count between 30 and 300 for all the three types of agars were selected for enumeration. The growth population (CFU/mL) was calculated using the formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{Total}\;\mathrm{growth}\;\mathrm{population}\frac{\mathrm{CFU}}{\mathrm{mL}}=\frac{\mathrm{Number}\;\mathrm{of}\;\mathrm{grown}\;\mathrm{colonies}}{\mathrm{Dilution}\;\mathrm{factor}\;\mathrm x\;\mathrm{Volume}\;\mathrm{used}\;\left(\mathrm{mL}\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Total</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">growth</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">population</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CFU</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mL</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Number</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">of</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">grown</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">colonies</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Dilution</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">factor</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Volume</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">used</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mL</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="784_2023_4940_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                  <p id="Par30">The researcher (SB) was trained by a laboratory assistant (MAZ) to perform the microbial colony count. SB and MAZ, who was considered the gold standard, measured microbial colony count for inter-examiner reliability, while SB measured microbial colony count 2 weeks later for intra-examiner reliability. Intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) performed using two-way mixed model for consistency resulted intra-examiner ICC of 0.897 (95% CI 0.821–0.938; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and inter-examiner ICC of 0.948 (95% CI 0.915–0.967; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), which were considered good (ICC between 0.75 and 0.90) and excellent reliabilities (ICC above 0.90), respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="Sec11">
                  <title>Secondary outcome measure</title>
                  <p id="Par31">The secondary outcome measure was the surface roughness value (Ra) of the working models used to fabricate the VFRs, recorded in micrometers (μm). It is an indirect measure of the surface roughness of the VFRs at the dental surfaces, which recorded the imprints of the working models during VFR fabrication when the softened heated VFR foils were pressed to cling closely to the working models before it hardened at normal temperature.</p>
                  <p id="Par32">Surface roughness analysis was performed using a 3D optical surface texture analyzer (InfiniteFocus, Alicona, Austria) on the working models of the first interventional VFRs (<italic>N</italic>=36). The working models were measured instead of the VFRs because the analyzer was not able to measure transparent objects like the VFRs. Since the rapid non-contact optical 3D measurement procedure reliably measures flat surfaces, the midpoint at the labial surface of the upper right central incisor was standardized as a reference point for measurement. The working model was placed on the stage and the reference point was scanned at 20 times magnification.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Sample size calculation</title>
                <p id="Par33">Sample size was determined based on a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] using G*Power Software (Version 3.1.9.2). Sample size calculation was performed based on an alpha significance level of 0.05 and a beta of 0.20 to achieve 80% power to detect a significant difference between the groups. Based on the calculation, the total number of participants needed for the trial was 27 with a minimum of nine participants per group. After consideration of a dropout rate of 30 per cent, a total number of 36 participants were recruited for the trial.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec13">
                <title>Randomization (random number generation, allocation concealment, implementation)</title>
                <p id="Par34">Randomization was stratified by gender since women had shown better oral health behavior and oral hygiene compared to men [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], thus may affect microbial count if they were not fairly distributed between the groups. The proportion of male to female was set at 1:5 due to unequal gender proportions of uptake for orthodontic treatment at our institution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Therefore, for a sample size of 36, the study would need to recruit six males and thirty females.</p>
                <p id="Par35">Block randomization was performed for each stratified group using an online block randomization list generator (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sealedenvelope.com">www.sealedenvelope.com</ext-link>) by another researcher (WNWH) who was not involved in the clinical procedure. Therefore, a list was generated for male participants with a block size of six and another list was generated for female participants with block sizes of three, six, and nine. The random allocation sequences were kept in sealed dark envelopes, labeled for gender, and numbered accordingly. Participants’ assignment to three groups, either conventional, FDM, or SLA group based on the random allocation sequence, was revealed when the envelopes were opened on the day of appointment for debonding. Participants were given a blinding code for analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec14">
                <title>Blinding</title>
                <p id="Par36">This was an open label trial because blinding was not possible. Even though participants were not informed to which group the VFRs were made from, the dental surfaces of the VFRs had imprints of the working models, which had different surface finishing. The researcher (SB) who enrolled the participants was not aware of the group allocation or block sizes until the envelopes were opened on the day of debonding appointment. However, subsequently SB could not be blinded of the participants’ group allocation since the same researcher performed all the laboratory and clinical procedures.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec15">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par37">SPSS was used to data analysis by another researcher (NMT) not involved in the laboratory and clinical procedures. The baseline data was tested for differences between the interventional groups. Chi-square test was used to compare for gender and ethnicity differences, while one way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare for age differences. Differences in compliance rates between groups at T1 and T2 were compared using chi-square test.</p>
                <p id="Par38">Shapiro-Wilk test used to assess for normality of the outcome measures showed that the data was not normally distributed (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05); thus, non-parametric analyses were applied.</p>
                <p id="Par39">Microbial adherence between the interventional groups and surface roughness measurement of the working models of the groups were compared using Kruskal-Wallis test. If there were any statistically significant differences between the mean ranks, Dunn’s post-hoc test with Bonferroni adjustment used to determine which group or groups were different from the others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The effect size was calculated (<italic>η</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>) where <italic>η</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 0.01 was considered small, <italic>η</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 0.059 was considered medium and <italic>η</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>= 0.138 was considered large [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par40">Wilcoxon signed-rank test was performed to compare microbial adherence between upper and lower retainers and between full-time and part-time wear. Follow-up analysis on effect size (<italic>r</italic>) was calculated where <italic>r</italic> = 0.1 was considered small, <italic>r</italic> = 0.3 was considered medium, and <italic>r</italic> = 0.5 was considered large [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par41">Kendall’s tau-b was used to test the association between surface roughness and microbial adherence. A value close to zero showed no association while a value close to 1 indicated strong association.</p>
                <p id="Par42">For all analyses, a <italic>p</italic> value of less than 0.05 was considered significant.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec16">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec17">
                <title>Participant flow</title>
                <p id="Par43">The CONSORT flowchart (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) shows the number of participants randomly allocated to each group, follow-up, and the number of dropouts and their reasons for dropping out.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Consort flowchart. (VFR-CONV, vacuum-formed retainer conventionally made on stone; VFR-FDM, vacuum-formed retainer made on fused-deposition modeling 3D model; VFR-SLA, vacuum-formed retainer made on stereolithography apparatus 3D model)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="784_2023_4940_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par44">Recruitment of participants began in September 2019. Treatment commenced in December 2019 and was completed in April 2021. A total of 42 patients were screened for eligibility, but six were excluded because four of them did not fulfill the inclusion criteria and the other two were not interested. Thus, a total of 36 participants had participated in the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec18">
                <title>Baseline data</title>
                <p id="Par45">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the baseline data for all three groups. Differences in the baseline gender, ethnicity, and age between the conventional group, FDM group, and SLA group were not statistically significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05). The compliance rates between the groups at T1 and T2 were also not significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Participant characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="2">Characteristics</th><th colspan="4">Distribution</th><th rowspan="3"><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th>Total (<italic>N</italic>=30)</th><th>Conventional (<italic>n</italic>=11)</th><th>FDM (<italic>n</italic>=10)</th><th>SLA (<italic>n</italic>=9)</th></tr><tr><th><italic>N</italic> (%)</th><th><italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th><italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th><italic>n</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">Gender</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="2"> Male</td><td>6 (16.7)</td><td>2 (18.2)</td><td>2 (20.0)</td><td>1 (11.1)</td><td>0.861<sup>π</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"> Female</td><td>30 (83.3)</td><td>9 (81.8)</td><td>8 (80.0)</td><td>8 (88.9)</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Ethnicity</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="2"> Malay</td><td>16 (53.3)</td><td>7 (63.6)</td><td>6 (60.0)</td><td>4 (44.4)</td><td>0.935<sup>π</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"> Chinese</td><td>14 (46.7)</td><td>4 (36.4)</td><td>4 (40.0)</td><td>5 (55.6)</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="2">Age</td><td align="center">Mean (SD)</td><td align="center">Mean (SD)</td><td align="center">Mean (SD)</td><td align="center">Mean (SD)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>24.13 (6.38)</td><td>26.00 (7.34)</td><td>23.40 (5.89)</td><td>22.67 (5.77)</td><td align="right">0.476<sup>∞</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Compliance</td><td align="center"><italic>N</italic> (%)</td><td align="center"><italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center"><italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center"><italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">T1</td><td>Compliant</td><td>21 (70)</td><td>7 (63.6)</td><td>7 (70.0)</td><td>7 (77.8)</td><td align="right" rowspan="2">0.790<sup>π</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Non-compliant</td><td>9 (30)</td><td>4 (36.4)</td><td>3 (30.0)</td><td>2 (22.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="2">T2</td><td>Compliant</td><td>28 (93.3)</td><td>11(100.0)</td><td>9 (90.0)</td><td>8 (88.9)</td><td align="right" rowspan="2">0.414<sup>π</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Non-compliant</td><td>2 (6.7)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>1 (10.0)</td><td>1 (11.1)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>π</sup>Chi-square test. <sup>∞</sup>One-way ANOVA</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec19">
                <title>Numbers analyzed</title>
                <p id="Par46">In total, 36 participants who fulfilled the inclusion and exclusion criteria took part in this study. However, one participant from conventional group did not wear the VFRs at all, while two from the FDM group could not be contacted. Two from the SLA group were no longer interested in the study and one from the SLA group had relocated. The dropouts occurred from the first follow-up and were excluded from all the analyses. Therefore, the final analysis only included eleven participants from conventional group, ten participants from FDM group, and nine participants from SLA group.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec20">
                <title>Outcomes</title>
                <p id="Par47">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> summarizes the mean, standard deviation, and quartiles of the microbial counts and surface roughness for each group.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="9">Microbial adherence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Arch</td><td>Regime</td><td>Group</td><td><italic>N</italic></td><td>Mean (CFU)</td><td>SD</td><td>25th</td><td>50th (Median)</td><td>75th</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9">Total microbial count</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Upper</td><td rowspan="3">Full-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>1.150</td><td>0.936</td><td>0.180</td><td>1.110</td><td>1.550</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>12.455</td><td>16.764</td><td>0.200</td><td>1.525</td><td>25.118</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>8.170</td><td>7.986</td><td>1.550</td><td>2.110</td><td>16.170</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Lower</td><td rowspan="3">Full-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>14.373</td><td>16.071</td><td>0.600</td><td>5.130</td><td>33.730</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>19.754</td><td>22.446</td><td>2.713</td><td>14.270</td><td>30.053</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>13.026</td><td>5.639</td><td>8.165</td><td>14.030</td><td>17.800</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Upper</td><td rowspan="3">Part-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>7.457</td><td>14.674</td><td>0.260</td><td>0.440</td><td>4.820</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>5.035</td><td>5.294</td><td>2.008</td><td>2.615</td><td>7.483</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>8.846</td><td>12.079</td><td>0.735</td><td>2.340</td><td>21.635</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Lower</td><td rowspan="3">Part-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>10.383</td><td>17.706</td><td>0.350</td><td>2.880</td><td>15.470</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>19.034</td><td>22.023</td><td>1.520</td><td>3.130</td><td>44.135</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>13.651</td><td>24.163</td><td>1.340</td><td>1.620</td><td>28.970</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><italic>Streptococcus</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Upper</td><td rowspan="3">Full-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>4.612</td><td>11.032</td><td>0.960</td><td>1.570</td><td>1.720</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>15.448</td><td>21.207</td><td>0.773</td><td>3.430</td><td>27.930</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>13.203</td><td>17.221</td><td>0.965</td><td>3.170</td><td>27.400</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Lower</td><td rowspan="3">Full-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>18.475</td><td>19.665</td><td>1.970</td><td>11.470</td><td>39.270</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>19.754</td><td>22.446</td><td>2.713</td><td>14.270</td><td>30.053</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>14.712</td><td>8.989</td><td>7.020</td><td>12.070</td><td>23.065</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Upper</td><td rowspan="3">Part-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>11.104</td><td>17.580</td><td>0.290</td><td>0.520</td><td>15.000</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>5.035</td><td>5.294</td><td>2.008</td><td>2.615</td><td>7.483</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>8.846</td><td>8.846</td><td>8.846</td><td>8.846</td><td>8.846</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Lower</td><td rowspan="3">Part-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>11.720</td><td>18.296</td><td>0.260</td><td>2.890</td><td>21.870</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>19.034</td><td>19.034</td><td>19.034</td><td>19.034</td><td>19.034</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>13.651</td><td>13.651</td><td>13.651</td><td>13.651</td><td>13.651</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9">Yeast</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Upper</td><td rowspan="3">Full-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>0.933</td><td>1.084</td><td>0.070</td><td>0.330</td><td>2.380</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>3.052</td><td>4.176</td><td>0.050</td><td>0.180</td><td>6.250</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>0.971</td><td>1.213</td><td>0.005</td><td>0.060</td><td>2.165</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Lower</td><td rowspan="3">Full-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>6.288</td><td>7.789</td><td>0.170</td><td>3.470</td><td>10.530</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>6.000</td><td>6.000</td><td>6.000</td><td>6.000</td><td>6.000</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>2.432</td><td>2.432</td><td>2.432</td><td>2.432</td><td>2.432</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Upper</td><td rowspan="3">Part-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>1.892</td><td>2.947</td><td>0.200</td><td>0.210</td><td>4.500</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>1.902</td><td>2.131</td><td>0.780</td><td>1.230</td><td>2.405</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>1.030</td><td>1.908</td><td>0.040</td><td>0.180</td><td>1.440</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Lower</td><td rowspan="3">Part-time</td><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>3.394</td><td>4.544</td><td>0.130</td><td>1.330</td><td>9.730</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>6.908</td><td>9.921</td><td>1.023</td><td>1.930</td><td>10.275</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>0.583</td><td>0.583</td><td>0.583</td><td>0.583</td><td>0.583</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9">Surface roughness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"/><td rowspan="4"/><td>Group</td><td>N</td><td align="center">Mean (𝜇m)</td><td>SD</td><td>25th</td><td>50<sup>th</sup> (Median)</td><td>75th</td></tr><tr><td>Conventional</td><td>12</td><td>1.49</td><td>0.60</td><td>0.91</td><td>1.39</td><td>1.99</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>12</td><td>1.01</td><td>0.29</td><td>0.69</td><td>1.06</td><td>1.29</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>12</td><td>0.66</td><td>0.19</td><td>0.54</td><td>0.60</td><td>0.72</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>FDM</italic> fused deposition modeling, <italic>SLA</italic> stereolithography apparatus</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par48">There were no differences in the total microbial count, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count, and yeast count between the three groups during full-time and part-time wear on either the upper VFRs or lower VFRs (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Although there was a significant difference for the yeast count of the lower VFRs during the part-time regime, post hoc analysis did not find any differences between the groups.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of the microbial adherence on vacuum-formed retainers (VFR) with different surface roughness</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3">Arch</th><th rowspan="3">Microbes Group</th><th colspan="5">Full-time regime</th><th colspan="5">Part-time regime</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2"><italic>N</italic></th><th rowspan="2">Mean rank</th><th rowspan="2"><italic>p</italic> value</th><th colspan="2">Effect size</th><th rowspan="2"><italic>N</italic></th><th rowspan="2">Mean rank</th><th rowspan="2"><italic>p</italic> value</th><th colspan="2">Effect size</th></tr><tr><th>Value</th><th>Descriptor</th><th>Value</th><th>Descriptor</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="12">Upper</td><td>Total</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>11.09</td><td>0.056</td><td>0.199</td><td rowspan="3">Large</td><td>11</td><td>13.00</td><td>0.465</td><td>0.042</td><td rowspan="3">Small</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>15.75</td><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>17.60</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>20.61</td><td/><td/><td>9</td><td>16.22</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Streptococcus</italic></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>12.09</td><td>0.268</td><td>0.081</td><td rowspan="3">Medium</td><td>11</td><td>13.45</td><td>0.612</td><td>0.031</td><td rowspan="3">Small</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>17.30</td><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>16.30</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>17.67</td><td/><td/><td>9</td><td>17.11</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Yeast</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>15.73</td><td>0.443</td><td>0.056</td><td rowspan="3">Medium</td><td>11</td><td>16.00</td><td>0.241</td><td>0.110</td><td rowspan="3">Large</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>17.80</td><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>18.40</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>12.67</td><td/><td/><td>9</td><td>11.67</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Lower</td><td>Total</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>13.82</td><td>0.727</td><td>0.023</td><td rowspan="3">Small</td><td>11</td><td>13.73</td><td>0.479</td><td>0.051</td><td rowspan="3">Medium</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>16.40</td><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>18.20</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>16.56</td><td/><td/><td>9</td><td>14.67</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Streptococcus</italic></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>14.91</td><td>0.921</td><td>0.006</td><td rowspan="3">Small</td><td>11</td><td>12.55</td><td>0.287</td><td>0.086</td><td rowspan="3">Medium</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>16.40</td><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>18.60</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>15.22</td><td/><td/><td>9</td><td>15.67</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Yeast</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Conventional</td><td>11</td><td>17.00</td><td>0.090</td><td>0.166</td><td rowspan="3">Large</td><td>11</td><td>16.18</td><td>0.027*<sup>$</sup></td><td>0.184</td><td rowspan="3">Large</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td>10</td><td>18.60</td><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>20.20</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td>9</td><td>10.22</td><td/><td/><td>9</td><td>9.44</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05 by Kruskal-Wallis test. <sup>$</sup>Post hoc by Dunnett T3 showed no significant differences between the groups (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05). <italic>FDM</italic> fused deposition modeling, <italic>SLA</italic> stereolithography apparatus</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par49">During full-time wear when all VFRs were assessed collectively, the total microbial count, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count, and yeast count were significantly (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) more in the lower VFRs compared to the upper VFRs (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). When the VFRs were assessed based on groups, only the conventional group showed a similar trend of having significantly (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) more total microbial count, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count, and yeast count in the lower VFRs compared to the upper retainers. During part-time wear when all VFRs were assessed collectively, the total microbial count, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count, and yeast count were also significantly (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) more in the lower VFRs compared to the upper retainers. However, when the VFRs were assessed based on groups, the difference in microbial colony counts between the upper and lower VFRs was not significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the microbial adherence on vacuum-formed retainers (VFR) of different arches (upper vs lower)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Regime</th><th rowspan="2">Group</th><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="4">Overall</th><th colspan="4">Conventional</th><th colspan="4">FDM</th><th colspan="4">SLA</th></tr><tr><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean rank</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th><th>Effect size (descriptor)</th><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean rank</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th><th>Effect size (Descriptor)</th><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean rank</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th><th>Effect size (descriptor)</th><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean rank</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th><th>Effect size (descriptor)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="12">Full-time (upper vs lower)</td><td rowspan="4">Total</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>8<sup>a</sup></td><td>12.00</td><td>0.005*</td><td>0.513 (Large)</td><td>2<sup>a</sup></td><td>1.50</td><td>0.008*</td><td>0.805 (Large)</td><td>2<sup>a</sup></td><td>7.50</td><td>0.201</td><td>0.404 (Medium)</td><td>4<sup>a</sup></td><td>3.50</td><td>0.313</td><td>0.337 (Medium)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>22<sup>b</sup></td><td>16.77</td><td/><td/><td>9<sup>b</sup></td><td>7.00</td><td/><td/><td>8<sup>b</sup></td><td>5.00</td><td/><td/><td>5<sup>b</sup></td><td>6.20</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Strep.</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>9<sup>d</sup></td><td>13.22</td><td>0.019*</td><td>0.427 (Medium)</td><td>1<sup>d</sup></td><td>1.00</td><td>0.004*</td><td>0.856 (Large)</td><td>4<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td>0.331</td><td>0.307 (Medium)</td><td>4<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.00</td><td>0.440</td><td>0.258 (Medium)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>21<sup>e</sup></td><td>16.48</td><td/><td/><td>10<sup>e</sup></td><td>6.50</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>e</sup></td><td>6.17</td><td/><td/><td>5<sup>e</sup></td><td>5.80</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Yeast</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>6<sup>g</sup></td><td>11.50</td><td>0.004*</td><td>0.527 (Large)</td><td>2<sup>g</sup></td><td>1.50</td><td>0.012*</td><td>0.754 (Large)</td><td>2<sup>g</sup></td><td>7.50</td><td>0.201</td><td>0.404 (Medium)</td><td>2<sup>g</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td>0.395</td><td>0.283 (Medium)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>21<sup>h</sup></td><td>14.71</td><td/><td/><td>8<sup>h</sup></td><td>6.50</td><td/><td/><td>8<sup>h</sup></td><td>5.00</td><td/><td/><td>5<sup>h</sup></td><td>3.80</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>3<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>1<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Part-time (upper vs lower)</td><td rowspan="4">Total</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>9<sup>a</sup></td><td>12.78</td><td>0.016*</td><td>0.441 (Medium)</td><td>4<sup>a</sup></td><td>3.50</td><td>0.091</td><td>0.510 (Large)</td><td>2<sup>a</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td>0.092</td><td>0.534 (Large)</td><td>3<sup>a</sup></td><td>4.67</td><td>0.313</td><td>0.337 (Medium)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>21<sup>b</sup></td><td>16.67</td><td/><td/><td>7<sup>b</sup></td><td>7.43</td><td/><td/><td>8<sup>b</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>b</sup></td><td>5.17</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Strep.</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>10<sup>d</sup></td><td>12.20</td><td>0.023*</td><td>0.415 (Medium)</td><td>5<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.40</td><td>0.327</td><td>0.295 (Medium)</td><td>2<sup>d</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td>0.092</td><td>0.534 (Large)</td><td>3<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.00</td><td>0.212</td><td>0.416 (Medium)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>20<sup>e</sup></td><td>17.15</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>e</sup></td><td>7.33</td><td/><td/><td>8<sup>e</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>e</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Yeast</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>13<sup>g</sup></td><td>11.77</td><td>0.163*</td><td>0.245 (Small)</td><td>4<sup>g</sup></td><td>2.50</td><td>0.074</td><td>0.483 (Large)</td><td>4<sup>g</sup></td><td>3.50</td><td>0.167</td><td>0.437 (Medium)</td><td>5<sup>g</sup></td><td>6.20</td><td>0.312</td><td>0.337 (Medium)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>16<sup>h</sup></td><td>17.63</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>h</sup></td><td>7.50</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>h</sup></td><td>6.83</td><td/><td/><td>4<sup>h</sup></td><td>3.50</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>1<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>1<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Total microbial on lower VFR &lt; Total microbial on upper VFR</p><p><sup>b</sup>Total microbial on lower VFR &gt; Total microbial on upper VFR</p><p><sup>c</sup>Total microbial on lower VFR = Total microbial on upper VFR</p><p><sup>d</sup><italic>Streptococcus o</italic>n lower VFR &lt; <italic>Streptococcus</italic> on upper VFR</p><p><sup>e</sup><italic>Streptococcus</italic> on lower VFR &gt; <italic>Streptococcus</italic> on upper VFR</p><p><sup>f</sup><italic>Streptococcus</italic> on lower VFR = <italic>Streptococcus</italic> on upper VFR</p><p><sup>g</sup>Yeast on lower VFR &lt; Yeast on upper VFR</p><p><sup>h</sup>Yeast on lower VFR &gt; Yeast on upper VFR</p><p><sup>i</sup>Yeast on lower VFR = Yeast on lower VFR</p><p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 by Wilcoxon signed-rank test; <italic>FDM</italic>, fused deposition modeling; <italic>SLA</italic>, stereolithography apparatus.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par50">When assessing the upper VFRs alone, there were no differences in the total microbial count, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count, and yeast count between full-time and part-time wear, as assessed collectively or by each group (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Similarly, when assessing the lower VFRs alone, there were no differences in the total microbial count, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count, and yeast count between full-time and part-time wear (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of the microbial adherence on vacuum-formed retainers (VFR) of different retention regimes (full-time vs part-time)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Arch</th><th rowspan="2">Group</th><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="4">Overall</th><th colspan="4">Conventional</th><th colspan="4">FDM</th><th colspan="4">SLA</th></tr><tr><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean rank</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th><th>Effect size (Descriptor)</th><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean rank</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th><th>Effect size (Descriptor)</th><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean Rank</th><th><italic>p</italic>-value</th><th>Effect Size (Descriptor)</th><th><italic>N</italic></th><th>Mean rank</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th><th>Effect size (Descriptor)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="12">Upper (full-time vs part-time)</td><td rowspan="4">Total</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>14<sup>a</sup></td><td>14.36</td><td>0.964</td><td>0.008 (Small)</td><td>6<sup>a</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td>0.593</td><td>0.161 (Small)</td><td>4<sup>a</sup></td><td>6.50</td><td>0.261</td><td>0.356 (Medium)</td><td>4<sup>a</sup></td><td>6.00</td><td>0.859</td><td>0.059 (Small)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>14<sup>b</sup></td><td>14.64</td><td/><td/><td>5<sup>b</sup></td><td>7.80</td><td/><td/><td>4<sup>b</sup></td><td>2.50</td><td/><td/><td>5<sup>b</sup></td><td>4.20</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>2<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Strep.</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>14<sup>d</sup></td><td>14.43</td><td>0.982</td><td>0.004 (Small)</td><td>6<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.00</td><td>0.423</td><td>0.241 (Small)</td><td>6<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.17</td><td>0.325</td><td>0.312 (Medium)</td><td>2<sup>d</sup></td><td>8.50</td><td>0.513</td><td>0.218 (Small)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>14<sup>e</sup></td><td>14.57</td><td/><td/><td>5<sup>e</sup></td><td>8.40</td><td/><td/><td>2<sup>e</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td/><td/><td>7<sup>e</sup></td><td>4.00</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>2<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Yeast</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>12<sup>g</sup></td><td>15.46</td><td>0.799</td><td>0.029 (Small)</td><td>4<sup>g</sup></td><td>6.38</td><td>0.504</td><td>0.188 (Small)</td><td>4<sup>g</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td>0.574</td><td>0.178 (Small)</td><td>4<sup>g</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td>0.497</td><td>0.139 (Small)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>14<sup>h</sup></td><td>11.82</td><td/><td/><td>7<sup>h</sup></td><td>5.79</td><td/><td/><td>4<sup>h</sup></td><td>3.50</td><td/><td/><td>3<sup>h</sup></td><td>3.33</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>4<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Lower (full-time vs part-time)</td><td rowspan="4">Total</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>18<sup>a</sup></td><td>13.22</td><td>0.425</td><td>0.146 (Small)</td><td>7<sup>a</sup></td><td>6.57</td><td>0.247</td><td>0.349 (Medium)</td><td>4<sup>a</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td>1.000</td><td>0.000 (Small)</td><td>7<sup>a</sup></td><td>4.00</td><td>0.514</td><td>0.218 (Small)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>10<sup>b</sup></td><td>16.80</td><td/><td/><td>4<sup>b</sup></td><td>5.00</td><td/><td/><td>4<sup>b</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td/><td/><td>2<sup>b</sup></td><td>8.50</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>2<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>c</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Strep.</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>21<sup>d</sup></td><td>12.33</td><td>0.202</td><td>0.233 (Small)</td><td>10<sup>d</sup></td><td>6.40</td><td>0.006*</td><td>0.832 (Large)</td><td>4<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td>1.000</td><td>0.000 (Small)</td><td>7<sup>d</sup></td><td>4.00</td><td>0.513</td><td>0.218 (Small)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>7<sup>e</sup></td><td>21.00</td><td/><td/><td>1<sup>e</sup></td><td>2.00</td><td/><td/><td>4<sup>e</sup></td><td>4.50</td><td/><td/><td>2<sup>e</sup></td><td>8.50</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>2<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Yeast</td><td>-ve Ranks</td><td>11<sup>g</sup></td><td>16.55</td><td>0.632</td><td>0.087 (Small)</td><td>5<sup>g</sup></td><td>7.60</td><td>0.656</td><td>0.134 (Small)</td><td>2<sup>g</sup></td><td>5.50</td><td>0.325</td><td>0.312 (Medium)</td><td>4<sup>g</sup></td><td>5.00</td><td>0.766</td><td>0.099 (Small)</td></tr><tr><td>+ve Ranks</td><td>17<sup>h</sup></td><td>13.18</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>h</sup></td><td>4.67</td><td/><td/><td>6<sup>h</sup></td><td>4.17</td><td/><td/><td>5<sup>h</sup></td><td>5.00</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Ties</td><td>2<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>2<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td>0<sup>i</sup></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>30</td><td/><td/><td/><td>11</td><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td/><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Total microbial during PT &lt; Total microbial during FT</p><p><sup>b</sup>Total microbial during PT &lt; &gt; Total microbial during FT</p><p><sup>c</sup>Total microbial during PT &lt; = Total microbial during FT</p><p><sup>d</sup><italic>Streptococcus</italic> during PT &lt; &lt; <italic>Streptococcus</italic> during FT</p><p><sup>e</sup><italic>Streptococcus</italic> during PT &lt; &gt; <italic>Streptococcus</italic> during FT</p><p><sup>f</sup><italic>Streptococcus</italic> during PT &lt; = <italic>Streptococcus</italic> during FT</p><p><sup>g</sup>Yeast during PT &lt; &lt; Yeast on during FT</p><p><sup>h</sup>Yeast during PT &lt; &gt; Yeast on during FT</p><p><sup>i</sup>Yeast during PT &lt; = Yeast on during FT</p><p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 by Wilcoxon signed-rank test; <italic>FDM</italic>, fused deposition modeling; <italic>SLA</italic>, stereolithography apparatus.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par51">The mean surface roughness of the conventional models, FDM models, and SLA models were 1.49 μm (S.D. 0.60), 1.01 μm (S.D. 0.29), and 0.66 μm (S.D. 0.19), respectively, which were significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). Post hoc pairwise comparison showed that the surface roughness was significantly lower in SLA compared to the conventional and FDM working models (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) but not between the conventional and FDM models (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Surface roughness of the working models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3">Group</th><th colspan="5">Kruskal-Wallis test</th><th colspan="5">Post hoc pairwise comparison</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2"><italic>N</italic></th><th rowspan="2">Mean rank</th><th rowspan="2"><italic>p</italic> value</th><th colspan="2">Effect size</th><th rowspan="2">Comparisons</th><th rowspan="2">Test statistics</th><th rowspan="2">Adjusted <italic>p</italic> value</th><th colspan="2">Effect size</th></tr><tr><th>Value</th><th>Descriptor</th><th>Value</th><th>Descriptor</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Conventional</td><td align="right">12</td><td>28.83</td><td/><td/><td/><td>SLA vs FDM</td><td>10.667</td><td>0.039*</td><td>0.305</td><td>Large</td></tr><tr><td>FDM</td><td align="right">12</td><td>19.67</td><td>0.000*</td><td>0.497</td><td>Large</td><td>SLA vs Conventional</td><td>17.833</td><td>0.000*</td><td>0.510</td><td>Large</td></tr><tr><td>SLA</td><td align="right">12</td><td>9.00</td><td/><td/><td/><td>FDM vs Conventional</td><td>7.167</td><td>0.287</td><td>0.205</td><td>Large</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05; <italic>FDM</italic>, fused deposition modeling; <italic>SLA</italic>, stereolithography apparatus.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par52">In terms of the association between surface roughness and microbial count, there was no correlation between the working model surface roughness and total microbial count of both upper and lower VFRs collectively regardless of retention regime (<italic>N</italic>=30; <italic>τ</italic><sub>b</sub> = −0.037, <italic>p</italic> = 0.775). There were no correlations between the surface roughness and total microbial count of both upper and lower VFRs collectively either during full-time wear (<italic>N</italic>=30; <italic>τ</italic><sub>b</sub> = −0.080, <italic>p</italic> = 0.543) or part-time wear (<italic>N</italic>=30; <italic>τ</italic><sub>b</sub> = −0.073, <italic>p</italic> = 0.579).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec21">
                <title>Harms</title>
                <p id="Par53">No harms were observed. No side effects or adverse events were reported by the participants.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec22">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <sec id="Sec23">
                <title>Interpretation</title>
                <p id="Par54">The current study showed that surface roughness of the working models varies according to the type of working models used, and the imprints can be observed on the VFRs. VFRs harbor oral microbes; the amount of colonization did not differ between VFRs with different surface roughness and between full-time and part-time use. However, lower VFRs tend to accumulate more oral microbes, potentially increasing the oral health risk in the lower arch compared to the upper arch.</p>
                <p id="Par55">Inner surfaces of the thermoplastic appliance are not completely smooth and have micro abrasions and irregularities, which may promote bacterial adhesion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The surface roughness threshold that facilitates biofilm formation is estimated to be at least 0.2 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Given that the surface roughness of the VFRs in the current study was indirectly measured to be above this threshold, the rough surfaces had encouraged microbial adherence in all groups. Nonetheless, the microbial adherence on VFRs in this study was not significantly different between VFRs with variable surface roughness as constructed on different types of working models. This concurred with an in vitro study that compared commercially available VFR materials with variable surface roughness, which found initial bacterial adhesion increased with time but were not statistically different between the VFRs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par56">The lack of association between surface roughness and microbial adhesion as found in this study suggests that surface roughness may not be the predominant factor for microbial adherence on VFRs. Other surface characteristics such as surface attraction to water and surface free energy also contribute to various biochemical interactions that influence the initial adhesion of microorganisms to surfaces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Thermoplastic VFRs have smoother and more hydrophilic surfaces, higher electron donor properties, and acid-base interactions compared to auto-polymerized acrylic resins, commonly used for Hawley retainers. Thus, thermoplastic retainers tended to have a more uniformly distributed pattern of bacterial attachment, while bacteria tended to aggregate on the rough surfaces of auto-polymerized acrylic resins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The electron donor/electron acceptor interactions of the acid-base element of surface free energy may have favored for the strong initial adhesion and uniform distribution between oral bacteria and the thermoplastic material, over surface roughness. Streptococci that are equipped with external appendages such as fimbriae exhibit cell-surface hydrophobicity contributed by the cell-surface molecules consisting of non-polar amino acids. This hydrophobic surface property, which is also possessed by oral candida, has been reported to be involved in the formation of hydrophobic bonds between streptococci and the oral surface during the early colonizing stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par57">When all VFRs were considered regardless of group, the current study found significantly more oral microbes in the lower VFRs than the upper VFRs during full-time wear. Further analysis by group, only the conventional group showed the same findings, where the total microbial count, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count, and yeast count were higher on the lower VFRs during full-time wear. Overall, during part-time wear, the total microbial count and <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count were higher in the lower VFRs compared to the upper VFRs. This may appear unusual as the salivary flow on the lower arch is expected to be good for self-cleansing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. However, it is possible that the design of the VFRs that covers the whole dentition may have inhibited the self-cleansing property and thus caused an increase in microbial load.</p>
                <p id="Par58">Saliva is comprised of a variety of electrolytes that includes sodium, potassium, calcium, magnesium, bicarbonate, and phosphates. Other components that can be found in saliva are salivary proteins such as immunoglobulins, proteins, enzymes, mucins, and nitrogenous products such as urea and ammonia. Salivary proteins and mucins serve to cleanse, aggregate, and/or attach oral microorganisms and contribute to dental plaque metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. As amphifunctional macromolecules, salivary proteins may act for as well as against the host [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], that is, they may have more than one function and perform similar functions. Prolonged exposure during full-time wear of the lower VFRs with saliva may have increased microbial adherence through self-multiplication of the microbes and co-adhesion of those carried over by the oral fluid. Hence, saliva that usually pools on the lower arch could also have supported the microbial growth.</p>
                <p id="Par59">In terms of duration of wear, the current study generally found no differences in microbial adherence on VFRs of variable surface roughness between full-time wear and part-time wear. However, on the lower VFRs of the conventional group, only the <italic>Streptococcus</italic> count was found to be higher during full-time wear compared with part-time wear. <italic>Streptococcus</italic> that adheres to a surface via hydrophobic interactions of the fimbriae and adhesin receptor interactions between the bacteria and salivary components on the surface form strong irreversible attachment that enables further co-adhesion of microbes, leading to the higher population observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], but in yeast attachment is determined by certain cell wall components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. VFRs that were fabricated on conventional models may have increased surface roughness as shown in our result, which may have promoted adherence of streptococci.</p>
                <p id="Par60">The finding of this study suggests that VFRs left in the containers during part-time wear may harbor oral microbes as much as the oral microbes that are present in the oral cavity as used during full-time wear. The instructions on VFR care given to participants were to clean the retainers using toothbrush and to keep the retainers in a covered container when not in use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The retainers were also kept in water, which may have harbored bacterial growth. Further research should investigate the effect of storage conditions on bacterial growth on VFRs.</p>
                <p id="Par61">The result of surface roughness measurement was statistically significant for the different types of working models used. SLA model was the smoothest, followed by FDM model, and the roughest was conventional model. The dental stone were mixed manually according to the water/powder ratio suggested by the manufacturer. Therefore, the smoothness of the mixture can vary between different technicians and may affect the consistency of the surface characteristic of the model produced. On the other hand, the FDM printed models are made of continuous filaments of thermoplastic polymers or fiber-reinforced polymers, while SLA printed models are produced using resin with photoactive monomers or hybrid polymer-ceramic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The FDM and SLA models are printed using their respective 3D printers with the same setting and printing parameters all the time. Therefore, the final outcome of these 3D printed models can be predicted to be reliable and not affected by operator inconsistency. In our study, the printing quality for SLA models was demonstrated to be better compared to FDM models. This finding is similar to other studies conducted where they also found that SLA has the highest quality of print while FDM had the poorest print quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec24">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p id="Par62">Measurement of the surface roughness was based on few assumptions. First, the VFR being a transparent material could not be directly measured by the surface texture analyzer. Since surface roughness of the VFRs had to be indirectly measured on their corresponding working models, it had to be assumed that the VFRs negatively copied all the imprints of the working models, and the imprints of the working models represented the negative imprints of the VFRs. Second, the labial surface of the incisors was chosen for measuring surface roughness because it was assumed that the VFR foils adapt closest on the smooth surface where the imprints of the 3D printing layers had the most clarity. VFR does not wrap well over undercut areas and curved surfaces such as the cervical margins and occlusal fossae. Thus, the imprints may not be as well-defined in these areas. Third, mechanical cleansing of VFR by toothbrushing may possibly affect the surface roughness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Thus, it had to be assumed that the increase in surface roughness by the participants was similar between groups.</p>
                <p id="Par63">Compliance was based on patients’ report, which is associated with recall bias, particularly if the data was recorded retrospectively during the follow-up visits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], or over-reporting to please the attending clinician and to avoid negative comments or judgments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The compliance of the study was considered good, contributed by the weekly reminder by the researcher. Participants were shown models of relapse cases to improve compliance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] from when the first interventional retainers were issued to emphasize the importance of retainers to prevent relapse.</p>
                <p id="Par64">The dropout rate of 17% in the current study was slightly higher than the attrition of 10% shown in a past study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. There are few factors that could have contributed to this. First, the most concerning factor is unreported problems with the retainers, particularly with VFR-FDM which had the highest dropout, followed by VFR-CV and VFR-SLA. This may contribute to a bias result. Second, it was a challenge to perform a clinical trial during the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic. Our trial commenced in December 2019, and our government had enforced movement control order in various phases from 18 March 2020, which had restricted movements throughout Malaysia as an effort to control the outbreak [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Although patients were allowed to attend for their dental appointments, there were many uncertainties in terms of mobility for the public, which possibly had contributed to a higher attrition in this study. Nonetheless, the study had an adequate sample with the minimum of nine participants per group.</p>
                <p id="Par65">The oral hygiene aids used were daily use of toothpaste using a toothbrush, which is commonly practiced by 99% of Malaysians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Other oral hygiene aid such as mouthwash can be an effective method to control cariogenic plaque formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. However, the use of mouthwash is still not a common practice among Malaysians. Mitha et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] reported only about 34.8% respondents use mouthwash daily, while the remaining respondents use mouthwash less frequently. Therefore, the study limited the oral hygiene aid that was a common practice, which was daily use of toothpaste using a toothbrush, to prevent confounders of poor compliance with other oral hygiene aid such as mouthwash.</p>
                <p id="Par66">The study did not use appliance cleansers since the focus was to measure the amount of bacterial adherence on retainers during use. The study demonstrated bacterial adherence on all three types of VFR used. Thus, toothbrushing alone is not sufficient to clean the retainer. It can be recommended to use appliance cleanser for improved appliance hygiene. Various types of appliances cleansers have shown different efficacy in cleaning the retainer material [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec25">
                <title>Generalizability</title>
                <p id="Par67">The results of the study can be applied to healthy young adults from both genders who had completed fixed appliances treatment with no history of smoking and systemic diseases. By stratifying for gender, we have controlled for any confounder of having more females who may have better oral hygiene than males when comparing between groups. Furthermore, microbial samples were collected at 3 months, which coincided with standard protocol for retainer review, yet would be long enough to detect change in microbial establishment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par68">The study can be applied for VFRs made on working models with surface roughness of at most 1.49 mm (SD 0.60). Mohd Tahir et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] used an FDM printer which had a layer resolution of 150 mm. However, technology has become more current such that FDM printers which are considered one of the cheapest commercially available printers are able to print at higher resolution as thin as 60 mm for FDM, while the SLA model was printed at 25 mm.</p>
                <p id="Par69">One of the advantages of the 3D printed models noted from this study was that the same replica can be used to repeat VFR constructions, while new casts of the conventional models had to be used for constructing the second VFR set. This is because 3D printed acrylic resin has better mechanical properties in terms of higher impact strength, hardness, compressive strength, and flexural strength in comparison with the dental stone models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. This can potentially be the cost-effective benefit when patients request for replacement retainers provided that there was no relapse.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec26">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="Par70">The propensity for microbial adherence on VFRs was not influenced by the degree of surface roughness imprints from working models, as made from conventional and 3D printed models. Clinicians can consider using either conventional, FDM or SLA models to make VFRs since the risk for microbial accumulation was comparable.</p>
              <p id="Par71">Lower VFRs have a higher propensity for microbial adherence than upper VFRs, thus potentially increasing the oral health risk in the lower arch. There was no difference in microbial adherence on VFRs between full-time and part-time wear; hence, the risk to the oral health was similar whether patients wore the VFRs full-time or part-time.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>The authors would like to thank Mohd Anuar Zainon for microbial count calibration and Mohammad Zabri Johari for statistical advice.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>SB was responsible for the conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, funding acquisition, investigation, methodology, project administration, and writing of the original draft. WNWH was responsible for the conceptualization, funding acquisition, methodology, project administration, resources, supervision, validation, visualization, and reviewing and editing the draft. FAR was responsible for the conceptualization, methodology, project administration, resources, supervision, visualization, and reviewing and editing the draft. NMT was responsible for the methodology, validation, formal analysis, and reviewing and editing the draft.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>The research was funded by the Universiti Malaya Dental Postgraduate Research Grant (DPRG/14/19).</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data availability</title>
              <p>Data of the study is available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar1">
                <title>Ethics approval</title>
                <p id="Par72">This study was performed in line with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Ethics approval was obtained from the Medical Ethics Research Committee, Faculty of Dentistry, Universiti Malaya [Ref: DF CD1811/0047(P); July 12, 2018]. The research was registered with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> (Ref: NCT03844425).</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar2">
                <title>Consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par73">Informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in the study.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Conflict of interest</title>
                <p id="Par74">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Traore</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Springthorpe</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sattar</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A quantitative study of the survival of two species of Candida on porous and non-porous environmental surfaces and hands</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>92</volume>
                  <fpage>549</fpage>
                  <lpage>555</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2002.01560.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11872132?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872132</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliades</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliades</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brantley</surname>
                      <given-names>WA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microbial attachment on orthodontic appliances: I. Wettability and early pellicle formation on bracket materials</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>108</volume>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
                  <lpage>360</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0889-5406(95)70032-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 7572846?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7572846</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marsh</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Oral microbiology</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Edinburgh/New York</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samaranayake</surname>
                      <given-names>LP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Essential microbiology for dentistry</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Churchill Livingstone Elsevier</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uygun-Can</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kadir</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akyüz</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Oral candidal carriage in children with and without dental caries</article-title>
                  <source>Quintessence Int</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <lpage>49</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17216907</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Urzúa</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hermosilla</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gamonal</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morales-Bozo</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Canals</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barahona</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Yeast diversity in the oral microbiota of subjects with periodontitis: Candida albicans and Candida dubliniensis colonize the periodontal pockets</article-title>
                  <source>Sabouraudia</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <fpage>783</fpage>
                  <lpage>793</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13693780802060899</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheridan</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>LeDoux</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McMinn</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Essix retainers: fabrication and supervision for permanent retention</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Orthod</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>45</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8478438?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8478438</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saleh</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hajeer</surname>
                      <given-names>MY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muessig</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Acceptability comparison between Hawley retainers and vacuum-formed retainers in orthodontic adult patients: a single-centre, randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <fpage>453</fpage>
                  <lpage>461</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjx024</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28430890?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28430890</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jaber</surname>
                      <given-names>ST</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hajeer</surname>
                      <given-names>MY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khattab</surname>
                      <given-names>TZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahaini</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the fused deposition modeling and the digital light processing techniques in terms of dimensional accuracy of printing dental models used for the fabrication of clear aligners</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Exp Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>591</fpage>
                  <lpage>600</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.366</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33258297?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33258297</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mohd Tahir</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wan Hassan</surname>
                      <given-names>WN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saub</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparing retainers constructed on conventional stone models and on 3D printed models: a randomized crossover clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <fpage>370</fpage>
                  <lpage>380</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjy063</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30321319?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30321319</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eroglu</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baka</surname>
                      <given-names>ZM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arslan</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative evaluation of salivary microbial levels and periodontal status of patients wearing fixed and removable orthodontic retainers</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>156</volume>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <lpage>192</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2018.08.022</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31375228?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31375228</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Türköz</surname>
                      <given-names>Ç</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bavbek</surname>
                      <given-names>NC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Varlik</surname>
                      <given-names>SK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akça</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of thermoplastic retainers on Streptococcus mutans and Lactobacillus adhesion</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>141</volume>
                  <fpage>598</fpage>
                  <lpage>603</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2011.11.021</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22554754?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22554754</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shao</surname>
                      <given-names>MY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>XD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental erosion and severe tooth decay related to soft drinks: a case report and literature review</article-title>
                  <source>J Zhejiang Univ Sci B</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                  <lpage>399</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.B0820245</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19434767?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19434767</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cifter</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gumru Celikel</surname>
                      <given-names>AD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cekici</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of vacuum-formed retainers on periodontal status and their retention efficiency</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>152</volume>
                  <fpage>830</fpage>
                  <lpage>835</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2017.05.029</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29173862?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29173862</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Low</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seneviratne</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samaranayake</surname>
                      <given-names>LP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hagg</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Ultrastructure and morphology of biofilms on thermoplastic orthodontic appliances in ‘fast’ and ‘slow’ plaque formers</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>577</fpage>
                  <lpage>583</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjq126</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21187528?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21187528</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Outhaisavanh</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The origin and evolution of the Hawley retainer for the effectiveness to maintain tooth position after fixed orthodontic treatment compare to vacuum-formed retainer: a systematic review of RCTs</article-title>
                  <source>Int Orthod</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <lpage>236</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ortho.2020.02.008</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32201168?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32201168</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wan Hassan</surname>
                      <given-names>WN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Othman</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chan</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahmad</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ali</surname>
                      <given-names>SN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abd Rohim</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessing agreement in measurements of orthodontic study models: digital caliper on plaster models vs 3-dimensional software on models scanned by structured-light scanner</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>150</volume>
                  <fpage>886</fpage>
                  <lpage>895</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2016.04.021</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27871715?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27871715</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malhotra</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rao</surname>
                      <given-names>SP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acharya</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vasudev</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative in vitro evaluation of efficacy of mouthrinses against Streptococcus mutans, Lactobacilli and Candida albicans</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Health Prev Dent</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <lpage>268</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22068182?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22068182</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghazal</surname>
                      <given-names>ARA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Idris</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hajeer</surname>
                      <given-names>MY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alawer</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cannon</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of removing Candida albicans from orthodontic acrylic bases: an in vitro study</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-019-0765-x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31046747?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31046747</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laudicina</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rufo</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Teacher’s manual to accompany learning guides for the medical microbiology laboratory</source>
                  <year>1985</year>
                  <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koo</surname>
                      <given-names>TK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>MY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A guideline of selecting and reporting intraclass correlation coefficients for reliability research</article-title>
                  <source>J Chiropr Med</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <lpage>163</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcm.2016.02.012</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27330520?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27330520</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farhadian</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Usefi Mashoof</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khanizadeh</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghaderi</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farhadian</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miresmaeili</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Streptococcus mutans counts in patients wearing removable retainers with silver nanoparticles vs those wearing conventional retainers: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>149</volume>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <lpage>160</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2015.07.031</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26827971?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26827971</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mamai-Homata</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koletsi-Kounari</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Margaritis</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gender differences in oral health status and behavior of Greek dental students: a meta-analysis of 1981, 2000, and 2010 data</article-title>
                  <source>J Int Soc Prev Community Dent</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2231-0762.175411</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27011935?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27011935</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chinna</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuen</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Statistical analysis using SPSS</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Kuala Lumpur</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allen</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bennett</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heritage</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>SPSS statistics version 22: A practical guide</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Cengage Learning</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teughels</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van Assche</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sliepen</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quirynen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of material characteristics and/or surface topography on biofilm development</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 2</issue>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <lpage>81</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2006.01353.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16968383?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968383</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tektas</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thurnheer</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliades</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Attin</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karygianni</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Initial bacterial adhesion and biofilm formation on aligner materials</article-title>
                  <source>Antibiotics (Basel)</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>908</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9120908</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33333723?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33333723</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al Groosh</surname>
                      <given-names>DH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bozec</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pratten</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hunt</surname>
                      <given-names>NP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The influence of surface roughness and surface dynamics on the attachment of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus onto orthodontic retainer materials</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Mater J</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <fpage>585</fpage>
                  <lpage>594</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4012/dmj.2014-045</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26438981?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26438981</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Razak</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Othman</surname>
                      <given-names>RY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abd Rahim</surname>
                      <given-names>ZH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of Piper betle and Psidium guajava extracts on the cell-surface hydrophobicity of selected early settlers of dental plaque</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <lpage>75</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2334/josnusd.48.71</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16858135?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16858135</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harun</surname>
                      <given-names>WHAW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Razak</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An in vitro study on the anti-adherence effect of Brucea javanica and Piper betle extracts towards oral Candida</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>58</volume>
                  <fpage>1335</fpage>
                  <lpage>1342</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.archoralbio.2013.07.001</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23915676</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dawes</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watanabe</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biglow-Lecomte</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dibdin</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of the velocity of the salivary film at some different locations in the mouth</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <fpage>1479</fpage>
                  <lpage>1482</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00220345890680110201</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 2531176?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2531176</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Humphrey</surname>
                      <given-names>SP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williamson</surname>
                      <given-names>RT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A review of saliva: normal composition, flow, and function</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>85</volume>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <lpage>169</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mpr.2001.113778</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11208206?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11208206</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Edgerton</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scannapieco</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reddy</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Levine</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Human submandibular-sublingual saliva promotes adhesion of Candida albicans to polymethylmethacrylate</article-title>
                  <source>Infect Immun</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>61</volume>
                  <fpage>2644</fpage>
                  <lpage>2652</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/iai.61.6.2644-2652.1993</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8500903?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8500903</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abranches</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeng</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kajfasz</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palmer</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wen</surname>
                      <given-names>ZT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Richards</surname>
                      <given-names>VP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brady</surname>
                      <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lemos</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Biology of oral streptococci</article-title>
                  <source>Microbiol Spectr</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.GPP3-0042-2018</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Singh A, Verma R, Murari A, Agrawal A (2014) Oral candidiasis: an overview. J Oral Maxillofac Pathol 18:S81-S85 10.4103/0973-029X.141325</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meade</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Millett</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Retention protocols and use of vacuum-formed retainers among specialist orthodontists</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>318</fpage>
                  <lpage>325</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/1465313313Y.0000000066</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24297964?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297964</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ngo</surname>
                      <given-names>TD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kashani</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imbalzano</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                      <given-names>KT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hui</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Additive manufacturing (3D printing): a review of materials, methods, applications and challenges</article-title>
                  <source>Compos B Eng</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>143</volume>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <lpage>196</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compositesb.2018.02.012</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kasparova</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grafova</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dvorak</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dostalova</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prochazka</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliasova</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Possibility of reconstruction of dental plaster cast from 3D digital study models</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed Eng Online</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-925X-12-49</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23289769</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Finnes</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>High definition 3D printing–comparing SLA and FDM printing technologies</article-title>
                  <source>J Undergrad Res</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choudhari</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Patil</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Product development and its comparative analysis by SLA, SLS and FDM rapid prototyping processes</article-title>
                  <source>IOP Conf Ser: Mater Sci Eng</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>149</volume>
                  <fpage>012009</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1757-899X/149/1/012009</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Šimunović</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blagec</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meštrović</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The influence of different cleaning protocols on the surface roughness of orthodontic retainers</article-title>
                  <source>Appl Sci</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>1319</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app13031319</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schott</surname>
                      <given-names>TC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meyer-Gutknecht</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mayer</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weber</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weimer</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison between indirect and objective wear-time assessment of removable orthodontic appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <lpage>175</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjw026</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27030283?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27030283</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Moghrabi</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salazar</surname>
                      <given-names>FC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pandis</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleming</surname>
                      <given-names>PS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Compliance with removable orthodontic appliances and adjuncts: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>152</volume>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2017.03.019</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28651764?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28651764</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ni</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yao</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A feasible method to improve adherence of Hawley retainer in adolescent orthodontic patients: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Patient Prefer</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>1525</fpage>
                  <lpage>1530</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/PPA.S94111</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hussin</surname>
                      <given-names>MZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farook</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nor</surname>
                      <given-names>NAM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hariri</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kadir</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zakaria</surname>
                      <given-names>NN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hassan</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wan Hassan</surname>
                      <given-names>WN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Resuming clinical teaching in the era of COVID-19: experiences and protocols from a dental school in Malaysia</article-title>
                  <source>Sains Malays</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <fpage>2123</fpage>
                  <lpage>2134</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17576/jsm-2021-5007-25</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mitha</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>ElNaem</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chandran</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rajah</surname>
                      <given-names>NP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fam</surname>
                      <given-names>TY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Babar</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jamshed</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Use of oral cleaning devices and their perceived benefits among Malaysians in Kuala Lumpur and Johor Bahru: an exploratory structured approach</article-title>
                  <source>J Pharm Bioallied Sci</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <lpage>225</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/JPBS.JPBS_296_16</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30568379?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30568379</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pithon</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sant'Anna</surname>
                      <given-names>LI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baião</surname>
                      <given-names>FC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>dos Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>RdaS</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maia</surname>
                      <given-names>LC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of the effectiveness of mouthwashes in reducing cariogenic biofilm in orthodontic patients: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <lpage>308</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2014.12.010</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25572792?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25572792</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR48">
                <label>48.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mitha</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Elnaem</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koh</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>En</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Babar</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jamshed</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Use and perceived benefits of mouthwash among Malaysian adults: an exploratory insight</article-title>
                  <source>J Adv Oral Res</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <lpage>14</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2229411220160302</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR49">
                <label>49.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kiatwarawut</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuvatanasuchati</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thaweboon</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sirisoontorn</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of various antimicrobial agents for thermoplastic polymeric retainers</article-title>
                  <source>Polymers</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>3753</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/polym14183753</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 36145897?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36145897</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR50">
                <label>50.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Czajkowska M, Walejewska E, Zadrozny L, Wieczorek M, Swieszkowski W, Wagner L, Mijiritsky E, Markowski J (2020) Comparison of dental stone models and their 3d printed acrylic replicas for the accuracy and mechanical properties. Materials (Basel) 13. 10.3390/ma13184066</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
