<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:47:35Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4520138" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4520138</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-08-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>dpjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2176-9451</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2177-6709</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dental Press International</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4520138</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4520138</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4520138</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26154456</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26154456</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2176-9451.20.3.050-057.oar</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Dentoalveolar mandibular changes with self-ligating
<italic>versus</italic> conventional bracket systems: A CBCT and dental cast
study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Almeida</surname>
                    <given-names>Marcio Rodrigues</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Futagami</surname>
                    <given-names>Cristina</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Conti</surname>
                    <given-names>Ana Cláudia de Castro Ferreira</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Oltramari-Navarro</surname>
                    <given-names>Paula Vanessa Pedron</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Navarro</surname>
                    <given-names>Ricardo de Lima</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Full professor of Orthodontics, Universidade Norte do Paraná (UNOPAR),
Londrina, Paraná, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>MSc in Orthodontics, Universidade Norte do Paraná (UNOPAR), Londrina,
Paraná, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Professor of Orthodontics, Universidade do Sagrado Coração (USC), Bauru,
São Paulo, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>PhD in Orthodontics, Universidade de São Paulo (USP), São Paulo, São
Paulo, Brazil</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Contact address:</bold> Marcio Rodrigues de Almeida Avenida Paris, 675 Jardim
Piza, Londrina -PR - Brazil CEP: 86041-120 - E-mail:
<email>marcioralmeida@uol.com.br</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>May-Jun</season>
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>May-Jun</season>
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>20</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>50</fpage>
              <lpage>57</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>02</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>26</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>OBJECTIVE:</title>
                  <p> The aim of the present study was to compare dentoalveolar changes in mandibular
arch, regarding transversal measures and buccal bone thickness, in patients
undergoing the initial phase of orthodontic treatment with self-ligating or
conventional bracket systems. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>METHODS:</title>
                  <p> A sample of 25 patients requiring orthodontic treatment was assessed based on the
bracket type. Group 1 comprised 13 patients bonded with 0.022-in self-ligating
brackets (SLB). Group 2 included 12 patients bonded with 0.022-in conventional
brackets (CLB). Cone-beam computed tomography (CBCT) scans and a 3D program
(Dolphin) assessed changes in transversal width of buccal bone (TWBB) and buccal
bone thickness (BBT) before (T<sub>1</sub>) and 7 months after treatment onset
(T<sub>2</sub>). Measurements on dental casts were performed using a digital
caliper. Differences between and within groups were analyzed by Student's t-test;
Pearson correlation coefficient was also calculated. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESULTS:</title>
                  <p> Significant mandibular expansion was observed for both groups; however, no
significant differences were found between groups. There was significant decrease
in mandibular buccal bone thickness and transversal width of buccal bone in both
groups. There was no significant correlation between buccal bone thickness and
dental arch expansion. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>CONCLUSIONS:</title>
                  <p> There were no significant differences between self-ligating brackets and
conventional brackets systems regarding mandibular arch expansion and changes in
buccal bone thickness or transversal width of buccal bone.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <sec>
                  <title>OBJETIVO:</title>
                  <p> o objetivo do presente estudo foi comparar as alterações dentoalveolares
transversais e a espessura óssea da arcada inferior em pacientes submetidos ao
tratamento ortodôntico utilizando sistemas de braquetes autoligáveis ou
convencionais. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>MÉTODOS:</title>
                  <p> uma amostra de 25 pacientes requerendo tratamento ortodôntico foi recrutada com
base no tipo de braquete. No Grupo 1, 13 pacientes foram tratados com braquetes
autoligáveis (SLB, <italic>slot</italic> 0,022"); o Grupo 2 incluiu 12 pacientes,
nos quais foram colados braquetes convencionais (CLB,
<italic>slot</italic>0,022"). Utilizou-se tomografia computadorizada de feixe
cônico e um programa 3D (Dolphin) para avaliar as alterações pré-tratamento
(T<sub>1</sub>) e 7 meses após o início desse (T<sub>2</sub>). As medições em
modelos de gesso foram realizadas com o auxílio de um paquímetro digital. As
diferenças intergrupos, bem como intragrupo, foram analisadas por meio de teste
<italic>t</italic> de Student. Além disso, o coeficiente de correlação de
Pearson foi utilizado. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESULTADOS:</title>
                  <p> alterações dentoalveolares significativas foram observadas em ambos os grupos.
Entretanto, não houve diferenças significativas entre os grupos. Houve uma
diminuição da espessura óssea na região posterior e das medidas transversais em
ambos os grupos. Não houve uma correlação significativa entre a espessura óssea
posterior e a expansão da arcada dentária, em nenhum dos dois sistemas de
braquetes utilizados. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>CONCLUSÕES:</title>
                  <p> comparando-se o uso dos aparelhos autoligáveis e convencionais, concluiu-se que
não houve diferenças dentoalveolares significativas quanto à expansão da arcada
inferior e quanto à espessura óssea posterior.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Orthodontic appliances</kwd>
                <kwd>Corrective orthodontics</kwd>
                <kwd>Orthodontic brackets</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="4"/>
                <table-count count="6"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="28"/>
                <page-count count="8"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>The ongoing search for innovation in Orthodontics has boosted the emergence or
re-emergence of appliances so as to offer patients more comfort, shorter treatment time,
improved post-treatment stability, and fewer side effects. Self-ligating brackets (SLB)
came back into scene in the seventies, arising strong expectancy, and became popular in
the nineties. Much empirical and anecdotal evidence as well as advantages were
attributed to these appliances: increased patient comfort, better oral hygiene,
increased patient cooperation, less chair time, shorter treatment time, greater patient
acceptance, expansion, and less dental extractions.<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</p>
              <p>Correcting dental crowding without extractions or interproximal reductions requires an
increase in arch perimeter in order to allow excellent teeth alignment. In the absence
of distal movements, the dimensional changes of the arch involve transversal and buccal
dental expansion.<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> It is a well-known fact that
both self-ligating and conventional ligating brackets (CLB) when used for non-extraction
treatment of dental crowding produce dentoalveolar expansion. The amount of transversal
increase depends on the mechanics applied in each case.<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
</p>
              <p>Before the introduction of computerized tomography, it was not possible to visualize the
buccal bone due to superposition that occurred in 2D radiographs.<sup>12,13</sup> To
achieve successful orthodontic treatment, the limits of orthodontic movement must be
respected, in order to prevent iatrogenic effects to the sustaining and protection
periodontium, such as gingival recessions, dehiscence and bone fenestrations. Studies
prior to cone-beam computed tomography (CBCT) scans assessed only radiographs and dental
casts, both of which used to be regarded as gold standards. Improvements in CBCT scans
revealed it to be a reliable method, which offers an excellent visualization of the
actual structures.<sup>14,15</sup> Timock <italic>et al</italic>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> investigated the accuracy and reproducibility
of measurements of alveolar bone height and thickness by means of CBCT imaging. They
found good precision and accuracy for both measurements.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</p>
              <p>The transversal response of the mandibular dental arch treated with CLB has been widely
studied in the literature, especially the dentoalveolar response on dental
casts.<sup>7,10,17,18</sup> However, little is known regarding CBCT scans used to
assess the mandibular alveolar bone of the posterior region, where buccal bone can be
detected and quantified.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This study aims at
testing the null hypothesis that there is no difference, regarding changes in
transversal width and buccal bone thickness in the mandibular arch, between patients
undergoing the initial phase of orthodontic treatment (7 months) with SLB and CLB
systems. </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <p>This research protocol was approved by Universidade Norte do Paraná (UNOPAR,
Londrina/PR, Brazil) Institutional Review Board. Patients and guardians were fully
informed about the study and its implications, and signed a consent form.</p>
              <p>For this prospective study, power analysis showed that a sample size of 12 patients in
each group would give 80% probability to detect a real difference of 1.4 mm in
intermolar distance and 0.2 mm in bone thickness, with a 95% (p &lt; 0.05) significance
level.<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The sample for the present
prospective randomized study was treated at Universidade Norte do Paraná (UNOPAR,
Londrina, PR, Brazil) from 2009 to 2012. All patients had complete orthodontic records
taken at the beginning (T<sub>1</sub>) of treatment and 7 months after treatment onset
(T<sub>2</sub>), including study models and CBCT scans. In selecting the sample, the
following inclusion criteria were applied: patients with Angle Class I malocclusion,
moderate-to-severe lower dental crowding (3.0 to 7.0 mm), absence of diastema, absence
of posterior crossbite, complete permanent teeth (except for third molars). Patients
were randomly divided into two groups: SLB and CLB. Out of the selected individuals,
none were excluded after treatment onset. Premolars extraction and tooth wear were not
included in the proposed treatment.</p>
              <p>Group 1 (G1) comprised 13 patients treated with 0.022 x 0.027-in slot SLB (EasyClip
Aditek, Cravinhos/SP, Brazil), with initial mean age of 18.58 years (SD = 5.43). Group 2
(G2) comprised 12 patients treated with 0.022 x 0.028-in slot CLB (3M Unitek, Monrovia,
Calif., USA), with initial mean age of 21.61 years (SD = 6.69). The archwires for Group
2 were tied to the brackets by means of a metallic ligature. Patients were
orthodontically treated during initial leveling and alignment for six months, following
the same sequence of round archwires: 0.013, 0.014 and 0.016-in nickel-titanium
archwires, according to the manufacturers's (Aditek) prescription (Damon system). Each
archwire remained in place for two months.</p>
              <p>Cone-beam computed tomography scans were obtained from all patients at two time
intervals prior to orthodontic treatment onset and 7 months after it. All CBCT scans
were carried out by a single experienced radiologist using the same scanner (i-Cat
Imaging Sciences International, Hatfield, Pennsylvania, USA) set up as follows: 22 x 16
cm fov, 40 sec, 120 kVp, 36 mA. This scanner has high-resolution sensors and affords
0.4-mm voxel images.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
</p>
              <p>CBCT scans were analyzed by one single operator who assessed mandibular bone changes by
means of Dolphin 3D software (Version 11.5<sup>(r)</sup>, Dolphin Imaging &amp;
Management Solutions, Chatsworth, Calif., USA) with a level of sensitivity set at
25%.</p>
              <p>Coronal slices were selected for the bone measurements (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig 1</xref>) and 1-mm thick cross-sections were made through the first molar (M1),
second premolar (P2) and first premolar (P1), in the right and left mandibular arches.
As for coronal slices, the mid portion of teeth (molars and premolars) was chosen. The
point selected for buccal bone measurement was the most external prominence of the
buccal bone (EBB) in the root most apical portion (apex). At this same height, a point
was projected from the parallel projection of the cusp point. The distance between the
two points was determined as BBT, buccal bone thickness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figs 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3</xref>). Thus, changes in BBT
were calculated by subtracting T<sub>1</sub> from T<sub>2</sub> values. For transversal
width of the buccal bone, the EBB point was used on the right and left sides. The
distance between right and left EBB was the transversal width of buccal bone (TWBB)
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig 1</xref>). Similarly, TWBB changes were
calculated by subtracting T<sub>1</sub> from T<sub>2 </sub>values. In order to confirm
whether transversal width and bone thickness measurements were taken on the same coronal
slices, the mid region of each posterior teeth was used as reference to ensure
consistency of slices.</p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Coronal slice and transversal width of buccal bone (TWBB).</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-20-03-00050-gf01"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Buccal bone thickness (BBT) measurements.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-20-03-00050-gf02"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Example of measurements for buccal bone thickness (BBT) of mandibular first
molars.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-20-03-00050-gf03"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>Intermolar distances, intersecond premolar distances, and interfirst premolar distances
were measured in dental casts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Fig 4</xref>) by means of
a previously calibrated digital caliper (Mitutoyo Caliper, Japan). In order to measure
the transversal distances, buccal cusp tips were selected for first and second
mandibular premolars, while mesiobuccal cusp tips were selected for first molars.</p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 4.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Intermolar width measured on a dental cast by means of a digital
caliper.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-20-03-00050-gf04"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Statistical analysis</title>
              <p>To assess intra and interexaminer reliability, ten CBCT scans were randomly selected and
remeasured four weeks apart by two operators. Intraexaminer error was assessed by means
of paired<italic> t-</italic>test and Dahlberg's formula. Interexaminer reliability was
assessed by intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC). Data were tested for normal
distribution by means of Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. As data were normally distributed,
parametric tests were applied. Results were described by parameters of mean and standard
deviation of T<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>2</sub> measurements for both groups. Independent
<italic>t-</italic>tests were used to compare the initial demographic data of both
groups. Paired and unpaired <italic>t</italic>-tests were used to compare intra and
intergroup changes. Finally, Pearson correlation coefficient was calculated to further
explore the association between dental expansion and expansion of TWBB. In all
statistical tests, the significance level was set at 5%.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> All statistical analyses were performed with SPSS software for Windows
version 17.0 (SPSS Inc, Chicago Ill.).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Systematic (paired <italic>t-</italic>test<italic>) </italic>and casual error
(Dahlberg's formula) showed no intraexaminer difference. Intraclass correlation
coefficients for bone thickness and transversal width of buccal bone measurements were
0.89 and 0.98, respectively, thereby showing acceptable reliability. Random error ranged
from 0.30 to 0.56 mm and from 0.53 to 1.08 mm for dental casts and CBCT measurements,
respectively.</p>
              <p>Patients' demographic distribution is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>. Both samples were comparable at treatment onset regarding the
following aspects: initial age, treatment time, intermolar distances, intersecond
premolar distances, interfirst premolar distances, TWBB and BBT measurements. Means and
standard deviation values for BBT and TWBB measurements at pretreatment (T<sub>1</sub>),
7 months after treatment onset (T<sub>2</sub>) and the changes observed
(T<sub>2</sub>-T<sub>1</sub>) are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Tables 2
to 4</xref>.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Patients' demographic distribution</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLB (G1) (n = 13)</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLB (G2) (n = 12)</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Initial mean age (years)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 18.58 ± 5.43</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 21.61 ± 6.69</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.221</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Treatment time (days)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 210.15 ± 41.44</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 218.17 ± 46.60</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.654</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="4" rowspan="1"> CBCT scans</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.34 ± 2.59</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.31 ± 1.32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.972</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.65 ± 2.23</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.44 ± 1.21</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.788</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.64 ± 2.38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.02 ± 3.56</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.613</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.82 ± 2.71</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.92 ± 2.11</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.927</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.24 ± 2.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.49 ± 2.10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.783</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.70 ± 2.78</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.87 ± 1.48</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.856</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 40.37 ± 2.43</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 38.94 ± 2.58</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.175</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 49.35 ± 4.44</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 49.17 ± 4.07</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.928</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 59.04 ± 4.86</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 59.16 ± 4.45</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.956</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="4" rowspan="1"> Dental cast measurements (mm)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4-4 width (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 33.95 ± 1.87</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 33.37 ± 2.36</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.749</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5-5 width (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 38.42 ± 2.18</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 38.57 ± 2.69</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.888</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6-6 width (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 44.85 ± 1.68</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 44.37 ± 2.76</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.612</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN01">
                      <p>M1 = first molar, P2 = second premolar and P1 = first premolar.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Mean and standard deviation at the beginning of treatment (T1) and 7 months
after treatment onset (T2), regarding changes in buccal bone thickness and
transversal width of buccal bone (CBCT measurements) for the CLB group</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measurements</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>2</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diff.</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.31 ± 1.32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.80 ± 1.86</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -1.51</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.016*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.44 ± 1.21</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.54 ± 1.46</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.90</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.039*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 38.94 ± 2.58</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 38.73 ± 2.88</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.21</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.613</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.02 ± 3.56</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3.14 ± 2.31</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.88</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.165</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.92 ± 2.11</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3.83 ± 2.01</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -1.09</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.007*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 49.17 ± 4.07</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 48.52 ± 3.72</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.66</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.222</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.49 ± 2.10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.18 ± 1.55</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.31</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.292</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.87 ± 1.48</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.08 ± 1.76</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.79</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.008*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 59.16 ± 4.45</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 58.90 ± 4.34</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.26</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.611</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN02">
                      <p>* p &lt; 0.05. M1 = first molar, P2 = second premolar and P1 = first
premolar.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Mean and standard deviation at the beginning of treatment (T1) and 7 months
after treatment onset (T2), regarding changes in buccal bone thickness and
transversal width of buccal bone (CBCT measurements) SLB group.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measurements</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>2</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diff.</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.34 ± 2.59</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.69 ± 1.64</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.66</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.177</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.65 ± 2.23</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.77 ± 2.01</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.88</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.019*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 40.37 ± 2.43</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 39.82 ± 2.67</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.56</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.076</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.64 ± 2.38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.00 ± 2.42</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.64</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.002*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.82 ± 2.71</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3.73 ± 2.40</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -1.09</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;0.001**</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 49.35 ± 4.44</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 49.34 ± 4.13</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.01</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.980</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.24 ± 2.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.93 ± 2.43</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.158</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.70 ± 2.78</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.16 ± 2.63</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.54</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.025*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 59.04 ± 4.86</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 58.94 ± 4.79</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.750</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN03">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p> p &lt; 0.05.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TFN04">
                      <label>**</label>
                      <p> p &lt; 0.01. M1 = first molar, P2 = second premolar and P1 = first
premolar.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 4.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Means and standard deviation at the beginning of treatment (T1) and 7
months after treatment onset (T2) measured by CBCT and comparing CLB and SLB
groups.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measurements</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLB (G1) (n = 13)</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLB (G2) (n = 12 )</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diff.</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.66 ± 1.65</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -1.51 ± 1.84</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.85</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.234</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.88 ± 1.17</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.90 ± 1.34</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.02</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.964</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.56 ± 1.04</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.21 ± 1.38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.35</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.475</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.64 ± 0.57</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.88 ± 2.06</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.25</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.681</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -1.09 ± 0.83</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -1.09 ± 1.16</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.995</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.01 ± 1.10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.66 ± 1.76</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.65</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.275</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1L BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.32 ± 0.75</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.31 ± 0.97</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.01</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.992</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1R BBT (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.54 ± 0.77</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.79 ± 0.85</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.25</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.452</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1 TWBB (mm)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.10 ± 1.15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.26 ± 1.72</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.16</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.537</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN05">
                      <p>M1 = first molar, P2 = second premolar and P1 = first premolar.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>Mandibular buccal bone thickness (BBT) decreased from T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub> for
both bracket types. BBT in the CLB group significantly decreased for P1L (-1.51 mm; p =
0.016), P1R (-0.9 mm; p = 0.039), P2R (-1.09 mm; p = 0.007) and M1R (-0.79 mm; p =
0.008). BBT in the SLB group significantly decreased for P1R (-0.88 mm, p = 0.019), P2L
(-0.64 mm; p = 0.002), P2R (-1.09 mm, p &lt; 0.001) and M1R (-0.54 mm; p = 0.025).
However, changes in TWBB measurements showed a slight decrease and were not considered
statistically significant in either one of the groups: for the CLB group, the following
measurements decreased: P1 (-0.21 mm; p = 0.613), P2 (-0.66 mm; p = 0.222) and M1 (-0.31
mm; p = 0.611); as for the SLB group, the following measurements decreased: P1 (-0.56
mm; p = 0.076) and P2 (-0.01 mm; p = 0.980), with an increase in M1 (0.10 mm; p =
0.750).</p>
              <p>Comparison between BBT and TWBB measurements from T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub>revealed
no significant differences between groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table
4</xref>). Additionally, no significant differences were found when comparing dental
casts at treatment onset (T<sub>1</sub>) and 7 months later (T<sub>2</sub>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t05">Table 5</xref>). An average increase of dental transversal
distances occurred from T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub>, which was considered
significant. Bracket type had no significant influence on changes in mandibular dental
arch. Differences between SLB and CLB for interfirst premolar width, intersecond
premolar width and intermolar width were -0.6 mm (p = 0.489), 0.35 mm (p = 0.465) and
0.46 mm (p = 0.180), respectively.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 5.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Means and standard deviation at the beginning of treatment (T1) and 7
months after treatment onset (T2) measured in dental casts and comparing CLB
and SLB groups.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measurements</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLB (G1) (n = 13)</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLB (G2) (n = 12 )</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diff.</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4-4 width</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.27 ± 1.95</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.87 ± 2.30</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> -0.60</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.489</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5-5 width</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.10 ± 1.00</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.75 ± 1.33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.35</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.465</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6-6 width</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.92 ± 0.88</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.46 ± 0.77</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.46</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.180</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>Furthermore, no statistically significant association was found between transversal
width of buccal bone (TWBB) and dental expansion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t06">Table
6</xref>).</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 6.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Pearson correlation coefficient between transversal width of buccal bone
(TWBB) and dental expansion within the two bracket system groups.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measurements</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P1 TWBB</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.467</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P2 TWBB</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.28</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.176</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M1 TWBB</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.09</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.676</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN06">
                      <p>M1 = first molar, P2 = second premolar and P1 = first premolar.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>In this sample, patients were treated by different dentists, but in order to obtain more
reliable results, measurements were made by only one previously calibrated examiner. The
error of the method used to assess intra and interexaminer reliability proved to be
small. No significant differences were found between measurements made by two operators
at two different time points. Interexaminer analysis showed that errors ranged from 0.30
to 1.08 mm. This may have occurred due to high resolution images offering excellent view
without overlapping structures.</p>
              <p>A disadvantage of the CBCT method is its greater radiation dose in comparison to
conventional radiographs (periapical and panoramic). However, CBCT is an invaluable tool
in orthodontic research. Good to excellent reliability of CBCT scans used for detection
of bone defects was demonstrated by Misch <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Furthermore, when compared to bidimensional radiographs, CBCT
showed great reliability and offered advantages when detecting and quantifying bone
fissures and fenestrations, as well as periodontal defects in the buccal bone.<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
</p>
              <p>Mandibular arch bone expansion studies with CBCT scans comparing SLB and CLB are rare in
the literature. And few studies have assessed the maxillary arch response to SLB and CLB
systems.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Nonetheless, some studies compared
arch expansion on dental casts and on digitized models, which may offer great
accuracy.<sup>7,10,11</sup> Claims have been made that SLB can result in broader arch
forms in comparison to CLB.<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Thus, this study
aimed at testing the null hypothesis that there are no significant differences in the
amount of expansion of the mandibular arch (dental and alveolar bone changes) during the
first 7 months of alignment and leveling when either SLB or CLB systems are used, as
demonstrated by analysis on CBCT and dental casts. </p>
              <p>According to Birnie,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Damon divulged his theory
that by using SLB with low friction and light forces more stable biological results
could be produced. Damon,<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> based on empirical and
anedotical evidence, attributed advantages to self-ligating brackets, among which is the
passive expansion of the arches. The Damon SLB system claims that post-treatment
computed tomography images show transverse arch development and normal alveolar bone on
buccal surface. Low friction and low force are purported to be good to physiologically
rebuild the alveolar bone.<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
</p>
              <p>The three-dimensional capability of CBCT makes it possible to noninvasively assess
alveolar bone changes for mandibular posterior teeth. We found that BBT and TWBB
measurements decreased from T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub> for both groups. A
significant difference occurred for the majority of measurements regarding BBT from
T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub> for both groups. There was significant difference for
the following measurements, from T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub>, regarding BBT changes:
CLB group - P1L (-1.51 mm, p = 0.016), P1R (-0.90 mm, p = 0.039), P2R (-1.09 mm, p =
0.007), M1R (-0.79 mm, p = 0.008); SLB group - P1R (-0.88 mm, p = 0.019), P2L (-0.64 mm,
p = 0.002), P2R (-1.09 mm, p &lt; 0.001), M1R (-0.54 mm, p = 0.025). However, no
significant differences were found between groups. Furthermore, no significant
differences from T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub> were observed between and within groups
for TWBB.</p>
              <p>The results of the present study confirm findings in the literature showing similar
behaviors for both brackets, particularly with regard to dental expansion assessed by
means of dental casts. Mandibular arch alignment resulted in transverse expansion
irrespective of the appliance system used. Interfirst premolar distances, measured on
dental casts with a digital caliper in both groups, increased (SLB, 1.27 mm; CLB, 1.87
mm). This result is similar to those found by Fleming <italic>et al,</italic>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> with an increase of 0.85 mm and 1.17 mm for SLB
and CLB, respectively. However, the change was not significantly different between the
two bracket systems. Further corroborating these findings, Vajaria el al<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> also found expansion in interfirst premolar
distances. As for intersecond premolar distances, there was an increase of 2.10 mm for
SLB and 1.75 mm for CLB; however, this increase was similar for both groups. Once again,
the results yielded by the present study are similar to those obtained by Fleming
<italic>et al</italic>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> (SLB= 1.43 mm, and CLB= 1.72 mm). Nevertheless,
contrary to our findings, Vajaria <italic>et al</italic>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> found a larger increase for the self-ligating
group (4.35 mm in comparison to 2.6 mm for the conventional group). Regarding intermolar
distances, there was an increase ranging from 1.4 to 2.4 mm for SLB, and from 0.43 to
1.85 mm for CLB.<sup>7,9,10,11,17,27,28</sup> On the other hand, a decrease in
intermolar distance was observed in only one study in which cases were treated by means
of premolar extractions.<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> We found
nonsignificant increases of mandibular first intermolar width for both SLB and CLB
groups, and there was no significant difference between the two bracket groups. The
present study showed molar expansion of 0.92 mm and 0.46 mm for SLB and CLB,
respectively. This result is in accordance with the study by Vajaria<italic> et
al.</italic>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Nonetheless, Pandis <italic>et al<sup><italic>10</italic>,<italic>17</italic></sup></italic> and Fleming <italic>et al</italic>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> found that SLB expanded more than CLB in the
molars region, and this difference was considered statistically significant.</p>
              <p>When the Pearson correlation coefficient was assessed, we found that the alveolar buccal
bone did not follow dental expansion. Therefore, the statements wherein self-ligating
brackets produce physiological and passive movements of the arches were not confirmed in
this study, at least 7 months after orthodontic treatment onset. Regarding buccal bone
changes, it seems that self-ligating appliances do not offer any advantages over the
conventional bracket system. Thus, the null hypothesis of the present study was
accepted; in other words, no significant differences were found between self-ligating
and conventional brackets systems regarding mandibular buccal bone plate expansion or
dentoalveolar expansion.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>» There is no difference between patients treated with self-ligating brackets or
conventional brackets, regarding mandibular dentoalveolar expansion.</p>
              <p>» There is no difference between patients treated with self-ligating brackets or
conventional brackets, regarding buccal bone plate changes (mandibular buccal bone
thickness and transversal width of buccal bone).</p>
              <p>» There were no significant correlations between buccal bone plate changes and
dentoalveolar expansion within groups.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="supported-by">
                <p>» The authors report no commercial, proprietary or financial interest in the products
or companies described in this article.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stolzenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The efficiency of the Russell attachment</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Oral Surg</source>
                  <year>1946</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>572</fpage>
                  <lpage>582</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20998745</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berger</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-ligation in the year 2000</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <lpage>81</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harradine</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The history and development of self-ligating brackets</article-title>
                  <source>Semin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Damon</surname>
                      <given-names>DH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Damon low-friction bracket: a biologically compatible
straight-wire system</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Orthod</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>670</fpage>
                  <lpage>680</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388398</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleming</surname>
                      <given-names>PS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>DiBiase</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>RT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-ligating appliances: evolution or revolution?</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>641</fpage>
                  <lpage>651</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19075378</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rinchuse</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miles</surname>
                      <given-names>PG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-ligating brackets: present and future</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>132</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <lpage>222</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17693372</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleming</surname>
                      <given-names>PS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>DiBiase</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarri</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>RT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of mandibular arch changes during alignment and leveling
with 2 preadjusted edgewise appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>136</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <lpage>347</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19732667</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleming</surname>
                      <given-names>PS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johal</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-ligating brackets in orthodontics. A systematic
review</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>80</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>575</fpage>
                  <lpage>584</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20050755</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>SS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Greenlee</surname>
                      <given-names>GM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>CL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Systematic review of self-ligating brackets</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>137</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>726.e1</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <page-range>726.e1-726.e18; discussion -7</page-range>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20685517</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pandis</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polychronopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliades</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-ligating vs conventional brackets in the treatment of mandibular
crowding: a prospective clinical trial of treatment duration and dental
effects</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>132</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <lpage>215</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17693371</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vajaria</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Begole</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kusnoto</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Galang</surname>
                      <given-names>MT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Obrez</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of incisor position and dental transverse dimensional
changes using the Damon system</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>647</fpage>
                  <lpage>652</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21446870</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tai</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishima</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shin</surname>
                      <given-names>JW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>3-dimensional cone-beam computed tomography analysis of transverse
changes with Schwarz appliances on both jaws</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>670</fpage>
                  <lpage>677</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21406000</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yagci</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Veli</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uysal</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ucar</surname>
                      <given-names>FI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ozer</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Enhos</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dehiscence and fenestration in skeletal Class I, II, and III
malocclusions assessed with cone-beam computed tomography</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <lpage>74</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21696298</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mah</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choo</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Practical applications of cone-beam computed tomography in
orthodontics</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>141</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>7S</fpage>
                  <lpage>13S</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20884934</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kortam</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tee</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fields</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of bone thickness on alveolar bone-height measurements from
cone-beam computed tomography images</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>139</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>e117</fpage>
                  <lpage>e127</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300222</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Timock</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cook</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McDonald</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leo</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crowe</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benninger</surname>
                      <given-names>BL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Accuracy and reliability of buccal bone height and thickness
measurements from cone-beam computed tomography imaging</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>140</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>734</fpage>
                  <lpage>744</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22051495</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pandis</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polychronopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Makou</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliades</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mandibular dental arch changes associated with treatment of crowding
using self-ligating and conventional brackets</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <lpage>253</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19959610</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tecco</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tete</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Perillo</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chimenti</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Festa</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Maxillary arch width changes during orthodontic treatment with fixed
self-ligating and traditional straight-wire appliances</article-title>
                  <source>World J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>290</fpage>
                  <lpage>294</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20072744</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cattaneo</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Treccani</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carlsson</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thorgeirsson</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Myrda</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cevidanes</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transversal maxillary dento-alveolar changes in patients treated with
active and passive self-ligating brackets: a randomized clinical trial using
CBCT-scans and digital models</article-title>
                  <source>Orthod Craniofac Res</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <lpage>233</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22008302</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pandis</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polychronopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliades</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sample size estimation: an overview with applications to orthodontic
clinical trial designs</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>140</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>e141</fpage>
                  <lpage>e146</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21967951</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leite</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Conti</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Navarro</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oltramari-Navarro</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of root resorption between self-ligating and conventional
preadjusted brackets using cone beam computed tomography</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1078</fpage>
                  <lpage>1082</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22409394</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Houston</surname>
                      <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The analysis of errors in orthodontic measurements</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1983</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>382</fpage>
                  <lpage>390</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6573846</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Misch</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yi</surname>
                      <given-names>ES</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarment</surname>
                      <given-names>DP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Accuracy of cone beam computed tomography for periodontal defect
measurements</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>77</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1261</fpage>
                  <lpage>1266</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16805691</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mol</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Balasundaram</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>In vitro cone beam computed tomography imaging of periodontal
bone</article-title>
                  <source>Dentomaxillofac Radiol</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
                  <lpage>324</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757716</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Birnie</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Damon passive self-ligating appliance system</article-title>
                  <source>Semin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <lpage>35</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>YL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qian</surname>
                      <given-names>YF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The clinical implication of self-ligating brackets</article-title>
                  <source>Shanghai Kou Qiang Yi Xue</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>431</fpage>
                  <lpage>435</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17924034</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleming</surname>
                      <given-names>PS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>DiBiase</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>RT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Randomized clinical trial of orthodontic treatment efficiency with
self-ligating and conventional fixed orthodontic appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>137</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>738</fpage>
                  <lpage>742</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20685528</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scott</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>DiBiase</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sherriff</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cobourne</surname>
                      <given-names>MT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Alignment efficiency of Damon3 self-ligating and conventional
orthodontic bracket systems: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>134</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>470.e1</fpage>
                  <lpage>470.e8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929262</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
