<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:47:10Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4686746" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4686746</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-12-29</datestamp>
        <setSpec>dpjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dpjo</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2176-9451</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2177-6709</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dental Press International</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4686746</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4686746</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4686746</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26691971</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2177-6709.20.6.060-067.oar</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Facial morphology and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Capistrano</surname>
                    <given-names>Anderson</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cordeiro</surname>
                    <given-names>Aldir</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Capelozza</surname>
                    <given-names>Leopoldino</given-names>
                    <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Almeida</surname>
                    <given-names>Veridiana Correia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Silva</surname>
                    <given-names>Priscila Izabela de Castro e</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Martinez</surname>
                    <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Almeida-Pedrin</surname>
                    <given-names>Renata Rodrigues</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Professor of Occlusion and Orthodontics, Faculdade de Odontologia de
Recife (FOR-PE), Recife, Pernambuco, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>MSc in Orthodontics, Universidade Sagrado Coração (USC), Bauru, São
Paulo, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Professor, Universidade Sagrado Coração (USC), Undergraduate and
Graduate programs, Bauru, São Paulo, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Postgraduate student, Cooperativa dos Odontologistas de Pernambuco
(COOPE), Recife, Pernambuco, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Student, Sindicato dos Odontologistas no Estado de Pernambuco (SOEPE),
Postgraduate program in Orthodontics, Recife, Pernambuco, Brazil</aff>
              <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Specialist in Sleep Medicine, Universidade de São Paulo (USP), São
Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil, and Stanford University, Stanford, California, USA</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Contact address:</bold> Anderson Capistrano
E-mail:<email>capiss@uol.com.br</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>Nov-Dec</season>
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Nov-Dec</season>
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>20</volume>
              <issue>6</issue>
              <fpage>60</fpage>
              <lpage>67</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>30</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2015</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective:</title>
                  <p> This study aimed at assessing the relationship between facial morphological
patterns (I, II, III, Long Face and Short Face) as well as facial types
(brachyfacial, mesofacial and dolichofacial) and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) in
patients attending a center specialized in sleep disorders. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods: </title>
                  <p>Frontal, lateral and smile photographs of 252 patients (157 men and 95 women),
randomly selected from a polysomnography clinic, with mean age of 40.62 years,
were evaluated. In order to obtain diagnosis of facial morphology, the sample was
sent to three professors of Orthodontics trained to classify patients' face
according to five patterns, as follows: 1) Pattern I; 2) Pattern II; 3) Pattern
III; 4) Long facial pattern; 5) Short facial pattern. Intraexaminer agreement was
assessed by means of Kappa index. The professors ranked patients' facial type
based on a facial index that considers the proportion between facial width and
height. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results: </title>
                  <p>The multiple linear regression model evinced that, when compared to Pattern I,
Pattern II had the apnea and hypopnea index (AHI) worsened in 6.98 episodes.
However, when Pattern II was compared to Pattern III patients, the index for the
latter was 11.45 episodes lower. As for the facial type, brachyfacial patients had
a mean AHI of 22.34, while dolichofacial patients had a significantly statistical
lower index of 10.52. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion: </title>
                  <p>Patients' facial morphology influences OSA. Pattern II and brachyfacial patients
had greater AHI, while Pattern III patients showed a lower index.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objetivo:</title>
                  <p> o objetivo deste estudo foi avaliar a associação entre os padrões morfológicos
faciais e tipos faciais (braquifacial, mesofacial e dolicofacial) com a Apneia
Obstrutiva do Sono (AOS) em pacientes de um centro especializado em distúrbios do
sono. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Métodos: </title>
                  <p>foram utilizadas fotografias faciais de frente, perfil e sorriso de 252
indivíduos, selecionados aleatoriamente entre pacientes que procuraram uma clínica
especializada em polissonografia. Para o diagnóstico morfológico facial, a amostra
foi enviada a três professores de Ortodontia treinados na classificação do padrão
facial, e cada um recebeu a orientação para classificar o padrão facial da
seguinte forma: 1 = Padrão I, 2 = Padrão II, 3 = Padrão III, 4 = Padrão Face Longa
e 5 = Padrão Face Curta. A concordância interexaminadores foi avaliada por meio do
Índice Kappa. O diagnóstico do tipo facial foi estabelecido por meio de um índice
facial que leva em consideração a proporção entre a largura e altura da face. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Resultados: </title>
                  <p>no modelo de regressão linear múltipla, ficou evidenciado que o Padrão II teve a
capacidade de agravar o índice de apneia e hipopneia (IAH) em 6,98, enquanto os
pacientes do Padrão III tinham esse índice atenuado em 11,45. Para o tipo facial,
os pacientes braquifaciais apresentaram um IAH médio de 22,34, enquanto o grupo
classificado como dolicofacial mostrou um índice menor, de 10,52, com
significância estatística. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusão: </title>
                  <p>o desenho morfológico facial se mostrou um considerável fator de agravamento ou
proteção da SAOS, onde os indivíduos Padrão II e braquifaciais tiveram IAH
maiores, enquanto nos pacientes Padrão III esse índice foi reduzido.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Diagnosis</kwd>
                <kwd>Face</kwd>
                <kwd>Obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="2"/>
                <table-count count="8"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="25"/>
                <page-count count="8"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>In the last 20 years, Dentistry has discussed cases of snoring and obstructive sleep
apnea (OSA). Within an interdisciplinary approach, neurologists, otolaryngologists,
physiotherapists, speech therapists and clinicians have all recognized the importance of
assessing these patients from the point of view of Dentistry, not only in terms of
therapeutic control, but also in preventing it by means of treating potential
malocclusions that could increase the risk of airway disorders, particularly when they
are associated with predisposing factors such as obesity, hypertension and aging.<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</p>
              <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a common disorder associated with snoring, upper airway
collapse at sleep, oxygen desaturation and fragmented sleep. It is also associated with
cardiovascular morbidity, risk of car accidents and general mortality.<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> OSA diagnosis is not simple, since polysomnography
requires patient's monitoring by a specialist at a sleep laboratory, which renders the
procedure relatively expensive and difficult. In order to simplify diagnosis, a study
aimed at assessing differences in craniofacial phenotype among caucasian patients with
OSA. The study found that detailed anatomic data, such as facial width, distance between
eyes, as well as mandibular length and chin-neck angle, were useful in predicting OSA
with a sensitivity index of 86%.<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
</p>
              <p>Anatomical airway narrowing is among the etiological factors of snoring and OSA. It
consists in soft tissues excess, macroglossia and retrognathism. This condition causes
great resistance that hinders air flow and engenders negative intraluminal pressure
while inspiring, thereby favoring breathing collapse. The risk of developing this
disorder significantly increases with weight gain, aging, increased neck circumference
and alcohol consumption. The following systemic conditions also appear as predisposing
factors: systemic hypertension, untreated hypothyroidism, acromegaly and nasal
obstruction.<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
</p>
              <p>OSA recognition in the overall population remains low and most patients are not
diagnosed.<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Thus, there is a critical,
clinical need to develop better methods that allow OSA recognition and diagnosis. The
present study was conducted to assess the relationship between facial morphological
pattern, within a contemporary context of genetic determinism, and OSA. This
relationship might stand for an important clinical evidence of quick, inexpensive and
simple diagnosis of a disease that significantly impairs patients' quality of life.</p>
              <p>The literature<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> has demonstrated a relationship between
craniofacial dimensions and upper airway structures in patients with OSA. These results
give support to the potential role facial measurements play in the anatomical phenotype
of OSA.</p>
              <p> Craniofacial morphology seems to be among the predisposing factors for the development
of OSA. Mandibular deficiency and increased anterior-inferior facial height highlight
such possibility.<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The majority of
publications<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> used cephalometric measurements to define
craniofacial morphology, which may cause considerable doubt and contradiction. In an
attempt to avoid it, the present study aims at assessing a diagnosis system that
considers the genetic determinism of craniofacial morphology, with specific methods
centered around a diagnosis concept based on facial patterns,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14 </xref>in addition to studying its relationship with
obstructive sleep apnea in adult patients.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Sample calculation</title>
                <p>For sample size calculation, alpha = 5% and the power of the test was of 80%.
Calculation was based on multiple linear regression analysis, with AHI as the
dependent variable; and sex, age, BMI, facial type (three categories) and facial
pattern (five categories) as independent variables, thereby totaling 11 predictor
variables. Effect size was set at 0.10 and minimal sample size was of 178 cases.
Calculation was carried out using the software developed by Soper,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> in 2014.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Sample selection</title>
                <p>The final sample comprised 252 patients with a mean age of 40.62 (from 18 to 62 years
old) and a mean BMI of 28.74 ± 4.73). A total of 157 men and 95 women who were
referred to a center specialized in sleep disorders and polysomnography. Patients'
main complaint involved snoring, insomnia, restless nights, chronic pain, memory
deficit, bruxism and daytime sleepiness. The research project from which the present
study originated was approved by Universidade Sagrado Coração (USC) Institutional
Review Board under protocol #412.260. All patients signed an informed consent
form.</p>
                <p>After interviewing an average of 900 patients, some of them were excluded based on
the following criteria:</p>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="simple">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» BMI over 40. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Impaired posterior occlusal support. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Patients with a beard that hindered facial analysis. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Patients using continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or intraoral
appliance and who were being subjected to the examination, so as to assess
the therapeutic effectiveness of the devices. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Craniofacial syndromic patients. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary diseases (CPOC) or
neurological or mental disorders who were affected by upper airway
infection. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Patients with history of orthognathic surgery or any other type of airway
surgery. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Patients under 18 and above 62 years old. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» Patients who, for any reason, did not agree in taking part in the
research. </p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>» After facial pattern analysis, other patients were also excluded for
presenting three different diagnoses. </p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p>The 252 individuals comprising the sample were divided into two groups according to
polysomnography results. The group without OSA (Group I, 77 patients) and the group
with OSA (Group II, 175 patients) which presented an AHI value greater than five
episodes of apnea per hour of sleep, enough to characterize the individuals as having
the disease.</p>
                <p>Frontal, lateral and smile standardized photographs were used to assess patients'
facial morphological pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig 1</xref>). The
photographs were inserted in a PowerPoint<sup>TM</sup> slide presentation and sent
via WeTransfer<sup>TM</sup> to three experienced orthodontic professors. Each
examiner was advised to classify patients' facial pattern according to the following:
1) Pattern I; 2) Pattern II; 3) Pattern III; 4) Long Facial Pattern; 5) Short Facial
Pattern. Examiners did not have access to patients' reports and, for this reason,
were unaware of those with and without OSA.</p>
                <p>
                  <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Figure 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>- Example of photograph set-up for diagnosis.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2176-9451-dpjo-20-06-00060-gf01"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p>Examiners reached facial type diagnosis through a facial index (n-gn/zy-zy)<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> that considers the proportion between facial
width and height, with a mean value of 88.5 for men and 86.2 for women (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>). Measurements were obtained with the
aid of Photoshop<sup>TM</sup> CS4 software (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig
2</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>- Facial index.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>Men</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>Women</bold>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesofacial</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.4 - 93.6</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.6 - 90.8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brachyfacial</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 83.4</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 81.6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dolichofacial</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 93.6</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 90.8</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Figure 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>- One of the patients comprising the sample. Image used to illustrate
how facial type was obtained.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2176-9451-dpjo-20-06-00060-gf02"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p>Patients were classified as mesofacial, brachyfacial and dolichofacial, as shown in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>. </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Error of the method</title>
                <p>To assess the error of classifying both facial pattern and type, Kappa index<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> was used (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>). For facial pattern, the diagnoses of three examiners were
crossed for each patient. Patients with three different diagnoses were excluded from
this study. Four patients were excluded by means of this criterion. As for facial
type, 30% of the sample was randomly selected, so as to reassess patients' facial
proportions after 30 days.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>- Agreement percentage and Kappa's values for intraexaminer agreement
assessment.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>Measurement</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>% of agreement</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>Kappa</bold>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examiner 1
<italic>versus</italic> Examiner 2</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.8</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examiner 1
<italic>versus</italic> Examiner 3</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.4</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examiner 2
<italic>versus</italic> Examiner 3</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.4</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facial type 1
<italic>versus</italic> Facial type 2</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.4</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>All assessments reached an agreement value that ranged between strong and nearly
perfect. Landis &amp; Koch's classification<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
was used as reference.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Data were arranged in tables and charts using absolute (n) and relative (%)
frequencies. Quantitative variables were described by mean and standard deviation
parameters.</p>
                <p>To assess the relationship between variables, Kruskal-Wallis, chi-square and
Spearman's correlation tests were used.</p>
                <p>To assess the combined effect of sex, age, BMI, facial type and facial pattern on the
AHI value, stepwise backward multiple linear regression analysis was used.
Significance level was set at 5% (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) for all tests. All
statistical procedures were carried out by means of Statistica version 12 (StatSoft
Inc., Tulsa, USA) software.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Of the 289 patients, 29 were excluded based on the exclusion criteria. A total of 260
patients were analyzed, four of which were excluded for presenting three different
morphological diagnoses, one for not having polysomnography concluded and three for not
having polysomnography results sent for analysis within a reasonable time. Thus, 252
patients were included in the statistical analysis.</p>
              <p>In terms of facial morphological pattern and OSA prevalence, patients were classified
according to data presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>. Data
analysis revealed statistical difference between Pattern II and long face. Despite no
relevant statistically significant difference, the percentage of short face individuals
with OSA is greater than expected, as it totaled 77.8% against 22.2% for individuals
without the disorder. Both percentages are significantly near those found for Pattern
II, 80.3% and 19.7%, respectively. When facial patterns were assessed by Kruskal-Wallis
test, according to the absolute AHI value, there was statistically significant
difference between Pattern II and long face (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table
4</xref>). Importantly, it is worth noting that the mean AHI value for the Pattern
III group (11.4) was nearly half that of the Pattern II group (22.51).</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>- Relationship between facial pattern and OSA.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="3"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Facial pattern</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Group I</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Group II</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                          <bold>Total</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>n</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>%</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>n</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>%</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern I</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern II</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.3</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern III</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short face</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.8</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long face</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.0</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN03">
                      <p>Chi-square (<italic>p</italic> = 0.009* - Pattern II ≠ Long Face).</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>- Comparison among the five facial patterns with regard to AHI measurements
based on Kruskal-Wallis test.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Facial pattern</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>n</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Mean</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>SD</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern I</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.97</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern II</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.51</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.05</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027 (P II ≠ L.F.)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern III</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.31</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short face</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.03</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.31</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long face</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.22</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.94</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="t05">Table 5</xref> shows no statistically significant
differences for distribution of facial types for groups I and II. Nevertheless, when
groups were classified according to the AHI value (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t06">Table 6</xref>), there was statistically significant difference between brachyfacial
patients with a mean AHI of 22.34, and dolichofacial patients with a mean AHI value of
10.52.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>- Relationship between facial type and OSA.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="3"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Facial type</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Without OSA</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>With OSA</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                          <bold>Total</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>n</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>%</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>n</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>%</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesofacial</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brachyfacial</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.5</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dolichofacial</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN05">
                      <p>Chi-square <italic>(p</italic> = 0.505 ns).</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>- Comparison among the three facial types with regard to AHI measurements
based on Kruskal-Wallis test.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Facial type</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>n</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Mean</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>SD</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesofacial</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.63</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.51</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brachyfacial</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.34</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.87</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B ≠ D</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dolichofacial</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.52</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.65</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>Results reveal that facial pattern influenced the apnea and hypopnea index (AHI)
severity when multiple linear regression analysis was used. This is because apnea is a
multifactorial disorder in which the interaction among variables, such as BMI, sex and
age, also influence AHI values. Importantly, multiple linear regression analysis is
considered adequate for data analysis, since it allows assessment of interaction between
two or among more than two variables.</p>
              <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="t07">Table 7</xref> shows that when using Pattern I as a
pattern of comparison, Pattern II had AHI severity worsened in 6.98 episodes.
Conversely, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t08">Table 8</xref> shows that, when Pattern II
was used as reference, Pattern I individuals had the AHI value reduced in 5.06 while
Pattern III patients had the AHI reduced in 11.45.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t07" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>- Stepwise backward multiple linear regression analysis with AHI as
dependent variable; and sex, age, BMI, facial type and facial pattern as
independent variables.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Independent variables</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>B</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>B pattern error</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Beta</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Adjusted R<sup>2</sup></bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-49.50</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.97</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex 0 = F; 1 = M</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.953</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.406</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.250</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.311</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.246</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern II P. I = 0</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.983</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.548</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t08" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 8</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>- Stepwise backward multiple linear regression analysis with AHI as
dependent variable; and sex, age, BMI, facial type and facial pattern as
independent variables.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Independent variables</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>B</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>B pattern error</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Beta</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Adjusted R<sup>2</sup></bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-44.76</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.84</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex: 0 = F; 1 = M</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.349</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.402</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.530</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.291</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.326</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern I P. II = 0</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.056</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.495</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.118</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern III P. II = 0</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.453</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.950</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.132</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021*</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="t08TFN08">
                      <p>* - statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t07">Tables 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t08">8</xref>, beta analysis reveals that the following factors influenced AHI
in ascending order: facial morphological pattern, male sex, age and BMI.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Craniofacial morphology plays an important role in OSA<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> in adult patients. Increased gonial angle,
changes in anterior and posterior facial height, decreased anterior cranial base and
mandibular deficiency seem to contribute to pharyngeal airway narrowing.<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</p>
              <p>Cephalometry is, without a doubt, the method most used in current literature to analyze
facial morphology and its relationship with OSA.<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Nevertheless, with a view to rendering
diagnosis easier, or at least suspecting the existence of the disease, front-view and
profile photographs have been used to assess anatomical data, such as facial width,
distance between the eyes, chin-neck angle and mandibular length.<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</p>
              <p>Morphological expression used for diagnosis in Orthodontics might be better assessed and
understood by means of facial soft tissues analysis. In this sense, cephalometry plays a
secondary and supplementary role and could not be used as a primary diagnostic tool to
determine facial morphology. The reproducibility and reliability of the method still
allow assessment of the influence of growth and therapeutic actions on facial
morphology.<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</p>
              <p>Analysis of facial morphology was based on the clinical experience of three professors
of Orthodontics. Intraexaminer agreement yielded good results (78.9%) with a Kappa index
of 0.65 (strong agreement). The methods employed in the present study were based on Reis
et al<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> who found an intraexaminer agreement of
72%, with Kappa index of 0.65 (strong agreement). Both values were close to those found
for the present study. With a view to rendering the relationship between facial
morphology, assessed within a subjective approach, and OSA, four individuals were
excluded from the sample due to having three different diagnoses.</p>
              <p>A total of 30% of the sample was randomly selected and measured again after 30 days, so
as to reassess patients' facial proportions. Agreement was of 90.4% with a Kappa index
of 0.90 (nearly perfect), thereby resulting in high reliability of research results.</p>
              <p>Due to lack of studies focusing on establishing a relationship between facial morphology
and obstructive sleep apnea, based on the subjective determination of facial
morphological pattern and facial type as well as analysis of proportion between facial
width and height, comparison of results is usually made with facial anthropometric
measurements and, most of times, by means of cephalometry.</p>
              <p>One of the most common findings in the literature addressing patients' facial morphology
is the relationship established between OSA and convex facial profile,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> even though Katyal et al's systematic
review<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> minimizes such association, at least
in children. Although no statistically significant difference was found, Pattern II
patients present greater OSA prevalence (80.3%) in comparison to patients without the
disorder (19.7%). In terms of AHI severity, Pattern II individuals present the greatest
incidence, with 22.51 episodes of apnea per hour of sleep in comparison to 11.40
episodes for Pattern III individuals who are morphologically opposite to Pattern
II.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> These results reveal a tendency of OSA
worsening in Pattern II patients, even though statistically significant difference was
only observed when the Pattern II group was compared to Long Face patients.</p>
              <p>As for patients' facial type, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t06">Table 6</xref> shows that
brachyfacial individuals with a mean AHI value of 22.34 are significantly different from
dolichofacial patients who yielded a mean AHI value of 10.52. This finding disagrees
with the results commonly found in the literature which does not establish a strong
association between dolichofacial patients and OSA.<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> However, this fact is not unanimous;<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> it is supported by Grauer et al<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> who used cone-beam computed tomography and did
not find any differences in airspace volume for dolichofacial patients. Moreover, the
study by Haskell et al<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>assessed 50 patients by
means of cone-beam computed tomography and found greater airspace in vertical
patients.</p>
              <p>With a view to highlighting the importance of the factors assessed herein (facial
pattern and type), multiple linear regression analysis was employed to assess the
relevance of the present variables in comparison to other OSA predicting factors, such
as obesity mathematically measured by BMI.<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> In the present analysis, Pattern II patients
had the AHI value increased in 6.98 episodes of apnea per hour of sleep when compared to
Pattern I individuals. Conversely, Pattern III patients had the AHI value reduced in
11.45 when compared with Pattern II patients. Data analysis suggests that while Pattern
II might render OSA more severe, Pattern III seems to protect patients against the
sleeping disorder. This statistical analysis did not reveal any relationship between
facial type and OSA.</p>
              <p>The low prevalence of long face (4.0%) and short face (3.6%) in the sample studied did
not allow us to make further inference with regard to the occurrence of OSA in either
one of these morphological groups. Likewise, low prevalence also seems to be found in
the overall population. In 2007, the study conducted by Siécola<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> comprised 151 children aged between 7 and 13 years old and who
were enrolled in two different schools in the city of Bauru. The study found a
prevalence of 5.96% of long-face individuals and 1.98% of short-face individuals.
Nevertheless, should the morphological diagnosis of long face be strongly associated
with OSA, as suggested by a few studies,<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> this group would be expected to appear in a
higher number in a sample selected at a clinics specialized in sleeping disorders where
69.5% of individuals had OSA.</p>
              <p>Due to being a multifactorial disease, the etiology of OSA is too diverse and complex to
be explained by a simple relationship established between facial morphology and the
development of the disease. However, therapeutic orthodontic actions should respect the
tendency towards these results and include functional aspects related to OSA in their
therapeutic practice. The importance of considering patients' craniofacial morphology as
a factor that protects or worsens OSA is confirmed by asystematic literature review
carried out by Pirklbauer et al<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> in 2011. The
authors found that the most effective surgical approach employed to treat OSA is
advancement of the maxilla and mandible, i.e., exactly when a drastic facial
morphological change occurs. Post-operative polysomnography results can be compared to
those yielded by CPAP therapy.</p>
              <p>Adult brachyfacial patients and Pattern II due to mandibular deficiency should be
included in the benefits of decompensatory orthodontic treatment for surgeries of
mandibular advancement: a functional breathing benefit that widens the upper airways
while reducing the anatomical risk of OSA development. Meanwhile, if patients comprising
this diagnostic group have incomplete growth, compensatory treatment with reduction in
intraoral volume, such as upper premolars extraction, should be avoided, as it could
result in maintenance or exacerbation of anatomical disadvantages likely to lead to the
development of OSA in the long term, particularly when associated with other
predisposing factors such as obesity and aging.<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
</p>
              <p>Adult Pattern III patients, however, should have mandible position preserved, in order
to avoid potential mandibular setback, unless supported by prognathism severity and
impaired esthetics. Thus, whenever recommending advancement of the maxilla, clinicians
should consider including the benefit of widening upper airways in patients' orthodontic
and surgical planning, thereby preserving the functional benefits these patients seem to
have with regard to the development of OSA. For growing patients, the protocol of
widening the maxilla is also supported by the gain in breathing volume, which minimizes
the potential for developing OSA, thereby providing patients with undeniable functional
benefits.</p>
              <p>The evidence of an association between facial morphology and OSA point to therapeutic
orthodontic modalities that preserve or enhance the shape of the anatomical traits of
the face, even though such gain is limited by genetic determinism. This approach would
aim at offering long-term functional respiratory, yet minimal, benefits.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>Based on the results of this study, it is reasonable to conclude that:</p>
              <p>
                <list list-type="simple">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>1) Pattern II seems to worsen OSA, whereas Pattern III seems to decrease its
severity; </p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>2) Brachyfacial type was more associated with severe apnea than the
dolichofacial type; </p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>3) The following aspects influence AHI in an ascending order: facial
morphological pattern, sex, age and BMI. </p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Our most sincere thanks to Sonocentro for providing the study sample. The center is
represented by Drs. Sandra Martinez, Frederico Jucá, Marcela Santos, José Enoque Godoy
and Patrícia Santos, as well as the technicians Marluce, Patrícia and Cilene who helped
us locating patients' reports. We also thank the orthodontists Fábio Guedes, Silvia Reis
and Aldir Cordeiro profusely for carefully assessing this study sample in terms of
patients' facial morphological pattern.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other" id="fn01">
                <label>»</label>
                <p> The authors report no commercial, proprietary or financial interest in the products
or companies described in this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other" id="fn02">
                <label>»</label>
                <p> Patients displayed in this article previously approved the use of their facial and
intraoral photographs.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hiestand</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Britz</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Phillips</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence of symptoms and risk of sleep apnea in the US population:
results from the national sleep foundation sleep in America 2005
poll</article-title>
                  <source>Chest</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>130</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>780</fpage>
                  <lpage>786</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16963675</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>RW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petocz</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prvan</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chan</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grunstein</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cistulli</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prediction of obstructive sleep apnea with craniofacial photographic
analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Sleep</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <lpage>52</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19189778</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caldas</surname>
                      <given-names>SGFR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santos-pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martins</surname>
                      <given-names>LP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matoso</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efetividade dos aparelhos intrabucais de avanço mandibular no
tratamento do ronco e da síndrome da apneia e hipopneia obstrutiva do sono
(SAHOS): revisão sistemática</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Dental Press Ortod Ortop Facial</source>
                  <season>Jul-Ago</season>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>14</issue>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <lpage>82</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>RW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chan</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grunstein</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cistulli</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Craniofacial phenotyping in obstructive sleep apnea-a novel
quantitative photographic approach</article-title>
                  <source>Sleep</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>45</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19189777</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>RW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sutherland</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chan</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeng</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grunstein</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Darendeliler</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Relationship between surface facial dimensions and upper airway
structures in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>
                  <source>Sleep</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1249</fpage>
                  <lpage>1254</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20857873</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Albajalan</surname>
                      <given-names>OB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samsudin</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hassan</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Craniofacial morphology of Malay patients with obstructive sleep
apnoea</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>509</fpage>
                  <lpage>514</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118908</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Di Francesco</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Monteiro</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paulo</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buranello</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imamura</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Craniofacial morphology and sleep apnea in children with obstructed
upper airways: differences between genders</article-title>
                  <source>Sleep Med</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>616</fpage>
                  <lpage>620</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22459090</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katyal</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pamula</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daynes</surname>
                      <given-names>CN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kennedy</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sampson</surname>
                      <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Craniofacial and upper airway morphology in pediatric sleep-disordered
breathing: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>143</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <lpage>30.e3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23273357</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kikuchi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Higurashi</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miyazaki</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Itasaka</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Facial patterns of obstructive sleep apnea patients using Ricketts'
method</article-title>
                  <source>Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>336</fpage>
                  <lpage>337</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11186102</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kubota</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nakayama</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Takada</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matsuyama</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sakai</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yoshizawa</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Facial axis angle as a risk factor for obstructive sleep
apnea</article-title>
                  <source>Intern Med</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>805</fpage>
                  <lpage>810</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16157977</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chang</surname>
                      <given-names>ET</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shiao</surname>
                      <given-names>GM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Craniofacial abnormalities in Chinese patients with obstructive and
positional sleep apnea</article-title>
                  <source>Sleep Med</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>403</fpage>
                  <lpage>410</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17658296</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banabilh</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asha'ari</surname>
                      <given-names>ZA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamid</surname>
                      <given-names>SS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence of snoring and craniofacial features in Malaysian children
from hospital-based medical clinic population</article-title>
                  <source>Sleep Breath</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <lpage>274</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17978839</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capelozza</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Diagnóstico em Ortodontia</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Maringá</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Dental Press</publisher-name>
                  <year>2004</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reis</surname>
                      <given-names>SAB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abrão</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Claro</surname>
                      <given-names>CAA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capelozza</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the determinants of facial profile
aesthetics</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Press J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <lpage>67</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soper</surname>
                      <given-names>DS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>A-priori sample size calculator for multiple regression [Software]</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.danielsoper.com/statcalc">http://www.danielsoper.com/statcalc</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farkas</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Posnick</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hreczko</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Growth patterns of the face: a morphometric study</article-title>
                  <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <lpage>315</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1643058</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleiss</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Statistical methods for rates and proportions</source>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
                  <year>1973</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Landis</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koch</surname>
                      <given-names>GG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The measurement of observer agreement for categorical
data</article-title>
                  <source>Biometrics</source>
                  <year>1977</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <lpage>174</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">843571</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reis</surname>
                      <given-names>SAB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abrão</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Claro</surname>
                      <given-names>CAA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fornazari</surname>
                      <given-names>RF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capelozza</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Agreement among orthodontists regarding facial pattern
diagnosis</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Press J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <lpage>72</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grauer</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cevidanes</surname>
                      <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Styner</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ackerman</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Proffit</surname>
                      <given-names>WR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pharyngeal airway volume and shape from cone-beam computed tomography:
relationship to facial morphology</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>136</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>805</fpage>
                  <lpage>814</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19962603</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banabilh</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samsudin</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suzina</surname>
                      <given-names>AH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dinsuhaimi</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Facial profile shape, malocclusion and palatal morphology in Malay
obstructive sleep apnea patients</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>80</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19852637</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huynh</surname>
                      <given-names>NT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morton</surname>
                      <given-names>PD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rompré</surname>
                      <given-names>PH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Papadakis</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Remise</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Associations between sleep-disordered breathing symptoms and facial
and dental morphometry, assessed with screening examinations</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>140</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>762</fpage>
                  <lpage>770</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22133940</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haskell</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haskell</surname>
                      <given-names>BS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spoon</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feng</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The relationship of vertical skeletofacial morphology to oropharyngeal
airway shape using cone beam computed tomography: possible implications for airway
restriction</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>84</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>548</fpage>
                  <lpage>554</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24168401</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siecola</surname>
                      <given-names>GS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Prevalência de padrão facial e má oclusão em populações de duas escolas
diferentes de Ensino Fundamental</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Bauru (SP)</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Universidade de São Paulo</publisher-name>
                  <year>2007</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pirklbauer</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russmueller</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stiebellehner</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nell</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinko</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Millesi</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Maxillomandibular advancement for treatment of obstructive sleep apnea
syndrome: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>e165</fpage>
                  <lpage>e176</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21605790</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
