<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:33Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10728525" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10728525</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-12-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>cedr</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" id="cre2814" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2057-4347</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRE2</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2057-4347</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10728525</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10728525</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10728525</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38018029</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38018029</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.814</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CRE2814</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="overline">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effectiveness of perioperative oral hygiene management using a cetylpyridinium chloride‐, dipotassium glycyrrhizinate, and tranexamic acid‐based mouthwash as an adjunct to mechanical oral hygiene in patients with maxillomandibular fixation: A randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">AIJIMA and YAMASHITA</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="cre2814-cr-0001" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Aijima</surname>
                    <given-names>Reona</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4016-8839</contrib-id>
                  <xref rid="cre2814-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="cre2814-cr-0002" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yamashita</surname>
                    <given-names>Yoshio</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cre2814-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <address>
                    <email>yamashy2@cc.saga-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="cre2814-aff-0001">
                <label>
                  <sup>1</sup>
                </label>
                <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Faculty of Medicine</named-content>
                <institution>Saga University</institution>
                <city>Saga</city>
                <country country="JP">Japan</country>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold> Yoshio Yamashita, Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Faculty of Medicine, Saga University, Nabeshima 5‐1‐1, Saga 849‐8501, Japan.<break/>
Email: <email>yamashy2@cc.saga-u.ac.jp</email>
<break/>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>9</volume>
              <issue seq="110">6</issue>
              <issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.v9.6</issue-id>
              <fpage>1044</fpage>
              <lpage>1050</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>05</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>31</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <!--&#x000a9; 2023 The Authors. Clinical and Experimental Dental Research published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd.-->
                <copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">© 2023 The Authors. <italic toggle="yes">Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</italic> published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CRE2-9-1044.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec id="cre2814-sec-0010">
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>Maxillomandibular fixation requires the jawbones to remain static. Mechanical cleaning is also carried out by brushing or with a water flosser to maintain the oral cavity in a hygienic state, but this cannot be considered sufficient. Mouthwashes are used as a substitute for mechanical cleaning or in a supplementary role after such cleaning. The aim is to evaluate the effectiveness of HABITPRO mouthwash, which contains cetylpyridinium chloride, dipotassium glycyrrhizinate, and tranexamic acid in the specific environment created by maxillomandibular fixation used as an adjunct to mechanical cleaning.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="cre2814-sec-0020">
                  <title>Material and Methods</title>
                  <p>A total of 55 patients who had undergone maxillomandibular fixation were randomly allocated to either a HABITPRO group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 29) or a placebo group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 26). To investigate their oral hygiene status, their plaque control record (PCR) was reviewed, and the caries‐related bacterial counts, pH, acid buffering capacity, white blood cell count, and ammonia in saliva were measured immediately before maxillomandibular fixation, on Day 10 of fixation, and immediately after fixation was released.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="cre2814-sec-0030">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>After approximately 2–3 weeks of mouthwash use, the PCR index also increased significantly in the placebo group compared with baseline, whereas it remained almost steady in the HABITPRO group. Additionally, salivary ammonia levels decreased significantly in the HABITPRO group compared to that of the placebo group.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="cre2814-sec-0040">
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Even with maxillomandibular fixation, continued gargling with HABITPRO mouthwash in the perioperative period as an adjunct to mechanical cleaning can help maintain better oral hygiene and reduce bacterial counts.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd id="cre2814-kwd-0001">cetylpyridinium chloride</kwd>
                <kwd id="cre2814-kwd-0002">dipotassium glycyrrhizinate</kwd>
                <kwd id="cre2814-kwd-0003">mouthwash</kwd>
                <kwd id="cre2814-kwd-0004">tranexamic acid</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group id="funding-0001">
                  <funding-source>None</funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="2"/>
                <table-count count="4"/>
                <page-count count="7"/>
                <word-count count="4845"/>
              </counts>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>2.0</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>December 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.3.6 mode:remove_FC converted:19.12.2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
            <notes>
              <p content-type="self-citation">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0029"><string-name><surname>Aijima</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Yamashita</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Effectiveness of perioperative oral hygiene management using a cetylpyridinium chloride‐, dipotassium glycyrrhizinate‐, and tranexamic acid‐based mouthwash as an adjunct to mechanical oral hygiene in patients with maxillomandibular fixation: a randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1045</fpage>–<lpage>1051</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.814</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </p>
            </notes>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="cre2814-sec-0050">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>It has long been known that the oral cavity is a breeding ground for bacteria, because it is not only maintained at a constant temperature, but it is also a moist environment (Aas et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The intraoral microbiota is known to change in accordance with the intraoral environment (Akiyama et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Sano et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Takeshita et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). As is well known, this means that the environment in the mouth, which anatomically is the entrance to both the digestive tract and the respiratory system, has a range of systemic effects. In addition to the diseases of aspiration pneumonia and diabetes mellitus, its contribution to frailty has also come under scrutiny in recent years (Lu &amp; Yang, <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Tanaka et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Xue et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Yoneyama et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>).</p>
              <p>Under normal circumstances when homeostasis is maintained, individuals are able to coexist with the commensal resident intraoral biota by means of their own immunity and natural purification. However, diminished immunity in the periprocedural period (whether the procedure involves surgery, radiotherapy, chemotherapy, or other treatment) or due to age means that homeostasis can no longer be maintained, and a range of problems can occur, including wound infection, stomatitis and resulting secondary infection, caries, and periodontitis. Stomatitis is a particular issue during radiotherapy and chemotherapy, and since it causes bleeding and pain, mechanical cleaning becomes difficult (Saadeh, <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). In addition, if food consumption by mouth decreases as a result of mucosal inflammation, nutritional status worsens, and the healing of this mucosal inflammation is delayed in a vicious circle.</p>
              <p>Special conditions caused by surgery are also known to affect the oral environment in various ways. For example, patients with a mandibular fracture and those who have undergone orthognathic surgery may undergo maxillomandibular fixation to encourage bony healing, but this means that they are unable to open their mouths and cannot eat by mouth for a certain period. The most common complication after these surgeries is postoperative infection. Antimicrobial administration plays an important role in the prevention of postoperative infections, but carries the risk of diarrhea and the increasing bacterial resistance (Thornhill et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Thus, reducing of oral bacterial counts is of paramount importance.　During this fixation period, physical oral cleaning is inadequate, and the oral environment deteriorates. Brushing and water flossing are used for mechanical cleaning, but this cannot be considered sufficient. Under these conditions, chemical cleaning by gargling with mouthwash has long been used as a supplementary cleaning method. There are several comparative studies of postoperative infection with antimicrobials in intermaxillary fixation patients, but there are no comparative studies with mouthwash (Davis et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Schaller et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p>
              <p>HABITPRO mouthwash contains the following three active ingredients: cetylpyridinium chloride (CPC), dipotassium glycyrrhizinate (GK2), and tranexamic acid (TXA), which are expected to have bactericidal, anti‐inflammatory, and hemostatic effects.</p>
              <p>The objective of this study was to investigate the effect of continued perioperative use of HABITPRO mouthwash with mechanical cleaning on the intraoral environment, particularly in patients undergoing maxillomandibular fixation, which is a specific treatment used in dental and oral surgery. Specifically, the intraoral environment was evaluated by testing the amount of dental plaque and salivary properties to investigate the effectiveness of this mouthwash during maxillomandibular fixation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="cre2814-sec-0060">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title>
              <p>In this study, single‐blind participants are blinded to the parallel group that was initiated within a single institution. The study was approved by the Saga University Hospital Research Ethics Committee (Protocol number 2019‐07‐01), and informed consent was obtained from all subjects and/or legally acceptable representative (LAR) of subjects to participate in the study.　This trial was registered at the University Hospital Medical Information Network (UMIN) Clinical Trials Registry (Registration number UMIN000046091). This study followed the 2010 Consolidated Standards for Reporting Trials (CONSORT) statement.　The study was performed in line with the principles of the declaration of Helsinki. Regarding setting sample size, there were few similar research reports in the past. This study was conducted under the actual conditions of daily clinical practice, and the sample size was set as the number of possible cases within the study period.</p>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0070">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Participants and study design</title>
                <p>The study subjects were patients in the Department of Dental and Oral Surgery of Saga University Hospital (Saga, Japan) who required maxillomandibular fixation either after orthognathic surgery or for the treatment of mandibular fracture between October 2019 and December 2022. The subjects were allocated by the envelope method to either the HABITPRO group or the placebo group. Patients with severe undernutrition (Alb ≤2.5 g/dL) or those who were unable to gargle unaided were excluded from the study (Table <xref rid="cre2814-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). During maxillomandibular fixation, they received transnasal enteral nutrition, with only water taken by mouth. The duration of fixation was 14–20 days. The HABITPRO group gargled with a mouthwash containing active ingredients (CPC, GK2, and TXA), and the placebo group with a mouthwash that did not contain any active ingredients (both mouthwash were provided by Earth Corporation). Both types of mouthwash were formulated so that there was no difference between them in factors such as color and taste. The procedure for intraoral cleaning started with mechanical cleaning with manual toothbrush using benzethonium chloride and a water flosser (Waterpik, Water Pik Inc.) for approximately 5 min, followed by gargling with the allocated mouthwash. No interdental cleaning aids were used. The cleaning was conducted four times a day after enteral nutrition (7:00, 11:00, 15:00, and 19:00), and the mouthwash was held and rinsed in the mouth for 30 s before it was spat out. A mondamin automatic dispenser (Earth Corporation) was used to dispense 20 mL for each use.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="cre2814-tbl-0001" content-type="Table">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Exclusion criteria.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <p>
                            <list list-type="simple">
                              <list-item>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <p>Having severe undernutrition from before the start of treatment (Alb ≤2.5 g/dL)</p>
                              </list-item>
                            </list>
                          </p>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <p>
                            <list list-type="simple">
                              <list-item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <p>Unable to gargle independently</p>
                              </list-item>
                            </list>
                          </p>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <p>
                            <list list-type="simple">
                              <list-item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <p>Considered by an investigator to be unsuitable to participate in the study for any other reasons</p>
                              </list-item>
                            </list>
                          </p>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <permissions>
                    <copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder>
                  </permissions>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0080">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Evaluation parameters</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="simple">
                    <list-item>
                      <label>(1)</label>
                      <p>Assessment of plaque adhesion status using the plaque control record (PCR).</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <label>(2)</label>
                      <p>Measurements with a saliva analyzer (Sill‐Ha, Arkray Marketing Inc.).</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p>Plaque‐disclosing dye (Shofu Inc.) was used to dye all the remaining tooth surfaces, and the state of plaque adhesion on the surface in the cervical region was scored. The method of implementation was prescribed for four tooth surfaces (buccal, mesial, distal, and lingual/palatal) before and after intermaxillary fixation, and for three tooth surfaces (buccal, mesial, and distal) during intermaxillary fixation, and multiple clinicians were assigned without blinding. Records were recorded on a standardized paper chart, and the analysis was calculated as plaque‐positive tooth surface/total tooth surface × 100 and was evaluated by one person in a blinded fashion. The saliva analyzer uses patients' saliva to measure six parameters related to caries (carious bacteria, pH, and acid buffering capacity), periodontal disease (leukocyte count and protein levels), and oral cleanliness (ammonia levels). Specifically, saliva was collected after the mouth had been washed out with 3 mL of water for 10 s. Drops of saliva were placed on a special test paper, which was measured by the analyzer. The ammonia level was measured by the glutamate dehydrogenase assay. Measurements (1) and (2) were made at three time points: immediately before maxillomandibular fixation (baseline); on Day 10 of fixation; and immediately after fixation was released. There was individual variation between patients in the intraoral environment at baseline. Therefore, the amount of change in each measured value over time was calculated and compared. In this study, the primary outcome of this study was focused on PCR to evaluate oral hygiene status. Along with the primary outcome, six parameters related to caries, periodontal disease, and oral cleanliness in saliva were assessed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0090">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>JMP version 14 was used for statistical analysis. The primary and secondary endpoints were compared between the HABITPRO and placebo groups. Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>‐test was used for continuous variables, and Fisher's exact test for nominal scales. The <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>‐value was set to the level of significance of 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="cre2814-sec-0100">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0110">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Study flow and baseline characteristics</title>
                <p>The flow of patients throughout this study is depicted in Figure <xref rid="cre2814-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. A total of 55 patients who had undergone maxillomandibular fixation were randomly allocated to either a HABITPRO group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 29) or a placebo group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 26). No side effects were observed in any group during the intervention. The study subjects were patients who required maxillomandibular fixation either after orthognathic surgery (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44) or for the treatment of mandibular fracture (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 11). They included 24 men and 31 women, aged 16–81 years (mean age 28.11 years). PCR data were analyzed for 43 of the 55 patients from whom these data could be collected due to difficulty during maxillomandibular fixation (22 patients in the placebo group and 21 in the HABITPRO group). There was no difference between the two groups in sex, smoking habits, age, disease, or number of teeth (Table <xref rid="cre2814-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). There were no reports of irritation‐caused pain or signs of mucosal inflammation in either the HABITPRO group or the placebo group. No patient dropped out of the study early.</p>
                <fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre2814-fig-0001">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Flow diagram of patients throughout the study.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="CRE2-9-1044-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="cre2814-tbl-0002" content-type="Table">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Patient distribution.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <thead valign="bottom">
                      <tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HABITPRO</th>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>‐Value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/female</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/14</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/17</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.789</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking habits</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes/no</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/23</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/25</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.23 (13.52)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00 (15.78)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.954</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jaw deformity/fracture</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/5</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/6</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of teeth</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.38 (1.92)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.72 (3.22)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="cre2814-tbl2-note-0001">
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">Note</italic>: Data represent the mean ± (SD).</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                  <permissions>
                    <copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder>
                  </permissions>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0120">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>The effectiveness of HABITPRO mouthwash on plaque control record</title>
                <p>To assess the intraoral environment, the amount of dental plaque was evaluated using PCR as the primary endpoint. The PCR index varied widely at baseline. After fixation release, in the placebo group, the index increased by +24.61 compared with baseline, with an increase in the amount of plaque adhering to the teeth, whereas in the HABITPRO group, it was almost unchanged from baseline after fixation release, decreasing by –2.00 (Table <xref rid="cre2814-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The difference between the two groups was significant　(Figure <xref rid="cre2814-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="cre2814-tbl-0003" content-type="Table">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Plaque control record.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="char" char="(" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="char" char="(" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    <thead valign="bottom">
                      <tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22 mean (SD)</th>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HABITPRO <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 21 mean (SD)</th>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>‐Value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.18 (17.26)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.77 (26.15)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026<xref rid="cre2814-tbl3-note-0001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMF 10ds</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.26 (24.05)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.17 (20.78)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.573</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After IMF</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.79 (31.41)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.77 (26.65)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐IMF 10ds)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−37.08 (31.27)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.40 (24.18)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐after IMF)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.61 (35.53)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (27.71)</td>
                        <td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009<xref rid="cre2814-tbl3-note-0001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="cre2814-tbl3-note-0002">
                      <p>Abbreviation: IMF, intermaxillary fixation.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="cre2814-tbl3-note-0001">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                  <permissions>
                    <copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder>
                  </permissions>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre2814-fig-0002">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Representative intraoral photograph on Day 10 of fixation and after fixation release. Plaque‐disclosing dye was used to dye all the tooth surfaces.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="CRE2-9-1044-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0130">
                <label>3.3</label>
                <title>The effectiveness of HABITPRO mouthwash on salivary properties</title>
                <p>We investigated six parameters in saliva (carious bacteria, pH, acid buffering capacity, leukocyte count, protein levels, and ammonia levels) to verify whether HABITPRO mouthwash affects caries, periodontal disease, and oral cleanliness (Table <xref rid="cre2814-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Interestingly, in the placebo group, the ammonia level related to oral cleanliness after fixation release increased by +5.42 compared with baseline. In the HABITPRO group, a marked decrease of –14.66 was evident. This difference between the two groups was significant. This result was consistent with the finding that the PCR index in the HABITPRO group remained stable and did not worsen after intermaxillary fixation was released.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="cre2814-tbl-0004" content-type="Table">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Salivary properties.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <thead valign="bottom">
                      <tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22 mean (SD)</th>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HABITPRO <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 21 mean (SD)</th>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>‐Value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. mutans</italic> metabolic activity</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐IMF 10ds)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.85 (32.93)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (26.36)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐after IMF)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.85 (33.45)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 (32.76)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidity</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐IMF 10ds)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.69 (30.73)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00 (34.72)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐after IMF)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96 (27.15)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03 (28.79)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.701</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buffer capacity</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐IMF 10ds)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.69 (34.20)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14 (32.04)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐after IMF)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.11 (31.47)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.07 (27.81)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leukocyte levels</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐IMF 10ds)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.84 (36.19)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.28 (27.84)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.523</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐after IMF)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.39 (31.61)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03 (36.21)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.666</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein levels</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐IMF 10ds)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85 (26.05)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.00 (29.29)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐after IMF)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27 (28.75)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.07 (26.12)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ammonia levels</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐IMF 10ds)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.00 (22.41)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.76 (32.14)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ (Pre‐after IMF)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.42 (21.21)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.66 (34.93)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014<xref rid="cre2814-tbl4-note-0001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="cre2814-tbl4-note-0002">
                      <p>Abbreviation: IMF, intermaxillary fixation.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="cre2814-tbl4-note-0001">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                  <permissions>
                    <copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder>
                  </permissions>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>The buffering capacity of saliva increased similarly by +4.11 compared with baseline in the placebo group, but decreased by –10.07 in the HABITPRO group. However, this difference between the two groups was not significant. There were no significant differences between the two groups in pH, carious bacteria, leukocyte count, or protein levels at any time point.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="cre2814-sec-0140">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Recent years have seen rising interest in oral health management. Although the rate of mouthwash use is not necessarily higher in Japan than in other countries, it has tended to increase in recent years. Initially, most people thought that mouthwash was used to eliminate bad breath, and it was often lumped together with fragrances, so that rather than using it regularly, people tended to use it occasionally in a way that was greatly removed from the goal of health management. Recently, however, it has gradually come to be thought of differently, as awareness has spread of the necessity of oral function management. The main uses of mouthwash now include cleaning the mouth, retaining moisture, preventing caries and periodontal disease, and preventing bad breath.</p>
              <p>Since oral intake is not performed during maxillomandibular fixation, it is known that saliva secretion decreases and oral dryness becomes more severe. Additionally, it has been reported that oral bacterial flora changes during tube feeding, leading to an increase in aspiration pneumonia (Finucane &amp; Bynum, <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>). In addition, oral hygiene becomes even more difficult during intermaxillary fixation. Mechanical cleaning with brushing and water flossing is important, but this can not be sufficient. During intermaxillary fixation, chemical cleaning using mouthwash is thought to be effective, but there are no reports about this matter. In our study, the PCR index significantly increased during intermaxillary fixation compared to that before surgery, suggesting that oral hygiene worsened.</p>
              <p>The mouthwash investigated in this study is compounded with three medicinal ingredients. As a cationic surfactant, CPC exerts a bactericidal action by adsorption on the bacterial cell membrane, which increases its fluidity and causes it to break down (Hwang et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Ioannou et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). It is also believed to have a bactericidal effect by denaturing proteins. GK2 is a natural ingredient derived from licorice recognized for its anti‐inflammatory properties, that is used to suppress stomatitis and throat inflammation (Michaelis et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Additionally, it has been reported that GK2 inhibits inflammation and ameliorates colitis in mice (Vitali et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). TXA is an artificial synthetic amino acid that is expected to have hemostatic and anti‐inflammatory actions (Jimenez et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Kämmerer et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Recently, it has been reported that TXA mouthwash is effective for preventing postoperative bleeding after tooth extraction (Carter et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Previously, efficacy of CPC‐based mouthwash and CPC/TXA‐based mouth rinse have been reported (Costa et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Lee et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Depending on the proportions in which these medications are combined, their pharmacological effects can cancel each other out. This CPC/GK2/TXA‐based mouthwash has been confirmed by the manufacturer's development department to ensure that the ingredients do not cancel each other out. Additionally, CPC/GK2/TXA‐based mouthwash inhibited propagation of the bacteria extracted from the postsurgical sutures after implant placement (Taninokuchi et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p>
              <p>In the present study, the effectiveness of this mouthwash was assessed in a specific environment resulting from maxillomandibular fixation. The results of the PCR experiments suggested that the use of a mouthwash containing active ingredients may suppress the adhesion of debris in comparison with the placebo group. During maxillomandibular fixation, all of the patients in this study carried out mechanical flossing with a Waterpik before using mouthwash. In both groups, the labial‐side tooth surfaces and mucosa were thus adequately cleaned by mechanical stimulation, but the present results showed that this alone was insufficient. The ammonia levels and buffering capacity of saliva were also affected by the mouthwash ingredients, despite Waterpik use. This may have been because the action of the Waterpik did not extend to the lingual‐side tooth surfaces or the tongue and other parts of the mucosa. A previous study found that the use of this mouthwash reduced debris adhesion to the sutures used in implant surgery, which supports the present results (Taninokuchi et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Salivary ammonia is thought to be generated by the metabolism of urea or amino acids by the ureases and amino acid‐metabolizing enzymes of oral bacteria (Kanapka &amp; Kleinberg, <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>; Shu et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Singer &amp; Kleinberg, <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>). Salivary ammonia concentration is associated with the total oral bacterial count, and gram‐negative bacilli produce particularly large amounts of ammonia. Gargling with this mouthwash effectively reduced the amount of ammonia in saliva, and it may significantly suppress these bacteria. The study subjects were generally young, with a mean age of 28 years, but the ammonia concentration in saliva has been shown to increase in accordance with age from age 40 years, which suggests that a greater effect might be obtained in older people. However, this is a topic for further study.</p>
              <p>Unlike oral medications, including antibiotics, mouthwash exerts direct local action to reduce systemic side effects. Therefore, mouthwash can be used continuously for a wide range of indications and used by a wide range of age patients. Barriers to the use of mouthwashes include irritation of the mucous membranes and their smell and taste. Therefore, taste and color can be important factors when choosing a mouthwash. In this study, the drug was used in patients ranging in age from 10 to 80 years and there were no adverse events such as mucositis or pain. In addition, there were no patients who were unable to use the product due to taste or odor preferences.</p>
              <p>The importance of oral management in the perioperative period is now recognized in both medicine and dentistry, and active interventions are now being performed (Bergan et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Soutome et al., <xref rid="cre2814-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). However, what must not be forgotten is that gargling is the basis of oral hygiene management, and moreover that it is essential that this become a daily habit, so that patient education is important. Symptoms such as a refreshing sensation in the mouth and demonstrating the results of oral hygiene management to patients who use mouthwash can be a factor in motivating and encouraging them to continue. Mouthwash use can also be effective when normal oral cleaning is difficult, such as in times of disaster or in long‐term care settings. It is generally marketed to prevent bad breath and is widely available for this purpose, but the type of mouthwash to be used must be chosen in light of its intended use. The mouthwash in the present study played a supplementary role in maintaining the oral environment after mechanical cleaning, and further improvements to its ingredients and composition are required. Of course, some active ingredients will give rise to cases of hypersensitivity. A certain percentage of adverse events is also known to occur as a result of povidone‐iodine, benzethonium chloride, and other active ingredients that have been widely used.</p>
              <p>During long‐term use, cost is another issue that must be resolved alongside taste preferences and irritation. The development of a versatile mouthwash for use not just in the perioperative period will be very important in terms of meeting a social need.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="cre2814-sec-0150">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>The present results suggest that the continued perioperative use of a mouthwash containing active ingredients may suppress the deterioration of the oral environment to some extent, even in the specific environment resulting from maxillomandibular fixation. This mouthwash may therefore provide a tool for perioperative oral hygiene management.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="cre2814-sec-0160">
              <label>6</label>
              <title>CLINICAL RELEVANCE</title>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0170">
                <label>6.1</label>
                <title>Scientific rationale for the study</title>
                <p>Management of the oral environment in patients with diseases of oral and maxillofacial region is very important to reduce not only the aggravation of dental caries and periodontal disease, but also local wound infections and aspiration pneumonia.　Patients who required maxillomandibular fixation for the treatment of mandibular fracture or orthognathic surgery, a stronger oral environment management is required. Mouthwashes are used as a substitute for mechanical cleaning or in a supplementary role after such cleaning. fixation.　However, little is known about the effectiveness of mouthwash in the specific environment created by maxillomandibular fixation.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0180">
                <label>6.2</label>
                <title>Principal findings</title>
                <p>CPC/GK2/TXA‐based mouthwash reduced the ammonia level related to oral cleanliness in saliva and the PCR index after fixation release.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="cre2814-sec-0190">
                <label>6.3</label>
                <title>Practical implications</title>
                <p>The continued use of CPC/GK2/TXA‐based mouthwash may suppress the deterioration of the oral environment, even in the specific environment resulting from maxillomandibular fixation. This mouthwash may be useful in perioperative oral hygiene management.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="cre2814-sec-0200">
              <title>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</title>
              <p>Yoshio Yamashita designed the study, Reona Aijima performed the experiments, all authors interpreted data, and Yoshio Yamashita wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="cre2814-sec-0220">
              <title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title>
              <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack id="cre2814-sec-0210">
              <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
              <p>The authors are grateful to participating staff members from the Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Faculty of Medicine, Saga University.</p>
            </ack>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="cre2814-sec-0320">
              <title>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</title>
              <p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="cre2814-bibl-0001">
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0001">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0001"><string-name><surname>Aas</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paster</surname>, <given-names>B. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stokes</surname>, <given-names>L. N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsen</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Dewhirst</surname>, <given-names>F. E.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Defining the normal bacterial flora of the oral cavity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Microbiology</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>5721</fpage>–<lpage>5732</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272510</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0002">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0002"><string-name><surname>Akiyama</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyamoto</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fukuda</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sano</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katagiri</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shobuike</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kukita</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamashita</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taniguchi</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Goto</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Development of a novel PCR method to comprehensively analyze salivary bacterial flora and its application to patients with odontogenic infections</article-title>. <source>Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, Oral Pathology, Oral Radiology, and Endodontology</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0003">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0003"><string-name><surname>Bergan</surname>, <given-names>E. H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tura</surname>, <given-names>B. R.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Lamas</surname>, <given-names>C. C.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Impact of improvement in preoperative oral health on nosocomial pneumonia in a group of cardiac surgery patients: A single arm prospective intervention study</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Medicine</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23921979</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0004">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0004"><string-name><surname>Carter</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Goss</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Tranexamic acid mouthwash‐ a prospective randomized study of a 2‐day regimen vs 5‐day regimen to prevent postoperative bleeding in anticoagulated patients requiring dental extractions</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14759109</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0005">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0005"><string-name><surname>Costa</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laguna</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herrera</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serrano</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alonso</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Sanz</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Efficacy of a new mouth rinse formulation based on 0.07% cetylpyridinium chloride in the control of plaque and gingivitis: A 6‐month randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Periodontology</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1007</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24024983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0006">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0006"><string-name><surname>Davis</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gregoire</surname>, <given-names>C. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davis</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Steeves</surname>, <given-names>T. W.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of surgical site infections following orthognathic surgery: A double‐blind, randomized controlled trial on a 3‐day versus 1‐day postoperative antibiotic regimen</article-title>. <source>Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>796</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27789268</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0007">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0007"><string-name><surname>Finucane</surname>, <given-names>T. E.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Bynum</surname>, <given-names>J. P.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Use of tube feeding to prevent aspiration pneumonia</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source>, <volume>348</volume>(<issue>9039</issue>), <fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1424</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0008">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0008"><string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>, <given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramalingam</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bienek</surname>, <given-names>D. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>You</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Alvarez</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of nanoemulsion in combination with cetylpyridinium chloride in multidrug‐resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>3568</fpage>–<lpage>3575</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23669390</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0009">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0009"><string-name><surname>Ioannou</surname>, <given-names>C. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanlon</surname>, <given-names>G. W.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Denyer</surname>, <given-names>S. P.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Action of disinfectant quaternary ammonium compounds against <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17060529</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0010">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0010"><string-name><surname>Jimenez</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iribarren</surname>, <given-names>J. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorente</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodriguez</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hernandez</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nassar</surname>, <given-names>M. I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brouard</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milena</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Mora</surname>, <given-names>M. L.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Tranexamic acid attenuates inflammatory response in cardiopulmonary bypass surgery through blockade of fibrinolysis: A case control study followed by a randomized double‐blind controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Critical Care</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>R117</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17988379</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0011">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0011"><string-name><surname>Kämmerer</surname>, <given-names>P. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frerich</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liese</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schiegnitz</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Al‐Nawas</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Oral surgery during therapy with anticoagulants—A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Clinical Oral Investigations</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25413495</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0012">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0012"><string-name><surname>Kanapka</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Kleinberg</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Catabolism of arginine by the mixed bacteria in human salivary sediment under conditions of low and high glucose concentration</article-title>. <source>Archives of Oral Biology</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1007</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6419713</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0013">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0013"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>J. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>, <given-names>J. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suh</surname>, <given-names>J. Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Um</surname>, <given-names>H. S.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>, <given-names>Y. G.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The antiplaque and bleeding control effects of a cetylpyridinium chloride and tranexamic acid mouth rinse in patients with gingivitis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Periodontal &amp; Implant Science</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28680709</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0014">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0014"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>H. K.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>P. C.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Cross‐sectional analysis of different variables of patients with non‐insulin dependent diabetes and their periodontal status</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Periodontics &amp; Restorative Dentistry</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14984148</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0015">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0015"><string-name><surname>Michaelis</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geiler</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naczk</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sithisarn</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leutz</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doerr</surname>, <given-names>H. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cinatl</surname><suffix>Jr.</suffix><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Glycyrrhizin exerts antioxidative effects in H5N1 influenza A virus‐infected cells and inhibits virus replication and pro‐inflammatory gene expression</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <elocation-id>e19705</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21611183</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0016">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0016"><string-name><surname>Saadeh</surname>, <given-names>C. E.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Chemotherapy‐ and radiotherapy‐induced oral mucositis: Review of preventive strategies and treatment</article-title>. <source>Pharmacotherapy</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15977916</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0017">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0017"><string-name><surname>Sano</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamashita</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fukuda</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taniguchi</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goto</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Miyamoto</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Comprehensive analysis of bacterial flora in postoperative maxillary cyst fluid by 16S rRNA gene and culture methods</article-title>. <source>ISRN Dentistry</source>, <volume>2012</volume>, <elocation-id>840483</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22685668</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0018">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0018"><string-name><surname>Schaller</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soong</surname>, <given-names>P. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zix</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iizuka</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Lieger</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The role of postoperative prophylactic antibiotics in the treatment of facial fractures: A randomized, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled pilot clinical study. Part 2: Mandibular fractures in 59 patients</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24012053</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0019">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0019"><string-name><surname>Shu</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morou‐Bermudez</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suárez‐Pérez</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivera‐Miranda</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Browngardt</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>Y. Y. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magnusson</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Burne</surname>, <given-names>R. A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The relationship between dental caries status and dental plaque urease activity</article-title>. <source>Oral Microbiology and Immunology</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17241172</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0020">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0020"><string-name><surname>Singer</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Kleinberg</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Quantitative assessment of urea, glucose and ammonia changes in human dental plaque and saliva following rinsing with urea and glucose</article-title>. <source>Archives of Oral Biology</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>923</fpage>–<lpage>929</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6580848</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0021">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0021"><string-name><surname>Soutome</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yanamoto</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Funahara</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasegawa</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komori</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamada</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kurita</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamauchi</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shibuya</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kojima</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakahara</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oho</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Umeda</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Effect of perioperative oral care on prevention of postoperative pneumonia associated with esophageal cancer surgery: A multicenter case‐control study with propensity score matching analysis</article-title>. <source>Medicine</source>, <volume>96</volume>, <elocation-id>e7436</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28816937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0022">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0022"><string-name><surname>Takeshita</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yasui</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shibata</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Furuta</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saeki</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eshima</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Yamashita</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Dental plaque development on a hydroxyapatite disk in young adults observed by using a barcoded pyrosequencing approach</article-title>. <source>Scientific Reports</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>8136</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25633431</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0023">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0023"><string-name><surname>Tanaka</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hirano</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kikutani</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohara</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Furuya</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tetsuo</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akishita</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Iijima</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Oral frailty as a risk factor for physical frailty and mortality in community‐dwelling elderly</article-title>. <source>The Journals of Gerontology: Series A</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>1661</fpage>–<lpage>1667</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0024">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0024"><string-name><surname>Taninokuchi</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakata</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inoue</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasugai</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Kuroda</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of a cetylpyridinium chloride‐, dipotassium glycyrrhizinate‐, and tranexamic acid‐based mouthwash after implant placement: A double‐blind randomised clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Oral Health &amp; Preventive Dentistry</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33600092</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0025">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0025"><string-name><surname>Thornhill</surname>, <given-names>M. H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dayer</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prendergast</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baddour</surname>, <given-names>L. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Lockhart</surname>, <given-names>P. B.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Incidence and nature of adverse reactions to antibiotics used as endocarditis prophylaxis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>2382</fpage>–<lpage>2388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25925595</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0026">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0026"><string-name><surname>Vitali</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palone</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cucchiara</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Negroni</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cavone</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costanzo</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aloi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dilillo</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Stronati</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Dipotassium glycyrrhizate inhibits HMGB1‐dependent inflammation and ameliorates colitis in mice</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <elocation-id>e66527</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840500</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0027">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0027"><string-name><surname>Xue</surname>, <given-names>Q. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bandeen‐Roche</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varadhan</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Fried</surname>, <given-names>L. P.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Initial manifestations of frailty criteria and the development of frailty phenotype in the Women's Health and Aging Study II</article-title>. <source>The Journals of Gerontology: Series A</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>984</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cre2814-bib-0028">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre2814-cit-0028"><string-name><surname>Yoneyama</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshida</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsui</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, &amp; <string-name><surname>Sasaki</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Oral care and pneumonia</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source>, <volume>354</volume>, <fpage>515</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
