<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:45:26Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6882661" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6882661</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-17</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jaos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jaos</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Faculdade De Odontologia De Bauru - USP</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6882661</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6882661</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6882661</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31778442</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">00402</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-7757-2019-0025</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Liposomal anesthetic gel for pain control during periodontal therapy in adults: a placebo-controlled RCT</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0777-5012</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Moraes</surname>
                    <given-names>Gustavo Simao</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6923-0037</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>dos Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>Isadora Benato</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4299-298X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pinto</surname>
                    <given-names>Shelon Cristina Souza</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4220-7838</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pochapski</surname>
                    <given-names>Marcia Thais</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9934-4027</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Farago</surname>
                    <given-names>Paulo Vitor</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2238-7168</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pilatti</surname>
                    <given-names>Gibson Luiz</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0347-0270</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>Fabio Andre</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>
Universidade Estadual de Ponta Grossa, Departamento de Odontologia, Ponta Grossa, Paraná, Brasil.</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>
Universidade Estadual de Ponta Grossa, Departamento de Ciências Farmacêuticas, Ponta Grossa, Paraná, Brasil.</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Corresponding address: Fabio Andre Santos, Universidade Estadual de Ponta Grossa - Departamento de Odontologia. Rua Carlos Cavalcanti, n.4748 - Bairro Uvaranas - <postal-code>84030-900</postal-code> - Ponta Grossa, PR, Brasil. Phone: <phone>+55 42 3220 3104</phone> e-mail: <email>fasantos@uepg.br</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection">
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>28</volume>
              <elocation-id>e20190025</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>01</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <p>Periodontal therapy usually requires local anesthesia. If effective, a non-invasive, liposomal anesthetic gel could increase the levels of acceptance of patients in relation to periodontal therapy.</p>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective:</title>
                  <p>This study investigated the efficacy of liposomal anesthetic gel for pain control during periodontal therapy.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methodology:</title>
                  <p>Forty volunteers with moderate to severe chronic periodontitis were recruited, of which at least three sextants required periodontal therapy. At least one of the selected teeth had one site with a probing depth of ≥4 mm. The volunteers received the following three gels: a placebo, lidocaine/prilocaine (Oraqix<sup>®</sup>), or a liposomal lidocaine/prilocaine, which were applied to different sextants. Pain frequency was registered during treatment and the volunteers received a digital counter to register any painful or uncomfortable experiences. At the end of each session, the volunteers indicated their pain intensity using rating scales (NRS-101 and VRS-4). The volunteers had their hemodynamic parameters measured by a non-invasive digital monitor.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>Pain frequency/intensity did not show statistical difference between intervention groups. The tested gels did not interfere with the hemodynamic indices. Dental anxiety, suppuration and probing depth could influence pain during periodontal therapy.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion:</title>
                  <p>Our results suggest limited indications for the use of non-invasive anesthesia when used for scaling and root planing. Intra-pocket anesthetic gel could be a good option for anxious patients, or those who have a fear of needles.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords:</title>
                <kwd>Anesthetics</kwd>
                <kwd>Periodontal debridement</kwd>
                <kwd>Pain management</kwd>
                <kwd>Dental scaling</kwd>
                <kwd>Clinical trial</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>Coordination of Higher Education and Graduate Training (CAPES)</funding-source>
                  <award-id>001</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="2"/>
                <table-count count="4"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="39"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Severe periodontitis is the sixth most prevalent condition worldwide, affecting 11% of the global population (743 million people aged 15-99 worldwide). It has remained static on a global scale during the last two decades. The age-standardized incidence of the disease did not change from 1990-2010 (696 and 701 cases per 100,000 person-years, respectively). These prevalence and incidence rates were similar for males and females, and increased with age, with a steep increase among individuals aged from 30 to 40 years old, remaining stable thereafter.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p>
              <p>Periodontal therapy usually involves supra and/or subgingival scaling and root planing (SRP),<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> which can be performed using periodontal curettes or sonic and ultrasonic instruments. The prevalence of pain and discomfort during SRP is variable, but studies report around 15% to 33% of patients describing it as a significantly painful experience.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Reasons for this include tissue trauma caused by instrumentation, dentin hypersensitivity,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> and the unpleasant noise and sensation produced by periodontal curettes and sonic or ultrasonic instruments when they come into contact with the tooth structure.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p>
              <p>The usual technique to control pain and discomfort during SRP is applying local anesthetic injections (nerve block or infiltration anesthesia).<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> However, patients often report a fear of needles, and complain about pain and discomfort caused by their insertion and prolonged numbness in the surrounding soft tissues.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> These factors can lead patients to delay, or even avoid, periodontal therapy.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref></p>
              <p>New anesthetic formulations have been developed to improve treatment conditions and ameliorate the patients' level of acceptance of dental procedures.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Oraqix<sup>®</sup> (25 mg/g lidocaine and 25 mg/g prilocaine) was developed with the addition of a thermosetting agent.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> The onset of anesthesia has been shown to range from 30 seconds to 2 minutes after its application, and some studies have demonstrated that it is the best non-invasive anesthesia option for SRP thus far.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Another alternative is the combination of local anesthetics with liposomal formulations, which can increase the duration of anesthesia, decrease central nervous and cardiac toxicity, and decrease circulating plasma levels.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Studies have shown significant skin and oral mucosa anesthesia using liposome-encapsulated anesthetics;<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> but until now, there has been no evaluation of their efficacy in the periodontal pocket, especially during SRP.</p>
              <p>The aim of this study was to compare the effects of a liposomal, lidocaine/prilocaine, thermosetting anesthetic gel for pain control during scaling and root planing (anti-infective periodontal therapy) compared to Oraqix<sup>®</sup> (positive control) gel, and a placebo gel (negative control). Our primary outcome was the frequency/intensity of pain, obtained by using a digital counter to register any painful experience; a numerical rating scale (NRS-101) and a verbal rating scale (VRS-4) were used. The secondary outcomes were hemodynamic parameters (systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, heart rate and oxygen saturation). The null hypothesis was that there would be no difference between intervention groups (placebo and anesthetic gels) in relation to pain control during scaling and root planing.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Methodology</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study population</title>
                <p>A flowchart of the overall study design is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>. After approval by the Joint Research and Ethics Committee (CEP – 78.2009.15036.09; Clinical Trials Registry: Primary Id Number: RBR-934sys), we selected forty volunteers for this randomized, double-blind, cross-over, placebo-controlled clinical trial. The volunteers were individually made aware of the study protocol and the aims of the study prior to enrollment. The study was performed according to the guidelines of the Helsinki Declaration.</p>
                <fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Flowchart of subjects throughout the stages of the study. At the end of the clinical trial, all untreated sextants received periodontal treatment</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="1678-7765-jaos-28-e20190025-gf01"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Sample size</title>
                <p>Sample size calculation was based on pain intensity (primary outcome) using visual analogue scale (VAS) data that was previously published in a study which reported the effects of intra-pocket lidocaine and prilocaine gel (2.5% each) in SRP.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> If the sample size in each intervention group was 38 (1:1:1 allocation ratio), a two-sided test would have 80% power at an effect size of 0.65, and 0.05 significance level in order to detect a minimum, clinically important difference of 15 units in the VAS. The sample size was increased to 40 volunteers per group to account for the potential loss of volunteers during the study. Sample size was calculated using a specific software (G*Power Version 3.1.9.2; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gpower.hhu.de">http://www.gpower.hhu.de</ext-link>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Randomization and allocation concealment</title>
                <p>Block randomization was used to allocate three sextants of each volunteer in relation to the interventions (placebo, Oraqix<sup>®</sup> and Liposomal), using a computer program (Microsoft® Excel for Mac version 10.4, 2011). The random allocation sequence was printed and sealed in envelopes with the volunteer's number on the outside. This procedure was performed and monitored by one researcher (FAS).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title>
                <p>The volunteers had to be aged 18 or older; they needed anti-infective periodontal therapy and had to have at least three sextants with a minimum of two vital teeth requiring scaling and root planing. They also needed to have sought dental care at the University Dental Clinic. At least two sites per sextant with a probing depth of 4 mm or more and clinical signs of periodontal disease (presence of supra/subgingival calculus and/or dental biofilm, as well as bleeding/suppuration on probing) were required for them to be included in this study.</p>
                <p>The exclusion criteria were: individuals undergoing periodontal maintenance; any allergic reaction to amide anesthetic; consumption of any analgesic or anti-inflammatory drugs in the 12 hours prior to treatment; individuals with a history of alcoholism; smokers; pregnant or lactating women; individuals with any non-controlled systemic disorder such as cardiac, neurological, kidney, liver, hematological or psychological alterations; individuals with presence of ulcerative lesions, abscesses or acute infections; individuals with the need for dental extraction in the selected sextants; individuals with dentin hypersensitivity; and individuals with endodontic treatment or any other alteration that could compromise the measurement of data.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Evaluation of clinical parameters</title>
                <p>The data regarding probing depth, width of keratinized mucosa, bleeding on probing (presence or absence), dental plaque (presence or absence) and suppuration (presence or absence) were obtained at baseline. Measurements were performed using a standardized UNC periodontal probe (Hu-Friedy<sup>®</sup>, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil). The volunteers were also asked to complete Corah's Dental Anxiety Scale (DAS) before the first treatment session.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Anesthetic procedures and treatment</title>
                <p>Three different gels were used in this study: a lidocaine/prilocaine thermosetting gel (Oraqix<sup>®</sup>, Dentsply, York, PA, United States), which served as positive control, a liposomal lidocaine/prilocaine thermosetting gel (granulated lecithin (6.6 g); isopropyl palmitate (7.6 mL); sorbic acid or benzoic acid (0.12 g); poloxamer 407 (6.78 g); poloxamer 188 (2.40 g); potassium sorbate or sodium benzoate (0.1 g); purified water (30 mL on the first day/10 mL on the second day); ethanol (2.5 mL); hydrochloric acid (0.1 mL); lidocaine (25 mg/g) and prilocaine (25 mg/g)). The large multilamellar liposomes were obtained by the thin film hydration method. Subsequently, lecithin and isopropyl palmitate were dissolved in chloroform. The lipid mixture was then deposited as a thin film into a round-bottomed flask using a rotary evaporator after full removal of the chloroform under vacuuming at 40°C in a temperature-controlled water bath for a period of 2 hours to ensure the absence of solvent residue. The films were suspended in 20 mmol/L HEPES buffer (7.4 pH, containing 154 mmol/L NaCl), and multilamellar vesicles were obtained after vortexing at room temperature (5 min, 25°C). Large multilamellar vesicles were prepared by extruding (20 cycles) these vesicles within 400 nm-membrane filters at 25°C using an extruder device (Lipex Biomembranes Inc. Vancouver, BC, Canada). The loaded liposomes containing lidocaine base (2.5%) and prilocaine base (2.5%) were prepared by adding these anesthetics directly to the previously obtained liposomes after extrusion at the final concentration of 5%. The loaded liposomes formed appear as concentric and non-concentric multilamellar vesicles by TEM with 327.5±17.5 nm and PDI of 0.21±0.08 by dynamic light scattering. The mean encapsulation efficiency was 54.9±15.2% by HPLC/DAD. The unloaded and loaded formulations were stable at 4°C for 3 months. The thermosetting gel was prepared using the poloxamer solutions (407 and 188). These polymers were dispersed in purified water via manual stirring. The solutions were then stored in a refrigerator at 4°C for at least 12 h to ensure complete solvation. Liposomal anesthetics were then added to the gel with manual stirring until a homogeneous dispersion was obtained. The placebo gel had the same composition as the liposomal gel, but without the anesthetic bases, and served as negative control. All the selected volunteers received the gels on different teeth, from different sextants, using a cross-over design and with one-week intervals between each appointment to avoid cross-over contamination (spill-over effect).<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> The anesthetic agents were stored in identical syringes and were identified only by letters. The anesthesia was administered by a blinded operator (SCSP) according to a randomization process, who also performed the periodontal therapy procedures. The sextants were isolated with cotton rolls and the anesthetic gel was placed inside the periodontal pocket for about one minute before SRP. A second examiner (GSM) was responsible for collecting the data of each volunteer. SRP was performed using Gracey and McCall curettes (Millennium<sup>®</sup>, Golgran, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil). The volunteers could ask for rescue anesthesia (3% prilocaine with 0.03 IU/mL felypressin injection, Citanest<sup>®</sup>, Dentsply, Catanduva, SP, Brazil) if they were still feeling pain after two applications of gel.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Pain evaluation</title>
                <p>Pain frequency was obtained during the SRP procedures; the volunteers received a digital counter to register any painful or uncomfortable experience. At the end of each session, the volunteers were asked to indicate pain intensity using the numerical rating scale (NRS-101), and discomfort using a four-point verbal rating scale (VRS-4) (1=none; 2=mild; 3=moderate; 4=severe). If rescue anesthesia was required, the pain and discomfort scores were obtained before it was administered. The volunteers were also asked to rate how unpleasant the taste of the anesthetic agent was (“acceptable”; “slightly unpleasant”; “very unpleasant” and “I would not like to receive it again”).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Assessment of hemodynamic parameters</title>
                <p>During the treatments, the volunteers had their hemodynamic parameters (systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, heart rate and oxygen saturation) measured by a non-invasive digital monitor (INMAX<sup>®</sup> Monitor Multiparamétrico, Instramed Indústria Médico Hospitalar Ltda, Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The data regarding pain frequency and the NRS-101 and VRS-4 pain scales did not show normal distribution and homogeneity of variance. The volunteers had different sextants treated with different numbers of teeth in each one, so a paired test would not be suitable; the Kruskal-Wallis non-parametric test was used to determine the differences between intervention groups.</p>
                <p>The clinical parameters, such as distribution of sextants, probing depth (≤3 mm, 4-5 mm or 6 mm) and keratinized mucosa (≤2 mm or &gt;2 mm), were compared using the chi-square test (χ<sup>2</sup>). The mean number of teeth, dental plaque, bleeding on probing, suppuration, probing depth and width of keratinized mucosa were analyzed by the Kruskal-Wallis test (non-normal distribution).</p>
                <p>A univariate regression analysis, with random intercept, was performed to explore the relationship between the primary outcome of interest (pain frequency/intensity) and the various risk factors<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>, comprising the following levels: site level (dental plaque, bleeding on probing, suppuration probing depth and width of keratinized mucosa), sextant level (position and number of teeth) and subject level (age, gender, periodontal diagnosis and dental anxiety).</p>
                <p>The hemodynamic parameters (systolic and diastolic blood pressure, heart rate and oxygen saturation) were analyzed at baseline, during and after treatment by repeated measures ANOVA and the paired t-test.</p>
                <p>The data obtained via trans-operative and post-operative scaling and root planing in the three intervention groups, such as volume of anesthetic gel applied, number of applications, need for additional (rescue) anesthesia, time required for periodontal therapy (per sextant), difficulties during treatment, post-operative discomfort due to treatment and the volunteers' perceptions of the gel's flavor were analyzed by the ANOVA, Kruskal-Wallis and χ<sup>2</sup> tests, according to the type and distribution of the variables.</p>
                <p>The tests were considered statistically significant when p&lt;0.05 (IBM<sup>®</sup> SPSS<sup>®</sup> 21.0 Statistics, IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Of the forty randomized volunteers, thirty-eight managed to conclude the study and two did not return for the second appointment. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> shows the study flowchart. The sample comprised 23 (60%) females and 15 (40%) males, aged from 26 to 73 years old (mean age: 43.6±11.2 years old) and diagnosed with localized periodontitis (45%) or generalized periodontitis (55%).</p>
              <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref> shows the pain felt during/after SRP by the different groups using pain frequency and the numerical rating scale (NRS-101) and verbal rating scale (VRS-4) values. The number of volunteers reporting no pain frequency during SRP was 19 (50%) for the placebo; 25 (66%) for Oraqix<sup>®</sup>, and 21 (55%) for liposomal gel. No statistically significant differences were found between intervention groups (p&gt;0.05). The mean ±SD (95% CI) values for NRS-101 were 31.6±31.9 (21.1 – 42.1) for the placebo; 20.5±23.5 (12.8 – 28.2) for Oraqix<sup>®</sup>; and 25.0±29.6 (15.3 – 34.7) for liposomal gel. The number of volunteers reporting no pain (pain scale=0) using the NRS-101 scale was two (5%) for the placebo; six (16%) for Oraqix<sup>®</sup>; and eight (21%) for liposomal gel. Using the VRS-4 scale, no pain was observed in 18 (47%), 26 (68%) and 25 (66%) volunteers for those who underwent SRP with the placebo, Oraqix<sup>®</sup>, and liposomal gel, respectively. No statistical differences were found between intervention groups (p&lt;0.05).</p>
              <fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Pain during/after scaling and root planing in periodontal therapy. (A) Median with interquartile range (lines) of pain frequency (no significant findings, p=0.316). (B) Median with interquartile range (lines) of NRS-101 (no significant findings,p =0.250). The dots correspond to each volunteer. (C). VRS-4 scores: Percentage of subjects in the Placebo, Oraqix<sup>®</sup>; and Liposomal groups who reported no, mild, moderate, and severe pain (no significant findings, p=0.231). Kruskal-Wallis test</title>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="1678-7765-jaos-28-e20190025-gf02"/>
              </fig>
              <p>The sextants, number of teeth, and clinical parameters (dental plaque, bleeding on probing, suppuration, probing depth, and width of keratinized mucosa) are shown in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The intervention groups showed statistically significant differences (p&lt;0.0001) for suppuration. Sextant position, number of teeth, dental plaque, bleeding on probing, probing depth, and width of the keratinized mucosa had a similar distribution, with no statistically significant differences (p&gt;0.05).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Distribution of sextants, number of teeth and periodontal clinical parameters: Dental plaque (DP); Bleeding on Probing (BoP); Suppuration; Probing depth (PD) and width of keratinized mucosa (KM)</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup width="9%" span="1">
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Intervention Groups</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Placebo</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Oraqix<sup>®</sup></th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Liposomal</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sextants (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.834ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper Right</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">6 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 (13)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">9 (24)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper Anterior</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 (13)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">8 (21)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">4 (11)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper Left</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">10 (26)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">6 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">6 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Left</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 (13)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">4 (11)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3 (8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Anterior</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 (13)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">6 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">8 (21)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Right</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">7 (18)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">9 (24)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">8 (21)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="12" rowspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of teeth<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">121</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">121</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">114</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.580ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.2±0.9</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.2±1.0</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.0±1.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IqR)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.0 (2.0 – 4.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.0 (2.8 – 4.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.0 (2.0 – 4.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="11" rowspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DP (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">65.7±32.1</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">72.4±25.3</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">69.3±31.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IqR)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">75.0 (37.5 – 100)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">75.0 (50.0 – 93.8)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">79.2 (50.0–100)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="12" rowspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BoP (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">89.8±18.2</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">82.0±26.0</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">89.4±15.1</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IqR)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">100 (87.5 - 100)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">91.7 (75.0 -100)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">100 (86.4 -100)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="12" rowspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suppuration (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">13.9±17.6a</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">0.0±0.0b</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">10.8±19.0a</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IqR)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">10.4 (0.0 – 18.8)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">0.0 (0.0 -0.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">0.0 (0.0 – 12.5)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" colspan="12" rowspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PD (mm)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.288ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.5±1.4</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.6±1.4</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.5±1.3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IqR)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.0 (3.0 – 4.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.0 (3.0 -4.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.0 (3.0 – 4.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="border-top: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sites (%) with PD per sextant<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤3 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-5 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤3 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-5 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤3 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-5 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.246ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All sextants</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">422 (58)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 (34)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">394 (54)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (37)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (9)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (56)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254 (37)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (6)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper Right</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (57)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (40)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (56)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (32)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (12)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (64)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (33)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper Anterior</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (61)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (32)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (7)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (51)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (38)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (11)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (51)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (40)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper Left</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (50)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (34)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (61)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (36)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (56)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (34)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (10)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Left</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (74)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (24)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (50)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (47)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (71)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (29)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Anterior</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (56)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (36)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (60)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (25)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (16)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (50)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (42)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Right</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (59)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (37)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (50)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (42)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (53)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (39)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="border-top: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Width of KM (mm)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.8±1.5</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.7±1.6</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">3.9±1.7</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IqR)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">4.0 (3.0 – 5.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">4.0 (2.0 – 5.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">4.0 (3.0 – 5.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" colspan="11" rowspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site (%) with KM<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.231ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤2 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">108 (21)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">131 (25)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">123 (24)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2 mm</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">411 (79)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">391 (75)</td>
                      <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">387 (76)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>2;</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN2">
                    <label>†</label>
                    <p>Kruskal-Wallis (different letters indicate significant difference. p&lt;0.0001).</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN3">
                    <p>ns not statistically significant (p≥0.05); s statistically significant (p&lt;0.05); IqR. (Interquartile range)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The multilevel regression analysis (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) showed statistical significance for the variance at two levels (subject and site). Subject-level variance, considering all the pain measurements, was responsible for 65% of the total outcome variation. Site-level variance was associated with 30% of the variation of the results. Taking into consideration the subject level covariates, the factors of dental anxiety and periodontal diagnosis (localized or generalized periodontitis) had an influence (p&lt;0.05) on the outcome, with at least two methods of pain intensity evaluation. The site-level covariates, suppuration and probing depth influenced (p&lt;0.05) pain intensity on at least two of the measurement scales (p&lt;0.05).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Three-level random intercept model for the outcome variable of pain during scaling and root planing using the restricted maximum likelihood estimation (REML)</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup width="14%" span="1">
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Dependent Variables</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fixed Effects</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Pain Frequency</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">NRS-101</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">VRS-4</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate (SE)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate (SE)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate (SE)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercept<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN4">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,085</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.848ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,367</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,907</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.442)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-1.804)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.817)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subject-level covariates</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,005</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,015</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,002</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.002)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.009)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.001)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,381</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,058</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.062)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.229)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.03)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Periodontal diagnosis</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,319</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,182</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,252</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.051)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.189)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.024)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,024</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,084</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,008</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.008)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.031)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.004)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sextant-level covariates</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of teeth</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,039</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,243</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,012</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.672ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.027)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.101)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.033)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Position</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,005</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,245</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.522ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,006</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.724ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.072)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.35)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.013)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site-level covariates</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dental plaque</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,0225</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.662ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,036</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.851ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,055</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.052)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.192)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.025)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bleeding on Probing</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,106</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,322</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,092</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.066)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.244)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.032)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suppuration</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,217</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,716</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,074</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.082)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.304)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.039)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probing Depth</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,007</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,02</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.016)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.061)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.008)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keratinized Mucosa</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,029</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,081</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,004</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.652ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.019)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.073)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.009)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Random effects</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subject level</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,316</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,523</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,106</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.074)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-1.294)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.025)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sextant level</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,054</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,415</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,005</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.035)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.270)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.003)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site level</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,246</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,107</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,036</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.008)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.065)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.011)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN4">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Formal significance of the intercept coefficient estimate remains trivial in the presence of covariates.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN4a">
                    <p>ns not statistically significant (p≥0.05);</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN4b">
                    <p>s statistically significant (p&lt;0.05)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p><xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> presents a comparison of the mean (±SD) hemodynamic parameters (secondary outcomes) of the different groups. Systolic blood pressure (Sys. BP), diastolic blood pressure (Dia. BP) and heart rate (HR) were assessed at distinct moments of the appointments, i.e., at baseline, during the procedure, and after the procedure; oxygen saturation (SpO<sub>2</sub>) was checked at baseline and after treatment. The results suggest that this type of intra-pocket anesthetic gel for periodontal SRP did not interfere with the hemodynamic indices.</p>
              <table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Comparison of mean (±SD) values of hemodynamic parameters</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup width="16%" span="1">
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN6">*</xref></th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lidocaine/prilocaine thermosetting gel (Oraqix<sup>®</sup>)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">liposomal lidocaine/prilocaine thermosetting gel</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sys. BP, mm Hg</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.7±17.72</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.5±17.98</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.0±21.37</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.967ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">During treatment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.4±18.03</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.1±18.84</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.2±19.53</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.919ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After treatment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.7±20.40</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.6±15.90</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.2±21.10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN6">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.821ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.326ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- - -</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV of Sys BP (%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79±3.89</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25±3.27</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.23±3.75</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.692ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dia. BP, mm Hg</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.66±12.97</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.37±10.08</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.37±14.84</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.766ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">During treatment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.84±11.41</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.26±10.58</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.11±13.15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After treatment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.58±13.68</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.37±11.95</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.63±12.60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN6">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.386ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- - -</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV of Dia BP (%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.94±5.84</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25±4.68</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56±4.69</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR, beats/min</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.92±18.63</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.16±17.30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.58±19.38</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">During Treatment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.55±23.16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.39±16.70</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.29±24.57</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.925ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After treatment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.37±19.17</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.97±18.56</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.45±19.97</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN6">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.704ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.923ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.518ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- - -</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV of HR (%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44±4.10</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13±3.17</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.19±4.79</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SpO<sub>2</sub>, %</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.26±1.97</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.53±1.67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.05±3.05</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.331ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After treatment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.66±1.76</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.55±1.57</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.26±1.88</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN7">‡</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.347ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.907ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564ns</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- - -</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV of SO<sub>2</sub> (%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65±0.53</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72±0.73</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81±1.61</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.708ns</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN5">
                    <p>Sys. BP, systolic blood pressure, Dia. BP, diastolic blood pressure, HR, heart rate, SpO<sub>2</sub>, oxygen saturation. CV, coefficient of variation</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN6">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Repeated measures ANOVA;</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN7">
                    <label>‡</label>
                    <p>Paired t test</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN8">
                    <p>ns not statistically significant (p≥0.05); s statistically significant (p&lt;0.05)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The results showed that the volume of gel applied, the number of applications, the need for additional (rescue) anesthesia, the time required to perform SRP during each session, the difficulties during periodontal treatment, and the discomfort caused by periodontal therapy were similar between the groups, as were the volunteers' perceptions of the gel's flavor, with no statistically significant differences between intervention groups (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Data obtained in trans- and postoperative scaling and root planing in the three intervention groups</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup width="20%" span="1">
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Intervention Groups</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oraqix<sup>®</sup></th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liposomal</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anesthetic gel volume (mL)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN9">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54±0.24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55±0.29</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53±0.28</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.754ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (Interquartile range)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.37 – 0.72)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.40 – 0.60)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.30 – 0.62)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of applications<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN10">‡</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61±0.79</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40±0.64</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45±0.76</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.396ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (Interquartile range)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.0 – 2.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.0 – 2.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.0 – 2.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Need for additional (rescue) anesthesia (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN11">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.250ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (79)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (92)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (82)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (21)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (18)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time required for scaling and root planing (min)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN9">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.719ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ±SD</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.03±6.02</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.13±5.40</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.05±5.94</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (Interquartile range)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (10.7 – 19.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0 (10.0 – 17.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (8.0 – 18.0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difficulties during periodontal therapy<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN11">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (89)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (97)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (100)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (11)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discomfort due to periodontal therapy<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN11">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.355ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (74)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (79)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (87)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (21)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (13)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volunteers' perceptions of the gel's flavor<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN11">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.722ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptable</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (74)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (69)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (71)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slightly unpleasant</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very unpleasant</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#DCDDDE">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I would not like to receive it again</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN9">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>ANOVA;</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN10">
                    <label>‡</label>
                    <p>Kruskal-Wallis;</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN11">
                    <label>†</label>
                    <p>2 .</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN11a">
                    <p>ns not statistically significant (p≥0.05);</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="TFN12">
                    <p>s statistically significant (p&lt;0.05)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The results of this study did not show statistically significant differences between intervention groups regarding pain and discomfort; therefore, the null hypothesis was accepted. Nevertheless, a recent systematic review concluded that topical anesthesia is superior to a placebo during probing and SRP because it reduces the risk and intensity of pain, as well as the need for rescue anesthesia.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> However, there are many differences between studies regarding intra-pocket anesthesia, such as study design;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> composition of the anesthetic gel;<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> use of occluded anesthesia;<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> numerically small point estimate differences between treatments;<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> and type of intervention.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Most of these studies did not consider variables such as the influence of acoustic or sound stimuli on the patients' perception of pain, anxiety and fear;<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> the possible discomfort caused by swallowing the gel during the procedures;<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> as well as short application time (30 seconds to 2 minutes),<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> removal of the gel during scaling and root planing, and dentin hypersensitivity during periodontal therapy.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p>
              <p>Our study had a cross-over design: all 38 volunteers were submitted to SRP using the three different gels (placebo and anesthetic) in different sextants. Sextant distribution and number of teeth per sextant were equivalent between intervention groups. The volunteers included in the study had similar periodontal parameters between sextants, including dental plaque, bleeding on probing, probing depth and width of the keratinized mucosa. Conversely, we found statistical differences regarding the percentage of suppuration. No suppuration sites were observed in the Oraqix<sup>®</sup> group; in contrast, suppuration sites were present in 14% of the placebo group and 11% of the liposomal gel group. Suppuration was associated with higher pain frequency/intensity (NRS-101) during scaling and root planning (multilevel regression analysis). With regard to the issue of probing depth, it was associated with a higher level of pain intensity (NRS-101 and VRS-4); our results can be compared with those of other studies<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> that had similar characteristics such as sample size and study design.</p>
              <p>The association of local anesthetics with liposomal formulations increases the duration of anesthesia, decreases central nervous and cardiac toxicity, and decreases circulating plasma levels.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Liposomal topical anesthetics provide a duration of approximately 10 min of anesthesia in the gingiva and buccal mucosa, results similar to those obtained by lidocaine-prilocaine cream.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> However, other factors could reduce the effectiveness of these local anesthetics, such as the possibility of removing the gel during scaling and root planing while using periodontal curettes or sonic/ultrasonic instruments; the presence of inflammation in the periodontal pockets, which can modify the anesthetics' pharmacological activity;<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> and the inability of keeping the periodontal pocket internally dry due to the continuous plasma transudate generated from a gingival trauma caused by scaling and root planing.<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> In our study, volunteers did not report transitory side effects due to the use of different topical anesthetics.</p>
              <p>This study is the first to evaluate hemodynamic parameters (systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, heart rate and oxygen saturation) and anxiety during SRP using non-invasive anesthesia. No statistically significant differences were found between groups, suggesting that lidocaine/prilocaine intra-pocket anesthetic gels do not interfere with these parameters. Anxiety and fear can have a pain-increasing effect, creating an intentional bias towards the painful stimuli or pain-related sensation. Anxiety-induced somatic changes may occur from the activation of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal axis, the main result being increased secretion of cortisol. Endogenous or exogenous epinephrine may cause or contribute to hemodynamic and cardiac changes.<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Dental anxiety may have an impact on the effect of local anesthesia, blood pressure, and oxygen saturation; it is significantly associated with increased heart rate.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Lidocaine-prilocaine cream may cause methemoglobinemia and change arterial blood saturation and pulse oximetry.<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> On the other hand, the lidocaine-prilocaine concentration observed after the intra-pocket application of Oraqix<sup>®</sup> was below the threshold levels for toxic effect.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Our study found a significant association between dental anxiety and pain, indicating that the use of non-invasive anesthesia might be a good option for anxious patients who have had previous negative experiences with conventional anesthesia.<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></p>
              <p>Some authors have reported that the use of split-mouth and cross-over designs significantly increased efficiency in statistical testing;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> however, others have argued that a parallel group study design would be more appropriate for this type of research in order to avoid the possibility of a carry-over or spill-over effects caused by the volunteers' perception of pain.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Even though a parallel group design might contribute to subject blinding,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> it could be influenced by factors such as age, gender, ethnicity, previous pain experience and education.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Our results showed that around 18% to 39% of the volunteers reported severe pain, suggesting that SRP can be a painful procedure for some patients. However, such findings can be widely divergent because they are influenced by factors such as age, type of periodontal therapy, and gender.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> In similar studies, some patients submitted to SRP using a placebo or anesthetic gel asked for rescue anesthesia, implying that this type of gel has limited applications.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref></p>
              <p>In our study, pain and discomfort were assessed during/after SRP using pain frequency and two pain-rating scales: a numerical rating scale (NRS-101) and a four-point verbal rating scale (VRS-4). Pain frequency provides similar results in comparison to the pain scale.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> The NRS-101 and VRS-4 scales are widely applied due to their validity, reliability and sensitivity;<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> nevertheless, they have some limitations linked to the patients' age and education level, as well as to their difficulty expressing pain using numbers.<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> In other similar studies using non-invasive periodontal anesthesia, the most common rating scales used were VRS and the visual analogue scale (VAS).<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> Although the latter is considered more sensitive, it has also been claimed that it is not as easy to understand as the NRS-101 and VRS-4 scales, which could lead to higher failure rates.<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> It is important to note that there is no ideal scale for measuring pain and the results need to be carefully interpreted by researchers.<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p>In conclusion, we did not find differences between intervention groups in relation to pain frequency/intensity (primary outcome). The use of intra-pocket anesthetic gel for periodontal SRP did not interfere with the hemodynamic parameters (secondary outcome). Our results suggest limited indications for the use of non-invasive periodontal anesthesia: firstly, because periodontal procedures usually cause low or moderate pain, and secondly, because patients sometimes prefer not to receive local anesthesia. Nevertheless, some patients may experience severe pain during non-surgical periodontal therapy, and conventional local anesthesia is often necessary. The use of an intra-pocket anesthetic gel could be a good option for maintenance patients, anxious patients, or those who have a fear of needles. This is the first study to evaluate liposomal, thermosetting anesthetic gel during SRP. Consequently, further studies should be performed to verify its application in dental practice.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>The authors wish to thank Dr. Sean Stroud for reading this manuscript and offering his valuable comments.</p>
              <p>This study was financed in part by the Coordination of Higher Education and Graduate Training (CAPES) – Finance Code 001.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B1-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frencken</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stenhouse</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Green</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laverty</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dietrich</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global epidemiology of dental caries and severe periodontitis - a comprehensive review</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>sp. Issue18</issue>
                  <fpage>S94</fpage>
                  <lpage>s105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12677</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28266116</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B1-gen-3">1- Frencken JE, Sharma P, Stenhouse L, Green D, Laverty D, Dietrich T. Global epidemiology of dental caries and severe periodontitis - a comprehensive review. J Clin Periodontol. 2017;44(sp. Issue18):S94-s105. doi: 10.1111/jcpe.12677</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B2-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Canakci</surname>
                      <given-names>CF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Canakci</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain experienced by patients undergoing different periodontal therapies</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1563</fpage>
                  <lpage>1573</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14219/jada.archive.2007.0105</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18056100</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B2-gen-3">2- Canakci CF, Canakci V. Pain experienced by patients undergoing different periodontal therapies. J Am Dent Assoc. 2007;138(12):1563-73. doi: 10.14219/jada.archive.2007.0105</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B3-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chung</surname>
                      <given-names>DT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bogle</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bernardini</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stephens</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riggs</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egelberg</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain experienced by patients during periodontal maintenance</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>74</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1293</fpage>
                  <lpage>1301</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2003.74.9.1293</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14584861</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B3-gen-3">3- Chung DT, Bogle G, Bernardini M, Stephens D, Riggs ML, Egelberg JH. Pain experienced by patients during periodontal maintenance. J Periodontol. 2003;74(9):1293-301. doi: 10.1902/jop.2003.74.9.1293</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B4-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karadottir</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lenoir</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barbierato</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bogle</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riggs</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sigurdsson</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain experienced by patients during periodontal maintenance treatment</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>536</fpage>
                  <lpage>542</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2002.73.5.536</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12027257</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B4-gen-3">4- Karadottir H, Lenoir L, Barbierato B, Bogle M, Riggs M, Sigurdsson T, et al. Pain experienced by patients during periodontal maintenance treatment. J Periodontol. 2002;73(5):536-42. doi: 10.1902/jop.2002.73.5.536</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B5-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>KC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hong</surname>
                      <given-names>HH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuo</surname>
                      <given-names>SB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>CD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wai</surname>
                      <given-names>YY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Human amygdala activation by the sound produced during dental treatment: a fMRI study</article-title>
                  <source>Noise Health</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>78</issue>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <lpage>342</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1463-1741.165063</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26356376</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B5-gen-3">5- Yu JF, Lee KC, Hong HH, Kuo SB, Wu CD, Wai YY, et al. Human amygdala activation by the sound produced during dental treatment: a fMRI study. Noise Health. 2015;17(78):337-42. doi: 10.4103/1463-1741.165063</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B6-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kochel</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Plichta</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schafer</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schongassner</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fallgatter</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schienle</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Auditory symptom provocation in dental phobia: a near-infrared spectroscopy study</article-title>
                  <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>503</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <lpage>51</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2011.07.058</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21862219</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B6-gen-3">6- Kochel A, Plichta MM, Schafer A, Schongassner F, Fallgatter AJ, Schienle A. Auditory symptom provocation in dental phobia: a near-infrared spectroscopy study. Neurosci Lett. 2011;503(1):48-51. doi: 10.1016/j.neulet.2011.07.058</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B7-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Derman</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lowden</surname>
                      <given-names>CE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kaus</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Noack</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pocket-depths-related effectiveness of an intrapocket anaesthesia gel in periodontal maintenance patients</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Dent Hyg</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <lpage>144</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/idh.12036</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23782519</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B7-gen-3">7- Derman SH, Lowden CE, Kaus P, Noack MJ. Pocket-depths-related effectiveness of an intrapocket anaesthesia gel in periodontal maintenance patients. Int J Dent Hyg. 2014;12(2):141-4. doi: 10.1111/idh.12036</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B8-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donaldson</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gelskey</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Landry</surname>
                      <given-names>RG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matthews</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sandhu</surname>
                      <given-names>HS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A placebo-controlled multi-centred evaluation of an anaesthetic gel (Oraqix) for periodontal therapy</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <lpage>175</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-051X.2003.00017.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12631173</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B8-gen-3">8- Donaldson D, Gelskey SC, Landry RG, Matthews DC, Sandhu HS. A placebo-controlled multi-centred evaluation of an anaesthetic gel (Oraqix) for periodontal therapy. J Clin Periodontol. 2003;30(3):171-5. doi: 10.1034/j.1600-051X.2003.00017.x</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B9-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Friskopp</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nilsson</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Isacsson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The anesthetic onset and duration of a new lidocaine/prilocaine gel intra-pocket anesthetic (Oraqix) for periodontal scaling/root planing</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>453</fpage>
                  <lpage>458</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-051x.2001.028005453.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11350509</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B9-gen-3">9- Friskopp J, Nilsson M, Isacsson G. The anesthetic onset and duration of a new lidocaine/prilocaine gel intra-pocket anesthetic (Oraqix) for periodontal scaling/root planing. J Clin Periodontol. 2001;28(5):453-8. doi: 10.1034/j.1600-051x.2001.028005453.x</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B10-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Antoniazzi</surname>
                      <given-names>RP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cargnelutti</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>DN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guimaraes</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zanatta</surname>
                      <given-names>FB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feldens</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Topical intrapocket anesthesia during scaling and root planing: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Dent J</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0103-6440201300131</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25672380</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B10-gen-3">10- Antoniazzi RP, Cargnelutti B, Freitas DN, Guimaraes MB, Zanatta FB, Feldens CA. Topical intrapocket anesthesia during scaling and root planing: a randomized clinical trial. Braz Dent J. 2015;26(1):26-32. doi: 10.1590/0103-6440201300131</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B11-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeffcoat</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geurs</surname>
                      <given-names>NC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magnusson</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacNeill</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mickels</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Intrapocket anesthesia for scaling and root planing: results of a double-blind multicenter trial using lidocaine prilocaine dental gel</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>895</fpage>
                  <lpage>900</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2001.72.7.895</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11495138</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B11-gen-3">11- Jeffcoat MK, Geurs NC, Magnusson I, MacNeill SR, Mickels N, Roberts F, et al. Intrapocket anesthesia for scaling and root planing: results of a double-blind multicenter trial using lidocaine prilocaine dental gel. J Periodontol. 2001;72(7):895-900. doi: 10.1902/jop.2001.72.7.895</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B12-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Steenberghe</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bercy</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Boever</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adriaens</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geers</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hendrickx</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Patient evaluation of a novel non-injectable anesthetic gel: a multicenter crossover study comparing the gel to infiltration anesthesia during scaling and root planing</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>1471</fpage>
                  <lpage>1478</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2004.75.11.1471</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15633323</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B12-gen-3">12- van Steenberghe D, Bercy P, De Boever J, Adriaens P, Geers L, Hendrickx E, et al. Patient evaluation of a novel non-injectable anesthetic gel: a multicenter crossover study comparing the gel to infiltration anesthesia during scaling and root planing. J Periodontol. 2004;75(11):1471-8. doi: 10.1902/jop.2004.75.11.1471</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B13-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Derman</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lowden</surname>
                      <given-names>CE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hellmich</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Noack</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of intra-pocket anesthesia gel on treatment outcome in periodontal patients: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>481</fpage>
                  <lpage>488</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12239</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24628437</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B13-gen-3">13- Derman SH, Lowden CE, Hellmich M, Noack MJ. Influence of intra-pocket anesthesia gel on treatment outcome in periodontal patients: a randomized controlled trial. J Clin Periodontol. 2014;41(5):481-8. doi: 10.1111/jcpe.12239</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B14-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winning</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polyzois</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nylund</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelly</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Claffey</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A placebo-controlled trial to evaluate an anesthetic gel when probing in patients with advanced periodontitis</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1492</fpage>
                  <lpage>1498</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2012.110106</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22376210</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B14-gen-3">14- Winning L, Polyzois I, Nylund K, Kelly A, Claffey N. A placebo-controlled trial to evaluate an anesthetic gel when probing in patients with advanced periodontitis. J Periodontol. 2012;83(12):1492-8. doi: 10.1902/jop.2012.110106</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B15-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herdevall</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klinge</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Persson</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huledal</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abdel-Rehim</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Plasma levels of lidocaine, o-toluidine, and prilocaine after application of 8.5 g Oraqix in patients with generalized periodontitis: effect on blood methemoglobin and tolerability</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Odontol Scand</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>61</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <lpage>234</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00016350310004106</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14582591</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B15-gen-3">15- Herdevall BM, Klinge B, Persson L, Huledal G, Abdel-Rehim M. Plasma levels of lidocaine, o-toluidine, and prilocaine after application of 8.5 g Oraqix in patients with generalized periodontitis: effect on blood methemoglobin and tolerability. Acta Odontol Scand. 2003;61(4):230-4. doi: 10.1080/00016350310004106</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B16-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magnusson</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geurs</surname>
                      <given-names>NC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harris</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hefti</surname>
                      <given-names>AF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mariotti</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mauriello</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Intrapocket anesthesia for scaling and root planing in pain-sensitive patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>74</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>597</fpage>
                  <lpage>602</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2003.74.5.597</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828139</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B16-gen-3">16- Magnusson I, Geurs NC, Harris PA, Hefti AF, Mariotti AJ, Mauriello SM, et al. Intrapocket anesthesia for scaling and root planing in pain-sensitive patients. J Periodontol. 2003;74(5):597-602. doi: 10.1902/jop.2003.74.5.597</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B17-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franz-Montan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baroni</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brunetto</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sobral</surname>
                      <given-names>VR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Venâncio</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Liposomal lidocaine gel for topical use at the oral mucosa: characterization, <italic>in vitro</italic> assays and <italic>in vivo</italic> anesthetic efficacy in humans</article-title>
                  <source>J Liposome Res</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <lpage>19</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/08982104.2014.911315</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24807821</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B17-gen-3">17- Franz-Montan M, Baroni D, Brunetto G, Sobral VR, Silva CM, Venâncio P, et al. Liposomal lidocaine gel for topical use at the oral mucosa: characterization, <italic>in vitro</italic> assays and <italic>in vivo</italic> anesthetic efficacy in humans. J Liposome Res. 2015;25(1):11-9. doi: 10.3109/08982104.2014.911315</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B18-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Araujo</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cereda</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brunetto</surname>
                      <given-names>GB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vomero</surname>
                      <given-names>VU</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pierucci</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santo</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                      <suffix>Neto</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pharmacological and local toxicity studies of a liposomal formulation for the novel local anaesthetic ropivacaine</article-title>
                  <source>J Pharm Pharmacol</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>1449</fpage>
                  <lpage>1457</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1211/jpp.60.11.0005</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957165</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B18-gen-3">18- Araujo DR, Cereda CM, Brunetto GB, Vomero VU, Pierucci A, Santo H Neto, et al. Pharmacological and local toxicity studies of a liposomal formulation for the novel local anaesthetic ropivacaine. J Pharm Pharmacol. 2008;60(11):1449-57. doi: 10.1211/jpp.60.11.0005</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B19-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boogaerts</surname>
                      <given-names>JG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lafont</surname>
                      <given-names>ND</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Declercq</surname>
                      <given-names>AG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luo</surname>
                      <given-names>HC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gravet</surname>
                      <given-names>ET</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bianchi</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidural administration of liposome-associated bupivacaine for the management of postsurgical pain: a first study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Anesth</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <lpage>320</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0952-8180(94)90079-5</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7946368</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B19-gen-3">19- Boogaerts JG, Lafont ND, Declercq AG, Luo HC, Gravet ET, Bianchi JA, et al. Epidural administration of liposome-associated bupivacaine for the management of postsurgical pain: a first study. J Clin Anesth. 1994;6(4):315-20. doi: 10.1016/0952-8180(94)90079-5</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B20-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eichenfield</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funk</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fallon-Friedlander</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cunningham</surname>
                      <given-names>BB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A clinical study to evaluate the efficacy of ELA-Max (4% liposomal lidocaine) as compared with eutectic mixture of local anesthetics cream for pain reduction of venipuncture in children</article-title>
                  <source>Pediatrics</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>109</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1093</fpage>
                  <lpage>1099</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.109.6.1093</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12042548</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B20-gen-3">20- Eichenfield LF, Funk A, Fallon-Friedlander S, Cunningham BB. A clinical study to evaluate the efficacy of ELA-Max (4% liposomal lidocaine) as compared with eutectic mixture of local anesthetics cream for pain reduction of venipuncture in children. Pediatrics. 2002;109(6):1093-9. doi: 10.1542/peds.109.6.1093</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B21-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franz-Montan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cogo</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bergamaschi Cde</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Volpato</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ranali</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Liposome-encapsulated ropivacaine for topical anesthesia of human oral mucosa</article-title>
                  <source>Anesth Anal</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>104</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1528</fpage>
                  <lpage>1531</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/01.ane.0000262040.19721.26</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B21-gen-3">21- Franz-Montan M, Silva AL, Cogo K, Bergamaschi Cde C, Volpato MC, Ranali J, et al. Liposome-encapsulated ropivacaine for topical anesthesia of human oral mucosa. Anesth Anal. 2007;104(6):1528-31. doi: 10.1213/01.ane.0000262040.19721.26</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B22-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franz-Montan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fraceto</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Volpato</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paula</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ranali</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Liposomal encapsulation improves the duration of soft tissue anesthesia but does not induce pulpal anesthesia</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Anesth</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
                  <lpage>317</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinane.2010.03.001</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20542419</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B22-gen-3">22- Franz-Montan M, Silva AL, Fraceto LF, Volpato MC, Paula E, Ranali J, et al. Liposomal encapsulation improves the duration of soft tissue anesthesia but does not induce pulpal anesthesia. J Clin Anesth. 2010;22(5):313-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2010.03.001</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B23-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Antczak-Bouckoms</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tulloch</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berkey</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Split-mouth and cross-over designs in dental research</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>7 Pt 1</issue>
                  <fpage>446</fpage>
                  <lpage>453</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-051X.1990.tb02343.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2201705</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B23-gen-3">23- Antczak-Bouckoms AA, Tulloch JF, Berkey CS. Split-mouth and cross-over designs in dental research. J Clin Periodontol. 1990;17(7 Pt 1):446-53. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.1990.tb02343.x</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B24-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tu</surname>
                      <given-names>YK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gilthorpe</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Griffiths</surname>
                      <given-names>GS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maddick</surname>
                      <given-names>IH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eaton</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnson</surname>
                      <given-names>NW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The application of multilevel modeling in the analysis of longitudinal periodontal data--part I: absolute levels of disease</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <lpage>136</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2004.75.1.127</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15025224</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B24-gen-3">24- Tu YK, Gilthorpe MS, Griffiths GS, Maddick IH, Eaton KA, Johnson NW. The application of multilevel modeling in the analysis of longitudinal periodontal data--part I: absolute levels of disease. J Periodontol. 2004;75(1):127-36. doi: 10.1902/jop.2004.75.1.127</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B25-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wambier</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geus</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chibinski</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wambier</surname>
                      <given-names>DS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rego</surname>
                      <given-names>RO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loguercio</surname>
                      <given-names>AD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Intra-pocket anaesthesia and pain during probing, scaling and root planing: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>754</fpage>
                  <lpage>766</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12565</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27097588</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B25-gen-3">25- Wambier LM, Geus JL, Chibinski AC, Wambier DS, Rego RO, Loguercio AD, et al. Intra-pocket anaesthesia and pain during probing, scaling and root planing: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Periodontol. 2016;43(9):754-66. doi: 10.1111/jcpe.12565</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B26-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Svensson</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petersen</surname>
                      <given-names>JK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Svensson</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of a topical anesthetic on pain and unpleasantness during scaling of gingival pockets</article-title>
                  <source>Anesth Prog</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <lpage>39</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8638858</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B26-gen-3">26- Svensson P, Petersen JK, Svensson H. Efficacy of a topical anesthetic on pain and unpleasantness during scaling of gingival pockets. Anesth Prog. 1994;41(2):35-9.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B27-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magnusson</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeffcoat</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donaldson</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otterbom</surname>
                      <given-names>IL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriksson</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Quantification and analysis of pain in nonsurgical scaling and/or root planing</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>135</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1747</fpage>
                  <lpage>1754</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14219/jada.archive.2004.0129</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15646610</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B27-gen-3">27- Magnusson I, Jeffcoat MK, Donaldson D, Otterbom IL, Henriksson J. Quantification and analysis of pain in nonsurgical scaling and/or root planing. J Am Dent Assoc. 2004;135(12):1747-54. doi: 10.14219/jada.archive.2004.0129</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B28-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Absalom</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Menon</surname>
                      <given-names>DK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>HL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Awake insertion of the laryngeal mask airway using topical lidocaine and intravenous remifentanil</article-title>
                  <source>Anaesthesia</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>61</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <lpage>35</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2044.2005.04471.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16409340</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B28-gen-3">28- Lee MC, Absalom AR, Menon DK, Smith HL. Awake insertion of the laryngeal mask airway using topical lidocaine and intravenous remifentanil. Anaesthesia. 2006;61(1):32-5. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.2005.04471.x</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B29-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Friskopp</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huledal</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Plasma levels of lidocaine and prilocaine after application of Oraqix, a new intrapocket anesthetic, in patients with advanced periodontitis</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
                  <lpage>429</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-051x.2001.028005425.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11350505</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B29-gen-3">29- Friskopp J, Huledal G. Plasma levels of lidocaine and prilocaine after application of Oraqix, a new intrapocket anesthetic, in patients with advanced periodontitis. J Clin Periodontol. 2001;28(5):425-9. doi: 10.1034/j.1600-051x.2001.028005425.x</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B30-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ueno</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsuchiya</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizogami</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Takakura</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Local anesthetic failure associated with inflammation: verification of the acidosis mechanism and the hypothetic participation of inflammatory peroxynitrite</article-title>
                  <source>J Inflamm Res</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <lpage>48</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JIR.S3982</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22096346</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B30-gen-3">30- Ueno T, Tsuchiya H, Mizogami M, Takakura K. Local anesthetic failure associated with inflammation: verification of the acidosis mechanism and the hypothetic participation of inflammatory peroxynitrite. J Inflamm Res. 2008;1:41-8. doi: 10.2147/JIR.S3982</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B31-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biagini</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Checchi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miccoli</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vasi</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castaldini</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Root curettage and gingival repair in periodontitis</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>59</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <lpage>129</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.1988.59.2.124</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3279178</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B31-gen-3">31- Biagini G, Checchi L, Miccoli MC, Vasi V, Castaldini C. Root curettage and gingival repair in periodontitis. J Periodontol. 1988;59(2):124-9. doi: 10.1902/jop.1988.59.2.124</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B32-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brand</surname>
                      <given-names>HS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gortzak</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palmer-Bouva</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abraham</surname>
                      <given-names>RE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abraham-Inpijn</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiovascular and neuroendocrine responses during acute stress induced by different types of dental treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Int Dent J</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <lpage>48</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7607744</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B32-gen-3">32- Brand HS, Gortzak RA, Palmer-Bouva CC, Abraham RE, Abraham-Inpijn L. Cardiovascular and neuroendocrine responses during acute stress induced by different types of dental treatment. Int Dent J. 1995;45(1):45-8.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B33-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liau</surname>
                      <given-names>FL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kok</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuo</surname>
                      <given-names>RC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hwang</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiovascular influence of dental anxiety during local anesthesia for tooth extraction</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>105</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <lpage>26</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tripleo.2007.03.015</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17656135</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B33-gen-3">33- Liau FL, Kok SH, Lee JJ, Kuo RC, Hwang CR, Yang PJ, et al. Cardiovascular influence of dental anxiety during local anesthesia for tooth extraction. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod. 2008;105(1):16-26. doi: 10.1016/j.tripleo.2007.03.015</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B34-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shamriz</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen-Glickman</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reif</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shteyer</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Methemoglobinemia induced by lidocaine-prilocaine cream</article-title>
                  <source>Isr Med Assoc J</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>250</fpage>
                  <lpage>254</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24834764</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B34-gen-3">34- Shamriz O, Cohen-Glickman I, Reif S, Shteyer E. Methemoglobinemia induced by lidocaine-prilocaine cream. Isr Med Assoc J. 2014;16(4):250-4.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B35-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mayor-Subirana</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yague-Garcia</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Valmaseda-Castellon</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arnabat-Dominguez</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berini-Aytes</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gay-Escoda</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Anesthetic efficacy of Oraqix(R) <italic>versus</italic> Hurricaine(R) and placebo for pain control during non-surgical periodontal treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>e192</fpage>
                  <lpage>e201</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4317/medoral.19202</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24316699</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B35-gen-3">35- Mayor-Subirana G, Yague-Garcia J, Valmaseda-Castellon E, Arnabat-Dominguez J, Berini-Aytes L, Gay-Escoda C. Anesthetic efficacy of Oraqix(R) <italic>versus</italic> Hurricaine(R) and placebo for pain control during non-surgical periodontal treatment. Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal. 2014;19(2):e192-201. doi: 10.4317/medoral.19202</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B36-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stoltenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Osborn</surname>
                      <given-names>JB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carlson</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hodges</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Michalowicz</surname>
                      <given-names>BS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A preliminary study of intra-pocket topical versus injected anaesthetic for scaling and root planing</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>892</fpage>
                  <lpage>896</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-051X.2007.01128.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17850608</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B36-gen-3">36- Stoltenberg JL, Osborn JB, Carlson JF, Hodges JS, Michalowicz BS. A preliminary study of intra-pocket topical versus injected anaesthetic for scaling and root planing. J Clin Periodontol. 2007;34(10):892-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2007.01128.x</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B37-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferreira-Valente</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pais-Ribeiro</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jensen</surname>
                      <given-names>MP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validity of four pain intensity rating scales</article-title>
                  <source>Pain</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>152</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>2399</fpage>
                  <lpage>2404</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2011.07.005</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21856077</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B37-gen-3">37- Ferreira-Valente MA, Pais-Ribeiro JL, Jensen MP. Validity of four pain intensity rating scales. Pain. 2011;152(10):2399-404. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2011.07.005</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B38-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williamson</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoggart</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain: a review of three commonly used pain rating scales</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Nurs</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>798</fpage>
                  <lpage>804</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2702.2005.01121.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000093</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B38-gen-3">38- Williamson A, Hoggart B. Pain: a review of three commonly used pain rating scales. J Clin Nurs. 2005;14(7):798-804. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2702.2005.01121.x</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B39-gen-2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santos Calderon</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peixoto</surname>
                      <given-names>RF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gomes</surname>
                      <given-names>VM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mota Correa</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alencar</surname>
                      <given-names>EN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rossetti</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Concordance among different pain scales in patients with dental pain</article-title>
                  <source>J Orofac Pain</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <lpage>131</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22558612</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B39-gen-3">39- Santos Calderon P, Peixoto RF, Gomes VM, Mota Correa AS, Alencar EN, Rossetti LM, et al. Concordance among different pain scales in patients with dental pain. J Orofac Pain. 2012;26(2):126-31.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
