<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:42:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7875544" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7875544</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-12</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jaos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jaos</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Faculdade De Odontologia De Bauru - USP</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7875544</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7875544</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7875544</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33624688</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">00406</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-7757-2020-0502</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effect of final irrigation with sodium hypochlorite at different temperatures on postoperative pain level and antibacterial activity: a randomized controlled clinical study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8145-8763</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>KARATAŞ</surname>
                    <given-names>Ertuğrul</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>AYAZ</surname>
                    <given-names>Nilay</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>ULUKÖYLÜ</surname>
                    <given-names>Esra</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>BALTACI</surname>
                    <given-names>Mustafa Özkan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>ADIGÜZEL</surname>
                    <given-names>Ahmet</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <institution content-type="orgname">Ataturk University</institution>
                <institution content-type="orgdiv1">Faculty of Dentistry</institution>
                <institution content-type="orgdiv2">Department of Endodontics</institution>
                <addr-line>
                  <named-content content-type="city">Erzurum</named-content>
                </addr-line>
                <country country="TR">Turkey</country>
                <institution content-type="original">Ataturk University, Faculty of Dentistry, Department of Endodontics, Erzurum, Turkey.</institution>
              </aff>
              <aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <institution content-type="orgname">Ataturk University</institution>
                <institution content-type="orgdiv1">Faculty of Science, Molecular Biology and Genetics Microbiology</institution>
                <addr-line>
                  <named-content content-type="city">Erzurum</named-content>
                </addr-line>
                <country country="TR">Turkey</country>
                <institution content-type="original">Ataturk University, Faculty of Science, Molecular Biology and Genetics Microbiology, Erzurum, Turkey.</institution>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"> Corresponding address: Ertuğrul Karataş Ataturk University - Faculty of Dentistry - Department of Endodontics – Erzurum – 25240 - Turkey. Phone: +90.442.231 3804 - Fax: +90.442.231 2270. e-mail: <email>dtertu@windowslive.com</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                  <p>Conflict of interest</p>
                  <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="con">
                  <p>Authors' contributions</p>
                  <p><bold>Karataş, Ertugrul:</bold> Data curation (Equal); Formal analysis (Equal); Funding acquisition (Equal); Investigation (Equal); Methodology (Equal); Supervision (Equal). Writing-original draft (Equal); Writing-review &amp; editing (Equal). <bold>Ayaz, Nilay:</bold> Data curation (Equal); Investigation (Equal); Methodology (Equal); Resources (Equal). <bold>Uluköylü, Esra:</bold> Investigation (Equal); Methodology (Equal). <bold>Baltacı, Mustafa Özkan:</bold> Methodology (Equal). <bold>Adıgüzel, Ahmet:</bold> Supervision (Equal)</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>29</volume>
              <elocation-id>e20200502</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>8</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p> To evaluate the effect of final irrigation of root canals with NaOCl solution at different temperatures on postoperative pain level and antimicrobial activity.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methodology</title>
                  <p> 45 patients were randomly divided into three groups using a web program according to the irrigation selected: NaOCl 2ºC, NaOCl 25ºC and NaOCl 45ºC. First root canal samples were collected before treatment (S1). After chemo-mechanical preparation, final irrigation was performed with the selected irrigant (NaOCl 2ºC, NaOCl 25ºC and NaOCl 45ºC) and second samples were collected (S2). Samples were subjected to quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction to evaluate the levels of total bacteria. The root canal treatments were completed and the participants were given instructions to record postoperative pain levels at 24, 48 and 72 hours, 5 days and 1 week after treatment using a visual analog scale (VAS).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p> The reduction in the number of total bacterial cell equivalents from S1 to S2 was statistically significant in all groups (p&lt;0.001). The NaOCl 2˚C group reported significantly less postoperative pain than the NaOCl 45˚C group (p&lt;0.05). Postoperative analgesic intake was significantly higher in the NaOCl 45˚C group than in the NaOCl 2˚C group (p&lt;0.05).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p> We conclude that final irrigation with NaOCl at different temperatures results in similar antibacterial effectiveness. Final irrigation with cold NaOCl (2˚C) is better than NaOCl 45˚C when comparing postoperative pain levels.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Sodium hypochlorite</kwd>
                <kwd>Pain, Postoperative</kwd>
                <kwd>Antibacterial activity</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="0"/>
                <table-count count="5"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="28"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl) is the most common irrigant used in endodontics because of its antibacterial and physicochemical properties<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> and its unique ability to dissolve necrotic tissue remnants.<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Mechanical instrumentation and NaOCl irrigation have shown to dramatically reduce the bacterial load in the root canal system.<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Unfortunately, irrigation with NaOCl during chemo-mechanical debridement does not always result in bacteria-free root canals.<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Achieving bacteria-free root canals is critically important, since several studies reported that the presence of bacteria at the time of root filling significantly influences the outcome of endodontic treatment.<sup><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>-<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Therefore, several attempts have been made to increase NaOCl antimicrobial effectiveness, such as passive ultrasonic irrigation as a supplementary disinfecting step<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> and using NaOCl with a higher concentration,<sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> volume<sup><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> or temperature.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Previously, Sirtes, et al. (2005) reported that NaOCl at 45˚C has better antibacterial efficacy than at 20˚C.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> However, preheated NaOCl superior antibacterial action and effect on postoperative pain level have not yet been clinically demonstrated; one clinical study reported that the temperature of preheated NaOCl (60˚C) starts to decrease as soon as the solution touches the root canal wall, reaching body temperature (35.7˚C) within a few minutes.<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Due to the ability of NaOCl to kill microorganisms in seconds,<sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and the lack of information about the clinical antibacterial efficacy of preheated NaOCl, it is important to investigate if preheated NaOCl exerts an additional antibacterial effect and affects the postoperative pain level clinically, since the temperature of the irrigation solution is known to affect postoperative pain.<sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Consequently, there are no clinical studies to support the use of preheated NaOCl for root canal irrigation. Our randomized controlled clinical study aimed to evaluate the effect of final irrigation of root canals with NaOCl solution at different temperatures on postoperative pain level and antimicrobial activity. The null hypothesis was that the solution temperature does not change the solution antibacterial effectiveness or the postoperative pain level in patients presenting teeth with asymptomatic apical periodontitis.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Methodology</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Case selection and treatment procedure</title>
                <p>Forty-five patients (26 women and 19 men) presenting incisor, canine or premolar teeth with radiographic and clinical evidence of asymptomatic apical periodontitis were included in our study. This study was approved by the ethics committee of the Faculty of Dentistry, Ataturk University (Opinion No. 2017-67) and an informed consent form was signed by all participants before the treatment. The sample size (n=13) was determined using a program (GPower; Franz Faul, University of Kiel, Germany), expecting a difference of 48% in proportions of positive cultures among groups,<sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> with a 80% power and a 0.05 alpha level. It was decided to enroll 15 patients per group to increase statistical power and to account for the loss of participants during the study. Clinical registration number is TCTR20200420005.</p>
                <p>Teeth with necrotic pulps, clinically confirmed by pulp sensibility tests and the absence of bleeding on accessing the pulp chamber, no previous history of endodontic treatment, a pocket depth of &lt;3 mm and having a periapical lesion with a periapical index score of 3, 4 or 5 (Ørstavik, et al. (١٩٨٦)) were included.<sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Exclusion criteria: patients that underwent treatment with antibiotics or NSAIDs within 1 month before the study; patients with any systemic disease; teeth that had received previous endodontic treatment; teeth with extensive destruction of the crown that prevented proper rubber dam isolation; and the presence of internal or external resorption. A web program (www.randomizer.org) was used to randomly assign the 45 participants into three groups (n=15). After randomization, the number of each group and of each patient were recorded. All the treatments were performed by one clinician (N.A.). Blinding the clinician to the groups was not feasible because of the recognizable temperature of the syringe. However, the patients were blinded to the groups.</p>
                <p>Root canal samples were collected under strict aseptic technique. Before treatment, an oral rinse was performed with 0.12% chlorhexidine and before isolation of the teeth with the rubber dam, supra-gingival scaling was performed to remove plaque, followed by cleansing with pumice. Before the access cavity preparation, 30% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and 2.5% NaOCl for 30 s was used for disinfection of the crowns and surrounding structures (dam and clamp). After the disinfection protocol, the NaOCl was inactivated using 5% sodium thiosulfate. Access cavities were prepared using sterile round burs under cooling with sterile saline solution. The disinfection protocol described previously was performed again after completing access cavity preparation. To prevent the penetration of disinfectants into the pulp chamber and root canals, a sterile cotton pellet was placed on the floor of the pulp chamber. Sodium thiosulfate was used to neutralize NaOCl effectiveness and first sterility control samples were taken with sterile paper points from the coronal surface of the tooth, rubber dam, clamp and access cavity walls. Paper points were transferred to Eppendorf tubes containing a Tris-EDTA buffer (10 mmol/L Tris hydrochloride and 1 mmol/L EDTA, pH 7.6) and then the samples were kept at -80ºC until bacterial presence was assessed with quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR). The teeth with negative sterility control samples for bacterial presence in the qPCR assay were included in our study.</p>
                <p>After working length determination with an electronic apex locator (Raypex 6; VDW, Munich, Germany), the root canals were filled with sterile saline solution, not allowing them to overflow, and then a gentle filling motion was performed with a sterile #15 K-file (Mani, Tochigi, Japan). To obtain the first bacteriological sample (S1), paper points (Dentsply Maillefer, Ballaigues, Switzerland) were used to soak up the intracanal fluid in the root canal. The sampling procedure was repeated using three paper points and each paper point was left in the root canal for at least 60 seconds. Then the paper points were transferred to a tube containing a Tris-EDTA buffer. Any contact between the paper points and the cavity walls was avoided to prevent contamination during transfer of the paper points into the tubes.</p>
                <p>Root canals were prepared using Reciproc files (R25, R40 or R50) (VDW, Munich, Germany), according to the manufacturer recommendations. During preparation, root canal irrigation was performed using 1 mL of 1% NaOCl between three pecking motions of the file and final irrigation was performed with 5 mL of 17% EDTA followed by 5 mL of 1% NaOCl (at different temperatures). According to the final irrigation, the groups were divided as follows:</p>
                <p>NaOCl 2ºC: Syringes filled with 5 mL of 1% NaOCl were kept in a fridge at -2 ºC. Before the irrigation procedure, the syringe was removed from the fridge and when the temperature of the syringe, which was checked with a thermometer, increased to 2ºC, root canal irrigation was performed for 1 minute (the room temperature was 24.2ºC).</p>
                <p>NaOCl 25ºC: A CanalPro syringe heater (Coltene, Altstätten, Switzerland) was used to heat a syringe filled with 5 mL of 1% NaOCl. The syringe was left in the device for 30 seconds to reach an average temperature of 26±0.2ºC, because the device cannot be set to a specific temperature. Then the syringe was removed from the device and when the temperature of the syringe, which was checked with a thermometer, decreased to 25ºC, root canal irrigation was performed for 1 minute (the room temperature was 24.2ºC).</p>
                <p>NaOCl 45ºC: A CanalPro syringe heater (Coltene, Altstätten, Switzerland) was used to heat a syringe filled with 5 mL of 1% NaOCl. The syringe was left in the device for 20 minutes to reach an average temperature of 48±0.2ºC, because the device cannot be set to a specific temperature. Then the syringe was removed from the device and when the temperature of the syringe, which was checked with a thermometer, decreased to 45<sup>º</sup>C, root canal irrigation was performed for 1 minute (the room temperature was 24.2ºC).</p>
                <p>After that, 2 mL of 0.5% sodium thiosulfate was used to inactivate the NaOCl and then the root canals were finally irrigated with distilled water. Second samples (S2) were taken as described above.</p>
                <p>Next, paper points were used to dry the root canals and the cold lateral compaction technique was used to obturate the root canals with gutta-percha cones and sealer (Sealapex, Kerr Corporation, Orange, CA). Permanent restorations were performed using flowable and nanohybrid composite resins (3M ESPE, St Paul, MN, USA). The participants were given instructions to record postoperative pain levels at 24, 48 and 72 hours, 5 days and 1 week after treatment using an 100 mm visual analog scale (VAS) as well as recording analgesic taken on the questionnaire. If a patient was referred to an unscheduled appointment, this was also recorded.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Quantitative real-time PCR analysis</title>
                <p>The total bacterial counts were evaluated using 16S ribosomal RNA gene-based qPCR with QuantiTect SYBR<sup>®</sup> Green PCR Kits (Qiagen) on a Rotor-Gene real-time PCR instrument (Qiagen) in a total reaction volume of 20 mL universal 16S ribosomal RNA gene-based primers (Forward primer 5’-ACTACGTGCCAGCAGCC-3’ and reverse primer 5’GGACTACCAGGGTATCTAATCC-3’); qPCR reaction conditions were 95°C for 15 min, and 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 s, 55°C for 30 s and 72°C for 30 s. For each cycle, the accumulation of PCR products was detected by monitoring the increase in fluorescence of the reporter dye (double-stranded DNA-binding SYBR Green). All measurements were performed in triplicate for samples and standards. In all experiments, triplicates of appropriate negative controls containing no DNA template were subjected to the same procedures to exclude or detect any possible contamination or carryover.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The Poisson regression model, which is the basic approach for modeling bacterial count data, was used as previously described.<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> For intragroup analysis, the Mann-Whitney U test was used to compare reduction of counts of total bacteria between the two samples (S1 and S2), since the data were not normally distributed. The chi-square test was used to compare the number of root canals positive for bacteria in S1 and S2 among the NaOCl 2ºC, NaOCl 25ºC and NaOCl 45ºC groups. The number of bacteria in S1 and S2 samples and the reduction (%) in the number of total bacteria from S1 to S2 among the groups were compared using the Kruskal-Wallis test. Data were analyzed with GraphPad Prism Software (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA) at a significance level of p=0.05.</p>
                <p>The Kruskal-Wallis test was used to compare postoperative pain values among the groups, because the data were not normally distributed. Linear regression analyses were conducted to determine the confounding effects introduced by covariates (tooth number, sex, treatment group and age). The chi-square test was used to analyze nominal data (tooth number, sex and analgesic intake). The statistical analyses for postoperative pain values were performed using IBM<sup>®</sup> SPSS<sup>®</sup> Statistics 20 software (IBM SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) at 5% significance level (p=0.05).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Since all the sterility control samples yielded negative results for bacteria and there was no patient loss during follow up, 45 patients (26 women and 19 men) were included in our study. Each patient contributed with 1 tooth and there was no statistically significant difference among the groups in comparison of sex, age and tooth number distribution (p&gt;0.05) (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Distribution of patients according to age, sex, tooth number and analgesic intake</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup width="20%" span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" style="font-weight:normal" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" style="font-weight:normal" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2ºC</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">25ºC</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">45ºC</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Age</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.93 ± 12.5</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.07 ± 9.83</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.13 ± 15.75</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.769</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.529</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth Number</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#11</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#12</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#21</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#22</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#31</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#32</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#33</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#35</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#41</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#44</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analgesic intake</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15<sup>a</sup></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13<sup>ab</sup></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>b</sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0<sup>a</sup></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup>ab</sup></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<sup>b</sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN1">
                      <p>Within the same row, values with the same letters were not statistically different at p=0.05</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <sec>
                <title>Total bacterial counts</title>
                <p><xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows total bacterial counts, which were analyzed using universal 16S rRNA gene-based primers, for S1 and S2 samples according to the groups. In the NaOCl 2˚C, 25˚C and 45˚C groups, a mean number of 6.47×10<sup>6</sup>, 5.18×10<sup>6</sup>and 5.76×10<sup>6</sup> bacterial counts in S1 was decreased to a mean of 3.66×10<sup>5</sup>, 2.7×10<sup>5</sup> and 3.31×10<sup>5</sup> bacterial counts in S2, respectively. The reduction in the number of total bacterial cell equivalents from S1 to S2 was statistically significant in all groups (p&lt;0.001). The percentage of reduction was 94.7, 95 and 93.9 for the NaOCl 2˚C, 25˚C and 45˚C groups, respectively. There was no statistically significant difference among the groups in terms of percentage of reduction of total bacterial counts (p&gt;0.05).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Changes in Total Bacterial Counts during Treatment</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup width="20%" span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" style="font-weight:normal" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">S1</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">S2</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduction (%)</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>NaOCl 2°C</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66 × 105</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.78 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94 × 105</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 × 105 – 8.21 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0- 6.21 × 105</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>NaOCl 25°C</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 × 105</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.55 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01 × 105</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22 × 106 - 6.69 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 – 5.11 × 105</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>NaOCl 45°C</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31 × 105</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.89 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81 × 105</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22 × 106 – 7.47 × 106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 – 5.58 × 104</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.384</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.418</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN2">
                        <p>S1: Sample taken before treatment</p>
                      </fn>
                      <fn id="TFN3">
                        <p>S2: Sample taken after chemo-mechanical preparation</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>The number of root canals positive for bacteria was also evaluated. Whereas all the S1 samples were positive for bacteria in all groups, 3 root canals from the NaOCl 2˚C group, 3 root canals from the NaOCl 25˚C group and 2 root canals from the NaOCl 45˚C group became negative for bacteria in S2 samples (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The difference among the groups in the number of root canals positive for bacteria was not statistically significant (p&gt;0.05).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Table 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>The Number of Root Canals Positive for Bacteria during Treatment</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup width="20%" span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" style="font-weight:normal" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl 2°C</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl 25°C</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl 45°C</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/15 (100)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/15 (100)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/15 (100)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/15 (80)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/15 (80)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/15 (86.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.859</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN4">
                        <p>The number of cases with a positive result/ number of cases (%)</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Postoperative pain</title>
                <p>Linear regression analyses revealed that postoperative pain level on day 1 was only influenced by the group (p&lt;0.05). Sex, age and tooth number did not influence the postoperative pain level on day 1 (p&gt;0.05). (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap id="t4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Table 4</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Linear Regression Model Findings for Postoperative Pain on Day 1</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup width="20%" span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" style="font-weight:normal" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B*</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Error</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.762</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.084</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-14.484</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.279</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.201</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.251</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.421</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.554</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth number</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.465</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.556</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>The mean postoperative pain level was 6.67±10.722, 16.87±27.604 and 40.0±50.709 for the NaOCl 2˚C, 25˚C and 45˚C groups, respectively. (<xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Statistical analysis showed that the NaOCl 2˚C group reported significantly less postoperative pain than the NaOCl 45˚C group (p&lt;0.05). However, there was no statistically significant difference between the NaOCl 2˚C and NaOCl 25˚C groups and between the NaOCl 25˚C and NaOCl 45˚C groups in postoperative pain level on day 1 (p&gt;0.05). Moreover, there was a statistically significant difference among the groups in postoperative analgesic intake. The number of patients that needed analgesic was 0, 2 and 5 for the NaOCl 2˚C, NaOCl 25˚C and NaOCl 45˚C groups, respectively. Postoperative analgesic intake was significantly higher in the NaOCl 45˚C group than in the NaOCl 2˚C group (p&lt;0.05). However, there was no statistically significant difference between the NaOCl 2˚C and NaOCl 25˚C groups and between the NaOCl 25˚C and NaOCl 45˚C groups in postoperative analgesic intake (p&gt;0.05).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap id="t5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Table 5</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Postoperative pain levels according to the groups</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup width="20%" span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" style="font-weight:normal" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaOCl</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" style="font-weight:normal" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2ºC</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">25ºC</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">45ºC</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<sup>st</sup> Day</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67<sup>a</sup>±10.722</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.87<sup>ab</sup>±27.604</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0<sup>b</sup>±50.709</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,03</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup>nd</sup> Day</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.13±10.176</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.13±27.118</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0±35.355</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,219</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<sup>rd</sup> Day</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13±7.726</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.13±17.221</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.33±19.97</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,059</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<sup>th</sup> Day</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.40±18.715</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.07±29.173</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.67±26.502</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<sup>th</sup> Day</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33±8.797</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,129</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN5">
                        <p>Within the same row, values with the same letters were not statistically different at P=0.05</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Our study compared the effect of NaOCl with different temperatures on elimination of bacteria from root canals and postoperative pain level. Since there was no significant difference among the groups in antibacterial effectiveness, but the temperature of the solution affected the postoperative pain level, the null hypothesis was partially rejected. According to the results of our study, chemo-mechanical preparation and final irrigation with EDTA + NaOCl was highly effective in significantly reducing the intracanal bacterial counts, irrespective of the NaOCl temperature. This is in agreement with previous studies, which reported statistically significant reduction of bacterial counts by chemo-mechanical preparation.<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> However, there was no statistically significant difference among the groups, when comparing NaOCl with different temperatures, in the removal of bacteria from root canals. Several studies investigated the antibacterial effect of NaOCl with different temperatures and conflicting results have been reported<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>-<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. Sirtes, et al.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> (2005) observed a 100-fold increase in NaOCl antibacterial efficacy when the solution was heated from 20°C to 45°C. Similarly, Giardino, et al.<sup><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> (2016) demonstrated better NaOCl antibacterial efficacy at 45°C than at 20°C. However, Sirtes et al. used NaOCl solution with a concentration of 0.001% and they added bacteria in phosphate-buffered saline into the NaOCl solution. That is, they did not use extracted teeth or dentine slices in their investigation to mimic clinical conditions, which may have affected the results, because the presence of organic (tissue remnants and inflammatory exudate) and inorganic matter (dentine) can weaken the antibacterial effectiveness of the NaOCl solution<sup><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. Moreover, they incubated the bacteria in the NaOCl solution for 10 minutes. Giardino, et al.<sup><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> (2016) also assessed the NaOCl antibacterial efficacy after a 10-minute contact, which is a relatively longer contact time when compared with clinical conditions. Moreover, both studies were culture-based; which are less sensitive than the qPCR, which can detect as-yet-uncultivated bacteria.<sup><xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> The methodological differences mentioned above could explain the difference in the findings of our study and the previous ones. Our findings could be explained by the strong antibacterial effect and the NaOCl concentration (1%) used in our study was efficient for killing sufficient bacteria in the root canal system. NaOCl can kill bacteria even at concentrations lower than 0.1%. Additionally, and consistent with our results, Carpio-Perochena, et al.<sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> (2015) compared NaOCl solutions with a concentration of 1% at different temperatures (22°C and 37°C) in terms of antibacterial efficacy and concluded that the temperature variation of the NaOCl is not relevant in killing or dissolving bacterial biofilms. Likewise, Gulsahi, et al.<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> (2014) reported that there is no significant difference between the NaOCl at 25°C and 37°C in killing <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> and <italic>Candida albicans</italic> for the same contact times. Therefore, it can be speculated that NaOCl with a concentration of 1% exerts a strong antibacterial efficacy that provides a substantial reduction in bacterial counts in the root canal system, regardless of the solution temperature.</p>
              <p>Our study also evaluated the effect of the NaOCl at different temperatures on the level of postoperative pain and showed that root canal irrigation with NaOCl at 45°C resulted in a significantly higher postoperative pain value than NaOCl at 2°C. This finding is in accordance with previous studies that reported less postoperative pain with the application of intracanal cryotherapy.<sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Cryotherapy leads to reduced cellular metabolism by dropping local temperature, which causes reduced blood flow.<sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Consequently, the effect of cryotherapy on limiting inflammation may explain the reduced postoperative pain value in NaOCl 2°C group.<sup><xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> However, the most important finding of our study was that, although there was no statistically significant difference between the NaOCl 25°C and NaOCl 2°C groups, postoperative pain reached the highest level in the NaOCl 45°C group, with a significant difference when compared with the NaOCl 2°C group. This means that using preheated NaOCl for root canal irrigation results in a higher postoperative pain value. Additionally, in the NaOCl 45°C group, the need for analgesic intake was significantly higher than in the NaOCl 2°C group. There are no previous studies evaluating the effect of intracanal irrigation with preheated NaOCl on the level of postoperative pain, therefore, a direct comparison cannot be performed. However, the postoperative pain-enhancing effect of the preheated NaOCl can be explained by the fact that heat increases tissue temperature, which results in vasodilatation.<sup><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Vasodilatation increases blood flow and allows leukocytes and plasma proteins to exit the circulation, which may cause an increase in inflammatory response, thus increasing postoperative pain.</p>
              <p>One of the limitations of our study is that the temperature of the solution in the root canal was not constant during the irrigation procedure. De Hemptinne, et al.<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> (2015) showed that the solution temperature (45°C) decreased to body temperature (37°C) in 60 seconds when the solution was used for root canal irrigation <italic>in vivo</italic>. However, since the NaOCl exerts its antibacterial efficacy in seconds,<sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> 60 seconds is enough to assess the antibacterial efficacy of the preheated NaOCl solution. Moreover, it can be claimed that a decrease in the temperature of the solution had no significant effect, since the preheated NaOCl group showed higher postoperative pain values than the NaOCl 2°C group. This means that the effect of the heat was clearly shown in our study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p>We conclude that preheating NaOCl does not provide any extra antibacterial effect and results in a higher postoperative pain value than the cold NaOCl when used for final irrigation of root canals of teeth with asymptomatic apical periodontitis.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Funded by the scientific research projects department of Atatürk University.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B1-gen-2">- Siqueira JF Jr, Guimarães-Pinto T, Rôças IN. Effects of chemomechanical preparation with 2.5% sodium hypochlorite and intracanal medication with calcium hydroxide on cultivable bacteria in infected root canals. J Endod. 2007;33(7):800-5. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2006.11.023</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B1-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guimarães-Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rôças</surname>
                      <given-names>IN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of chemomechanical preparation with 2.5% sodium hypochlorite and intracanal medication with calcium hydroxide on cultivable bacteria in infected root canals</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>800</fpage>
                  <lpage>805</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2006.11.023</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17804315</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B2-gen-2">- Zehnder M. Root canal irrigants. J Endod. 2006;32(5):389-98. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2005.09.014</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B2-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zehnder</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Root canal irrigants</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <lpage>398</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2005.09.014</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16631834</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B3-gen-2">- Card SJ, Sigurdsson A, Orstavik D, Trope M. The effectiveness of increased apical enlargement in reducing intracanal bacteria. J Endod. 2002;28(11):779-83. doi: 10.1097/00004770-200211000-00008</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B3-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Card</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sigurdsson</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Orstavik</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trope</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effectiveness of increased apical enlargement in reducing intracanal bacteria</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>779</fpage>
                  <lpage>783</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004770-200211000-00008</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12470024</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B4-gen-2">- Zandi H, Rodrigues RC, Kristoffersen AK, Enersen M, Mdala I, Ørstavik D, et al. Antibacterial effectiveness of 2 root canal irrigants in root-filled teeth with infection: a randomized clinical trial. J Endod. 2016;42(9):1307-13. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2016.06.006</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B4-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zandi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                      <given-names>RC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kristoffersen</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Enersen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mdala</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ørstavik</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Antibacterial effectiveness of 2 root canal irrigants in root-filled teeth with infection: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1307</fpage>
                  <lpage>1313</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2016.06.006</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27452293</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B5-gen-2">- Sjögren U, Figdor D, Persson S, Sundqvist G. Influence of infection at the time of root filling on the outcome of endodontic treatment of teeth with apical periodontitis. Int Endod J. 1997;30(5):297-306. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-2591.1997.00092.x. Erratum in: Int Endod J 1998;31(2):148.</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B5-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sjögren</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Figdor</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Persson</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sundqvist</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of infection at the time of root filling on the outcome of endodontic treatment of teeth with apical periodontitis</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <lpage>306</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2591.1997.00092.x</pub-id>
                  <comment>Erratum in: Int Endod J 1998;31(2):148</comment>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9477818</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B6-gen-2">- Waltimo T, Trope M, Haapasalo M, Ørstavik D. Clinical efficacy of treatment procedures in endodontic infection control and one year follow-up of periapical healing. J Endod. 2005;31(12):863-6. doi: 10.1097/01.don.0000164856.27920.85</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B6-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Waltimo</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trope</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haapasalo</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ørstavik</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical efficacy of treatment procedures in endodontic infection control and one year follow-up of periapical healing</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>863</fpage>
                  <lpage>866</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.don.0000164856.27920.85</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306819</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B7-gen-2">- Zandi H, Petronijevic N, Mdala I, Kristoffersen AK, Enersen M, Rôças IN, et al. Outcome of endodontic retreatment using 2 root canal ırrigants and ınfluence of ınfection on healing as determined by a molecular method: a randomized clinical trial. J Endod. 2019;45(9):1089-98.e5. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2019.05.021</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B7-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zandi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petronijevic</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mdala</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kristoffersen</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Enersen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rôças</surname>
                      <given-names>IN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Outcome of endodontic retreatment using 2 root canal ırrigants and ınfluence of ınfection on healing as determined by a molecular method: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1089</fpage>
                  <lpage>1098</lpage>
                  <comment>e5</comment>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2019.05.021</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31300248</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B8-gen-2">8 - Mohmmed SA, Vianna ME, Penny MR, Hilton ST, Mordan NJ, Knowles JC. Investigations into <italic>in situ</italic> Enterococcus faecalis biofilm removal by passive and active sodium hypochlorite irrigation delivered into the lateral canal of a simulated root canal model. Int Endod J. 2018;51(6):649-62. doi: 10.1111/iej.12880</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B8-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mohmmed</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vianna</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Penny</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hilton</surname>
                      <given-names>ST</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mordan</surname>
                      <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Knowles</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Investigations into in situ Enterococcus faecalis biofilm removal by passive and active sodium hypochlorite irrigation delivered into the lateral canal of a simulated root canal model</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>649</fpage>
                  <lpage>662</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iej.12880</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29178348</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B9-gen-2">9 - Gomes BP, Ferraz CC, Vianna ME, Berber VB, Teixeira FB, Souza-Filho FJ. In vitro antimicrobial activity of several concentrations of sodium hypochlorite and chlorhexidine gluconate in the elimination of <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic>. Int Endod J. 2001;34(6):424-8. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-2591.2001.00410.x</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B9-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gomes</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferraz</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vianna</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berber</surname>
                      <given-names>VB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teixeira</surname>
                      <given-names>FB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza</surname>
                      <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>In vitro antimicrobial activity of several concentrations of sodium hypochlorite and chlorhexidine gluconate in the elimination of Enterococcus faecalis</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>424</fpage>
                  <lpage>428</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2591.2001.00410.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556507</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B10-gen-2">- Gazzaneo I, Vieira GC, Pérez AR, Alves FR, Gonçalves LS, Mdala I, et al. Root canal disinfection by single- and multiple-instrument systems: effects of sodium hypochlorite volume, concentration, and retention time. J Endod. 2019;45(6):736-41. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2019.02.017</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B10-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gazzaneo</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vieira</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pérez</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alves</surname>
                      <given-names>FR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gonçalves</surname>
                      <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mdala</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Root canal disinfection by single- and multiple-instrument systems: effects of sodium hypochlorite volume, concentration, and retention time</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>736</fpage>
                  <lpage>741</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2019.02.017</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30981431</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B11-gen-2">- Sirtes G, Waltimo T, Schaetzle M, Zehnder M. The effects of temperature on sodium hypochlorite short-term stability, pulp dissolution capacity, and antimicrobial efficacy. J Endod. 2005;31(9):669-71. doi: 10.1097/01.don.0000153846.62144.d2</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B11-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sirtes</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Waltimo</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schaetzle</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zehnder</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of temperature on sodium hypochlorite short-term stability, pulp dissolution capacity, and antimicrobial efficacy</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>669</fpage>
                  <lpage>671</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.don.0000153846.62144.d2</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123703</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B12-gen-2">12 - de Hemptinne F, Slaus G, Vandendael M, Jacquet W, De Moor RJ, Bottenberg P. <italic>In vivo</italic> ıntracanal temperature evolution during endodontic treatment after the ınjection of room temperature or preheated sodium hypochlorite. J Endod. 2015;41(7):1112-5. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2015.02.011</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B12-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Hemptinne</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Slaus</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vandendael</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jacquet</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Moor</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bottenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>In vivo ıntracanal temperature evolution during endodontic treatment after the ınjection of room temperature or preheated sodium hypochlorite</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1112</fpage>
                  <lpage>1115</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2015.02.011</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25814243</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B13-gen-2">13 - Vianna ME, Gomes BP, Berber VB, Zaia AA, Ferraz CC, Souza-Filho FJ. <italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of the antimicrobial activity of chlorhexidine and sodium hypochlorite. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod. 2004;97(1):79-84. doi: 10.1016/s1079-2104(03)00360-3</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B13-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vianna</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gomes</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berber</surname>
                      <given-names>VB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaia</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferraz</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza-Filho</surname>
                      <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>In vitro evaluation of the antimicrobial activity of chlorhexidine and sodium hypochlorite</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>97</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <lpage>84</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1079-2104(03)00360-3</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14716261</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B14-gen-2">- Gundogdu EC, Arslan H. Effects of various cryotherapy applications on postoperative pain in molar teeth with symptomatic apical periodontitis: a preliminary randomized prospective clinical trial. J Endod. 2018;44(3):349-54. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2017.11.002</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B14-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gundogdu</surname>
                      <given-names>EC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arslan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of various cryotherapy applications on postoperative pain in molar teeth with symptomatic apical periodontitis: a preliminary randomized prospective clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <lpage>354</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2017.11.002</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29398090</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B15-gen-2">- Vera J, Ochoa J, Romero M, Vazquez-Carcaño M, Ramos-Gregorio CO, Aguilar RR, et al. Intracanal cryotherapy reduces postoperative pain in teeth with symptomatic apical periodontitis: a randomized multicenter clinical trial. J Endod. 2018;44(1):4-8. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2017.08.038</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B15-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vera</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ochoa</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Romero</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vazquez-Carcaño</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramos-Gregorio</surname>
                      <given-names>CO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aguilar</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Intracanal cryotherapy reduces postoperative pain in teeth with symptomatic apical periodontitis: a randomized multicenter clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>4</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2017.08.038</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29079057</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B16-gen-2">- Peters LB, van Winkelhoff AJ, Buijs JF, Wesselink PR. Effects of instrumentation, irrigation and dressing with calcium hydroxide on infection in pulpless teeth with periapical bone lesions. Int Endod J. 2002;35(1):13-21. doi: 10.1046/j.0143-2885.2001.00447.x</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B16-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peters</surname>
                      <given-names>LB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Winkelhoff</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buijs</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wesselink</surname>
                      <given-names>PR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of instrumentation, irrigation and dressing with calcium hydroxide on infection in pulpless teeth with periapical bone lesions</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <lpage>21</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0143-2885.2001.00447.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11858203</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B17-gen-2">- Rôças IN, Provenzano JC, Neves MA, Siqueira JF Jr. Disinfecting effects of rotary ınstrumentation with either 2.5% sodium hypochlorite or 2% chlorhexidine as the main ırrigant: a randomized clinical study. J Endod. 2016;42(6):943-7. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2016.03.019</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B17-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rôças</surname>
                      <given-names>IN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Provenzano</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neves</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Disinfecting effects of rotary ınstrumentation with either 2.5% sodium hypochlorite or 2% chlorhexidine as the main ırrigant: a randomized clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>943</fpage>
                  <lpage>947</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2016.03.019</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27142579</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B18-gen-2">- Ørstavik D, Kerekes K, Eriksen HM. The periapical index: A scoring system for radiographic assessment of apical periodontitis. Dental Traumatology. 1986;2:20-34. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-9657.1986.tb00119.x</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B18-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ørstavik</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kerekes</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eriksen</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The periapical index: A scoring system for radiographic assessment of apical periodontitis</article-title>
                  <source>Dental Traumatology</source>
                  <year>1986</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <lpage>34</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-9657.1986.tb00119.x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B19-gen-2">- Del Carpio-Perochena A, Bramante CM, Duarte MH, Andrade FB, Graeff MZ, Silva MM, et al. Effect of temperature, concentration and contact time of sodium hypochlorite on the treatment and revitalization of oral biofilms. J Dent Res Dent Clin Dent Prospects. 2015;9(4):209-15. doi: 10.15171/joddd.2015.038</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B19-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Del Carpio-Perochena</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bramante</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duarte</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andrade</surname>
                      <given-names>FB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Graeff</surname>
                      <given-names>MZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal>et al</etal>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of temperature, concentration and contact time of sodium hypochlorite on the treatment and revitalization of oral biofilms</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res Dent Clin Dent Prospects</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <lpage>215</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15171/joddd.2015.038</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26889356</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B20-gen-2">- Giardino L, Mohammadi Z, Beltrami R, Poggio C, Estrela C, Generali L. Influence of temperature on the antibacterial activity of sodium hypochlorite. Braz Dent J. 2016;27(1):32-6. doi: 10.1590/0103-6440201600627</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B20-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giardino</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mohammadi</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beltrami</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poggio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Estrela</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Generali</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of temperature on the antibacterial activity of sodium hypochlorite</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Dent J</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0103-6440201600627</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27007342</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B21-gen-2">21 - Gulsahi K, Tirali RE, Cehreli SB, Karahan ZC, Uzunoglu E, Sabuncuoglu B. The effect of temperature and contact time of sodium hypochlorite on human roots infected with Enterococcus faecalis and <italic>Candida albicans</italic>. Odontology. 2014;102(1):36-41. doi: 10.1007/s10266-012-0086-x</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B21-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gulsahi</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tirali</surname>
                      <given-names>RE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cehreli</surname>
                      <given-names>SB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karahan</surname>
                      <given-names>ZC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uzunoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sabuncuoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of temperature and contact time of sodium hypochlorite on human roots infected with Enterococcus faecalis and Candida albicans</article-title>
                  <source>Odontology</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>102</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10266-012-0086-x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23011474</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B22-gen-2">22 - Haapasalo HK, Sirén EK, Waltimo TM, Ørstavik D, Haapasalo MP. Inactivation of local root canal medicaments by dentine: an <italic>in vitro</italic> study. Int Endod J. 2000;33(2):126-31. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-2591.2000.00291.x</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B22-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haapasalo</surname>
                      <given-names>HK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sirén</surname>
                      <given-names>EK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Waltimo</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ørstavik</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haapasalo</surname>
                      <given-names>MP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inactivation of local root canal medicaments by dentine: an in vitro study</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <lpage>131</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2591.2000.00291.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11307453</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B23-gen-2">- Tejada S, Baca P, Ferrer-Luque CM, Ruiz-Linares M, Valderrama MJ, Arias-Moliz MT. Influence of dentine debris and organic tissue on the properties of sodium hypochlorite solutions. Int Endod J. 2019;52(1):114-22. doi: 10.1111/iej.12986</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B23-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tejada</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baca</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferrer-Luque</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ruiz-Linares</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Valderrama</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arias-Moliz</surname>
                      <given-names>MT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of dentine debris and organic tissue on the properties of sodium hypochlorite solutions</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>52</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <lpage>122</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iej.12986</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30019752</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B24-gen-2">- Siqueira JF Jr, Rôças IN. Exploiting molecular methods to explore endodontic infections: Part 1--current molecular technologies for microbiological diagnosis. J Endod. 2005;31(6):411-23. doi: 10.1097/01.don.0000157989.44949.26</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B24-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rôças</surname>
                      <given-names>IN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Exploiting molecular methods to explore endodontic infections: Part 1--current molecular technologies for microbiological diagnosis</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>411</fpage>
                  <lpage>423</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.don.0000157989.44949.26</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15917679</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B25-gen-2">- Keskin C, Özdemir Ö, Uzun İ, Güler B. Effect of intracanal cryotherapy on pain after single-visit root canal treatment. Aust Endod J. 2017;43(2):83-8. doi: 10.1111/aej.1217</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B25-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keskin</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Özdemir</surname>
                      <given-names>Ö</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uzun</surname>
                      <given-names>İ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Güler</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of intracanal cryotherapy on pain after single-visit root canal treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Endod J</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <lpage>88</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aej.1217</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27699913</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B26-gen-2">- Capps SG, Brook M. Cryotherapy and intermittent pneumatic compression for soft tissue trauma. Athl Ther Today. 2009;14(1):2-4. doi: 10.1123/att.14.1.2</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B26-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capps</surname>
                      <given-names>SG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brook</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cryotherapy and intermittent pneumatic compression for soft tissue trauma</article-title>
                  <source>Athl Ther Today</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>2</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/att.14.1.2</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B27-gen-2">- Laureano JR Filho, Oliveira e Silva ED, Batista CI, Gouveia FM. The influence of cryotherapy on reduction of swelling, pain and trismus after third-molar extraction: a preliminary study. J Am Dent Assoc. 2005;136(6):774-8; quiz 807. doi: 10.14219/jada.archive.2005.0261</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="B27-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laureano</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira e Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>ED</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batista</surname>
                      <given-names>CI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gouveia</surname>
                      <given-names>FM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The influence of cryotherapy on reduction of swelling, pain and trismus after third-molar extraction: a preliminary study</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>136</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>774</fpage>
                  <lpage>778</lpage>
                  <comment>quiz 807</comment>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14219/jada.archive.2005.0261</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16022042</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="B28-gen-2">28 - Reid RW, Foley JM, Prior BM, Weingand KW, Meyer RA. In: Abstracts of the 46th Annual Meeting American College of Sports Medicine [Internet]; 1999 June 2-6; Washington State, USA. p. S208. (Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise; vol. 31, n. 5). Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005768-199905001-00957</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="B28-gen-3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reid</surname>
                      <given-names>RW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Foley</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prior</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weingand</surname>
                      <given-names>KW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meyer</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Abstracts of the 46th Annual Meeting American College of Sports Medicine</source>
                  <comment>Internet</comment>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <season>Jun-Jun</season>
                  <publisher-loc>Washington State, USA</publisher-loc>
                  <size units="pages">S208</size>
                  <comment>Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise; vol. 31, n. 5</comment>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005768-199905001-00957</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
