<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10913007" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10913007</identifier>
        <datestamp>2024-03-06</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jamasd</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Pediatr</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Pediatr</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>JAMA Pediatrics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2168-6203</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2168-6211</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10913007</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10913007</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10913007</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38436947</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38436947</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2023.6770</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">poi230100</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="domain" specific-use="print">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Investigation</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="featured" specific-use="electronic">
                  <subject>Featured</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="online-first">
                  <subject>Online First</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="allowCommenting">
                  <subject>Comments</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Noninferiority of Silver Diamine Fluoride vs Sealants for Reducing Dental Caries Prevalence and Incidence</article-title>
                <subtitle>A Randomized Clinical Trial</subtitle>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Noninferiority of Silver Diamine Fluoride vs Sealants for Reducing Dental Caries Prevalence and Incidence</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Noninferiority of Silver Diamine Fluoride vs Sealants for Reducing Dental Caries Prevalence and Incidence</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ruff</surname>
                    <given-names>Ryan Richard</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <degrees>MPH</degrees>
                  <xref rid="poi230100aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="poi230100aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Barry Godín</surname>
                    <given-names>Tamarinda J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DDS</degrees>
                  <xref rid="poi230100aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Niederman</surname>
                    <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DMD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="poi230100aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="poi230100aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Epidemiology &amp; Health Promotion, New York University College of Dentistry, New York</aff>
              <aff id="poi230100aff2"><label>2</label>New York University School of Global Public Health, New York</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <title>Article Information</title>
                <p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> December 19, 2023.</p>
                <p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published Online:</bold> March 4, 2024. <?xpp bx;1?>doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2023.6770</uri></p>
                <p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. © 2024 Ruff RR et al. <italic>JAMA Pediatrics</italic>.</p>
                <corresp id="poi230100cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Ryan Richard Ruff, PhD, MPH, Department of Epidemiology &amp; Health Promotion, New York University College of Dentistry, 380 Second Ave, Room 3-09, New York, NY 10010 (<email xlink:href="ryan.ruff@nyu.edu">ryan.ruff@nyu.edu</email>).</corresp>
                <p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Ruff had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
                <p><italic>Concept and design</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Statistical analysis</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Obtained funding</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Supervision</italic>: All authors.</p>
                <p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Ruff reported grants from the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute and the National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities during the conduct of the study. Dr Barry Godín reported grants from the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute during the conduct of the study. Dr Niederman reported grants from the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute and the National Institutes of Health, nonfinancial support from Colgate (toothbrushes and toothpaste), GC America (glass ionomer), and Elevate Oral Care (silver diamine fluoride) during the conduct of the study as well as consulting fees from Delta Dental Washington outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p>
                <p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> Research presented in this report was funded by the <funding-source rid="sp1">Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</funding-source> (PCS-160936724).</p>
                <p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funder had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
                <p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-POI230100-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 3</xref>.</p>
                <p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> We thank Denise Guerrero, CDA (assistant research scientist); Topaz Murray Small, MPA (project administrator); Nydia Santiago-Galvin, RN, MPH (community engagement officer); Rachel Whittemore, MPH (clinical research coordinator); Haley Gibbs, BA (administrative assistant); and Priyanka Sharma, MPH (dental hygienist and clinical team lead), of the New York University College of Dentistry; and the members of the CariedAway clinical team, without whom the study would not have been successful. All nonauthor contributors were compensated by the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute.</p>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-03-04T10:00">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.-->
              <volume>178</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>354</fpage>
              <lpage>361</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright 2024 Ruff RR et al. <italic>JAMA Pediatrics</italic>.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamapediatr-e236770.pdf">jamapediatr-e236770.pdf</self-uri>
              <self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/archpedi/fullarticle/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2023.6770"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="key-points">
                <title>Key Points</title>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-1">
                  <title>Question</title>
                  <p>Is silver diamine fluoride noninferior to dental sealants and atraumatic restorations in the prevalence of dental caries when used in schools?</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-2">
                  <title>Findings</title>
                  <p>In this randomized clinical trial of 7418 children, the incidence of dental caries was comparable between children treated with silver diamine fluoride and those treated with dental sealants and atraumatic restorations. For caries prevalence, silver diamine fluoride was noninferior in adjusted models.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-3">
                  <title>Meaning</title>
                  <p>The findings suggest that silver diamine fluoride can be effectively used as a primary intervention for school-based caries prevention.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic">
                <p>This randomized clinical trial evaluates the use of silver diamine fluoride for reducing the prevalence of dental caries.</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-4">
                  <title>Importance</title>
                  <p>Dental caries is the world’s most prevalent noncommunicable disease and a source of health inequity; school dental sealant programs are a common preventive measure. Silver diamine fluoride (SDF) may provide an alternative therapy to prevent and control caries if shown to be noninferior to sealant treatment.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-5">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>To determine whether school-based application of SDF is noninferior to dental sealants and atraumatic restorative treatment (ART) in the prevalence of dental caries.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-6">
                  <title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title>
                  <p>The Silver Diamine Fluoride Versus Therapeutic Sealants for the Arrest and Prevention of Dental Caries in Low-Income Minority Children (CariedAway) study was a pragmatic noninferiority cluster-randomized clinical trial conducted from February 2018 to June 2023 to compare silver diamine fluoride vs therapeutic sealants for the arrest and prevention of dental caries. Children at primary schools in New York, New York, with at least 50% of the student population reporting as Black or Hispanic and at least 80% receiving free or reduced lunch were included. This population was selected as they are at the highest risk of caries in New York. Students were randomized to receive either SDF or sealant with ART; those aged 5 to 13 years were included in the analysis. Treatment was provided at every visit based on need, and the number of visits varied by child. Schools with preexisting oral health programs were excluded, as were children who did not speak English. Of 17 741 students assessed for eligibility, 7418 were randomized, and 4100 completed follow-up and were included in the final analysis.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-7">
                  <title>Interventions</title>
                  <p>Participants were randomized at the school level to receive either a 38% concentration SDF solution or glass ionomer sealants and ART. Each participant also received fluoride varnish.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-8">
                  <title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title>
                  <p>Primary study outcomes were the prevalence and incidence of dental caries.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-9">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>A total of 7418 children (mean [SD] age, 7.58 [1.90] years; 4006 [54.0%] female; 125 [1.7%] Asian, 1246 [16.8%] Black, 3648 [49.2%] Hispanic, 153 [2.1%] White, 114 [1.5%] multiple races or ethnicities, 90 [1.2%] other [unspecified], 2042 [27.5%] unreported) were enrolled and randomized to receive either SDF (n = 3739) or sealants with ART (n = 3679). After initial treatment, 4100 participants (55.0%) completed at least 1 follow-up observation. The overall baseline prevalence of dental caries was approximately 27.2% (95% CI, 25.7-28.6). The odds of decay prevalence decreased longitudinally (odds ratio [OR], 0.79; 95% CI, 0.75-0.83) and SDF was noninferior compared to sealants and ART (OR, 0.94; 95% CI, 0.80-1.11). The crude incidence of dental caries in children treated with SDF was 10.2 per 1000 tooth-years vs 9.8 per 1000 tooth-years in children treated with sealants and ART (rate ratio, 1.05; 95% CI, 0.97-1.12).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-10">
                  <title>Conclusions and Relevance</title>
                  <p>In this school-based pragmatic randomized clinical trial, application of SDF resulted in nearly identical caries incidence compared to dental sealants and ART and was noninferior in the longitudinal prevalence of caries. These findings suggest that SDF may provide an effective alternative for use in school caries prevention.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-poi230100-11">
                  <title>Trial Registration</title>
                  <p>ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT03442309" ext-link-type="uri">NCT03442309</ext-link></p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source id="sp1">Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="H1-1-POI230100">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Dental caries is the world’s most prevalent noncommunicable disease.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> The National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research<sup><xref rid="poi230100r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> estimates that more than 50% of US children between the ages of 6 and 8 years have experienced caries, with the rate in some racial and ethnic minority groups exceeding 70%. The United Nations considers oral diseases to be a major global burden that shares common risk factors with other noncommunicable diseases, and the World Health Organization Global Oral Health Action Plan<sup><xref rid="poi230100r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> names oral disease prevention as a primary strategic objective, recommending the use of cost-effective, community-based methods to prevent caries. In 2022, the World Health Organization added glass ionomer sealants and silver diamine fluoride (SDF) to its Model List of Essential Medicines.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Despite increases in Medicaid entitlements for dental benefits, there remain persistent access challenges to oral disease prevention throughout the US. More than 69 million individuals in the US live in dental care health professional shortage areas.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> The US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention<sup><xref rid="poi230100r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> recommends school sealant programs to increase access to care and improve health equity. Dental sealants—thin coatings applied to the pits and fissures of teeth to protect against bacteria—can prevent the onset of carious lesions and arrests them in the early stages.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="poi230100r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> However, the burgeoning costs of care limits their use in schools.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Alternatively, SDF is a colorless alkaline solution consisting of silver and fluoride with antimicrobial properties that remineralizes teeth. In clinical studies, SDF application prevents caries in the primary dentition compared to placebo<sup><xref rid="poi230100r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> and arrests existing caries.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> SDF can be applied in minutes<sup><xref rid="poi230100r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> and is a cost-effective strategy to reduce the burden of caries, particularly in under resourced areas.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> In 2017, the US Food and Drug Administration<sup><xref rid="poi230100r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> granted breakthrough therapy status to SDF.</p>
              <p>The Silver Diamine Fluoride Versus Therapeutic Sealants for the Arrest and Prevention of Dental Caries in Low-Income Minority Children (CariedAway) pragmatic<sup><xref rid="poi230100r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> randomized clinical trial<sup><xref rid="poi230100r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> investigated the use of SDF as an alternative therapy for community-based caries control and prevention. Primary clinical outcomes for CariedAway included the noninferiority of SDF compared to dental sealants and atraumatic restorative treatment (ART) in the 2-year arrest of existing dental caries<sup><xref rid="poi230100r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> and the 4-year prevalence of caries. We report on the cumulative incidence and prevalence of caries over 4 years.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-2-POI230100">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="H2-1-POI230100">
                <title>Design and Participants</title>
                <p>CariedAway was a longitudinal noninferiority pragmatic cluster-randomized clinical trial<sup><xref rid="poi230100r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> conducted from February 1, 2019, to June 1, 2023. The trial was approved by the New York University School of Medicine Institutional Review Board, is registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (<ext-link xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT03442309" ext-link-type="uri">NCT03442309</ext-link>), and is reported following the Enhancing the Quality and Transparency of Health Research (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.equator-network.org/" ext-link-type="uri">EQUATOR</ext-link>) reporting guideline. The trial protocol is <xref rid="note-POI230100-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>.</p>
                <p>Any school in the New York, New York, metropolitan area with a total student population consisting of at least 50% Black or Hispanic students and with at least 80% of students receiving free or reduced lunch was eligible for inclusion. This population was selected as they are at the highest risk of caries in New York City. For enrolled schools, any child with parental written informed consent and participant assent was enrolled. While any child meeting these criteria was enrolled, inclusion into analysis was restricted to those aged 5 to 13 years. Additional exclusion criteria were if the school had a preexisting oral health program or if the child did not speak English.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-2-POI230100">
                <title>Interventions and Procedures</title>
                <p>Our primary experimental condition consisted of a 38% SDF solution (2.24 F-ion mg/dose). The active control consisted of glass ionomer cement sealants and atraumatic restorations, a minimally invasive approach that consists of preventive and restorative components to halt the progression of caries.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="poi230100r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Each participant also received a 5% sodium fluoride application.</p>
                <p>For the experimental treatment, petroleum jelly was first applied to the lips and surrounding skin to prevent temporary staining that can result from direct contact of SDF with the soft tissue. Isolation was achieved by placing gauze and cotton rolls between the teeth to be treated and the tongue and cheek. One to 2 drops of SDF were dispensed into a mixing well and applied using a microapplicator to all posterior asymptomatic cavitated lesions as well as pits and fissures of premolars and molars. The material was agitated on the surface of all cavities using a scrubbing motion for a minimum of 30 seconds, followed by 60 seconds of air-drying time. One unit dose of fluoride varnish was then applied to all teeth to mask the taste of the SDF. The procedure was then repeated every 6 months per protocol with the exception of the disruption in study activities due to COVID-19.</p>
                <p>For the active control, cavity conditioner was first applied to pits and fissures for 10 seconds. Sealant capsules were mixed for 10 seconds at 4000 rpm and then applied directly via the finger-sweep technique to all pits and fissures of bicuspids and molars, ensuring that closed margins were achieved. Atraumatic restorations were also placed on asymptomatic cavitated lesions, and fluoride varnish was applied to all teeth. At successive observations, sealants were reapplied to any unsealed or partially sealed bicuspids and molars. All treatments in both groups were provided in a dedicated room in each school using mobile equipment. Treatments in both groups were continued as long as the child was enrolled in the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-3-POI230100">
                <title>Examiners</title>
                <p>Treatments in the experimental group were provided by either dental hygienists or registered nurses, and by dental hygienists in the active control. All dental hygienists and registered nurses received identical training prior to the start of the academic year. Training consisted of didactic and experiential activities including screening, treatment protocol standardization exercises, and mock patient interactions.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-4-POI230100">
                <title>Data Collection and Outcomes</title>
                <p>Primary outcomes were the prevalence and incidence of dental caries. Caries diagnosis was determined through a full visual-tactile oral examination following the International Caries Detection and Assessment System (ICDAS) adapted criteria for epidemiology and clinical research settings.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Each tooth surface was assessed as being either intact/sound, sealed, restored, decayed, or arrested. Screening criteria considered lesions scored as a 5 (distinct cavity with visible dentin) or 6 (extensive, more than half the surface, distinct cavity with visible dentin) on the ICDAS scale as decay. Any clinical presentation of a filling (eg, amalgam, composite, or stainless steel crown) on a tooth that previously was recorded as sound was analyzed as decay, as it indicated disease incidence occurring between observations.</p>
                <p>Demographic data, including sex, race, and ethnicity, were obtained prior to treatment for future analyses. Race and ethnicity data were collected via self-report to support future assessment of effects within sociodemographic groups. Categories were derived from the New York City Department of Education. Participants selecting “other” race or ethnicity included all those not included in specific categories.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-5-POI230100">
                <title>Randomization and Blinding</title>
                <p>Schools were block-randomized to either the experimental or active control arm using a random number generator performed by one of us (R. R. R.) and verified by another (T. B. G.). Due to the staining effect of SDF, patients would be able to derive their groups. Clinicians were not blinded as the procedures differed for each treatment; however, they were not able to discern who treated each participant at prior study observations.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-6-POI230100">
                <title>Impact of COVID-19</title>
                <p>Data in CariedAway were collected biannually. However, due to the impact of COVID-19, schools in New York City were closed to health care professionals from March 2020 through September 2021. The time elapsed between observations corresponding to this period was approximately 2 years.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-7-POI230100">
                <title>Power</title>
                <p>Sample size calculations for the longitudinal prevalence of caries were previously reported<sup><xref rid="poi230100r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> assuming a power of 0.80, error rate of 5%, a repeated measures correlation of 0.5, and a per-visit attrition rate of 20%. Estimates also assumed a minimally detectable effect size of 0.25 and an intraclass correlation coefficient of 0.10, yielding a sample size of 12 874. However the observed intraclass correlation coefficient, computed using intercept-only mixed effects models, ranged from 0.013 (prevalence) to 0.015 (incidence). Thus, the final participant enrollment was sufficient for power requirements.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-8-POI230100">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>At each observation, the proportion of participants in treatment groups with new caries or fillings was determined and bootstrapped confidence intervals for the difference were computed, accounting for any clustering effect of schools. We assessed longitudinal noninferiority using mixed-effects logistic regression models, where the outcome was the presence or absence of any new caries at each observation. Models included random intercepts for individual participants and school. Our noninferiority margin (0.10) was previously selected based on historical evidence and clinical judgement as to what would be an acceptable difference in efficacy for the prevention of dental caries.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="poi230100r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> We converted the margin to the odds ratio (OR) scale by taking the average of the success proportion in the active control arm and determining the equivalent margin (OR δ, 0.63).<sup><xref rid="poi230100r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> We tested noninferiority at any observation by including an interaction between treatment and time, followed by a model with no interaction to assess noninferiority marginally. Comparisons to the OR δ were made using a (1 − 2α) confidence interval for the effect of treatment.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p>
                <p>We calculated the incidence rate for the total number of individual teeth that developed caries (in tooth-years) and derived the rate ratio as the most efficient estimator due to the small degree of intracluster correlation in responses.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> We then modeled the per-person number of caries present at each observation using multilevel mixed-effects negative binomial regression. Prespecified subgroup analyses for the effect of treatment over time and by the presence or absence of caries at baseline were performed.</p>
                <p>We also conducted a series of supplementary analyses. To account for censored observations, we analyzed caries incidence using Cox proportional hazards regression with nonparametric maximum likelihood estimation.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> We then assessed whether treatment by either a dental hygienist or registered nurse affected caries prevalence in the experimental group. Finally, we restricted the primary analysis to only those participants who were enrolled and received their first examination and treatment in the 6 months prior to school shutdowns due to COVID-19 to ensure that all analyzed participants had the same elapsed time between observations. Statistical significance was determined at <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. Analysis was conducted in Stata version 18 (StataCorp) and R version 4.2.3 (R Foundation).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-3-POI230100">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>A total of 7418 participants were enrolled across 48 schools (mean [SD] age, 7.58 [1.90] years; 4006 [54.0%] female; 125 [1.7%] Asian, 1246 [16.8%] Black, 3648 [49.2%] Hispanic, 153 [2.1%] White, 114 [1.5%] multiple races or ethnicities, 90 [1.2%] other [unspecified], 2042 [27.5%] unreported) (<xref rid="poi230100f1" ref-type="fig">Figure</xref>; <xref rid="poi230100f1" ref-type="fig"/><xref rid="poi230100t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). After randomization, there were 3739 participants (50.4%) in the experimental group (SDF) and 3679 (49.6%) in the active control group (sealant and ART). There were 4100 participants (55.5%) who completed at least 1 follow-up observation: 2063 (50.32%) in the experimental group and 2037 (49.68%) in the active control. The mean (SD) study observation time was 3.7 (0.32) years. The overall prevalence of baseline untreated caries was 26.7%, or 27.2% (95% CI, 25.7-28.6) for the experimental group and 26.2% (95% CI, 24.8-27.6) for the active control group. Within the SDF arm, 764 of 3735 baseline participants (20.5%) and 1154 of 8509 individual participant encounters (13.5%) were treated by registered nurses.</p>
              <fig position="float" id="poi230100f1" fig-type="figure">
                <label>Figure. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>CONSORT Flow Diagram</title>
                  <p>The average time elapsed between observations across all participants was as follows. First follow-up, 507 days; second, 300 days; third, 195 days; fourth, 169 days; fifth, 171 days; sixth, 170 days; seventh: 159 days. Any study dropout was considered and logged as lost to follow-up. No other reasons were documented, as the child most likely left the school.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jamapediatr-e236770-g001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="poi230100t1">
                <label>Table 1. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Sample Demographic Characteristics Overall and by Treatment</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col width="26.04%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="24.65%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="24.65%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="24.66%" span="1"/>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th>
                      <th colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No. (%)</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Overall</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental<xref rid="poi230100t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active control<xref rid="poi230100t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrolled participants</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7418 (100.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3739 (50.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3679 (49.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Baseline decay</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1980 (26.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1016 (27.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">964 (26.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4006 (54.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1954 (52.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2052 (55.8)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3412 (46.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1785 (47.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1627 (44.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Race and ethnicity<xref rid="poi230100t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (1.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (2.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (1.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1246 (16.8)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">650 (17.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">596 (16.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3648 (49.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1766 (47.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1882 (51.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153 (2.1)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (2.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (1.8)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Multiple</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (1.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (1.8)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (1.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other<xref rid="poi230100t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (1.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (1.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (0.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unreported</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2042 (27.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1026 (27.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1016 (27.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age at baseline, mean (SD), y</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (1.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (1.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (1.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retained participants</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4100 (100.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2063 (50.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2037 (49.7)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Baseline decay</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1140 (27.8)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">584 (28.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">556 (27.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2228 (54.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1088 (52.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1140 (56.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1872 (45.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">975 (47.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">897 (44.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Race and ethnicity<xref rid="poi230100t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (1.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (2.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (0.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">794 (19.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">416 (20.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378 (18.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2329 (57.1)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1155 (56.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1174 (57.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (2.1)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (2.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (1.5)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Multiple</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (1.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (1.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (1.1)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other<xref rid="poi230100t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (1.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (2.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (1.4)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unreported</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">682 (16.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">296 (14.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (19.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age at baseline, mean (SD), y</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (1.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (1.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (1.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="poi230100t1n1">
                    <label>
                      <sup>a</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Experimental refers to treatment with silver diamine fluoride.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t1n2">
                    <label>
                      <sup>b</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Active control refers to dental sealant and atraumatic restorative treatment.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t1n3">
                    <label>
                      <sup>c</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Race and ethnicity data were collected via self-report using categories derived from the New York City Department of Education to support future assessment of effects within sociodemographic groups.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t1n4">
                    <label>
                      <sup>d</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Unspecified.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The prevalence of participants with no new caries or fillings at each observation (<xref rid="poi230100t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) was similar in both groups, with differences in prevalence ranging from −0.001 to 0.031 across study observations. Bootstrapped confidence intervals were below the noninferiority margin. For mixed-model analyses of caries prevalence over time (<xref rid="poi230100t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), the interaction effect between time and treatment was not significant, indicating that noninferiority should be assessed marginally. Across both groups, the odds of untreated decay significantly decreased by approximately 21% at each observational visit (OR, 0.79, 95% CI, 0.75-0.83). Comparing the active control to the experimental treatment after adjusting for confounders, the OR was 0.94 (95% CI, 0.80-1.11; 90% CI, 0.82-1.08). The confidence interval for the marginal effect was outside the estimated OR δ.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="poi230100t2">
                <label>Table 2. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Prevalence of Participants Without New Caries or New Fillings at Each Observation<xref rid="poi230100t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col width="12.52%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="14.42%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="19.35%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="19.36%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="34.35%" span="1"/>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Observation</th>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Duration, d<xref rid="poi230100t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
                      <th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Prevalence</th>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Difference (95% CI)</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Active control<xref rid="poi230100t2n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental<xref rid="poi230100t2n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2nd</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (−0.00 to 0.07)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3rd</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.00 (−0.04 to 0.04)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4th</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (−0.05 to 0.05)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (−0.03 to 0.06)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="poi230100t2n1">
                    <label>
                      <sup>a</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Any single instance of decay or new fillings not previously observed was considered treatment failure.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t2n2">
                    <label>
                      <sup>b</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Duration was days between observations.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t2n3">
                    <label>
                      <sup>c</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Active control refers to dental sealant and atraumatic restorative treatment.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t2n4">
                    <label>
                      <sup>d</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Experimental refers to treatment with silver diamine fluoride.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="poi230100t3">
                <label>Table 3. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Longitudinal Caries Prevalence and Effect of Sealants and Atraumatic Restorative Treatment Compared With Silver Diamine Fluoride for Untreated Decay on Any Dentition</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col width="35.41%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="27.11%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="27.11%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="10.37%" span="1"/>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds ratio (SE)</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observational period</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.02)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75-0.83</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active control vs experimental<xref rid="poi230100t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.08)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80-1.11</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.47</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline decay</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.75 (9.72)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.74-104.17</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous care</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.12)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56-1.02</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.07</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, males</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.09)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90-1.26</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.47</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race and ethnicity<xref rid="poi230100t3n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.24)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44-1.45</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.47</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.12)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84-1.31</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.61</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.19)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37-1.15</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.14</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Multiple</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.33)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42-1.81</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.71</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other<xref rid="poi230100t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 (0.64)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16-3.81</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unreported</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.12)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76-1.22</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.75</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="poi230100t3n1">
                    <label>
                      <sup>a</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Active control refers to dental sealant and atraumatic restorative treatment and experimental to treatment with silver diamine fluoride.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t3n2">
                    <label>
                      <sup>b</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Race and ethnicity data were collected via self-report using categories derived from the New York City Department of Education to support future assessment of effects within sociodemographic groups.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t3n3">
                    <label>
                      <sup>c</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Unspecified.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>For newly observed caries across the full study duration (<xref rid="poi230100t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), the crude incidence rate in the experimental group was 10.2 caries per 1000 tooth-years. The rate in the active control was 9.8 caries per 1000 tooth-years, for a rate ratio of 1.05 (95% CI, 0.97-1.12) and a preventive fraction of 0.023. From adjusted models for longitudinal caries incidence (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-POI230100-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>), the overall risk rate over time reduced (incidence rate ratio [IRR], 0.83; 95% CI, 0.81-0.85) with each observation. The risk comparing participants in the dental sealants with ART group to those in the SDF group was 0.92 (95% CI, 0.83-1.04). There were no significant interactions between treatment and time and treatment and baseline decay status.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="poi230100t4">
                <label>Table 4. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Incidence Rate of Dental Caries for Experimental and Active Control<xref rid="poi230100t4n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col width="16.68%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="16.66%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="16.67%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="16.66%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="16.66%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="16.67%" span="1"/>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental<xref rid="poi230100t4n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active control<xref rid="poi230100t4n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence rate difference (95% CI)</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence rate ratio (95% CI)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caries, No.</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1625</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1433</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3058</td>
                      <td rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">0.000 (−0.000 to 0.001)</td>
                      <td rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">1.046 (0.973 to 1.123)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth-years, No.</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 979</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 653</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">303 632</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence rate</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="poi230100t4n1">
                    <label>
                      <sup>a</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Each condition also received fluoride varnish.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t4n2">
                    <label>
                      <sup>b</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Experimental refers to treatment with silver diamine fluoride.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="poi230100t4n3">
                    <label>
                      <sup>c</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Active control refers to dental sealant and atraumatic restorative treatment.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>In supplementary analyses, the hazard ratio comparing the active control to experimental for time to first observed carious lesion was 0.91 (95% CI, −0.823 to 1.08). There were no significant differences in caries prevalence in children treated with SDF by registered nurses compared to dental hygienists (OR, 0.89; 95% CI, 0.67-1.19). For the restricted subsample, 4718 CariedAway participants were enrolled and treated in the 6 months prior to school closures due to COVID-19, 2998 of whom were viable for follow-up after pandemic restrictions were lifted (eFigure in <xref rid="note-POI230100-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). At the completion of the trial, follow-up data were obtained for 1831 participants (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-POI230100-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). Results for longitudinal analyses for caries prevalence (eTable 3 in <xref rid="note-POI230100-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>) and incidence (eTable 4 in <xref rid="note-POI230100-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>) were similar to that of full-sample analyses.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-4-POI230100">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>School sealant programs have demonstrated effectiveness in reducing the risk of dental caries,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> yet are underused due to the burdensome costs of care.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Many children subsequently continue to live with untreated disease, which can lead to systemic infection and negatively affect child development.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> In this randomized clinical trial of primary school-aged children, application of SDF with fluoride varnish was noninferior compared to dental sealants, fluoride varnish, and ART in the longitudinal prevalence of caries when used in a school program. We conclude that SDF is an effective alternative for community-based prevention that may help address these existing barriers.</p>
              <p>Although SDF is primarily used as a caries-arresting agent, it is also effective in the prevention of new caries.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="poi230100r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> There is a reduced risk of new caries on surrounding sound dentition when existing lesions are treated,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> and SDF is more effective than fluoride varnish in preventing new caries in early childhood.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> However, prior short-term comparative assessments of SDF have yielded conflicting results on its superiority relative to glass ionomer sealants and atraumatic restorations.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="poi230100r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> These previous trials were also restricted to either 12 or 24 months of observation, and little long-term evidence exists.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="poi230100r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Approximately 1 in 4 of children participating in CariedAway had untreated caries at baseline (1 in 3 for the COVID-19 sample), and 11% had preexisting sealants. Following treatment, the overall odds of dental caries decreased by approximately 20% in both study arms. The risk of incident dental caries was nearly identical in both treatment groups, resulting in a very small preventive fraction between the included interventions. Similarly, the data indicate no significant differences across treatment in the risk of first caries eruption or when modeling the total number of new dental caries experienced overall, nor is there sufficient evidence to indicate whether there are differences in treatment effect over time or based on the presence of disease at baseline. Dental sealants have an estimated 50% preventive fraction for caries compared to placebo, with research estimating the prevention of more than 3 million cavities attributable to sealants.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> The similarity in observed incidence from CariedAway may support a similar conclusion for the application of SDF.</p>
              <p>In addition to clinical effectiveness, the simplicity and financial implications of a school-based SDF program can result in considerable cost savings to the public. A review of existing SDF treatment protocols identified application times as low as 10 seconds per tooth,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> suggesting that more children can be treated in less time. Use of SDF as a caries management strategy also reduces Medicaid program expenditures,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> is the most cost-effective option in populations with a high risk of dental caries,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> and is more cost-efficient compared to ART,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> although potential restrictions from Medicaid reimbursement may persist.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup></p>
              <p>In 2022, the American Medical Association approved a category III <italic>Current Procedural Terminology </italic>code authorizing nondental health care professionals to administer SDF, and research indicates that treatment of early childhood caries using SDF by physicians in primary care settings is both feasible and acceptable.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> Similarly, the American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry published guidance on physician use of SDF for caries management,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> and surveys of pediatricians by the American Academy of Pediatricians reveal an interest in and recognized need for SDF.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> More than one-fourth of participants in the SDF arm of the CariedAway trial were treated by registered nurses, and our results for incident caries over 4 years corroborate other findings on the effectiveness of nurses in providing SDF.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> School-based caries prevention may have greater student participation when school nurses partner with hygienists in the delivery of care,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> and our results empower nurses as primary agents in caries prevention. With more than 132 000 school nurses estimated to be currently in the US<sup><xref rid="poi230100r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> and given their growing involvement in oral health promotion and prevention,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> these findings can expand the scope of practice for both school nurses and family practices.</p>
              <p>While the American Dental Association<sup><xref rid="poi230100r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> and the American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry<sup><xref rid="poi230100r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> include SDF in their clinical recommendations for caries management, known complications with SDF application include potential oral soft tissue irritation, temporary staining of the oral mucosa, and permanent staining of porous tooth structure.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Despite thousands of SDF applications in CariedAway, we encountered no adverse events and received only 1 complaint regarding staining, which pertained to superficial skin staining from accidental spillage that was mistaken for bruising. Separate findings from CariedAway did not indicate a negative impact of SDF therapy on oral health-related quality of life, which included measures for aesthetic perceptions of the oral cavity.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Other research concludes that a high proportion of parents of children treated with SDF remain satisfied with their child’s dental appearance,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="poi230100r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> that aesthetic concerns are mitigated with posterior application,<sup><xref rid="poi230100r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> and that no differences were found in adverse events or aesthetic perceptions when comparing children treated with SDF vs sealant and ART.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup></p>
              <sec id="H2-9-POI230100">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>As a pragmatic trial, there are concerns regarding subject attrition and any bias from external care. Our analysis used all available observations for study participants, considered a subset of participants that had equal rates of follow-up due to COVID-19, and identified any treated dentition by clinicians outside the CariedAway program. Additionally, the presented findings assessed caries prevalence inclusive of both children who did and did not begin the study with active untreated decay, which has, to our knowledge, not been reported previously, as those with untreated caries at baseline may have a higher risk of subsequent disease development. We also included multiple assessments of prevention, including any incidence of decay, overall prevalence, time to first eruption, and estimates at both the tooth and person levels. While attrition is a clear weakness, the pragmatic nature of the trial reflects the real-world experience of a school-based model that uses SDF for long-term caries management.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-5-POI230100">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>Untreated dental caries has maintained a 30-year position at the top of the global disease prevalence lists.<sup><xref rid="poi230100r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup> Results from the CariedAway randomized clinical trial demonstrate the longitudinal effectiveness of SDF when used in school-based caries prevention and can be used by clinicians, practices, and communities in the global pursuit of oral health equity.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="REF-POI230100">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="poi230100r1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Bernabe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcenes</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>GBD 2017 Oral Disorders Collaborators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national levels and trends in burden of oral conditions from 1990 to 2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease 2017 Study</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>362</fpage>-<lpage>373</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034520908533</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32122215?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32122215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</collab></person-group>. Dental caries (tooth decay) in children age 2 to 11. Accessed August 10, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nidcr.nih.gov/research/data-statistics/dental-caries/children" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nidcr.nih.gov/research/data-statistics/dental-caries/children</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. Draft global oral health action plan: 2023-2030. Accessed January 23, 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/draft-global-oral-health-action-plan-(2023-2030)" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/draft-global-oral-health-action-plan-(2023-2030)</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. WHO model lists of essential medicines. Accessed August 10, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/groups/expert-committee-on-selection-and-use-of-essential-medicines/essential-medicines-lists" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/groups/expert-committee-on-selection-and-use-of-essential-medicines/essential-medicines-lists</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Health Resources &amp; Services Administration</collab></person-group>. Health workforce shortage areas. Accessed January 23, 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://data.hrsa.gov/topics/health-workforce/shortage-areas" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.hrsa.gov/topics/health-workforce/shortage-areas</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naavaal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scherrer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>School-based dental sealant programs prevent cavities and are cost-effective</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2233</fpage>-<lpage>2240</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2016.0839</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27920311?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27920311</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Cabalén</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bono</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burrow</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nonrestorative caries treatment: a systematic review update</article-title>. <source>Int Dent J</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>746</fpage>-<lpage>764</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.identj.2022.06.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35879115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kashbour</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Worthington</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boyers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pit and fissure sealants versus fluoride varnishes for preventing dental decay in the permanent teeth of children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<elocation-id>CD003067</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD003067.pub5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33142363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33142363</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linabarger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lesaja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of school sealant programs on oral health among youth and identification of potential barriers to implementation</article-title>. <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>970</fpage>-<lpage>978.e4</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adaj.2022.05.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35953306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35953306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajendra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veitz-Keenan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of silver diamine fluoride in preventing caries in the primary dentition: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Caries Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000488686</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29874642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29874642</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Brignardello-Petersen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Silver diamine fluoride seems to be effective in preventing and arresting root caries in older adults compared with placebo, but there is very low certainty in the magnitude of the benefit</article-title>. <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>150</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e3</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adaj.2018.06.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30119828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30119828</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duangthip</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>ECM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of the protocol of SDF therapy for arresting caries</article-title>. <source>Int Dent J</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>588</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.identj.2022.06.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35843730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35843730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Gierth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coughlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gkekas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Essential medicines for dental caries: cost-effectiveness of ART and SDF</article-title>. <source>Eur J Public Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>suppl 3</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckac131.010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Silver fluoride as a treatment for dental caries</article-title>. <source>Adv Dent Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034517743750</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29355428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29355428</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norrie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pragmatic trials</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>375</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>463</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1510059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27518663?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27518663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Silver diamine fluoride versus therapeutic sealants for the arrest and prevention of dental caries in low-income minority children: study protocol for a cluster randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Trials</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>523</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13063-018-2891-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30257696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30257696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barry-Godín</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of silver diamine fluoride on caries arrest and prevention: the CariedAway school-based randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<elocation-id>e2255458</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.55458</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 36757696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36757696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Frencken</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Atraumatic restorative treatment and minimal intervention dentistry</article-title>. <source>Br Dent J</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>223</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>189</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2017.664</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28798450?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28798450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Saber</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Housseiny</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alamoudi</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Atraumatic restorative treatment and interim therapeutic restoration: a review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Dent J (Basel)</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/dj7010028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30866534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30866534</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Gugnani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandit</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>International caries detection and assessment system (ICDAS): a new concept</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Pediatr Dent</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10005-1089</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27672245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27672245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>US Food and Drug Administration</collab></person-group>. Non-inferiority clinical trials to establish effectiveness: guidance for industry. Accessed January 23, 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/media/78504/download" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.fda.gov/media/78504/download</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Randomized trial on fluorides and sealants for fissure caries prevention</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>753</fpage>-<lpage>758</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034512452278</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22736448?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22736448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tunes da Silva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for equivalence and noninferiority testing</article-title>. <source>Biol Blood Marrow Transplant</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>)(<supplement>suppl</supplement>):<fpage>120</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbmt.2008.10.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19147090?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19147090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Mascha</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sessler</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Equivalence and noninferiority testing in regression models and repeated-measures designs</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>678</fpage>-<lpage>687</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/ANE.0b013e318206f872</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21304155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21304155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parpia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cousens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for the analysis of incidence rates in cluster randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>839</fpage>-<lpage>846</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/31.4.839</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12177032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Maximum likelihood estimation for semiparametric transformation models with interval-censored data</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biomet/asw013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27279656?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27279656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palmisano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bukhari</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Longitudinal caries prevalence in a comprehensive, multicomponent, school-based prevention program</article-title>. <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>-<lpage>233.e11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adaj.2020.12.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33632412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33632412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Senthi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Susser</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsutsui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Oral health, academic performance, and school absenteeism in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>150</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>121.e4</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adaj.2018.09.023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30473200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30473200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevention of dental caries by silver diamine fluoride</article-title>. <source>Compend Contin Educ Dent</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>158</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 30829497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30829497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Llodra</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menardia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of silver diamine fluoride for caries reduction in primary teeth and first permanent molars of schoolchildren: 36-month clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>721</fpage>-<lpage>724</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/154405910508400807</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16040729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040729</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajendra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veitz-Keenan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of silver diamine fluoride in preventing caries in the primary dentition: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Caries Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000488686</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29874642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29874642</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tailor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of silver diamine fluoride and sodium fluoride varnish in preventing new carious lesion in preschoolers: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Pediatr Dent</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10005-2488</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 37020768?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37020768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Satyarup</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagarajappa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahapatra</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalai</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of the effectiveness of 38% silver diamine fluoride and atraumatic restorative treatment for treating dental caries in a school setting: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Dent Med Probl</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17219/dmp/143547</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35506381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35506381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Monse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heinrich-Weltzien</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Palenstein Helderman</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Caries preventive efficacy of silver diammine fluoride (SDF) and ART sealants in a school-based daily fluoride toothbrushing program in the Philippines</article-title>. <source>BMC Oral Health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6831-12-52</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23171244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23171244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooch</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espinoza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Vital signs: dental sealant use and untreated tooth decay among U.S. school-aged children</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>41</issue>):<fpage>1141</fpage>-<lpage>1145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6541e1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27764075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27764075</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Johhnson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serban</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tomar</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Projecting the economic impact of silver diamine fluoride on caries treatment expenditures and outcomes in young U.S. children</article-title>. <source>J Public Health Dent</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>221</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jphd.12312</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30741498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30741498</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Schwendicke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Göstemeyer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cost-effectiveness of root caries preventive treatments</article-title>. <source>J Dent</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2016.10.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27984089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27984089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Implementation of a primary care physician-led cavity clinic using silver diamine fluoride</article-title>. <source>J Public Health Dent</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jphd.12331</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31389017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31389017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry.</collab></person-group> Physician use of silver diamine fluoride (SDF) in dental caries management. Accessed December 17, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.aapd.org/globalassets/sdf-guidance-for-physicians_aapd_2023.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aapd.org/globalassets/sdf-guidance-for-physicians_aapd_2023.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>American Academy of Pediatrics</collab></person-group>. Pediatricians and pediatric oral health: knowledge and attitudes about silver diamine fluoride in pediatric practice. Accessed December 17, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://downloads.aap.org/DOPCSP/AAPSDFFullSurveyFinalReport.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://downloads.aap.org/DOPCSP/AAPSDFFullSurveyFinalReport.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godín</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effectiveness of medical nurses in treating children with silver diamine fluoride in a school-based caries prevention program</article-title>. <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>. Published online October 24, <year>2023</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cdoe.12925</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 37873685?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37873685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Mattheus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loos</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vogeler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The development and implementation of a school-based dental sealant program for Hawaii public schools</article-title>. <source>J Sch Health</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/josh.13401</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 37857279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37857279</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r43">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Willgerodt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Public school nursing practice in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Sch Nurs</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>232</fpage>-<lpage>244</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1059840517752456</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29343160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29343160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r44">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Buerlein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Promoting children’s oral health. a role for school nurses in prevention, education, and coordination</article-title>. <source>NASN Sch Nurse</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1942602X09353053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20440951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20440951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r45">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Slayton</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Urquhart</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>MWB</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence-based clinical practice guideline on nonrestorative treatments for carious lesions: a report from the American Dental Association</article-title>. <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>837</fpage>-<lpage>849.e19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adaj.2018.07.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30261951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30261951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r46">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marghalani</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ureles</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of silver diamine fluoride for dental caries management in children and adolescents, including those with special health care needs</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Dent</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 29070149?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29070149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r47">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barry Godín</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Silver diamine fluoride, atraumatic restorations, and oral health-related quality of life in children aged 5-13 years: results from the CariedAway school-based cluster randomized trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Oral Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-022-02159-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35413873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35413873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r48">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Huebner</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milgrom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cunha-Cruz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Parents’ satisfaction with silver diamine fluoride treatment of carious lesions in children</article-title>. <source>J Dent Child (Chic)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 32151304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32151304</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r49">
                <label>49</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Duangthip</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>MHT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>ECM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse effects of silver diamine fluoride treatment among preschool children</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034517746678</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29237131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29237131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r50">
                <label>50</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janal</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niederman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Parental perceptions and acceptance of silver diamine fluoride staining</article-title>. <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>510</fpage>-<lpage>518.e4</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adaj.2017.03.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28457477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28457477</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r51">
                <label>51</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Vollú</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rougemount Teixeira</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of 30% silver diamine fluoride compared to atraumatic restorative treatment on dentine caries arrestment in primary molars of preschool children: a 12-months parallel randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Dent</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<elocation-id>103165</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2019.07.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31279925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31279925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="poi230100r52">
                <label>52</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. Global oral health status report: towards universal health coverage for oral health by 2030. Accessed January 25, 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240061484" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240061484</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-POI230100-1">
              <supplementary-material id="note-POI230100-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Trial protocol</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamapediatr-e236770-s001.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>eTable 1. Longitudinal caries incidence and the effect of sealants with ART compared to silver diamine fluoride, full sample</p>
                  <p>eFigure. CONSORT diagram, COVID-19 sample</p>
                  <p>eTable 2. Sample demographics overall and by treatment, COVID-19 sample</p>
                  <p>eTable 3. Longitudinal caries prevalence and the effect of sealants with ART compared to silver diamine fluoride, COVID-19 sample</p>
                  <p>eTable 4. Longitudinal caries incidence and the effect of sealants with ART compared to silver diamine fluoride, COVID-19 sample</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamapediatr-e236770-s002.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 3.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Data sharing statement</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamapediatr-e236770-s003.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </notes>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
