<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:38:20Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10357712" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10357712</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-07-21</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcorhl</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10357712</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10357712</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10357712</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37468940</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37468940</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3205</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-023-03205-6</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Reflection on patients’ experience with orthodontic appliances wear and its impact on oral health related quality of life: observational comparative study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Abutaleb</surname>
                    <given-names>Maram A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>maram2020@std.mans.edu.eg</email>
                    <email>m.adulkaderabutaleb@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Latief</surname>
                    <given-names>Mohammad H Abd El</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>mohammadhasan@mans.edu.eg</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Montasser</surname>
                    <given-names>Mona A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>mmontasser11@yahoo.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10251.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000103426662</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthodontics, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Mansoura University, </institution></institution-wrap>Mansoura, 35516 Egypt </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <elocation-id>502</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>5</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par20">The objective of this study was to explore and compare patient’s experience with the use of a removable functional appliance or fixed orthodontic appliance and its influence on oral health-related quality of life.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Material and methods</title>
                  <p id="Par21">This clinical trial included 81 participants having Class II Division 1 and age ranging between 10 and 16 years. The participants were included in any of a three equal groups according to the set inclusion and exclusion criteria; Group 1: patients treated with a Twin-Block functional appliance; Group 2: patients treated with a fixed orthodontic appliance only; and Group 3 (control group): patients not in orthodontic treatment yet. The COHIP SF-19 was used. Patients were given the questionnaire as follows: Group 1: (1) after at least 8 months from starting treatment; (2) after completing phase 1 by 2–3 months without wearing the appliance; Group 2: (1) just before debonding; (2) after finishing the treatment by 2–3 months without any appliances; and Group 3: (1) at the patient’s first visit to the orthodontic clinic; (2) after 2–3 months from the first visit to the orthodontic clinic and before starting any treatment.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par22">The 81 participants were 31 males and 50 females with median age of 13 years. The total COHIP SF-19 scores at baseline were 57 (49–64), 67 (63–72), and 47 (42–53) for the Twin-Block, the fixed appliance, and the malocclusion groups, respectively. Two-month mean scores adjusted to the baseline scores were 64.82 ± 1.15, 65.65 ± 1.47, and 54.45 ± 1.44 for the Twin-Block, the fixed appliance, and the malocclusion groups, respectively.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p id="Par23">Both at baseline and two-months (adjusted to the baseline scores), participants in the malocclusion group showed compromised socio-emotional quality of life and reported the poorest total OHRQoL. At the baseline, better socio-emotional and total OHRQoL was reported by the fixed appliance group compared to the Twin-Block group but, after two months both groups gave similar sores. Therefore; patients’ perceptions about their experience with the orthodontic appliance might change.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Malocclusion</kwd>
                <kwd>Orthodontic appliances</kwd>
                <kwd>Oral health</kwd>
                <kwd>Quality of life</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>Mansoura University</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <open-access>
                  <p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p>
                </open-access>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par24">Malocclusion is a serious public health problem worldwide. Though malocclusion is neither a life-threatening condition nor a disease, its treatment is highly sought-after [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Malocclusion, including Class II Division 1, has a detrimental influence on self-confidence as well as social life, and it has unpleasant psychological implications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. On daily function, the effect of a person’s oral health, well-being, and overall quality of life is called oral health-related quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Thus, it has been proposed that malocclusion causes harm to OHRQoL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par25">Some research focuses on patients’ perceptions of the body image in the planning stages of orthodontic treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Klages et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] stated that malocclusions have psychological influences on youths and reduce their social interactions and self-confidence. Youths are very concerned about the appearance of their teeth corroborating the theory that dentofacial aesthetics are significant in social interactions as well as psychological well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par26">Patients are concerned with orthodontic therapy for improving their appearance, psychological well-being, quality of life, and dental function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The fixed orthodontic appliance is the standard appliance for the treatment of malocclusion. According to Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] in the first month, fixed appliances diminish the quality of life, but function and discomfort levels improve as therapy proceeds. The fixed orthodontic appliance components, such as brackets, may cause pain, an unpleasant appearance, discomfort, and functional restrictions during therapy, which reduce patients’ oral health-related quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. However, it is significant to remember the patient’s own perceived expectations of the treatment outcomes in regard to the presenting problem. Patients with their teeth aligned to a high degree who use fixed appliances and who used to be embarrassed by their teeth because of their malocclusion will have a favourable perception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par27">Patients getting removable and fixed orthodontic appliances experienced different levels of pain and discomfort, and eating disturbances; previous research found an inconsistency in the influence of fixed and removable orthodontic treatment techniques on oral health-related quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par28">The Twin-Block functional appliance is highly recommended for the first phase treatment of Class II malocclusion in growing patients because of their high acceptance and compliance with the appliance’s wear. The appliance’s two-piece design allows for greater speech and mastication flexibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In the United Kingdom and the United States, O’Brien et al. state that the Twin-Block appliance is the most used functional appliance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. On the other hand, some studies examine the effects of Twin-Block on OHRQoL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Moreover, it is not certain if an individual who uses functional appliances has better oral health results than the one who uses fixed appliances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The comparison between the oral health consequences of functional and fixed orthodontic treatment is a challenge, and additional research is needed before clinical practitioners can choose the kind of orthodontic appliance therapy.</p>
              <p id="Par29">Broder et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] developed the Child Oral Health Impact Profile (COHIP) for measuring OHRQoL in children; there are versions of the COHIP for both children and their carers. The COHIP evaluates the child’s dental health, social and emotional well-being, functional well-being, school environment, self-esteem, and overall OHRQoL. The COHIP was initially designed to assess “oral–facial well-being” in children with age range from 8 to 15 years. The COHIP incorporation of positive aspects of OHRQoL such as confidence and attractiveness is an essential aspect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Later on, Broder et al. [ 22] designed COHIP-SF 19, a short form with 19 questions and three subscales (socio-emotional well-being, functional well-being, and oral health) that retains the original version’s psychometric qualities. The validity and reliability of the COHIP-SF 19 was tested on groups of children including a group of orthodontic patients with age range from 9 to 17 years.</p>
              <p id="Par30">Some short forms are ideal for large surveys since they are easier to use and understand, quicker to complete, and so cost less. Arheiam et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] translated COHIP-SF 19 into Arabic, where his study was conducted for cross-culturally adapting the original English language COHIP-SF 19 to Arabic culture and testing its psychometric properties in a population-based sample of 12-year-old children in schools. The current study examined the experiences of the patients with fixed and removable orthodontic appliances in everyday activities, oral symptoms, and food intake.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Ethical considerations</title>
                <p id="Par31">The Research Ethics Committee of Faculty of Dentistry – Mansoura University provided ethical permission before starting the study (Code: A14030821). The patients’ parents or guardians were thoroughly told about the survey and signed informed consent. The patients’ acceptance to participate in the survey was also obtained.</p>
                <p id="Par32">The following information was gathered for each participant: an allocation number, name, gender, age, telephone number, address, and a unique code. All patients’ information was kept confidential. The data was kept in a secure location, with no one else having access to it except the principal investigator.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Sample size</title>
                <p id="Par33">It was calculated using Power Analysis and Sample Size Software (PASS, version 15, 2017). NCSS, LLC, Kaysville, Utah, USA, ncss.com/software/pass.</p>
                <p id="Par34">The biostatistician hypothesized an effect size (f = 0.4) between the three research groups based on a review of the literature (no appliance group, fixed appliance group, and clinical appliance group) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. A sample size of 27 participants was gathered for each of the three groups whose means would be compared in one-way ANOVA research. Using the F test with a 0.05 significance level, the total sample of 81 patients obtains 89.5% power to detect differences between means over the option of equal means. The effect size (Cohan<sup>,</sup> s f = m /, which is 0.4), represents the magnitude of the variance in the means.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Study participants, eligibility criteria, and settings</title>
                <p id="Par35">The sample was recruited with specific inclusion and exclusion criteria. Inclusion criteria: Class II, Division 1 malocclusion, and age ranging between 10 and 16 years; exclusion criteria: patients suffering from craniofacial disorders and patients who did not approve of taking part.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p id="Par36">A random sample was recruited from the postgraduate orthodontic clinic of the Faculty of Dentistry, Mansoura University.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Study groups</title>
                <p id="Par37">The study consisted of three groups:</p>
                <p id="Par38"><bold>Group 1 (n = 27)</bold> included patients who used the Twin-Block functional appliances for treatment (Phase 1).</p>
                <p id="Par39"><bold>Group 2 (n = 27)</bold> included patients who were treated with fixed orthodontic appliances only.</p>
                <p id="Par40"><bold>Group 3 (n = 27)</bold> included patients who were not in orthodontic treatment yet. This group was the control group.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>The questionnaire</title>
                <p id="Par41">The main portion of the questionnaire (COHIP-SF 19) comprises 19 items separated into three conceptual subscales: socio-emotional well-being (10 items), functional well-being (4 items), and oral health (5 items). These items are divided into positive and negative answers. Two of the 19 questions utilized positive wording while, 17 of the 19 questions utilized negative wording; after the scoring of the 17 negatively worded items was reversed, the total score ranged from 0 to 76, with the higher score indicating better quality of life. A five-point Likert scale (never = 0, virtually never = 1, occasionally = 2, fairly frequently = 3, and almost always = 4) is used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Application of the COHIP-SF 19</title>
                <p id="Par42">Participants were given the questionnaire (COHIP-SF-AR) once informed consent was obtained. Though asked by a co-investigator to illustrate any difficult or confusing questions or material that they wanted to understand, all adolescents stated that all of the questions and content were clear. As a result, no further adjustments to the questionnaire’s text were required.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>The questionnaire was administered to the patients at two time points (baseline and after two-month)</title>
                <p id="Par43"><bold>Group 1</bold> (1) Baseline: after at least 8 months from starting treatment; (2) Two-months: after completing phase 1 for 2–3 months without wearing the appliance.</p>
                <p id="Par44"><bold>Group 2</bold> (1) Baseline: just before debonding; (2) Two-months: after finishing the treatment by 2–3 months without any appliance.</p>
                <p id="Par45"><bold>Group 3</bold> (1) Baseline: at the first visit of the patient to the clinic; (2) Two-months: after 2–3 months from the first questionnaire before starting treatment.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Study interventions</title>
                <p id="Par46">The participants were seated on the dental chair with their parents present. The investigator conducted the participants’ COHIP19-SF-AR questionnaires and asked only the participants to answer.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par47">The data was put into an Excel spreadsheet (v. 2010, Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, USA). IBM-SPSS software (IBM Corp., 2019) was used to enter and evaluate data. IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 26.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY) N (%) was employed to represent qualitative data. The Chi-square test was employed to determine the relation between two nominal variables. The quantitative data was first checked for normality using the Shapiro-Wilk test, with the data considered normally distributed if p &gt; 0.050. If the data was distributed normally, it was reported as the mean SD (or SE), otherwise as the median (Q1-Q3). For comparing non-normally distributed quantitative data between the three groups, the Kruskal-Wallis H-test was utilised. After adjusting for pre-intervention scores as variables, one-way analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) and its nonparametric counterpart (Quade’s rank ANCOVA) were used to compare post-intervention scores between groups. For analyzing the relationship between a dichotomous variable and a quantitative variable, point biserial correlation was utilized. To determine the direction and intensity of the link between two quantitative variables, Spearman’s correlation was utilized. Cronbach’s alpha was used for measuring internal consistency. If the p value was less than 0.050 for any of the tests conducted, the results were regarded to be statistically important. When necessary, appropriate charts were improved for graphically displaying the findings.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec13" sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec14">
                <title>Reliability tests for COHIP-SF 19 scores</title>
                <p id="Par48">Reliability tests for the COHIP-SF 19 scores using Cronbach’s alpha for internal consistency of COHIP-19 SF score, showed values mostly ≥ 0.7 for the socio-emotional and total score at Baseline and Two-months, while the values of oral health and functional well-being were &lt; 0.7. Although Cronbach’s alpha values for oral health and functional well-being improved slightly after two months, the values were still below 0.7.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec15">
                <title>Age and sex distribution in 3 groups</title>
                <p id="Par49">No statistically significant variation existed in sex distribution across the three groups (p = 0.370). There were 50 females (14, 19, and 17 in groups 1, 2, and 3, respectively). The difference in age between these groups; however, was statistically significant (Kruskal-Wallis H-test, H [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] = 33.764, P = 0.001). Age was statistically significantly greater in group 2 vs. groups 1 and 3 (adjusted P = 0.001), but not between groups 1 and 3 (adjusted P = 1.000). For the whole cohort, the median age was 13 years, ranging from 10 to 16 years (12, 16, and 12 for groups 1, 2, and 3, respectively).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec16">
                <title>Baseline COHIP-SF 19 scores in three groups</title>
                <p id="Par50">Baseline COHIP-SF 19 scores in the three groups showed no statistically significant differences in the groups’ oral health and functional well-being scores; however, the socio- emotional well-being score and overall COHIP-SF 19 score were statistically higher in the fixed appliance group followed by the Twin-Block group and finally the malocclusion group, Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p>
                <p id="Par51">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Baseline COHIP-SF 19 scores in the three groups</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Characteristic</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="3">Group</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Test of significance</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">Group 1</th>
                          <th align="left">Group 2</th>
                          <th align="left">Group 3</th>
                          <th align="left">H [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]</th>
                          <th align="left">p-value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Oral health score</td>
                          <td align="left">16 (14–18)</td>
                          <td align="left">16 (13–18)</td>
                          <td align="left">15 (14–17)</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">1.205</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.547</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Functional well-being score</td>
                          <td align="left">14 (12–14)</td>
                          <td align="left">14 (12–15)</td>
                          <td align="left">14 (13–16)</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">4.122</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.127</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>Socio-emotional well-being score</p>
                            <p>Pairwise comparisons</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>28 (23–34)</p>
                            <p>A</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>40 (38–40)</p>
                            <p>B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">19 (15–23) C</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">53.302</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">
                            <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>Total COHIP-SF 19 score</p>
                            <p>Pairwise comparisons</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>57 (49–64)</p>
                            <p>A</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>67 (63–72)</p>
                            <p>B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>47 (42–53)</p>
                            <p>C</p>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">43.988</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">
                            <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p>Notes: Data is median (Q1-Q3), test of significance is Kruskal-Wallis H-test. Pairwise comparisons are presented as letters (similar letters = insignificant difference, different letters = significant difference).</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec17">
                <title>Two-months COHIP-SF 19 scores in the three groups</title>
                <p id="Par53">Two-months COHIP SF-19 scores in the three groups showed that overall, scores of each of the four subscales were significantly lower in the malocclusion group than the Twin-Block and fixed appliance groups (except for oral health scores and functional well-being scores, where there was no significant difference between the fixed appliance and malocclusion groups, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p>
                <p id="Par54">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab2">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Two-months COHIP-SF 19 scores in the three groups</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Characteristic</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="3">Group</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Test of significance</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">Group 1</th>
                          <th align="left">Group 2</th>
                          <th align="left">Group 3</th>
                          <th align="left">H [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]</th>
                          <th align="left">p-value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Oral health score</td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>18 (16–20)</p>
                            <p>A</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>16 (14–18)</p>
                            <p>A, B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>16 (14–17)</p>
                            <p>B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">6.399</td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>0.041</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Functional well-being score</td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>16 (14–16)</p>
                            <p>A</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>16 (14–16)</p>
                            <p>A, B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>14 (14–16)</p>
                            <p>B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">6.421</td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>0.040</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>Socio-emotional well-being score</p>
                            <p>(Pairwise comparisons)</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>34 (28–38)</p>
                            <p>A</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>40 (40–40)</p>
                            <p>B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>20 (17–24)</p>
                            <p>C</p>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">56.914</td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>Total COHIP-SF 19 score</p>
                            <p>(Pairwise comparisons)</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>66 (57–72)</p>
                            <p>A</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>72 (68–73)</p>
                            <p>A</p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <p>49 (46–55)</p>
                            <p>B</p>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">45.621</td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p>Notes: Data is median (Q1-Q3), test of significance is Kruskal-Wallis H-test. Pairwise comparisons are presented as letters (similar letters = insignificant difference, different letters = significant difference)</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec18">
                <title>Correlations between baseline COHIP SF-19 scores, age, and sex</title>
                <p id="Par55">Correlation results showed a statistically significant positive correlation between oral health scores and sex as female gave higher scores than males at baseline, Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>a. Also, there was a statistically significant positive correlation between total oral health scores and age in the malocclusion group after two months from the first questionnaire, Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">3</xref>b.</p>
                <p id="Par56">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab3">
                    <label>Table 3a</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Correlations between baseline COHIP SF-19 scores, age, and sex</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Characteristic</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">OHS</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">FWS</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">SEWS</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Total scores</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">r</th>
                          <th align="left">p</th>
                          <th align="left">r</th>
                          <th align="left">p</th>
                          <th align="left">r</th>
                          <th align="left">p</th>
                          <th align="left">R</th>
                          <th align="left">P</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9">
                            <bold>Group 1 (Twin-Block, n = 27)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Age (years)</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.116</td>
                          <td align="left">0.563</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.023</td>
                          <td align="left">0.910</td>
                          <td align="left">0.072</td>
                          <td align="left">0.721</td>
                          <td align="left">0.042</td>
                          <td align="left">0.835</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Sex</td>
                          <td align="left">0.165</td>
                          <td align="left">0.411</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.278</td>
                          <td align="left">0.161</td>
                          <td align="left">0.178</td>
                          <td align="left">0.375</td>
                          <td align="left">0.130</td>
                          <td align="left">0.520</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9">
                            <bold>Group 2 (Fixed appliance, n = 27)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Age (years)</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.116</td>
                          <td align="left">0.563</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.023</td>
                          <td align="left">0.910</td>
                          <td align="left">0.072</td>
                          <td align="left">0.721</td>
                          <td align="left">0.042</td>
                          <td align="left">0.835</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Sex</td>
                          <td align="left">0.419</td>
                          <td align="left">0.030</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.043</td>
                          <td align="left">0.832</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.209</td>
                          <td align="left">0.295</td>
                          <td align="left">0.028</td>
                          <td align="left">0.889</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9">
                            <bold>Group 3 (Control group, n = 27)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Age (years)</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.288</td>
                          <td align="left">0.146</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.093</td>
                          <td align="left">0.643</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.126</td>
                          <td align="left">0.536</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.205</td>
                          <td align="left">0.306</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Sex</td>
                          <td align="left">0.050</td>
                          <td align="left">0.804</td>
                          <td align="left">0.172</td>
                          <td align="left">0.392</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.252</td>
                          <td align="left">0.204</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.163</td>
                          <td align="left">0.416</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p id="Par57">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab4">
                    <label>Table 3b</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Correlations between post-intervention COHIP SF-19 scores, age, and sex</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Characteristic</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">OHS</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">FWS</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">SEWS</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Total scores</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">r</th>
                          <th align="left">P</th>
                          <th align="left">r</th>
                          <th align="left">P</th>
                          <th align="left">r</th>
                          <th align="left">P</th>
                          <th align="left">R</th>
                          <th align="left">P</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9">
                            <bold>Group 1 (Twin-Block, n = 27)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Age (years)</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.076</td>
                          <td align="left">0.706</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.092</td>
                          <td align="left">0.648</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.155</td>
                          <td align="left">0.439</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.147</td>
                          <td align="left">0.466</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Sex</td>
                          <td align="left">0.185</td>
                          <td align="left">0.357</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.285</td>
                          <td align="left">0.150</td>
                          <td align="left">0.108</td>
                          <td align="left">0.593</td>
                          <td align="left">0.108</td>
                          <td align="left">0.593</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9">
                            <bold>Group 2 (Fixed appliance, n = 27)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Age (years)</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.076</td>
                          <td align="left">0.706</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.092</td>
                          <td align="left">0.648</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.155</td>
                          <td align="left">0.439</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.146</td>
                          <td align="left">0.466</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Sex</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.058</td>
                          <td align="left">0.772</td>
                          <td align="left">0.099</td>
                          <td align="left">0.624</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.211</td>
                          <td align="left">0.292</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.088</td>
                          <td align="left">0.662</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9">
                            <bold>Group 3 (Control group, n = 27)</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Age (years)</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.401</td>
                          <td align="left">0.038</td>
                          <td align="left">0.105</td>
                          <td align="left">0.601</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.186</td>
                          <td align="left">0.353</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.273</td>
                          <td align="left">0.169</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Sex</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.077</td>
                          <td align="left">0.701</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.183</td>
                          <td align="left">0.362</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.119</td>
                          <td align="left">0.553</td>
                          <td align="left">-0.178</td>
                          <td align="left">0.375</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p>Notes: r = correlation coefficient (Point biserial for sex, and Spearman’s for others). OHS = oral health score. FWS = functional well-being score. SEWS = socio-emotional well-being score. Total = Total COHIP SF-19 scores</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec19">
                <title>Comparisons between two-months scores of the three groups adjusted to the baseline scores</title>
                <p id="Par58">Higher oral health scores were seen in the Twin-Block group than in the fixed appliance group followed by the malocclusion group; nonetheless, this difference, statistically, was not important (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">4</xref>). It also showed a higher functional well-being score in the Twin-Block group than in both the fixed appliance and malocclusion groups. This difference in Two-months functional well-being scores after controlling (adjusting) for Baseline scores was statistically significant. Pairwise comparisons revealed that the difference was statistically significant for Twin-Block and malocclusion groups (p-value = 0.005 [Quade’s rank ANCOVA], and 0.013 [one-way ANCOVA]). Results also showed higher socio-emotional well-being scores in the fixed appliance group than in both the Twin-Block and malocclusion groups. The difference was significant statistically between the fixed appliance group and the malocclusion group (p-value = 0.015 [Quade’s rank ANCOVA], and &lt; 0.001 [one-way ANCOVA]). Finally, results also showed the highest total COHIP SF-19 scores in the fixed appliance group, followed by the Twin-Block group and then the malocclusion group. Pairwise comparisons revealed that the difference was statistically significant between both the Twin-Block and the fixed appliance groups and the malocclusion group (p-value = 0.001 [Quade’s rank ANCOVA], and &lt; 0.001 [One-way ANCOVA]) and (p-value = 0.025 [Quade’s rank ANCOVA], and &lt; 0.001 [One-way ANCOVA]) respectively, Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p>
                <p id="Par59">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab5">
                    <label>Table 4</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Two-months scores adjusted to the baseline scores in the three groups</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <bold>Group</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4">
                            <bold>Means and variability</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">
                            <bold>One-way ANCOVA</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">
                            <bold>Quade’s rank ANCOVA</bold>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">
                            <bold>Unadjusted</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">
                            <bold>Adjusted</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">
                            <bold>F</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">
                            <bold>P-value</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">
                            <bold>F</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">
                            <bold>p-value</bold>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>Mean</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>SD</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>Mean</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>SE</bold>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5">
                            <bold>Oral Health</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 1</td>
                          <td align="left">17.37</td>
                          <td align="left">2.79</td>
                          <td align="left">17.33</td>
                          <td align="left">0.458</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">2.921</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">0.060</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">3.044</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">0.053</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 2</td>
                          <td align="left">16.19</td>
                          <td align="left">2.15</td>
                          <td align="left">16.15</td>
                          <td align="left">0.458</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 3</td>
                          <td align="left">15.78</td>
                          <td align="left">2.24</td>
                          <td align="left">15.85</td>
                          <td align="left">0.459</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5">
                            <bold>Functional well-being</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 1</td>
                          <td align="left">15.26</td>
                          <td align="left">1.23</td>
                          <td align="left">15.37</td>
                          <td align="left">0.269</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">4.462</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <bold>0.015</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">5.366</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <bold>0.007</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 2</td>
                          <td align="left">14.96</td>
                          <td align="left">1.43</td>
                          <td align="left">14.96</td>
                          <td align="left">0.265</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 3</td>
                          <td align="left">14.33</td>
                          <td align="left">1.57</td>
                          <td align="left">14.23</td>
                          <td align="left">0.296</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5">
                            <bold>Socio-emotional well-being</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 1</td>
                          <td align="left">31.96</td>
                          <td align="left">7.38</td>
                          <td align="left">32.04</td>
                          <td align="left">0.928</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">13.383</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">4.336</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <bold>0.016</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 2</td>
                          <td align="left">39.11</td>
                          <td align="left">2.01</td>
                          <td align="left">34.73</td>
                          <td align="left">1.314</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 3</td>
                          <td align="left">19.96</td>
                          <td align="left">5.48</td>
                          <td align="left">24.26</td>
                          <td align="left">1.303</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5">
                            <bold>Total OHRQoL</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                          <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 1</td>
                          <td align="left">64.59</td>
                          <td align="left">8.91</td>
                          <td align="left">64.82</td>
                          <td align="left">1.149</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">17.018</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">7.729</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <bold>0.001</bold>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 2</td>
                          <td align="left">70.26</td>
                          <td align="left">4.61</td>
                          <td align="left">65.65</td>
                          <td align="left">1.471</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Group 3</td>
                          <td align="left">50.07</td>
                          <td align="left">6.26</td>
                          <td align="left">54.45</td>
                          <td align="left">1.443</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p>Notes: ANCOVA = analysis of covariance. SD = standard deviation. SE = standard error</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec20">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par60">In the current study, the children took the same questionnaire a second time after 2–3 months to examine the effect of time on their perceptions. The time interval was selected to be 2–3 months since this was a period regarded as not long enough for the participant’s OHRQoL to alter considerably but long enough for the participants to forget their earlier replies.</p>
              <p id="Par61">The COHIP-SF 19 form that was used in this study was validated and proven to be reliable in both its original English version [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] as well as in its Arabic version [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Thus, COHIP-SF 19 is a psychometrically sound tool for measuring oral health-related quality of life in preadolescents and adolescents. In the current study, when the internal consistency of the COHIP-19 SF scores was assessed, using Cronbach’s alpha, it was observed that the socio-emotional and total scores were satisfactory; however, the functional well-being subscales and oral health displayed unsatisfactory results. Results were similar at baseline and after two months. This is in agreement with other published data found on both the Arabic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and Japanese versions of COHIP-SF 19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. A low alpha value might be due to the small number of question [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par62">The findings of the current study presented no statistically significant differences in sex distribution among the three groups. This was advantageous because the results about the effect of sex on the subjects’ perceptions were mixed in previous studies. Thiruvenkadam et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] evaluated the oral health-associated quality of life of children who sought orthodontic treatment, and found no statistically significant difference in COHIP SF scores between girls and boys and The results of the current study agrees as the only positive correlation was observed between oral health scores and sex in the fixed appliance group at base line where the scores were higher in females than in males. In contrast, the COHIP-SF-19 levels were lower in girls than in boys in the New Caledonia COHIP-SF-19 validation study while, the Japanese COHIP-SF-19 validation research indicated greater results for girls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Previous research that used the Chinese COHIP-SF 19 noticed no gender differences in total or socio-emotional well-being subscores; however, females had higher functional well-being and oral health subscores than males [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par63">General health-related quality of life (HRQoL) has often been reported to be higher in children than adolescents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. However; in the Japanese children, the increased functional well-being subscores in the older group while the social-emotional well-being subscores were lower in the older age group. It is worth mentioning that COHIP-SF 19 was suggested to be used for comparing OHRQoL in orthodontic patients, with age range from 9 to 17 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The results of the current study showed almost no significant correlation between age and OHRQoL subscales within each of the three groups which is most probably related to the homogenously selected groups.</p>
              <p id="Par64">Just after finishing the treatment (baseline assessment), the results of the present study indicated an important difference between the three groups, with the malocclusion group expressing the worst experience, followed by the Twin-Block group and then the fixed appliance group. At Two-months, compared to the fixed appliance group and the Twin-Block group, the malocclusion group had the worst quality of life, but the fixed appliance and the Twin-Block groups had similar quality of life although the scores were slightly higher in the fixed appliance group. Previous studies documented the psychological effect of malocclusion on patients’ quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Similarly, in an assessment for OHRQoL of orthodontic patients using fixed and Twin-Block appliances done by Alzoubi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] patients reported that their quality of life was improved; after treatment, there were no statistically noticeable differences between both groups, which suggests that the perceived impact of removable functional appliances on OHRQoL may be overestimated by clinicians. Treating the malocclusion enhances the quality of life regardless of the appliance. The findings of the current study showed that after two months, patients’ reflections on their treatment experience were not different between the fixed and removable appliances. As time passes, patients’ perceptions change.</p>
              <p id="Par65">Just after finishing the treatment (the baseline assessment), patients in all groups had similar functional well-being, a situation that changed after two months, with the best functional well-being in the Twin-Block group followed by the fixed appliance group and then the malocclusion group. Looking at the socio-emotional well-being differences, they were obvious. The malocclusion group had the lowest scores both at the baseline and after two months in comparison to the other two groups. Just after finishing the treatment, patients in the fixed appliance group showed significantly higher scores than the Twin-Block group, which could be attributed to the nature of the appliance; removable vs. fixed appliance. Patients in the fixed appliance group might have been happier to realize that they are in the last stage of treatment and about to remove the appliance finally. After two months without the appliance, both the fixed appliance and functional appliance groups had similar socio-emotional well-being.</p>
              <p id="Par66">In the present study, the findings of the malocclusion group were consistent with those of previous studies that showed that a great number of patients who required orthodontic treatments felt ashamed and inferior; the more the need for treatment, the greater the person’s humiliation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. De Oliveira and Sheiham [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]conducted a study on Brazilian adolescents and revealed that adolescents who had malocclusion and were treated, had a better oral OHRQoL than those who were still under treatment or who never had treatment. Furthermore, Helm et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] stated that orthodontic patients (not only as children but also as adults) feel shame and suffer from self-consciousness. Another study revealed that young people with greater treatment requirements were more socially isolated than those with lower treatment needs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Also, previous studies found that orthodontic patients are more concerned with aesthetic and social issues than with interference with daily tasks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. However, some studies have shown no relationship between malocclusion and self-consciousness or shame [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par67">One of the limitations of the study is the inability to adhere to one gender or design different sex groups that would have been more insightful; however, the results showed no statistical difference in sex distribution among the groups. The same applies to age; it would have been better to have groups with no statistical age range differences; however, COHIP-SF 19 is suitable for a wide age range, as elaborated upon in the discussion section.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec21" sec-type="conclusion">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="Par68">Both at baseline and Two-months (adjusted to the baseline scores), participants in the malocclusion group showed compromised socio-emotional quality of life and reported the poorest total OHRQoL. At the baseline, better socio-emotional and total OHRQoL was reported by the fixed appliance group compared to the Twin-Block group but, after two months both groups gave similar sores. Therefore; patients’ perceptions about their experience with the orthodontic appliance might change. Just after finishing the treatment, patients in all groups had similar functional well-being, while after two months; the best functional well-being was in the Twin-Block group followed by the fixed appliance group, and then the malocclusion group.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>COHIP SF-19</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par70">Child Oral Health Impact Profile Short Form − 19</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>COHIP-SF-AR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par73">Child Oral Health Impact Profile -Short Form-Arabic</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>COHIP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par72">Child Oral Health Impact Profile</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>OHRQoL</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par71">Oral Health Related Quality of Life</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Not applicable.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>MAM choose the research point and developed the research design in cooperation with MAA and MHA. MAA conducted the questionnaire with supervision from MHA. MAA extracted and organized the data with help from MHA. MAA prepared the first version of the manuscript. MAM contributed to the interpretation of the data and revised the manuscript critically for important intellectual content and made the final version. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript and ensured the integrity of the research.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data Availability</title>
              <p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar201">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par301">The study was executed in accordance with Declaration of Helsinki and approval from the research ethics committee of Faculty of Dentistry – Mansoura University was obtained (Code: A14030821) before starting the study. Patients’ parents or guardians signed a written consent to participate in the study.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar202">
                <title>Consent for publication</title>
                <p id="Par302">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par69">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petersen</surname>
                      <given-names>PE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global policy for improvement of oral health in the 21st century–implications to oral health research of World Health Assembly 2007, World Health Organization</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0528.2008.00448.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19046331?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19046331</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feng</surname>
                      <given-names>Z-C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Z-M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cai</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>D-W</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of malocclusion on oral health-related quality of life in young adults</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>85</volume>
                  <fpage>986</fpage>
                  <lpage>91</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2319/101714-743.1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25531421?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531421</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sakaryali</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bani</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cinar</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alacam</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the impact of early childhood caries, traumatic dental injury, and malocclusion on oral health-related quality of life for turkish preschool children and families</article-title>
                  <source>Niger J Clin Pract</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>817</fpage>
                  <lpage>23</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/njcp.njcp_581_18</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31187768?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31187768</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yan</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jian</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of pain perception, anxiety, and impacts on oral health-related quality of life between patients receiving clear aligners and fixed appliances during the initial stage of orthodontic treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjaa037</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32613250?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32613250</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petti</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Over two hundred million injuries to anterior teeth attributable to large overjet: a meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Traumatol</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/edt.12126</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25263806?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25263806</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McGrath</surname>
                      <given-names>CPJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between the severity of Malocclusion, assessed by Occlusal Indices, and oral Health Related Quality of Life: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Health Prev Dent</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <lpage>23</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30027162?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30027162</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klages</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Claus</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wehrbein</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zentner</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Development of a questionnaire for assessment of the psychosocial impact of dental aesthetics in young adults</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cji083</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16257989?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16257989</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asgari</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahmady</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yadegarfar</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eslamipour</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of orthodontic treatment need by patient-based methods compared with normative method</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Res J (Isfahan)</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>636</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24348622?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24348622</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hassan</surname>
                      <given-names>AH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amin</surname>
                      <given-names>HES</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association of orthodontic treatment needs and oral health-related quality of life in young adults</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>137</volume>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2008.02.024</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20122429?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20122429</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yassir</surname>
                      <given-names>YA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McIntyre</surname>
                      <given-names>GT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bearn</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of labial fixed appliance orthodontic treatment on patient expectation, experience, and satisfaction: an overview of systematic reviews</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <lpage>30</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjz043</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31147683?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31147683</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>DW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>LP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fixed orthodontic appliance therapy and its impact on oral health-related quality of life in chinese patients</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>80</volume>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2319/010509-9.1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19852639?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19852639</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mansor</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saub</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Othman</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Changes in the oral health-related quality of life 24 h following insertion of fixed orthodontic appliances</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod Sci</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <lpage>102</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2278-0203.105880</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24987635?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24987635</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jawaid</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qadeer</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fahim</surname>
                      <given-names>MF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain perception of orthodontic treatment - A cross-sectional study</article-title>
                  <source>Pakistan J Med Sci</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alzoubi</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hariri</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mulligan</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Attard</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An evaluation of oral health-related quality of life in orthodontic patients treated with fixed and twin blocks appliances</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod Sci</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <lpage>70</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jos.JOS_124_16</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28546959?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28546959</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shalish</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cooper-Kazaz</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ivgi</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Canetti</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsur</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bachar</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Adult patients’ adjustability to orthodontic appliances. Part I: a comparison between Labial, Lingual, and Invisalign™</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <fpage>724</fpage>
                  <lpage>30</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjr086</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21750242?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21750242</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>White</surname>
                      <given-names>DW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Julien</surname>
                      <given-names>KC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jacob</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campbell</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buschang</surname>
                      <given-names>PH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Discomfort associated with Invisalign and traditional brackets: a randomized, prospective trial</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>87</volume>
                  <fpage>801</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2319/091416-687.1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28753032?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28753032</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baysal</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uysal</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Soft tissue effects of Twin Block and Herbst appliances in patients with class II division 1 mandibular retrognathy</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <lpage>81</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjq187</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21357655?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21357655</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>MI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neela</surname>
                      <given-names>PK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Unnisa</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jaiswal</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahmed</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Purkayastha</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dentoskeletal effects of Twin Block appliance in patients with class II malocclusion</article-title>
                  <source>Med Pharm reports</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>95</volume>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>O’Brien</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wright</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Conboy</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sanjie</surname>
                      <given-names>YW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mandall</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chadwick</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of early orthodontic treatment with the twin-block appliance: a multicenter, randomized, controlled trial. Part 1: Dental and skeletal effects</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofac Orthop</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>124</volume>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <lpage>43</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0889-5406(03)00352-4</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campbell</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Millett</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelly</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cooke</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cronin</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Frankel 2 appliance versus the modified twin block appliance for phase 1 treatment of Class II division 1 malocclusion in children and adolescents: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>90</volume>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2319/042419-290.1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31613144?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31613144</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Broder</surname>
                      <given-names>HL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson-Genderson</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reliability and convergent and discriminant validity of the child oral Health Impact Profile (COHIP Child’s version)</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <lpage>31</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0528.2007.0002.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17615047?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17615047</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arheiam</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baker</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ballo</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Elareibi</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fakron</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harris</surname>
                      <given-names>RV</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The development and psychometric properties of the arabic version of the child oral health impact profile-short form (COHIP- SF 19)</article-title>
                  <source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <lpage>27</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-017-0796-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29132377?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29132377</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ceran Serdar</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cihan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yücel</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Serdar</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sample size, power and effect size revisited: simplified and practical approaches in pre-clinical, clinical and laboratory studies</article-title>
                  <source>Biochem Med</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>27</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Broder</surname>
                      <given-names>HL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson-Genderson</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sischo</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reliability and validity testing for the child oral Health Impact Profile-Reduced (COHIP-SF 19)</article-title>
                  <source>J Public Health Dent</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <fpage>302</fpage>
                  <lpage>12</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1752-7325.2012.00338.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22536873?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22536873</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Minamidate</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haruyama</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The development, validation, and psychometric properties of the japanese version of the child oral Health Impact Profile-Short Form 19 (COHIP-SF 19) for school-age children</article-title>
                  <source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-020-01469-y</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32653004?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32653004</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thiruvenkadam</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asokan</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>John</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geetha Priya</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prathiba</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Oral health-related quality of life of children seeking orthodontic treatment based on child oral health impact profile: a cross-sectional study</article-title>
                  <source>Contemp Clin Dent</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>396</fpage>
                  <lpage>400</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0976-237X.161899</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26321842?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26321842</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Skandrani</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Osta</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pichot</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eschevins</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pereira</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tubert-Jeannin</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validation of the french version of COHIP-SF-19 among 12-years children in New Caledonia</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>358</fpage>
                  <lpage>75</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-022-02370-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 35982450?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35982450</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xia</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ge</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Translation and psychometric properties of the chinese (Mandarin) version of the child oral Health Impact Profile-Short Form 19 (COHIP-SF 19) for school-age children</article-title>
                  <source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <lpage>77</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-014-0169-1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25433408?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25433408</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bisegger</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cloetta</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>von Rueden</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abel</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ravens-Sieberer</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duer</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Health-related quality of life: gender differences in childhood and adolescence</article-title>
                  <source>Soz Praventivmed</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <lpage>91</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00038-005-4094-2</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16300172?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16300172</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Michel</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bisegger</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fuhr</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abel</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Age and gender differences in health-related quality of life of children and adolescents in Europe: a multilevel analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Qual Life Res</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>1147</fpage>
                  <lpage>57</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-009-9538-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19774493?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19774493</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Onyeaso</surname>
                      <given-names>CO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sanu</surname>
                      <given-names>OO</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Perception of personal dental appearance in nigerian adolescents</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofac Orthop</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>127</volume>
                  <fpage>700</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2003.12.028</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mandall</surname>
                      <given-names>NA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matthew</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fox</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wright</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Conboy</surname>
                      <given-names>FM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>O’Brien</surname>
                      <given-names>KD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prediction of compliance and completion of orthodontic treatment: are quality of life measures important?</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjm077</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17971352?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17971352</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Urban</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bakr</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Severity of dentofacial deformity, the motivations and the outcome of surgery in skeletal class III patients</article-title>
                  <source>Chin Med J (Engl)</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <fpage>1031</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12150737?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12150737</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheiham</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Orthodontic treatment and its impact on oral health-related quality of life in brazilian adolescents</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/146531204225011364</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15071148?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15071148</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Helm</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kreiborg</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Solow</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychosocial implications of malocclusion: a 15-year follow-up study in 30-year-old Danes</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1985</year>
                  <volume>87</volume>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9416(85)90020-X</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 3855604?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3855604</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chin</surname>
                      <given-names>WC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>YS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>YR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tan</surname>
                      <given-names>PWW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>JYJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Short-term and long-term psychological impact and quality of life of patients undergoing orthognathic surgery</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed J</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <fpage>549</fpage>
                  <lpage>56</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bj.2021.06.002</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34118465?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34118465</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gatto</surname>
                      <given-names>RCJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garbin</surname>
                      <given-names>AJÍ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Corrente</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garbin</surname>
                      <given-names>CAS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The relationship between oral health-related quality of life, the need for orthodontic treatment and bullying, among brazilian teenagers</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Press J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <lpage>80</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2177-6709.24.2.073-080.oar</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramos</surname>
                      <given-names>ITM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nabarrette</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vedovello-Filho</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Menezes</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Meneghim</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vedovello</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Correlation between malocclusion and history of bullying in vulnerable adolescents</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>92</volume>
                  <fpage>677</fpage>
                  <lpage>82</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2319/100721-749.1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 35666207?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35666207</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
