<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:43:21Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7523782" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7523782</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-14</datestamp>
        <setSpec>medicine</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7523782</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7523782</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7523782</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32991450</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-20-04830</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000022352</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">22352</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>4700</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                  <subject>Clinical Trial/Experimental Study</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Antiretroviral treatment and its impact on oral health outcomes in 5 to 7 year old Ugandan children</article-title>
                <subtitle>A 6 year follow-up visit from the ANRS 12174 randomized trial</subtitle>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Birungi</surname>
                    <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BDS, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
                    <sup>∗</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fadnes</surname>
                    <given-names>Lars T.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DTM&amp;H, MD, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>c</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>d</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Engebretsen</surname>
                    <given-names>Ingunn M.S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tumwine</surname>
                    <given-names>James K.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MBChB, M.Med, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                    <sup>e</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Åstrøm</surname>
                    <given-names>Anne Nordrehaug</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BDS, DDPH, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <on-behalf-of>for ANRS 12174 AND 12341 study groups</on-behalf-of>
              </contrib-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zheng.</surname>
                    <given-names>Li Wu</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Clinical Dentistry</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Global Health and Primary Health Care</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Center for international health, Department of Global Health and Primary Health Care, University of Bergen</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Addiction Medicine, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway</aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Pediatrics and Child Health, School of Medicine, College of Health Sciences, Makerere University Kampala, Uganda.</aff>
              <author-notes id="cor1">
                <corresp><label>∗</label>Correspondence: Nancy Birungi, Årstadveien 19, Bergen 5009, Norway (e-mail: <email>Nancy.Birungi@uib.no</email>).</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <day>25</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>25</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>99</volume>
              <issue>39</issue>
              <elocation-id>e22352</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>26</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2020 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0" specific-use="CC-BY-NC">
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission from the journal. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="medi-99-e22352.pdf"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="toc">
                <p>Supplemental Digital Content is available in the text</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec sec-type="background">
                  <title>Background:</title>
                  <p>Antiretroviral therapy for HIV in sub-Saharan Africa has transformed the highly infectious virus to a stable chronic condition, with the advent of Highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART). The longterm effects of HAART on the oral health of children are understudied.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective:</title>
                  <p>To compare the effect of lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine on oral health indicators (dental caries, gingivitis, tooth eruption, and oral health related quality of life) in 5 to 7 year old HIV-1 exposed uninfected children from the ANRS 12174 trial.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="methods">
                  <title>Methods:</title>
                  <p>This study used data collected in 2017 among children aged 5 to 7 years from the Ugandan site of the ANRS 12174 randomized trial (ClinicalTrials.gov no: NCT00640263) implemented between 2009 and 2012 in Mbale district, Eastern Uganda. The intervention was lopinavir-ritonavir or lamuvudine treatment to prevent vertical HIV-1 transmission. One hundred thirty-seven and 139 children were randomized to receive lopinavir-ritonavir or lamivudine treatment at day 7 postpartum to compare efficacy of prevention of vertical HIV-1 transmission. At follow up, the children underwent oral examination using the World Health Organization methods for field conditions. The oral health related quality of life was assessed using the early childhood oral health impact scale. Negative binomial and logistic regression were used for the analysis of data.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Main outcome measures:</title>
                  <p>Dental caries, gingivitis, tooth eruption, and oral health related quality of life) in 5 to 7 year old HIV-1 exposed uninfected children.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="results">
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>The prevalence of dental caries was 48% in the study sample: 49% in the lopinavir-ritonavir arm and 48% in the lamivudine treatment group. The corresponding mean decayed missing filled teeth and standard deviation was 1.7 (2.4) and 2.3 (3.7) The mean number (standard deviation) of erupted permanent teeth was 3.8 (3.7) and 4.6 (3.9) teeth in the lopinavir- and lamivudine group, respectively. The prevalence of reported impacts on oral health was 7% in the lopinavir-ritonavir and 18% in the lamivudine group. Gingivitis had a prevalence of 7% in the lopinavir-ritonavir and 14% lamivudine treatment group. The regression analysis revealed 70% less reported impacts on oral health in lopinavir-ritonavir group than the lamivudine treatment group with an incidence rate ratio of 0.3 (95% confidence interval: 0.1<bold>–</bold>0.9).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="conclusion">
                  <title>Conclusions:</title>
                  <p>HIV exposed uninfected infants in the lopinavir-ritonavir group reported less impacts on oral health than the lamivudine treatment group. Dental caries, gingivitis, and tooth eruption were not significantly affected by the treatment lopinavir-ritonavir or lamivudine.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Trial Registration ClinicalTrials.gov identifier:</title>
                  <p>NCT00640263.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>antiretroviral</kwd>
                <kwd>children</kwd>
                <kwd>clinical trial</kwd>
                <kwd>dental caries</kwd>
                <kwd>gingivitis</kwd>
                <kwd>oral health related quality of life</kwd>
                <kwd>public health</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group id="award1" award-type="Fundref">
                  <funding-source>European and Developing Countries Clinical Trials Partnership</funding-source>
                  <award-id>CT.2006.33020.004</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>Not Applicable</principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
                <award-group id="award2" award-type="Fundref">
                  <funding-source>Research Council of Norway</funding-source>
                  <award-id>GlobVac grant number 183600</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>Not Applicable</principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec>
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Human immune virus (HIV) treatment programs in sub-Saharan Africa have transformed HIV infection from being a highly lethal infectious disease to a condition with many similarities to other chronic diseases.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Especially, the introduction of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) using 3 or more antiretroviral drugs in combination, has led to significant declines in HIV-associated morbidity and mortality.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Among the commonly used antiretroviral drugs are the nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor like lamivudine and the protease inhibitors (PIs) like lopinavir-ritonavir.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> Both drugs have been used as first- or second-line treatment options, for children, adolescents, and adults.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>It is important to investigate the long-term safety aspects of antiretroviral drug regimens in order to maximise control of HIV while at the same time minimizing adverse events. The ANRS 12174 multi-center trial investigated consequences of providing lopinavir/ritonavir versus lamivudine to exposed uninfected infants and reported less weight gain at 50 weeks among infants given lopinavir–ritonavir compared to infants receiving lamivudine. This indicates a negative growth effect that could have adverse health- and developmental consequences among infants given lopinavir-ritonavir.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> Recently, another study from ANRS 12174 found that lopinavir-ritonavir was associated with dose-dependent adrenal dysfunction in infants.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>A study from Iran compared adult persons with HIV receiving HAART to HAART naïve controls and reported no differences related to crown and root caries.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Similar conclusions were also reported from the United states in an HIV cohort of women.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> However, from Thailand it has been reported that HIV infected adults with long-term use of HAART (commonly non PI based regimens) showed a greater risk of having gingival bleeding on probing and oral lesions than their counterparts on short – term HAART.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> In contrast, Bretz et al found that adult patients who received antiretroviral therapy (ART) had a less occurrence of dental caries than patients not taking these medications.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> The studies involving children with regard to HIV infection have focused on reporting the prevalence of oral lesions and not the effect of HAART on oral health outcomes These studies reported high prevalence of dental caries.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> However 1 study from the Unites States involving youth aged between 10 and 18 years explored the association between combination antiretroviral therapy (cART) and oral health outcomes (dental and periodontal) lesions and found that youth who had received combination antiretroviral treatment containing integrase inhibitors had significantly higher number of teeth with untreated active caries than those with cART without intergrase inhibitors. This study also found that the youth with later initiation of PIs had significantly higher decayed, missing filled teeth/surfaces (DMFT/S) scores than the youth initiating PI at an earlier stage.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> Other oral health conditions like reduced salivary flow rates and salivary gland engorgement have also been associated with HAART and specifically with PI based HAART.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>The literature regarding the association of HAART with oral conditions shows mixed findings. The long-term impact of exposure to HAART on children's oral health status is understudied and requires more documentation. The purpose of this study was to compare the effect of lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine on oral health indicators (dental caries, gingivitis, tooth eruption, and oral health related quality of life) of 5 to 7 year old HIV exposed uninfected children from the ANRS 12174 trial.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec>
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Study setting and design</title>
                <p>This study presents data for analysis of secondary outcomes from the Ugandan mother-children pairs participating in the ANRS 12174 randomized trial (ClinicalTrials.gov no: NCT00640263) implemented between 2009 and 2012 and the ANRS 12341 follow-up study carried out between March 2017 and February 2018 in Mbale district, Eastern Uganda.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup></p>
                <p>In summary, the ANRS 12174 promoting infant health and nutrition in Sub African Africa: safety and efficacy-pre exposure propylaxis (PROMISE-PEP) trial was a multicenter randomized trial recruiting women in antenatal clinics at 4 African sites: Ouagadougou University Teaching Hospital (urban site in Burkina Faso), East London Hospital Complex (urban site in South Africa); Mbale Regional Referral Hospital (semi-rural site in Uganda); and Lusaka University Teaching Hospital (urban site in Zambia). The aim was to compare lopinavir–ritonavir with lamivudine (given from day 7 after birth until either 50 weeks or 1 week after cessation of breastfeeding) on the rate of HIV-1 transmission and adverse events among HIV-1-exposed uninfected infants in Africa. The participating mothers followed routine national prevention guidelines until day 7 postpartum when their new-borns were randomized to either lopinavir–ritonavir (Kaletra, Abbott, Chicago) or generic lamivudine. Detailed information about this trial has been published previously.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> The inclusion criteria for the infants were: being singleton; breastfed at day 7 by their mothers; a negative HIV-1 DNA PCR at day 7; and having received any prevention of mother to child treatment. For the mothers the criteria were: being 18 years or older, having intention to continue breastfeeding, HIV-1 infected, and not eligible for ART at the time of the study (clinically determined or because CD4 count &lt;350 cells per μL), not intending to move out of the area in the next year, and gave consent to participate for herself and her infant. The exclusion criteria were: new-borns who had clinical signs or biological abnormalities of grade 2 or higher on the US National Institutes of Health Division of AIDS adverse events grading tables, with exceptions for hemoglobin (not included if hemoglobin &lt;120 g/L) and absolute neutrophil count (not included if neutrophils &lt;1200 cells per μL [1.20 × 10<sup>9</sup>/L]); or if they presented with serious congenital malformations or birthweight was 2.0 kg or lower.</p>
                <p>During the ANRS 121741 PROMISE- PEP trial 7 day old babies were randomized to the lopinavir–ritonavir or lamivudine in a 1:1 ratio (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The study participants and data collectors, data managers, and statisticians were masked to the allocation arm. However, given the poor palatability of lopinavir-ritonavir, some parents might have known their child's treatment allocation. The infants received locally available pediatric liquid formulations of either lopinavir–ritonavir (Kaletra, Abbott); 40 mg of Lopinavir and 10 mg of ritonavir, twice a day if weighing 2 to 4 kg, and 80 mg and 20 mg, twice a day if weighing &gt;4 kg) or generic lamivudine (7.5 mg twice a day if weighing 2–4 kg, 25 mg twice a day if weighing 4–8 kg, and 50 mg twice a day if weighing &gt;8 kg).</p>
                <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Trial profile.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e22352-g001"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Two hundred seventy-six infants were recruited to the Ugandan site of the ANRS 121741 PROMISE-PEP trial with 137 (50%) randomized to lopinavir–ritonavir and 139 (50%) to lamivudine. In 2017, in a follow-up visit at the age of around 6 years, 166 children were followed-up. Two of the children were excluded due to HIV seroconversion with 164 eligible for enrollment. The loss to follow-up was 42% and 40% in the Lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine groups, respectively. The reasons for loss to follow were relocation and child deaths (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Primary outcomes</title>
                <p>The outcomes of this study were: dental caries experience, gingivitis, oral health related quality of life, number of retained primary and erupted permanent teeth.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Interview with mothers at baseline (7 days post-partum) and follow-up (2017)</title>
                <p>Data at baseline and follow-up was collected using semi-structured interviews with mothers in the local language (Lumasaaba). Details of data collection and capture are described elsewhere.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> The oral health questionnaire used at follow-up has been developed and tested previously in a similar population.<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> The oral health data was entered in Epidata software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epidata.dk/">www.epidata.dk</ext-link>). The interview schedule included questions about socio-demographic characteristics in terms of age, sex, marital status, level of education, and type of income. A wealth index based on ownership of household assets, such as furniture, electricity, type of water source, roof material, and type of toilet assessed at the baseline interview, was constructed and categorized into wealth quintiles. This socio-economic asset index was initially categorized into quintiles ranging 1 to 5 (most poor–least poor) and then recoded into the 2 categories (ie, the poorest and least poor) for analysis. The oral health related quality of life (OHRQoL) was assessed at follow up in 2017 using.<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> a slightly modified and abbreviated version of the Early Childhood Oral Health Impact Scale scale previously assessed for its psychometric properties among preschool children in Uganda.<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> The scale, consists of the child impact section and family impact section, which are proxy measures of children's OHRQoL with parents as respondents to assist children in evaluating their own quality of life. The child impact section, was assessed using 5 of its original 9 questions, covering the original 4 subdomains: symptoms, function, psychology, self-image, and child social interaction. The family impact section was assessed using the original 4 questions covering 2 domains of family distress and family function. Response categories were rated on a 5-point Likert scale. Total OHRQoL scores were constructed by adding the Child and Family impact scores. A dichotomy variable in terms of “0” equal to no total OHRQoL impact and “1” equal to at least 1 OHRQoL impact was constructed for analyses.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Clinical oral examination of children at follow-up visit (2017)</title>
                <p>The clinical oral examination was performed by 2 experienced dental surgeons (NB and MM). Dental caries were assessed on fully erupted primary teeth using the decayed, missing, and filled teeth index (dmft) in accordance with the World Health Organization guidelines for field conditions.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> A tooth was documented as decayed if it was visually cavitated with the aid of a dental mirror and periodontal probe. A tooth was qualified as missing when extracted due to caries, as confirmed by the mother. In the present analysis, dmft was used as a count variable and a dichotomous variable. The count variable was the sum of the decayed, missed or filled teeth. The dichotomized variable was categorized as absent for dmft count equal to “0” and present for dmft count greater than “0.” To assess gingivitis of the children, the modified community periodontal index was used.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> Each tooth was scored according to the presence or absence of gingival bleeding, indicative of presence or absence of gingival inflammation, using a periodontal probe across the gingival margins of the teeth.</p>
                <p>The retained primary teeth and permanent dentition were assessed by manually counting the retained primary and fully erupted permanent teeth.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Reliability measurements</title>
                <p>Duplicate clinical examinations were carried out after 2 weeks by dental surgeons (NB and MM) with 26 children not involved in the original study cohort but considered to be representative of the study participants. The calibration exercise comparing dmft scores for each primary tooth within and between examiners revealed intra- and inter-rater reliability of median Kappa (interquartile range) of 0.6 (0.5–0.7) and 0.7 (0.5–0.8), respectively. The corresponding scores for the DMFT of caregivers were 0.7 (0.5–0.9) and 0.6 (0.4–0.8), respectively.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.6</label>
                <title>Data cleaning and statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The statistical package Stata/<sc>SE 16</sc> (Stata Corp LLC, College Station, TX) was used for analysis. To compare baseline characteristics at randomization in the study sample at follow-up, means for continuous and proportions for categorical variables were used. Negative binomial regression with incidence rate ratio (IRR) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) was used to assess the effect of lopinavir-ritonavir or lamivudine on dmft count and OHRQOL impacts. Logistic regression with odds ratios and 95% CIs was used to assess the effect of lopinavir-ritonavir or lamivudine on gingivitis, OHRQoL, and dental caries experience (dmft &gt;0). To adjust for potential differences in loss-to-follow- up between study groups an inverse probability weight method with a probit regression was used to predict risk of lost-to-follow-up based on social economic position, years of education, and site of residence. The median of the inverse probability weight was 1.8</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <label>2.7</label>
                <title>Ethics</title>
                <p>Ethical approval for the study was granted by the Makerere University School of Medicine Research Ethics Committee (REC REF 2018-030) and the Uganda National Council for Science and Technology (HS 2373), and Regional Committees for Medical and Health Research Ethics, Western Norway [(REK) (2017/760/REC Sør-Øst)]. Signed or thumb-printed informed consent was obtained from each mother before study participation. The consent procedure was approved by the ethics committees.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec>
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Sample characteristics</title>
                <p>The baseline characteristics of the 164 children analyzed at follow-up, paralleled those at baseline and there were similar numbers of participants in the lopinavir–ritonavir (n = 80) and lamivudine (n = 84) treatment groups, respectively. With regard to loss to follow-up, the number lost was similar across the treatment groups with respect to both the categorical and continuous variables. However, loss to follow up was more likely among slightly younger women and women with higher viral load. Median maternal age (interquartile range) in the study group at baseline was 27 (23–28) and 28 (23–30) in the lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine treatment groups, respectively. Corresponding figures among those lost to follow up were 25 (23–28) and 25 (22–28) years. The viral load in the study group at baseline was 150 (150–338) and 150 (150–1396) viral copies/μL in the lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine treatment groups, respectively. Corresponding figures among those lost to follow up were 228 (150–3376) and 293 (150–3476) viral copies/μL (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Baseline characteristics (number and percentage [n and %]) among those included and lost to follow-up by treatment arm.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e22352-g002"/>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>As indicated in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, the average age of the children at follow was 6 years across the treatment groups. The prevalence of dental caries was 48% (dmft &gt;0) in the total study group and 49% and 48% in the lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine treatment groups, respectively. The corresponding mean dmft and standard deviation values were 1.7 (2.4) and 2.3 (3.7). The pattern of mean dmft was similar across the treatment groups with most of anterior teeth in the upper jaw and molars depicting higher frequency as is the usual pattern of dmft experience (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The average number of retained primary teeth was comparable across treatment groups and amounted to 17 teeth. The lopinavir group had on average a lower number of erupted permanent teeth than the lamivudine group with a mean number (standard deviation) of 3.8 (3.7) and 4.6 (3.9<bold>)</bold> teeth, respectively (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). A small percentage of mothers, (13%), reported impacts on oral health, with 7% and 18% in the lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine groups, respectively. The prevalence of gingival bleeding was 12% in the study sample with 7% and 14% in the lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine treatment groups, respectively.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Summary data; mean, standard deviation (SD), number (n), and proproptions (%) in the total group and by treatment allocation at follow-up.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e22352-g003"/>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Distribution of mean dmft (decayed, missing filled teeth) by tooth type in the maxilla for lopinavir-ritonavir (top left) and lamivudine (top right) group. Also distribution of mean dmft in mandible lopinavir-ritonavir (bottom left) and lamivudine group (bottom right).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e22352-g004"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Average numbers of retained primary teeth and erupted permanent teeth in lopinavir-ritonavir and lamivudine treatment groups.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e22352-g005"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Negative binomial regression did not indicate statistically significant differences between the treatment groups with respect to dental caries experience, gingivitis, retained primary teeth, and erupted permanent teeth. The corresponding IRRs, with 95% CIs were 0.7 (0.4–1.3), 0.3 (0.05–1.8) and 0.8 (0.6–1.2), respectively. There were 70% less impacts reported in lopinavir-ritonavir group than in the lamivudine treatment group with IRR of 0.3 (95% CI: 0.1–0.9) (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Dental caries experience, oral health related quality of life, retained primary teeth, and number of erupted permanent teeth by treatment group using negative binomial regression.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e22352-g006"/>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Logistic regression showed no significant differences between the treatment groups with respect to dental caries experience, gingivitis, and oral health related quality of life. The corresponding odds ratio (95% CIs): were 1.0 (0.6–2.0), 0.6 (0.2–1.5) and 0.4 (0.1–1.0) respectively (Supplemental Digital Content [Additional file], Table SI).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>According to the present findings, having received lopinavir-ritonavir or lamivudine during the trial period did not have a significant long term effect on children's dental caries experience, gingivitis, the number of retained primary- and erupted permanent teeth at follow-up. In contrast, children receiving lopinavir-ritonavir were less likely than their counterparts receiving lamivudine to experience oral impacts or reduced oral health related quality of life at follow up.</p>
              <p>The random assignment of children is a strength of this study as randomized trial designs minimize the risk of confounding. Furthermore, the dental examiners and research assistants were blind to the allocation status of study participants limiting possible measurement bias.</p>
              <p>Due to the long follow-up time, there was attrition, which reduced the sample size. This could have led to unequal groups and a problem with differential loss to follow up. However, we compared baseline characteristics in the available study sample and those lost to follow-up and as reported the treatment groups remained comparable indicating that the randomization had been maintained. Also, the reduced sample size could involve the epidemiological possibility of type II errors. The non-statistically significant differences were predominantly smaller. We acknowledge the limitation that assessment of dental caries at cavity level under field conditions without using x-rays might lead to underestimation of dental caries prevalence as the early incipient lesions are left out.</p>
              <p>It is difficult to compare the findings of this study with other studies. This is because most of the literature focuses on persons with HIV infected on ART while our study involved HIV exposed uninfected children who had received lopinavir-lopinavir or lamuvudine to prevent vertical transmission. A study from the US focusing on the effect of cART on oral outcomes (dental caries and periodontal) found that perinatally HIV infected youth initiated later on PIs had significantly higher DMFT/S scores than periantally HIV youth initiated to the PIs at an earlier age.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> However, this study unlike our study whose children were taking HAART as prophlaxis to prevent vertical transmission, excluded children who were taking HAART as propylaxis Thus, our study is one of the first to investigate the potential effect of antiretroviral drugs on children's oral health independent of HIV infection. So far research findings are mixed with some studies indicating that HAART is not associated with dental caries<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> while other studies have found both negative<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> and positive associations between HIV infected people on HAART and dental caries.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> Thus, Kalanzi et al and Glick et al published case reports that recommended further studies. In other studies involving the ANRS 12174 trial participants, Blanche et al observed less weight gain in infants given lopinavir–ritonavir while Kariyawasam et al. found lopinavir–ritonavir to be associated with dose dependent adrenal dysfunction.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>A possible explanation for lesser-reported oral impacts reported in the lopinavir-ritonavir group could be due to higher prevalence of gingivitis, dental caries, and number of teeth in the lamivudine group compared to the lopinavir-ritonavir group although this was not statistically significant. It has been established in the literature that oral health impacts are associated with clinical findings but is also influenced by social and cultural factors.<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup></p>
              <p>Further research is recommended to further clarify the relationship of HAART on oral health of children.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>HIV exposed uninfected infants in the lopinavir-ritonavir group reported less impacts on oral health than their counterparts in the lamivudine treatment group. Dental caries, gingivitis, and tooth eruption were not significantly affected by lopinavir-ritonavir or lamivudine pre exposure prophylaxis.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>This study used data collected in the context of the ANRS 12174 clinical trial and 12341 study. We are grateful to the ANRS 12174 and 12341 for sharing data and giving us the opportunity to carry out oral assessments. We acknowledge Dr. Mohammad Matovu (MM) for assistance with the oral examination.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Nancy Birungi, Lars Fadnes, Ingunn Engebretsen, James Tumwine, Anne Åstrøm.</p>
              <p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Nancy Birungi, Lars Fadnes, Ingunn Engebretsen, Anne Åstrøm.</p>
              <p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Nancy Birungi.</p>
              <p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Nancy Birungi, Anne Åstrøm.</p>
              <p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Nancy Birungi, Lars Fadnes, Ingunn Engebretsen, James Tumwine, Anne Åstrøm.</p>
              <p><bold>Project administration:</bold> Nancy Birungi, James Tumwine, Anne Åstrøm.</p>
              <p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Anne Åstrøm.</p>
              <p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> Nancy Birungi, Lars Fadnes, Ingunn Engebretsen, James Tumwine, Anne Åstrøm.</p>
              <p><bold>Writing - review and editing:</bold> Nancy Birungi, Lars Fadnes, Ingunn Engebretsen, James Tumwine, Anne Åstrøm.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
                <caption>
                  <title>Supplemental Digital Content</title>
                </caption>
                <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="medi-99-e22352-s001.docx" orientation="portrait" id="d38e699" position="anchor"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="abbr">
                <p>Abbreviations: ART = antiretroviral treatment, cART = combined antiretoviral treatment, CI = confidence interval, dmft/s = decayed missing filled teeth/surfaces, HAART = highly active antiviral treatment, HIV = human immune virus, IRR = incidence rate ratio, OHRQoL = oral health related quality of life, PIs = protease inhibitors, PROMISE-PEP = promoting infant health and nutrition in Sub African Africa: safety and efficacy-pre exposure propylaxis, REC = Regional Ethical Committee.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>How to cite this article: Birungi N, Fadnes LT, Engebretsen IM, Tumwine JK, Åstrøm AN. Antiretroviral treatment and its impact on oral health outcomes in 5 to 7 year old Ugandan children: a 6 year follow-up visit from the ANRS 12174 randomized trial. <italic>Medicine</italic>. 2020;99:39(e22352).</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Clinical Trial Number: NCT00640263.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Trial protocol: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/12/246">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/12/246</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>ANRS 12174 and 12341 study group members: Inserm 1058, University of Montpellier, France: Philippe Van de Perre (principal investigator), Nicolas Nagot, Jean-Pierre Molès (coordinating investigators), Catherine Quillet (international project leader), Roselyne Vallo, Valerie Marechal (central lab coordinator), Marianne Peries (central data managers &amp; biostatisticians), Dorine Neveu (biostatistician), Vincent Foulongne (virologist), Michel Segondy (virologist)</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>University of Paris V, France: Stephane Blanche (pediatrician), Jean-Marc Treluyer (pharmacologist), Deborah Hirt (modeler)</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Makerere University, Uganda: James K Tumwine (site principal investigator), Grace Ndeezi, Charles Karamagi, Philippa Musoke (investigators), Paul Bangirana (co-investigator), Proscovia M Mugaba, Mary Kwagala, Joyce Nalugya, (site coordinators), Joan Murungi, Julian Abeso (study physicians), Nancy Birungi (study dentist), Simon Baryeija, Frederic Juma (pharmacists), Jesca Kanyago (psychologist), Hawa Nabuuma Muweesi (lab coordinator), Evelyn Ninsiima, Daniel Prince Mwesigwa (lab technologists), Caleb Bwengye Kata, Stuart Katushabe (data managers),</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>University of Ouagadougou, Burkina Faso: Nicolas Meda (site principal investigator), Rasmata Ouédraogo (biologist), (pediatrician), Eric Somé, Souleymane Tassembedo, Noelie Yamaego-Zoungrana, (site trial coordinators), Diarra Yé, Myriam Amoussou, Emmanuel Dembele, (pediatricians), Désiré Néboua, Aissatou Bélemviré (study physicians), Arsène Zongo (site pharmacist), Binta Djiga, Lydia Sanfo (psychologists), Hugues A. Traoré (site clinical study monitor), Christelle Nadembega (site biological study monitor), Justin Konaté (assistant of biological study monitor), Abass Ouédraogo (pharmacist assistant), Armel Bambara (data manager), Justine Boncoungou (social worker), Danielle Zoungrana (social worker), Isidore Traoré (international monitor)</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>University of Western Cape, South Africa: Cheryl Nikodem (site principal investigator until February 2011), Justus Hofmeyr (site principal investigator from March 2011), Mandisa Singata (principal investigator), Kim Harper, Debra Jackson, David Sanders, Joanne Batting.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>This study used data collected in the context of the ANRS 12174 clinical trial and 12341 study funded by the French National Institute of Health and Medical Research – National Agency for Research on AIDS and Viral Hepatitis (Inserm–ANRS), the European Developing Countries Clinical Trials Partnership (EDCTP; grant number CT.2006.33020.004), the Research Council of Norway (GlobVac grant number 183600) and the Total Foundation. NB benefited from a postdoctoral research position funded by the Department of Clinical Dentistry, Faculty of Medicine, University of Bergen.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>[1]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>UNAIDS</collab>. <comment>Global HIV &amp; AIDS statistics—2019 Fact Sheet: UNAIDS. 2019. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.unaids.org/en/resources/documents/2019/2019-UNAIDS-data">https://www.unaids.org/en/resources/documents/2019/2019-UNAIDS-data</ext-link>. Accessed on 08.09.2020</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>[2]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palella</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorman</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Declining morbidity and mortality among patients with advanced human immunodeficiency virus infection. HIV Outpatient Study Investigators</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>338</volume>:<fpage>853</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9516219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>[3]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>IVD</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiretroviral drugs</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>322</volume>:<fpage>1410</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11397751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>[4]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Hentig</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lopinavir/ritonavir: appraisal of its use in HIV therapy</article-title>. <source>Drugs Today</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17460785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>[5]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croxtall</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lopinavir/ritonavir: a review of its use in the management of HIV-1 infection</article-title>. <source>Drugs</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1885</fpage>–<lpage>915</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20836579</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>[6]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tylleskar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Peries</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Growth in HIV-1-exposed but uninfected infants treated with lopinavir–ritonavir versus lamivudine: a secondary analysis of the ANRS 12174 trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet HIV</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e307</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30814028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>[7]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kariyawasam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peries</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Foissac</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lopinavir-ritonavir impairs adrenal function in infants</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1030-1039</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>[8]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezaei-Soufi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Davoodi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdolsamadi</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dental caries prevalence in human immunodeficiency virus infected patients receiving highly active anti-retroviral therapy in Kermanshah, Iran</article-title>. <source>Cell J</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24518976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>[9]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dental caries in HIV-seropositive women</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15505238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>[10]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nittayananta</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Talungchit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaruratanasirikul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of long-term use of HAART on oral health status of HIV-infected subjects</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>[11]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bretz</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Medication usage and dental caries outcome-related variables in HIV/AIDS patients</article-title>. <source>AIDS Patient Care STDS</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11054939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>[12]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Aguiar Ribeiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Portela</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The oral health of HIV-infected Brazilian children</article-title>. <source>Int J Paediatr Dent</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23121171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>[13]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Kamary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Enwonwu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Perinatal HIV infection and exposure and their association with dental caries in Nigerian children</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28746260</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>[14]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiboski</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>ST-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The association between oral disease and type of antiretroviral therapy among perinatally HIV-infected youth</article-title>. <source>AIDS</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>2497</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30096069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>[15]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navazesh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of HAART on salivary gland function in the Women's Interagency HIV Study (WIHS)</article-title>. <source>Oral Dis</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>[16]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kankasa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumwine</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extended pre-exposure prophylaxis with lopinavir–ritonavir versus lamivudine to prevent HIV-1 transmission through breastfeeding up to 50 weeks in infants in Africa (ANRS 12174): a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>387</volume>:<fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26603917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>[17]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tylleskär</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exclusive breastfeeding promotion by peer counsellors in sub-Saharan Africa (PROMISE-EBF): a cluster-randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>378</volume>:<fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21752462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>[18]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birungi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadnes</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Engebretsen</surname><given-names>IMS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of maternal HIV-1 severity with dental caries: an observational study of uninfected 5- to 7-yr-old children of HIV-1-infected mothers without severe immune suppression</article-title>. <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31994250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>[19]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birungi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadnes</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Okullo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of breastfeeding promotion on early childhood caries and breastfeeding duration among 5 year old children in eastern Uganda: a cluster randomized trial</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0125352</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25938681</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>[20]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pahel</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozier</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parental perceptions of children's oral health: the Early Childhood Oral Health Impact Scale (ECOHIS)</article-title>. <source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17263880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>[21]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masumo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Child- and family impacts of infants’ oral conditions in Tanzania and Uganda–a cross sectional study</article-title>. <source>BMC Oral Health</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>538</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>[22]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Who</collab>. <article-title>Oral Health Surveys: Basic Methods</article-title>. <edition>5th Edition</edition><publisher-loc>Albany, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>[23]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalanzi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayanja-Kizza</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanjako</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extensive dental caries in a HIV positive adult patient on ART; case report and literature review</article-title>. <source>BMC Oral Health</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>1205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30526565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>[24]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe caries and the use of protease inhibitors</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>[25]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birungi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadnes</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nankabirwa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Caretaker's caries experience and its association with early childhood caries and children's oral health-related quality of life: a prospective two-generation study</article-title>. <source>Acta Odontol Scand</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27571601</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
