<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:40:18Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9645140" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9645140</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-11-14</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bdj</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz Dent J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz Dent J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bdj</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Brazilian Dental Journal</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0103-6440</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4760</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Fundação Odontológica de Ribeirão Preto</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9645140</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9645140</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9645140</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35262556</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35262556</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0103-6440202204237</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Validation of the brazilian version of the oral health impact profile
- Aesthetic questionnaire</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3415-8557</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hanan</surname>
                    <given-names>Simone Assayag</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5497-6514</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cohen-Carneiro</surname>
                    <given-names>Flávia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4439-0189</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Herkrath</surname>
                    <given-names>Fernando José</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0798-2479</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
                    <given-names>Branca Heloisa</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9880-4856</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Loguércio</surname>
                    <given-names>Alessandro Dourado</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2469-0291</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Martins</surname>
                    <given-names>Leandro de Moura</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2053-5008</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Herkrath</surname>
                    <given-names>Ana Paula Corrêa de Queiroz</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> School of Dentistry, Federal University of Amazonas, Manaus,
Amazonas, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Superior School of Health Sciences, State University of Amazonas,
Manaus, Amazonas, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> Instituto Leônidas e Maria Deane, Oswaldo Cruz Foundation, Manaus,
Amazonas, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label> Department of Community and Preventive Dentistry, School of
Dentistry, Rio de Janeiro State University, Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro,
Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label> School of Dentistry, Department of Restorative Dentistry, State
University of Ponta Grossa, Ponta Grossa, Paraná, Brazil.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Correspondence: Ana Paula Corrêa de Queiroz Herkrath Av. Ayrão
1539, Praça 14 de Janeiro, CEP 69.025-050, Manaus, Amazonas, Brazil.
Tel:+55-92-3305-4901. e-mail: anapaulaqueiroz@gmail.com</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>07</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <season>Jan-Feb</season>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>33</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>77</fpage>
              <lpage>86</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>20</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <p>The aim of the study was to develop the Brazilian version of the Oral Health
Impact Profile - Aesthetic Questionnaire (OHIP-Aes-Braz) and test its
psychometric properties. The questionnaire test versions were developed by a
panel of experts and a pre-test was conducted in a focus group. Data used for
testing its psychometric properties were obtained from a randomized controlled
clinical trial on tooth bleaching. Seventy-nine Brazilian adults were included.
The questionnaires were applied before tooth bleaching treatment (baseline), one
week (T1), and one month after the intervention (T2). Reliability was assessed
in terms of internal consistency and stability, while validity was ascertained
by criterion and construct validity. The sensitivity to change was assessed
comparing the total scores at baseline and T2, using the Wilcoxon test (α =
0.05). Both stability and internal consistency (intra-class correlation
coefficient=0.95, Cronbach’s α = 0.92) proved to be adequate. Construct validity
was confirmed as the correlation between OHIP-Aes-Braz scores with tooth color
satisfaction and self-perceived oral health were in the expected direction. A
positive correlation between OHIP-Aes-Braz and OHIP-14 (rs=0.63) and OIDP
(rs=0.77) was observed. The instrument was responsive once differences in total
scores before and after treatment were statistically significant (p&lt;0.001).
The OHIP-Aes-Braz presented good psychometric properties and showed sensitivity
to change regarding aesthetics evaluation in Brazilian adults treated with tooth
bleaching. A valid and reliable instrument allows a suitable assessment of oral
health-related quality of life in Brazilian patients submitted to aesthetics
dental interventions.</p>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <title>Resumo</title>
                <p>O objetivo do estudo foi desenvolver a versão brasileira do Oral Health Impact
Profile - Aesthetic Questionnaire (OHIP-Aes-Braz) e testar suas propriedades
psicométricas. As versões de teste do questionário foram desenvolvidas por um
painel de especialistas e um pré-teste foi realizado em um grupo focal. Os dados
usados para testar suas propriedades psicométricas foram obtidos a partir de um
ensaio clínico randomizado controlado de clareamento dental. Setenta e nove
brasileiros adultos foram incluídos. Os questionários foram aplicados antes do
tratamento clareador (baseline), uma semana (T1) e um mês após a intervenção
(T2). A confiabilidade foi avaliada em termos de consistência interna e
estabilidade, enquanto a validade foi avaliada pela validade de critério e de
construto. A sensibilidade à mudança foi avaliada pela comparação entre os
escores totais no baseline e T2, usando o teste de Wilcoxon ((=0,05). Tanto a
estabilidade quanto a consistência interna (coeficiente de correlação
intraclasse=0,95, alfa de Cronbach=0,92) mostraram-se adequadas. A validade de
construto foi confirmada uma vez que a correlação dos escores do OHIP-Aes-Braz
com a satisfação com a cor dos dentes e a autopercepção da saúde bucal foram na
direção esperada. Uma correlação positiva entre OHIP-Aes-Braz e OHIP-14
(<italic>r</italic>
<sub><italic>s</italic></sub> =0,63) e OIDP (<italic>r</italic>
<sub><italic>s</italic></sub> =0,77) foi observada. O instrumento foi responsivo uma vez que as
diferenças nos escores totais antes e depois do tratamento foram
estatisticamente significantes (p&lt;0,001). O OHIP-Aes-Braz apresentou boas
propriedades psicométricas e mostrou sensibilidade a mudanças na avaliação
estética em adultos brasileiros submetidos ao clareamento dental. Um instrumento
válido e confiável permite uma avaliação adequada da qualidade de vida
relacionada à saúde bucal em pacientes brasileiros submetidos a intervenções
odontológicas estéticas.</p>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Key Words:</title>
                <kwd>Dental esthetics</kwd>
                <kwd>quality of life</kwd>
                <kwd>tooth bleaching</kwd>
                <kwd>questionnaire</kwd>
                <kwd>validity</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="3"/>
                <table-count count="2"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="25"/>
                <page-count count="10"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Oral health has traditionally been assessed by clinical criteria, which does not
express the subjective impact of oral health problems on individuals’ lives. The
shift from the disease-centered concept of health (biomedical model) into a
multidimensional theory led to the emergence of the construct health-related quality
of life (HRQoL). The understanding that oral health is also related to the
individuals’ physical, mental and psychosocial well-being denotes the importance of
oral health in people’s quality of life <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>. Oral health related quality of life (OHRQoL) expresses to what extent oral
disorders affect psychosocial functioning and well-being <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>. Among other features, dental aesthetics can impact OHRQoL, which also
explains the growth of cosmetic dentistry <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Aesthetics represents a concept based on subjective perception and varies from
individual to individual. Thus, dental aesthetic itself, as well as the results of
interventions to improve it, are hard to evaluate, especially if aesthetics’
assessment uses professional normative criteria but does not account for the
individual’s perspective <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. Normative clinical indicators measure biological sequelae, but not the
suffering, limitations, and expectations faced by individuals due to a pathological
condition. On the other hand, self-reported subjective measures help to understand
the patient’s perceptions and needs when making therapeutic decisions and in the
evaluation of the results of dental treatments <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Several instruments have been used to measure OHRQoL. The Oral Health Impact Profile
(OHIP) is one of the most used for this purpose. Some authors have shown an
association between dental aesthetics and OHRQoL, which makes OHIP suitable for the
study of the impacts of aesthetic dental treatments <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>. This instrument originally presents 49 questions (OHIP-49), which limits
its use in clinical studies. Thus, shorter versions were developed, including the
aesthetics one: the OHIP-Aesthetic (OHIP-Aes). OHIP-Aes was firstly developed by
Wong, Cheung and McGrath <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> in a Chinese population submitted to tooth bleaching. The instrument derived
from the Chinese version of OHIP-49, and was originally published in the English
language <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. OHIP-Aes seems to be more appropriate than OHIP-49 and other OHIP versions
to detect changes involving dental aesthetics, especially in relation to tooth color
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Cross-cultural validation of quality-of-life questionnaires are important so that
they can be applied in locations and cultural contexts other than that where they
were developed, also allowing for comparison of results between countries and
different populations <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. The OHIP-Aes has already been validated in two languages - English <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> and Spanish <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>, but not in the Portuguese language yet. Studies developed in Chile have
used the version of OHIP-Aes translated and validated into Spanish by Núñez et al.
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> to assess the impact of tooth whitening on patients’ quality of life <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>. The English version has also been used to assess the impact of tooth
whitening <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The aim of this paper was to develop the Portuguese version of OHIP-Aes, through
translation and cross-cultural adaptation, as well as to evaluate the psychometric
properties (reliability, validity, and responsiveness) of the instrument, in a
population of Brazilian adults treated with tooth bleaching.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>Material and methods</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study design and sample calculation</title>
                <p>The study was designed to validate the OHIP-Aes instrument in the Portuguese
version (OHIP-Aes-Braz), using a sample of patients undergoing tooth whitening
in a controlled, randomized, parallel and triple-blinded clinical trial,
approved by the Research Ethics Committee (CAAE number 44564115.4.0000.5020) and
registered in the Brazilian Clinical Trials Registry (RBR-9mys6q). The clinical
trial objective was to test the efficacy and tooth sensitivity to whitening
treatment in adult patients who used desensitizing toothpaste, compared to those
who used regular toothpaste. The dentifrice tubes were covered with an opaque
band marked with numbered codes to blind the participants to group
allocation.</p>
                <p>The sample size was calculated considering that the study should have a 5%
significance level and 80% power to detect a minimal difference of 3.5 in the
overall score of OHIP-Aes between the two treatment groups. Previous studies had
suggested that this detectable difference should be at least 3 to 5 units <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. Thus, in order to allow for 15% dropout rate, a sample size of 80
patients (40 per group) was determined.</p>
                <p>A total of 79 adult individuals, aged 18 or over (range 18-39), of both sexes
participated in the study; after being informed about the study objectives and
procedures they signed the informed consent forms and were enrolled. Eligibility
criteria were individuals with the six maxillary anterior teeth free of caries,
without restorations on the labial surfaces, with superior central incisors
color shade A2 or darker (Vita Classical; Vita Zahnfabrik, Bad Säckingen,
Germany). The exclusion criteria were individuals who reported previous anterior
teeth sensitivity or who presented anterior teeth with enamel cracks, exposed
dentin, or severe internal discoloration (e.g., tetracycline stains, fluorosis,
etc.), individuals with active periodontal disease, pregnant or lactating women,
and patients using any anti-inflammatory, analgesics or antioxidant
medicines.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Dental whitening procedures, evaluation, and application of
questionnaires</title>
                <p>Participants answered OHIP-Aes questionnaire before being submitted to tooth
whitening. The instrument was applied in duplicate at this stage, with a
one-week interval between assessments (time 0 = baseline and time 0.1 = one week
after baseline, before intervention). The questionnaire was self-administered,
always under the supervision of a researcher, who was trained to help the
participants to answer the questionnaire with standardized explanations, when
asked to. Tooth whitening was performed in two sessions with the in-office
technique, using 35% hydrogen peroxide (Whiteness HP Maxx, FGM Produtos
Odontológicos, Joinville, SC, Brazil) in three 15-minute applications per
session, with an interval of one week between sessions, following the
manufacturer’ recommendations.</p>
                <p>The color evaluation was performed using a Vita classical (Vita Zahnfabrik, Dad
Säckingen, Germany) value-oriented shade guide, by two calibrated operators who
were blinded to the allocation assignment. The data was registered at the
beginning (time 0) and one month (time 2) after the intervention. A variation of
Vita Classical units between both times (() was used to measure the color
change. The intensity of tooth sensitivity was also registered using a Visual
Analogue Scale.</p>
                <p>The OHIP-Aes questionnaire was applied two times before the intervention (time 0
and time 0.1), one week (time 1) and one month (time 2) after the intervention
(<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f1">
                    <label>Figure 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Study timeline, with evaluation times for primary and secondary
outcomes.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="1806-4760-bdj-33-01-77-gf1" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Development of the Portuguese version of OHIP-Aes</title>
                <p>A flowchart of the translation and cross-cultural adaptation steps and the
psychometric properties evaluation of the Portuguese version of OHIP-Aes is
presented in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f2">
                    <label>Figure 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Flowchart of the translation and cross-cultural adaptation and
evaluation of the psychometric properties of the instrument.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="1806-4760-bdj-33-01-77-gf2" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p>The OHIP-Aes instrument was originally developed and validated in the English
language and derived from OHIP-49 items <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. It comprises 14 questions covering seven dimensions: functional
limitation (items 1 and 2), physical pain (items 3 and 4), psychological
discomfort (items 5 and 6), physical disability (items 7 and 8), psychological
disability (items 9 and 10), social disability (items 11 and 12) and handicap
(items 13 and 14) <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>.</p>
                <p>For each of the 14 questions from OHIP-Aes, patients are asked how often they
experienced the impact “in the past two weeks”. The original OHIP-49
investigates impacts in the last six months. This change was proposed and tested
in a previous study, in order to be sensitive to changes in OHRQoL of patients
undergoing tooth whitening and proved to be adequate <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. The answers, as in the original instrument, were presented in a Likert
scale coded as ‘never’ (0), ‘hardly ever’ (1), ‘occasionally’ (2), ‘fairly
often’ (3), and ‘very often’ (4) <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. The total score is calculated by adding the items scores and can vary
from 0 to 56. The higher the score, the worse the aesthetic oral health
impact.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Conceptual and item equivalence</title>
                <p>For the development of the Portuguese version of OHIP-Aes, the original
instrument developed in English language <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> was analyzed for conceptual and item equivalence by a panel of experts,
using the focus group methodology. This first step aimed to verify whether the
items selected for the English language instrument were relevant to the
Brazilian culture <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> since OHIP-Aes was initially validated in a population of young Chinese
adults.</p>
                <p>At the end of this stage, the group of experts concluded that some items of
OHIP-Aes in English differed from the items that they considered appropriate for
the Brazilian culture. Therefore, two versions of the instrument were tested.
The first version (named OHIP-Aes-V1) consisted of the
translation-back-translation of the 14 items enclosed in the original
instrument, published in English. The second version (named OHIP-Aes-V2)
consisted of 11 questions translated from the original instrument plus three
questions suggested by the panel of experts to be tested as substitutes for
questions 1, 2, and 9 of OHIP-Aes-V1. They were chosen from the 49-item original
instrument version <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>: “Did you have difficulty chewing any food because of problems with your
teeth, mouth or dentures?”, “Did you have trouble pronouncing a word because of
problems with your teeth, mouth or dentures?” and “Were you upset because of
problems with your teeth, mouth or dentures?” and translated into
Portuguese.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Semantic equivalence</title>
                <p>A pre-test of the questionnaire preliminary version was carried out with a group
of individuals with sociodemographic characteristics similar to those who would
be part of the main study (young adults of both sexes and who had completed
elementary school). Individual interviews followed by a focus group were
conducted <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>. Initially, five people were individually interviewed to express their
understanding of the questionnaire and explain how they arrived at their
respective answers. The interviews were recorded so that more than one analyst
could evaluate them later. Subsequently, three participants were gathered into a
focus group in order to discuss the aspects of the questionnaire that were
identified as unclear during the individual interviews. They could also suggest
terms or adaptations in the items, favoring their understanding, if
necessary.</p>
                <p>After the pre-test stage, the changes or adaptations suggested in the wording of
items were re-evaluated by the panel of experts at the final review of the
instrument. An expert in the English language judged whether the suggested
changes would help the comprehension of the instrument in the Portuguese
language without changing the meaning of the item in the English language.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Reliability</title>
                <p>The reliability of both versions (OHIP-Aes-V1 and OHIP-Aes-V2) was assessed by
their stability and internal consistency. The internal consistency was
determined by the correlation between different items that compose the
instrument and the degree of scale homogeneity. The results of the instrument
applied at time 0.1 were analyzed for inter-item correlation and total
item-score correlation (item-rest), using Cronbach's alpha coefficient. After
that, a final version of the instrument, derived from the tested items that
presented better internal consistency, was used for subsequent tests. This
version was named OHIP-Aes-Braz.</p>
                <p>According to the test-retest model, the OHIP-Aes-Braz instrument stability was
determined applying the instrument twice to the same individual, in a time
interval in which there was no change in the individual’s state concerning the
dental aesthetics. Therefore, the group of 79 individuals seeking bleaching
treatment answered the questionnaire at the beginning of the study (baseline).
After one week (time 0.1), without any therapeutic intervention or any change in
the dental aesthetics, 77 individuals answered the questionnaire again. The
agreement of the scores obtained in both moments was evaluated using the
intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Evaluation of the validity of OHIP-Aes-Braz</title>
                <p>The validity of OHIP-Aes-Braz, that is, its ability to detect impacts of dental
aesthetics on individuals’ quality of life, was assessed by the association
between the total score of the instrument and clinical and subjective parameters
related to dental aesthetics, both measured at baseline (time 0).</p>
                <p>The convergent construct validity was evaluated by the correlation between the
total score of the instrument and the aesthetic self-perception single item
question. The question used was: “How much are you satisfied with the color of
your teeth?”. The responses were recorded in a five-point Likert scale: ‘very
dissatisfied’ <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>, ‘dissatisfied’ <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>, ‘neither satisfied nor dissatisfied’ <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>, ‘satisfied’ <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>, and ‘very satisfied’ <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Convergent validity was also assessed through the correlation between
the total score of the instrument and the individuals’ oral health
self-perception, which was also measured in an ordinal scale ranging from 1 to
5. The higher the score, the better the oral health perception <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>.</p>
                <p>The concurrent criterion validity was assessed by the correlation between the
total scores of OHIP-Aes-Braz and the total scores of the validated Brazilian
versions of the instruments OHIP-14 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> and Oral Impact on Daily Performances (OIDP) <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. The OIDP has already been used to measure impacts related to tooth
whitening on Brazilian individuals’ OHRQoL <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Evaluation of the discriminatory ability of OHIP-Aes-Braz</title>
                <p> The OHIP-Aes-Braz discriminatory ability was analyzed by comparing the
differences between the total scores after tooth whitening in patients with and
without reported sensitivity one week post-treatment (time 1), and in
dissatisfied/neutral patients and patients satisfied with the color of their
teeth one month after treatment (time 2). The Wilcoxon test was used.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Responsiveness of OHIP-Aes-Braz</title>
                <p>The OHIP-Aes-Braz responsiveness, that is, its ability to detect changes over
time resulting from the intervention, was assessed by sensitivity to change in
the construct in patients undergoing tooth whitening. The OHIP-Aes-Braz
instrument sensitivity in detecting these changes was evaluated by the
difference between the total scores before (time 0) and after treatment (time
2).</p>
                <p>The responsiveness of OHIP-Aes-Braz was also compared to the changes detected
using OHIP-14 and OIDP, through the correlation of the differences between the
final and initial scores of the instruments (() and the post-bleaching color of
the upper central incisors.</p>
                <p>The comparison of pre- and post-treatment scores was performed using the paired
Wilcoxon test. Correlations were assessed using Spearman correlation
coefficient. The software Stata SE, version 15.0 (StataCorp LCC, College Station
TX, USA), was used for all analyzes, adopting a 5% significance level.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>One hundred twenty-one patients were examined for eligibility. Seventy-nine patients
were included in the randomized clinical trial. The sociodemographic characteristics
of the study population were as follows: 63.3% were female, the mean age was 24.4 +
5.0 years old, the marital status was single for 83.5%, the mean years of schooling
was 15.3 + 1.7, and 64.6% had monthly family income of more than five Brazilian
minimum wages (1BMW=US$ 193.00 at the study time). Sixty-seven patients were
evaluated at the end of follow-up (time 2), considering losses to follow-up (n=11)
and one patient who did not receive the intervention for declining to participate
after inclusion in the study.</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Reliability assessment of the OHIP-Aes-V1 and OHIP-Aes-V2 tested
versions</title>
                <p>Although Cronbach's alpha coefficient was high for both versions, items 1 and 2
of the OHIP-Aes-V1 version and item 9 of the OHIP-Aes-V2 version contributed to
a better internal consistency, that is, a better correlation between items and
the total score.</p>
                <p>Thus, the final tested version included the 13 questions translated from the
original instrument <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>, the OHIP-Aes-V1, and one question (item 9) extracted from the panel of
experts’ recommendations. This final version of the instrument was named
OHIP-Aes-Braz and it was used for the stability and internal consistency
analysis, as well as for all other analysis of validity, discriminatory ability
and responsiveness. The instrument in the Portuguese language is shown in
Appendix A. The Cronbach’s alpha coefficient for OHIP-Aes-Braz total score was
0.92 (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For test-retest
reliability, the ICC was 0.95 (95%CI 0.92-0.97).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Internal consistency for the total score and items of the
OHIP-Aes-Braz.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item-test correlation</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item-rest correlation</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cronbach’s alpha*</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7937</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7314</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9127</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8602</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8137</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9090</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2615</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1592</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9314</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2214</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1302</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9304</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8733</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8448</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9077</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8761</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8397</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9071</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4674</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4412</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9224</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9261</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9031</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8445</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8106</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9089</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 10</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9277</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9085</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9044</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 11</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6691</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6463</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9192</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 12</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7510</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7302</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9172</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 13</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8092</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7757</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9112</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz 14</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8204</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8008</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9144</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Total Score </td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9205</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Assessment of the OHIP-Aes-Braz validity</title>
                <p>The OHIP-Aes-Braz instrument showed convergent construct validity since the
baseline total scores presented a significant negative correlation with color
satisfaction and self-perception of oral health, as expected (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Individuals less satisfied with
the color of their teeth reported a greater impact on OHRQoL, and the better the
individual’s self-perceived oral health, the lower the instrument total
scores.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Convergent and concurrent criterion construct validity
assessment.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="4"/>
                        <col span="4"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Convergent validity</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Concurrent criterion
validity</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Satisfaction with tooth
color</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Self-perceived oral health</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">OHIP-14 total score</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"> OIDP total score</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>r</italic>
                            <sub>s</sub>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>r</italic>
                            <sub>s</sub>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>r</italic>
                            <sub>s</sub>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>r</italic>
                            <sub>s</sub>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHIP-Aes-Braz total score</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.25</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.50</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN1">
                        <p><italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub>, Spearman's rank correlation coefficient</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>When evaluating the concurrent criterion validity through the correlation between
the OHIP-Aes-Braz and OHIP-14 and OIDP total scores, it was observed that there
were significant positive correlations between the instruments. The greater the
impact measured by OHIP-Aes-Braz, the greater the impact measured by OHIP-14 and
OIDP (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Discriminatory ability</title>
                <p>When comparing the difference in post-whitening total scores in
dissatisfied/neutral patients and patients satisfied with tooth color at the end
of treatment, OHIP-Aes-Braz was able to discriminate these groups of patients
(Mann-Whitney test, p = 0.01).</p>
                <p>The ability of OHIP-Aes-Braz to discriminate individuals with and without tooth
sensitivity was assessed at the immediate postoperative follow-up (time 1, one
week after the last tooth whitening session). At this time, the postoperative
sensitivity was still elevated. The mean total score of the instrument in
patients without sensitivity (2.93 ± 4.8) was lower than in patients with
sensitivity (4.13 ± 6.0); however, this difference was not statistically
significant (Mann-Whitney test, p = 0.12). It is worth mentioning that 30 days
after the end of the treatment no individuals reported tooth sensitivity (data
not shown).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Responsiveness</title>
                <p>There was a significant difference in OHIP-Aes-Braz total scores between times 0
and 2 (paired Wilcoxon test, p&lt;0.001) and also between times 1 and 2 (paired
Wilcoxon test, p &lt;0.001) (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>),
demonstrating that the instrument was sensitive to detect changes in OHRQoL
resulting from an aesthetic intervention.</p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f3">
                    <label>Figure 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Variation in the mean of OHIP-Aes-Braz total scores at different
study times.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="1806-4760-bdj-33-01-77-gf3" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p>When comparing the OHIP-Aes-Braz responsiveness to the changes regarding the
clinical difference in the upper central incisors color using OHIP-14
(<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub>=0.01, p=0.94) and OIDP (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub>=-0.04, p=0.74), it was observed that only the variation in the
OHIP-Aes total score was statistically significant (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub>=-0.26, p=0.03). It means that OHIP-Aes-Braz was responsive to
clinical outcomes related to the dental aesthetics, that is, the bleached teeth
color, whereas OIDP and OHIP-14 were not.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The psychometric properties of Portuguese version of OHIP-Aes-Braz proved to be
adequate, considering the validity and the excellent stability and internal
consistency observed. The final version of the instrument validated in this study,
OHIP-Aes-Braz, derivated from the original instrument OHIP-Aes published in English
and validated in a Chinese population <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. We replaced an item (item 9 in the OHIP-Aes original version) by another
(item 34 in the original OHIP-49) as suggested by the expert panel. The original
question, “Have you got difficult to relax because of problems with your teeth,
mouth or dentures?” was replaced by “Have you got upset because of problems with
your teeth, mouth or dentures?”. Considering the results of the statistical
analyses, it is reasonable to believe that this approach did not compromise the
validity of the final Brazilian version of the instrument. Actually, the
questionnaire containing this item proved to be more appropriate to represent the
construct of interest in the studied population.</p>
              <p>The proposed instrument, OHIP-Aes-Braz, showed excellent stability and internal
consistency, and a moderate correlation among almost all items. The temporal
stability was equivalent to that assessed on the other two validated versions of the
OHIP-Aes (5, 8). Although an internal consistency greater than 0.70 is considered
satisfactory for comparisons between groups <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>, the internal consistency in the present study was higher than that assessed
on the English language validation <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> and in the Spanish language <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>When assessing instrument’s homogeneity, moderate correlations between items are
desirable; high correlations may reveal redundancy and low correlations imply that
they do not offer a relevant contribution to the scale. Items 3 (sensitivity to cold
and hot foods) and 4 (pain in the oral cavity) showed values of correlation with the
total scale score below 0.20, which might suggest that they could be deleted since,
according to Streiner and Norman <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>, an item-rest correlation below 0.20 indicates the need to remove or
reformulate these items. However, before eliminating items with low correlation, it
is prudent to consider the rationale behind the development of the items; low values
of correlation between some items and the total score were also observed in other
studies that justified the maintenance of these items <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The OHIP-Aes-Braz instrument items assess more than one construct dimension so that
weak correlations between items and the total score may occur. In the present study,
both items that showed a lower correlation with the scale total score belong to the
“physical pain” domain. A plausible explanation would be the sample’s socioeconomic
characterization, which could probably justify a greater use of dental services and
the absence of pain and sensitivity before clinical intervention (when the
instrument internal consistency was assessed). On the other hand, aesthetic
interventions can cause transient postoperative sensitivity or pain, such as
post-bleaching sensitivity, so that these individuals’ quality of life can be
modulated for better or worse depending on the balance between aesthetic improvement
and side effects of treatment <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>. Thus, the presence of items related to the “physical pain” dimension is
relevant in instruments that can be used to assess OHRQoL in aesthetic clinical
intervention studies.</p>
              <p>In addition to presenting excellent stability and internal consistency, the
OHIP-Aes-Braz instrument showed construct and criterion validity. There was a
significant negative correlation between OHIP-Aes-Braz and satisfaction with tooth
color, as well as with individuals’ self-perceived oral health. It means that
individuals less satisfied with their tooth color had a greater negative impact on
OHRQoL and those with better self-perceived oral health had a lesser negative impact
on their quality of life. For criterion validity, OHIP-Aes-Braz measurements were in
the same direction as the other instruments tested, OIDP and OHIP-14.</p>
              <p>The OHIP-Aes-Braz was also able to discriminate satisfied patients from those not
satisfied with tooth color at the post-treatment, similar to versions in other
languages <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. The instrument was also able to detect changes due to an aesthetic
intervention, proving to be responsive. The OHIP-Aes-Braz was responsive for
clinical outcomes related to dental aesthetics (whitened teeth) whereas OIDP and
OHIP-14 were not. The positive change in quality of life of patients who had their
teeth whitened was evident in the dental aesthetics self-perception one month after
treatment, which supports the hypothesis that tooth whitening positively impacts the
individuals’ OHRQoL and improves the dental aesthetics self-perception at the late
postoperative period.</p>
              <p>It is expected that once the tooth whitening effect persists, patients will continue
to experience positive psychological, social and functional impacts <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>. Estay et al. <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> showed that tooth whitening was associated with more favorable attitudes
towards oral health and a better self-perceived image, with immediate and long-term
social, psychological, and aesthetic positive impacts. However, this hypothesis
deserves future studies.</p>
              <p>It is important to clarify that this study was primarily designed to test the
efficacy of dental bleaching on a sample of adults living in a Brazilian city. The
sample consisted mostly of young individuals who sought an exclusively aesthetic
treatment, with family income above five minimum wages and who had attended an
average of 15 years of study. It should not be considered a representative sample of
the Brazilian population. Then, the generalization of our results must be made with
caution; testing the instrument before using it in other settings is recommended.
Furthermore, other aspects deserve to be pointed out as possible limitations of the
study. There was a dropout rate of 15% which could have resulted in selection bias.
However, the characteristics related to sociodemographic and clinical and subjective
measures were similar between those who discontinued and those who were followed
until the end of the study. In addition, the study power was not compromised, since
it was within the rate calculated at the beginning of the study, satisfying the
minimum sample of patients.</p>
              <p>Another relevant issue is that the color change was the main clinical aspect
investigated. Although tooth color is one of the main characteristics concerning
dental aesthetics, it would be suitable to test this instrument in other
interventions intended to modify other important aspects of dental aesthetic, such
as the size, shape, and position of teeth <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. The original reduced version of OHIP, OHIP-14, has been extensively used in
clinical studies for various aesthetic interventions such as prosthetic
rehabilitation <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>, implants <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>, and orthodontic treatment <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref>. It would be useful to test if OHIP-Aes, compared to OHIP-14, would have
better psychometric properties or be more responsive to these aesthetic
interventions, just as it was in this study for tooth whitening.</p>
              <p>The Portuguese version of the OHIP-Aes instrument, OHIP-Aes-Braz, which was adapted
and tested in this study showed reliability, in terms of internal consistency and
stability. It also proved to be valid, discriminatory, and responsive, being
sensitive to the change in the perception of OHRQoL in adults submitted to tooth
bleaching.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Glick</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williams</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kleinman</surname>
                      <given-names>DV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vujicic</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watt</surname>
                      <given-names>RG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weyant</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new definition for oral health developed by the FDI World
Dental Federation opens the door to a universal definition of oral
health</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dent J</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>221</volume>
                  <fpage>792</fpage>
                  <lpage>793</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27981999</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Locker</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allen</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>What do measures of ‘oral health-related quality of life’
measure?</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <lpage>411</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039281</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McGrath</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>AHH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheung</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The sensitivity and responsiveness of an oral health related
quality of life measure to tooth whitening</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>697</fpage>
                  <lpage>702</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16139701</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bersezio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martín</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herrera</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loguercio</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernández</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of at-home whitening on patients’ oral health,
psychology, and aesthetic perception</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <lpage>228</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30537968</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Núñez</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dreyer</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martín</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moncada</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validation of the Spanish OHIP-Aesthetic questionnaire for
Chilean adults</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Oral Craniofac Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>4</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bruhn</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Darby</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McCombs</surname>
                      <given-names>GB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lynch</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vital tooth whitening effects on oral health-related quality of
life in older adults</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Hyg</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>86</volume>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <lpage>247</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22947847</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vildosola</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bersezio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herrera</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bortolatto</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saad</surname>
                      <given-names>JRC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of 6% hydrogen peroxide concentration for
toothbleaching - a double-blind, randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <fpage>965</fpage>
                  <lpage>972</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26057085</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>AHH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheung</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McGrath</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Developing a short form of Oral Health Impact Profile (OHIP) for
dental aesthetics: OHIP-aesthetic</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <lpage>72</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17244139</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kothari</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gray</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lyons</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tan</surname>
                      <given-names>XW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brunton</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vital bleaching and oral-health-related quality of life in
adults: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>84</volume>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <lpage>29</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30904560</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bersezio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martín</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peña</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rubio</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Estay</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vernal</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness and impact of the walking bleach technique on
esthetic self-perception and psychosocial factors: A randomized double-blind
clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>596</fpage>
                  <lpage>605</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29144879</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bersezio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martín</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Angel</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bottner</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Godoy</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Avalos</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Teeth whitening with 6% hydrogen peroxide and its impact on
quality of life: 2 years of follow-up</article-title>
                  <source>Odontology</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>107</volume>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <lpage>125</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29961213</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Estay</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Angel</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bersezio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tonetto</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jorquera</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peña</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The change of teeth color, whiteness variations and its
psychosocial and self-perception effects when using low vs. high
concentration bleaching gels: a one-year follow-up</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <lpage>255</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32917192</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernández</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bersezio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bottner</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Avalos</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Godoy</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Inda</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Longevity, Esthetic Perception, and Psychosocial Impact of Teeth
Bleaching by Low (6%) Hydrogen Peroxide Concentration for In-office
Treatment: A Randomized Clinical Trial</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <lpage>52</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27571237</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Locker</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jokovic</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clarke</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessing the responsiveness of measures of oral health-related
quality of life</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14961835</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nadanovsky</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Brazilian version of the Oral
Health Impact Profile - Short form</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <lpage>314</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leão</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Questionários na pesquisa odontológica</part-title>
                  <source>Epidemiologia e bioestatística na pesquisa odontológica</source>
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luiz</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nadanovsky</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <publisher-loc>São Paulo</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Atheneu</publisher-name>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <lpage>289</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortes</surname>
                      <given-names>MIS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marcenes</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheiham</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of traumatic injuries to the permanent teeth on the oral
health-related quality of life in 12-14-year-old children</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <lpage>198</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12000342</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meireles</surname>
                      <given-names>SS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goettems</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dantas</surname>
                      <given-names>RV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bona</surname>
                      <given-names>AD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>IS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Demarco</surname>
                      <given-names>FF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Changes in oral health related quality of life after dental
bleaching in a double-blind randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <lpage>121</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24316342</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bland</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Altman</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Statistics notes - Cronbach’s alpha</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>314</volume>
                  <fpage>572</fpage>
                  <lpage>572</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9055718</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Streiner</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Norman</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Health measurement scales: a practical guide to their development and
use</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                  <year>1995</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen-Carneiro</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rebelo</surname>
                      <given-names>MAB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza-Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ambrosano</surname>
                      <given-names>GMB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salino</surname>
                      <given-names>AV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pontes</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of the OHIP-14 and prevalence and
severity of oral health impacts in a rural riverine population in Amazonas
State, Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>Cad Saúde Pública</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>1122</fpage>
                  <lpage>1130</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20657977</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goettems</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandez</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donassollo</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donassollo</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Demarco</surname>
                      <given-names>FF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of tooth bleaching on oral health-related quality of life
in adults: A triple-blind randomised clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>105</volume>
                  <fpage>103564</fpage>
                  <lpage>103564</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33359042</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Øzhayat</surname>
                      <given-names>EB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gotfredsen</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Patient-reported effect of oral rehabilitation</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
                  <lpage>376</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30556146</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Toia</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wennerberg</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torrisi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farina</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Corrà</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cecchinato</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Patient satisfaction and clinical outcomes in implant-supported
overdentures retained by milled bars: two-year follow-up</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <fpage>624</fpage>
                  <lpage>633</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30806481</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feu</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miguel</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Celeste</surname>
                      <given-names>RK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of orthodontic treatment on oral health-related quality of
life</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <fpage>892</fpage>
                  <lpage>898</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23593976</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
