<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:37:34Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10040111" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10040111</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-03-27</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcorhl</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10040111</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10040111</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10040111</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36966288</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36966288</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2864</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-023-02864-9</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Dental pain perception and emotional changes: on the relationship between dental anxiety and olfaction</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Alkanan</surname>
                    <given-names>Sarah Abdulaziz Mohammed</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>Sarah.alkanan@qudent.org</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Alhaweri</surname>
                    <given-names>Hadeel Saleh</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>Hadeel.alhaweri@qudent.org</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Khalifa</surname>
                    <given-names>Ghada Amin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>G.Khalifa@qu.edu.sa</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ata</surname>
                    <given-names>Shaimaa Mohamed Saeed</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>s.ata@qu.edu.sa</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Resident Dentist, Qusaiba Hospital, Qassim, Saudi Arabia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Resident Dentist, Aljreir Alshamaly Primary Health Care Center, Qassim, Saudi Arabia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412602.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9421 8094</institution-id><institution>Professor of Maxillofacial Surgery and Diagnostic Science, College of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Qassim University, </institution></institution-wrap>Qassim, Saudi Arabia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412602.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9421 8094</institution-id><institution>Lecturer of Community Dentistry and Oral Epidemiology, College of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Qassim University, </institution></institution-wrap>Qassim, Saudi Arabia </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <elocation-id>175</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>7</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">The purpose of the study was to determine to what extent olfactory aromatherapy reduces the intensity of dental pain and the level of dental anxiety. It also attempted to corelate between olfactory aromatherapy, stages of dental visits, and various dental procedures.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">Female patients were enrolled in a randomized controlled study. Olfactory aromatherapy was performed using lavender oils. Patients were randomly assigned to one of two groups: the lavender group, in which patients inhaled 2% lavender vapors, and the control group, in which patients inhaled water vapors. Pain score, anxiety score, and changes in vital signs were among the predictable variables. Anxiety and pain were assessed using the Modified Dental Anxiety Scale (MDAS), Speilberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI), and visual analog scales (VAS). The vital signs were systolic (SBP) and diastolic (DBP), heart rate (HR), respiratory rate (RR), and oxygen saturation (Spo2). Variables were evaluated before inhalations, 20 min after inhalations, at the end of settings, and on the following day.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">Each group had 175 participants. Pain and anxiety scores were significantly reduced, and all vital signs improved, except for DBP. The MDAS, STAI, and pain scores are reduced by 3.4, 4.2, and 2.4 times, respectively, compared to the control group. Olfactory aromatherapy had the greatest impact during the phase of waiting rooms.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">When compared to the control group, olfactory aromatherapy reduces anxiety scores three to four times more. Pain perception is reduced by twice as much as in the control group. It also significantly reduces the anxiety associated with minor to moderately stressful dental procedures.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Supplementary Information</title>
                  <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12903-023-02864-9.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Dental pain</kwd>
                <kwd>Dental anxiety</kwd>
                <kwd>Aroma therapy</kwd>
                <kwd>Lavender</kwd>
                <kwd>Essential oil </kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par5">Dental anxiety and fear are defined as an abnormal fear of going to the dentist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Dental anxiety is the fifth most common type of anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. It is the primary impediment to receiving proper dental treatment. Anxiety is triggered in dental clinics by a variety of factors, including sights (needles and blood), sounds of hand pieces (preparations), smells (cut dentin and bone, materials such as eugenol), and sensation (high-recurrence vibration), all of which stimulate the sensory system in the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. To control and minimize pain perception and associated emotional changes, various techniques are used to manage dental fear and anxiety. Psychotherapeutic and/or pharmacological interventions are included. Anxiolytics are dangerous, necessitate specialized equipment, and may be contraindicated in certain patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par6">Aromatherapy is the use of essential oils for therapeutic purposes, and it has received attention as an alternative medicine method to control anxiety during medical settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. It entails inhaling, absorbing, or ingesting essential oils to alleviate anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The sense of smell can induce chemical changes in the human body that range from pleasant to repulsive. So, the smell is used to improve health; this is known as olfactory aromatherapy, which is a type of complementary medicine that uses smell. There have been few studies that investigate the relationship between olfactory aromatherapy, pain perception, and anxiety in dental settings.</p>
              <p id="Par7">To the best of our knowledge, the majority of those articles only stated whether or not olfactory aromatherapy is effective, but they made no predictions about its potency. Furthermore, the majority of those studies searched the impact of olfactory aromatherapy on local anesthesia and tooth extraction procedures, but not on other dental procedures. Moreover, they did not investigate at which stage of dental visits olfactory aromatherapy is most effective. As a result, this study was designed to answer the following questions: 1) What is the potency of olfactory aromatherapy in reducing pain perception and anxiety during dental visits? 2) Which dental procedure is significantly influenced by the use of olfactory aromatherapy? And 3) When is the greatest effect of olfactory aromatherapy recorded in dental settings? Therefore, this study amid to investigate to what extent olfactory aromatherapy is able to reduce the intensity of dental pain and the level of dental anxiety. It also attempted to corelate between olfactory aromatherapy, stages of dental visits, and various dental procedures.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p id="Par8">A prospective randomized double-blind controlled parallel grouped clinical trial was conducted on dental patients who attended the outpatient Dental clinics at Qassim University's College of Dentistry between March 2018 and January 2021. For olfactory aromatherapy, lavender essential oil was chosen to stimulate smell. The patients were randomly assigned to one of two groups: the control group, in which the patients inhaled plain distal water vapors, and the lavender group, in which patients inhaled lavender oil vapors. Age, gender, and time were avoided as confounding factors because they have a large impact on pain perception and anxiety as reported by many authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. As a result, patients were chosen based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The required permissions and informed consent were obtained; the study was approved by the Dental Ethical Committee, College of Dentistry, Qassim University, Saudi Arabia on 20/3/2018 with approval registry number "EA/3006/2018." On 11/5/2022, the study was retrospectively registered at clinicalTrials.gov, with the identifier "NCT05369936."<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The study’s inclusion and exclusion criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Inclusion Criteria</th><th align="left">Exclusion Criteria</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Adult females over 18 years</td><td align="left">Males</td></tr><tr><td align="left">females who attended morning dental clinics at 9 am</td><td align="left"><p>Females who had:</p><p>- Allergies</p><p>- Bronchial asthma</p><p>- Common cold</p><p>- Pulmonary diseases</p><p>- Migraine</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>Females who were liable for:</p><p><bold>-</bold> Administration of the local anesthesia</p><p><bold>-</bold> Teeth preparation either for filling procedures or crown preparations</p><p><bold>-</bold> Endodontic treatment</p><p><bold>-</bold> Teeth extraction</p><p><bold>-</bold> Subgingival curettage and scaling</p></td><td align="left"><p>Females who taking:</p><p>- Antidepressants</p><p>- Anxiolytic drugs</p><p>- Opioids</p><p>- Other medications that affect emotional responses</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Pregnant female</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Sampling, randomization, and blindness</title>
                <p id="Par9">The sample size was calculated using the PASS 16 Power Analysis and Sample Size Software version 2018 (NCSS, LLC. Kaysville, Utah, USA, ncss.com/software/pass). The results indicated that the total sample size for the study has to be 338 subjects (169 patients in each group), with = 0.05 and power = 80%. To account for any dropouts, the sample size in each group was increased to 175 participants. The patient sequences were used for randomization. Patients with even numbers were assigned to the lavender group, while those with odd numbers were assigned to the control group. To ensure the validity of the study's findings, both groups were treated on different days to guarantee that the smell of lavender oil was completely removed from the clinics and waiting room. The following steps were taken to achieve blindness: 1) The patients, dentists who treated them, and evaluators who interviewed them to measure the study's variables were not informed about the study, so the vaporizers were placed as part of the clinic's and waiting room's equipment throughout the study's period, and 2) The investigators who reviewed the questionnaires and the statistician who analyzed the study's results only knew the study's groups as A and B.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Study variables</title>
                <p id="Par10">The predictable variable was the ability of olfactory aromatherapy to reduce dental pain and anxiety. This ability was calculated in terms of pain perception and emotional changes during phases of dental settings where different dental procedures were performed. The intensity of pain felt before, during, and after dental procedure was used to evaluate pain perception. To determine emotional changes, the anxiety level and the measurements of patients’ vital signs were measured before, during, and after dental procedures as well. The primary outcome variables were the changes in the preoperative dental anxiety, dental pain intensity, and baseline measurements of the patients’ vital signs (SBP, DBP, HR, RR, Spo2). The secondary outcome variables included the phase of the dental setting and dental procedures where olfactory aromatherapy had the greatest effect. Furthermore, the need for postoperative analgesics or anxiolytics after dental settings was documented as an additional record.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Data collection</title>
                <p id="Par11">The patients’ demographic information was recorded. The MDAS questionnaire (a simplified scale with five questions and scores ranging from one to five) and the STAI questionnaire (a scale consists of 40 questions and has a score range of 20 to 80) were used to assess the level of dental anxiety. The intensity of pain was measured using VAS, with scores ranging from 0 to 100 mm. All of the aforementioned scales were compiled into a single questionnaire, which was given to each patient four times. The first questionnaire was given to ever patient an hour before exposure to vapors in the waiting room (Phase I), and its results were used as baseline measurements. The second one was obtained 20 min after vapor exposure in setting rooms (Phase II).</p>
                <p id="Par12">Following the completion of the dental procedures, the third questionnaire was completed (Phase III). The fourth questionary was obtained on the following day after dental procedures (Phase IV). Phases I and II were completed in the waiting room, while phases III and IV were completed in dental clinics. Two senior staff members were in charge of collecting and reviewing the questionnaires, and each was assigned to one of the study's groups. The same healthcare staff measured the patients' vital signs four times in the same order as the questionnaires. The SBP and DBP were measured in millimeters of mercury using a sphygmomanometer and stethoscope. The patients were asked to stand up straight, and the sphygmomanometer cuff was inserted around their upper left arms, with a 2.5-inch distance between the antecubital fossa of the arm and the lower edge of the cuff. The blood pressure was measured after the stethoscope was placed over the brachial artery. The HR, RR, and Spo<sub>2</sub> were measured using a finger pulse oximeter.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Intervention</title>
                <p id="Par13">After completing the first questionnaire and measuring the vital signs (phase I), 20 drops (0.25 mL) of 100% organic essential lavender oil (Lavandula angustifolia, 10 mL, Australian Certified Organic Pty Ltd., Brisbane, Australia) and 50 mL of distal water were added to an electrical aromatherapy vaporizer near the patient's chair at a distance of 20 cm in the waiting room. After 20 min, the second questionnaire was given the patients and their vital signs were measured (phase II). Then, the patient was transferred to dental clinics, where the lavender vaporizer was placed 20 cm away from the dental unit. Every 20 min, 20 drops of lavender oil were added to the vaporizer until the dental treatment was completed. Before the patient left the clinic, the third questionnaire was completed and measurements of the vital signs were also recorded (phase III). For phase IV of the study, all patients were given 0.25 mL of lavender oil from the same bottle to use at home. Three drops of lavender oil were deposited on a cotton pad, and the patients were instructed to inhale it for five minutes from a distance of ten centimeters three times per day until they returned the following day to complete the fourth questionnaire.</p>
                <p id="Par14">On the day of the control group, the waiting room and clinics were thoroughly ventilated to ensure that the lavender scent was completely removed from the environment. The vaporizer was also placed 20 cm away from the patient's chair in the waiting room, but it was only filled with plain distal water. All of the above-mentioned lavender group protocol was also applied to the patients in the control group, except for using olfactory aromatherapy at home. They were only instructed to perform the standard postoperative dental care at home. All dental procedures, in both groups, were performed under local anesthesia with vasoconstrictor using nerve block local anesthetic techniques (Mepivacaine 2% and epinephrine 1:100,000). All patients were instructed to adminstrate diclofenac sodium 50 mg twice daily if they experienced postoperative pain.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par15">Our data was analyzed using SPSS Version 25.0 for Windows (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). All participants' baseline characteristics were expressed using descriptive statistics. The variables were summarized into mean and standard deviation, and the results were analyzed using the two-sample t and ANOVA tests. The two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test was used to compare baseline differences between groups. The paired <italic>t</italic>-test was used to compare variables before and after intervention. <italic>P</italic>-values less than 0.05 and confidence intervals of 95% were considered significant.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec9">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>Demographic data and baseline assessment</title>
                <p id="Par16">Only 350 female subjects out of 470 met the inclusion criteria for the study. There were 175 patients in each group, with an average age of 23.5 ± 1.12 years. None of the patients were dropped off and all the study’s phases were completed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> summarizes the study's demographic data and baseline parameters of the patients. In terms of all preoperative data, both groups were homogeneous. There were no adverse reactions such as nausea, severe hypotension, or syncope observed due to inhalation of lavender oil. Each questionnaire needed patients seven to ten minutes to be answered, and the investigators scored it in five minutes. The first phase's results (prior to inhaling vapors) revealed that all anxiety levels ranged from moderate to extremely high. This was reflected in the intensity of the pain, which ranged from mild to severe. The baseline vital sign measurements showed a slight increase, except for the Spo<sub>2</sub> percentage, which showed a slight decrease in blood oxygen saturation.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The study’s flow diagram demonstrating dental patients who participated in each group</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2864_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The patients’ demographic data and results of the baseline of the study’s variables (phase I)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Patients (<italic>n</italic> = 350)</th><th align="left">Lavender Group (<italic>n</italic> = 175)</th><th align="left">Control Group (<italic>n</italic> = 175)</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>- value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Age (in years):</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Mean ± SD</td><td align="left">23.98 ± 0.109</td><td align="left">23.72 ± 0.201</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">0.220</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Standard Error</td><td align="left">0.31</td><td align="left">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Confidence level (95%)</td><td align="left">23.98 ± 0.606</td><td align="left">23.72 ± 0.595</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Gender</td><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Nationality:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Saudi</td><td align="left">120 (34.29%)</td><td align="left">115 (32.86%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.123</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -None- Saudi</td><td align="left">55 (15.71%)</td><td align="left">60 (17.14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Educational level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Elementary school</td><td align="left">10 (2.86%)</td><td align="left">8 (2.29%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">0.211</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Middle school</td><td align="left">24 (6.86%)</td><td align="left">22 (6.28%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -High school</td><td align="left">38 (10.86%)</td><td align="left">40 (11.43%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -College</td><td align="left">101(28.85%)</td><td align="left">102 (29.14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Post graduate</td><td align="left">2 (0.57%)</td><td align="left">3 (0.86%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Social status:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Single</td><td align="left">123 (35.15%)</td><td align="left">129 (36.86%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="4">0.142</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Married</td><td align="left">34 (9.71%)</td><td align="left">31 (8.86%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Divorced</td><td align="left">14 (4%)</td><td align="left">12 (3.43%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Widow</td><td align="left">4 (1.14%)</td><td align="left">3 (0.85%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Dental Procedures:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Local Anesthesia</td><td align="left">175 (50%)</td><td align="left">175 (50%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="6">0.203</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Crown preparations</td><td align="left">50 (14.29%)</td><td align="left">48 (13.71%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Subgingival scaling</td><td align="left">44 (12.57%)</td><td align="left">50 (14.29%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Cavity preparations</td><td align="left">26 (7.43%)</td><td align="left">30 (8.57%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Pulp Extirpation</td><td align="left">27 (7.71%)</td><td align="left">23 (6.57%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Extractions</td><td align="left">28 (8%)</td><td align="left">24 (6.86%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Baseline SBP (mmHg)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">140.56 ± 16.53</td><td align="left">142.32 ± 12.36</td><td align="left">0.763</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Baseline DBP (mmHg)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">81.63 ± 11.24</td><td align="left">80.45 ± 10.23</td><td align="left">0.320</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Baseline HR (beat/min)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">76.61 ± 10.21</td><td align="left">76.81 ± 11.23</td><td align="left">0.654</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Baseline RR (breathes/min)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">17.82 ± 1.30</td><td align="left">17.80 ± 1.34</td><td align="left">0.764</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Spo<sub>2</sub> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">96.65% ± 1.78</td><td align="left">96.22% ± 2.89</td><td align="left">0.879</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Baseline MDAS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">7.43 ± 0.121</td><td align="left">7.73 ± 0.152</td><td align="left">0.122</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Fairly anxious:</td><td align="left">89 (25.43%)</td><td align="left">87 (24.86%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">0.432</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Very anxious:</td><td align="left">50 (14.29%)</td><td align="left">54 (15.43%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Extremely anxious</td><td align="left">36 (10.29%)</td><td align="left">34 (9.71%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Baseline STAI</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">75.54 ± 10.65</td><td align="left">76.58 ± 11.12</td><td align="left">0.111</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Degree:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> - Moderate</td><td align="left">89 (25.43%)</td><td align="left">96 (27.43%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.213</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> - High</td><td align="left">86 (24.57%)</td><td align="left">79 (22.57%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Baseline Pain Score</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">89.78 ± 1.23</td><td align="left">93.21 ± 2.23</td><td align="left">0.233</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Intensity:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Mild pain</td><td align="left">75 (21.43%)</td><td align="left">69 (19.71%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">0.212</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Moderate pain</td><td align="left">62 (17.71%)</td><td align="left">68 (19.43%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Severe pain</td><td align="left">38 (10.86%)</td><td align="left">38 (10.86%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SD</italic> Standard Deviation, <italic>SBP</italic> Systolic Blood Pressure, <italic>DBP</italic> Diastolic Blood Pressure, <italic>HR</italic> Heart Rate, <italic>RR</italic> Respiratory Rate, <italic>Spo2</italic> Oxygen Saturation, <italic>MDAS</italic> Modified Dental Anxiety Scale, <italic>STAI</italic> Speilberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analog Scale</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Anxiety and pain scores assessment in waiting room</title>
                <p id="Par17">The baseline scores of the STAI, MDAS, and pain, in the lavender group, were significantly lower in the second phase of the study (after inhaling vapors for 20 min) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The mean change in the STAI was—4.7 ± 8.60, while the MDAS and pain scores were -2.21 ± 0.13 and—8.82 ± 3.34, respectively. According to the ANOVA test results, lavender aromatherapy significantly reduced the MDAS, STAI, and pain scores by 3.4, 4.2, and 2.4 points, respectively, compared to the control group (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Furthermore, all vital signs were also significantly improved, except for the DBP. In the control group, all of the examined parameters were improved, but without any statistical significance, except for the HR.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of the study’ variables at the baseline (phase I) and the end of the second phase in the lavender and control groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Lavender Group (Mean ± SD)</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Control Group (Mean ± SD)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Phase I</th><th align="left">Phase II</th><th align="left">Change</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>- value</th><th align="left">Baseline</th><th align="left">Phase 2</th><th align="left">Change</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SBP</td><td align="left"><p>140.56</p><p> ± 16.53</p></td><td align="left">133.16 ± 12.20</td><td align="left">- 7.4 ± 12.34</td><td char="." align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">142.32 ± 12.36</td><td align="left"><p>137.09</p><p> ± 10.04</p></td><td align="left">- 5.23 ± 11.24</td><td char="." align="char">0.143</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBP</td><td align="left"><p>81.63</p><p> ± 11.24</p></td><td align="left">80.43 ± 6.87</td><td align="left"><p>- 1.2</p><p> ± 10.25</p></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.062</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left">80.45 ± 10.23</td><td align="left"><p>79.69</p><p> ± 9.98</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.76</p><p> ± 10.54</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.239</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HR</td><td align="left"><p>76.61</p><p> ± 10.21</p></td><td align="left">69.26 ± 7.76</td><td align="left"><p>- 7.35</p><p> ± 9.21</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.041</td><td align="left">76.81 ± 11.23</td><td align="left"><p>71.68</p><p> ± 5.67</p></td><td align="left">- 5.13 ± 2.98</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.042</bold><sup><bold>$</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">RR</td><td align="left">17.82 ± 1.30</td><td align="left">16.48 ± 0.78</td><td align="left"><p>- 1.34</p><p> ± 0.12</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.041</td><td align="left"><p>17.80</p><p> ± 1.34</p></td><td align="left"><p>16.82</p><p> ± 6.98</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.98</p><p> ± 2.14</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.214</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spo<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><p>96.65%</p><p> ± 1.78</p></td><td align="left"><p>97.98%</p><p> ± 1.96</p></td><td align="left"> + 1.33% ± 0.25</td><td char="." align="char">0.032</td><td align="left">96.22% ± 2.89</td><td align="left">96.78% ± 0.87</td><td align="left"> + 0.56% ± 0.29</td><td char="." align="char">0.367</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MDAS</td><td align="left"><p>7.43</p><p> ± 0.121</p></td><td align="left">5.22 ± 0.54</td><td align="left">- 2.21 ± 0.13</td><td char="." align="char">0.012</td><td align="left"><p>7.73</p><p> ± 0.15</p></td><td align="left"><p>7.30</p><p> ± 0.98</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.43</p><p> ± 0.21</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.340</td></tr><tr><td align="left">STAI</td><td align="left"><p>75.54</p><p> ± 10.65</p></td><td align="left"><p>70.84</p><p> ± 9.91</p></td><td align="left">- 4.7 ± 8.60</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td><td align="left">76.58 ± 11.12</td><td align="left"><p>76.02</p><p> ± 0.87</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0. 56</p><p> ± 0.43</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.653</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pain score</td><td align="left">89.78 ± 1.23</td><td align="left"><p>80.96</p><p> ± 0.87</p></td><td align="left">- 8.82 ± 3.34</td><td char="." align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">93.21 ± 2.23</td><td align="left"><p>90.84</p><p> ± 4.76</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 2.37</p><p> ± 0.67</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.087</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SD</italic> Standard Deviation, <italic>SBP</italic> Systolic Blood Pressure, <italic>DBP</italic> Diastolic Blood Pressure, <italic>HR</italic> Heart Rate, <italic>RR</italic> Respiratory Rate, <italic>Spo</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub> Oxygen saturation, <italic>MDAS</italic> Modified Dental Anxiety Scale, <italic>STAI</italic> Speilberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analog Scale</p><p><sup>*</sup>Not Significant</p><p><sup>$</sup>Significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The amount of change in vital signs, anxiety, and pain scores between the first and second phases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameters</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Lavender Group (Mean ± SD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Control Group(Mean ± SD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>- Value</th><th align="left" colspan="3">ANOVA test</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Coefficient</th><th align="left">95% CI</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SBP changes</td><td align="left">- 7.4 ± 12.34</td><td align="left">-5.23 ± 11.24</td><td char="." align="char">0.124</td><td align="left">- 2.9</td><td align="left">-8.5, 2.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBP changes</td><td align="left">- 1.2 ± 10.25</td><td align="left">-0.76 ± 10.54</td><td char="." align="char">0.231</td><td align="left">- 1.5</td><td align="left">-3.5, 5.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HR changes</td><td align="left">- 7.35 ± 9.21</td><td align="left">-5.13 ± 2.98</td><td char="." align="char">0.063</td><td align="left">- 2.4</td><td align="left">- 5.7, 1.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RR changes</td><td align="left">- 1.34 ± 0.12</td><td align="left">-0.98 ± 2.14</td><td char="." align="char">0.240</td><td align="left">- 0.9</td><td align="left">- 1.7,0.03</td><td char="." align="char">0.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spo<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"> + 1.33% ± 0.25</td><td align="left"> + 0.56% ± 0.29</td><td char="." align="char">0.154</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">1.3, 0.21</td><td char="." align="char">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MDAS changes</td><td align="left">- 2.21 ± 0.13</td><td align="left">-0.43 ± 0.21</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.021</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><bold>- 3.4</bold><sup><bold>^</bold></sup></td><td align="left">-5.7,—0.8</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.014</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">STAI changes</td><td align="left">- 4.7 ± 8.60</td><td align="left">-0. 56 ± 0.43</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.023</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><bold>- 4.2</bold><sup><bold>^</bold></sup></td><td align="left">- 6.9,—0.9</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.012</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pain score changes</td><td align="left">- 8.82 ± 3.34</td><td align="left">- 2.37 ± 0.67</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.012</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><bold>- 2.4</bold><sup><bold>^</bold></sup></td><td align="left">- 4.7,—0.5</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.023</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SD</italic> Standard Deviation, <italic>SBP</italic> Systolic Blood Pressure, <italic>DBP</italic> Diastolic Blood Pressure, <italic>HR</italic> Heart Rate, <italic>RR</italic> Respiratory Rate, <italic>Spo</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub> Oxygen saturation, <italic>MDAS</italic> Modified Dental Anxiety Scale, <italic>STAI</italic> Speilberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analog Scale</p><p><sup>*</sup> Significant ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; <italic>95% CI</italic> 95% confidence interval</p><p><sup>^</sup> The pleasant scent of the lavender significantly reduced the MDAS, STAI, and pain scores 3.4, 4.2, and 2.4 more than the control group, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Changes in anxiety and pain scores at the end of dental procedures</title>
                <p id="Par18">Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> compares the second and third phases of the research. The lavender aromatherapy improved all parameters better than the distal water, but the differences were only significant for anxiety, pain intensity, and SBP. At the end of the dental procedures, lavender aromatherapy reduced scores by 1.2 (for MDAS), 2.2 (for STAI), and 1.4 (for pain intensity) times more than the control group (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). Those findings revealed that the olfactory aromatherapy had the greatest effect in the waiting room.<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of the study’ variables between the second and third phases of the study within each group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Lavender Group (Mean ± SD)</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Control Group (Mean ± SD)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Phase II</th><th align="left">Phase III</th><th align="left">Change</th><th align="left">P- value</th><th align="left">Phase 2</th><th align="left">Phase 3</th><th align="left">Change</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SBP</td><td align="left">133.16 ± 12.20</td><td align="left">130.34 ± 1.23</td><td align="left">-2.82 ± 0.03</td><td char="." align="char">0.031<sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><p>137.09</p><p> ± 10.04</p></td><td align="left"><p>135.85</p><p> ± 1.34</p></td><td align="left">- 1.24 ± 1.29</td><td char="." align="char">0.153</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBP</td><td align="left"><p>78.43</p><p> ± 6.87</p></td><td align="left"><p>77.98</p><p> ± 0.98</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.55</p><p> ± 0.25</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.132</td><td align="left"><p>77.69</p><p> ± 9.98</p></td><td align="left"><p>77.25</p><p> ± 0.23</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.44</p><p> ± 0.94</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.165</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HR</td><td align="left">69.26 ± 7.76</td><td align="left"><p>68.84</p><p> ± 0.43</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.42</p><p> ± 0.81</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.061</td><td align="left"><p>71.68</p><p> ± 5.67</p></td><td align="left"><p>70.68</p><p> ± 0.23</p></td><td align="left">- 1.00 ± 0.58</td><td char="." align="char">0.252</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RR</td><td align="left"><p>16.48</p><p> ± 0.78</p></td><td align="left"><p>16.12</p><p> ± 0.96</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.36</p><p> ± 0.12</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.101</td><td align="left"><p>16.82</p><p> ± 6.98</p></td><td align="left"><p>16.21</p><p> ± 0.36</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.61</p><p> ± 0.14</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.143</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spo<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><p>97.98%</p><p> ± 1.96</p></td><td align="left"><p>98.23%</p><p> ± 0.34</p></td><td align="left"> + 0.25% ± 0.25</td><td char="." align="char">0.112</td><td align="left">96.78% ± 0.87</td><td align="left"><p>96.99%</p><p> ± 0.75</p></td><td align="left"> + 0.21% ± 0.26</td><td char="." align="char">0.367</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MDAS</td><td align="left"><p>5.22</p><p> ± 0.54</p></td><td align="left"><p>3.47</p><p> ± 0.84</p></td><td align="left">- 1.75 ± 0.13</td><td char="." align="char">0.012<sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><p>7.30</p><p> ± 0.98</p></td><td align="left"><p>6.96</p><p> ± 0.57</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.34</p><p> ± 0.21</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.140</td></tr><tr><td align="left">STAI</td><td align="left"><p>70.84</p><p> ± 9.91</p></td><td align="left">66.41 ± 0.35</td><td align="left">- 4.43 ± 8.60</td><td char="." align="char">0.001<sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><p>76.02</p><p> ± 0.87</p></td><td align="left"><p>75.45</p><p> ± 0.85</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 0.57</p><p> ± 0.63</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.136</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pain score</td><td align="left"><p>80.96</p><p> ± 0.87</p></td><td align="left"><p>69.31</p><p> ± 0.42</p></td><td align="left">- 11.56 ± 0.25</td><td char="." align="char">0.003<sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><p>90.84</p><p> ± 4.76</p></td><td align="left"><p>89.14</p><p> ± 0.64</p></td><td align="left"><p>- 1.7</p><p> ± 0.37</p></td><td char="." align="char">0.077</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SD</italic> Standard Deviation, <italic>SBP</italic> Systolic Blood Pressure, <italic>DBP</italic> Diastolic Blood Pressure, <italic>HR</italic> Heart Rate, <italic>RR</italic> Respiratory Rate, <italic>Spo</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub> Oxygen saturation, <italic>MDAS</italic> Modified Dental Anxiety Scale, <italic>STAI</italic> Speilberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analog Scale</p><p><sup>*</sup>Significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Percentage of changes in the vital signs, anxiety and pain scores of the study’s groups between second and third phases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameters</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Lavender Group (Mean ± SD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Control Group (Mean ± SD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>- Value</th><th align="left" colspan="3">ANOVA test</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Coefficient</th><th align="left">95% CI</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SBP changes</td><td align="left">-2.82 ± 0.03</td><td align="left">- 1.24 ± 1.29</td><td align="left">.241</td><td align="left">- 2.9</td><td align="left">-6.5, 1.8</td><td align="left">.323</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBP changes</td><td align="left">- 0.55 ± 0.25</td><td align="left">- 0.44 ± 0.94</td><td align="left">.131</td><td align="left">- 1.5</td><td align="left">-1.4, 6.6</td><td align="left">.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HR changes</td><td align="left">- 0.42 ± 0.81</td><td align="left">- 1.00 ± 0.58</td><td align="left">.073</td><td align="left">- 2.4</td><td align="left">- 3.4, 1.4</td><td align="left">.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RR changes</td><td align="left">- 0.36 ± 0.12</td><td align="left">- 0.61 ± 0.14</td><td align="left">.140</td><td align="left">- 0.9</td><td align="left">- 1.5,0.08</td><td align="left">.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spo<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"> + 0.25% ± 0.25</td><td align="left"> + 0.21% ± 0.26</td><td align="left">.104</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">1.3, 0.21</td><td align="left">.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MDAS changes</td><td align="left">- 1.75 ± 0.13</td><td align="left">- 0.34 ± 0.21</td><td align="left"><bold>.031</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><bold>- 1.2</bold><sup><bold>^</bold></sup></td><td align="left">-2.4,—0.4</td><td align="left"><bold>.054</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">STAI changes</td><td align="left">- 4.43 ± 8.60</td><td align="left">- 0.57 ± 0.63</td><td align="left"><bold>0.013</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><bold>- 2.2</bold><sup><bold>^</bold></sup></td><td align="left">- 5.8,—0.4</td><td align="left"><bold>.022</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pain score changes</td><td align="left">- 11.56 ± 0.25</td><td align="left">- 1.7 ± 0.37</td><td align="left"><bold>0.012</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td><td align="left"><bold>- 1.4</bold><sup><bold>^</bold></sup></td><td align="left">- 2.7,—0.6</td><td align="left"><bold>.024</bold><sup><bold>*</bold></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SD</italic> Standard Deviation, <italic>SBP</italic> Systolic Blood Pressure, <italic>DBP</italic> Diastolic Blood Pressure, <italic>HR</italic> Heart Rate, <italic>RR</italic> Respiratory Rate, <italic>Spo</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub> Oxygen saturation, <italic>MDAS</italic> Modified Dental Anxiety Scale, <italic>STAI</italic> Speilberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analog Scale</p><p><sup>*</sup>Significant <italic>ANCOVA</italic> analysis of covariance, <italic>95% CI</italic> 95% confidence interval</p><p><sup>^</sup>The pleasant scent of the lavender significantly reduced the MDAS, STAI, and pain scores 1.2, 2.2, and 1.4 more than the control group, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec13">
                <title>Correlation between dental procedures and olfaction</title>
                <p id="Par19">Olfactory aromatherapy had a significant effect on pain perception and emotional changes associated with all dental procedures except cavity preparations, where the difference was insignificant (<italic>p</italic>-value = 0.10). Despite this, the <italic>p</italic>-value for pain intensity was 0.05, indicating marginal significance (Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>). Finally, olfactory aromatherapy significantly reduced postoperative pain (<italic>p</italic>-value = 0.02). Only 19 patients in the lavender group needed postoperative analgesics, compared to 48 in the control group.<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>The difference between the study’s groups in regard to the dental procedures and pain scores during dental settings (Phase IV)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Procedure</th><th align="left">Lavender Group</th><th align="left">Control Group</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Local Anesthesia:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Pain score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">33.45 ± 2.23</td><td align="left">47.32 ± 1.25</td><td align="left">0.041</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">-Anxiety level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Before</td><td align="left">Moderate anxiety</td><td align="left">Moderate anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> After</td><td align="left">Mild anxiety</td><td align="left">Moderate anxiety</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Crown preparations:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Pain score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">29.87 ± 2.15</td><td align="left">45.32 ± 2.35</td><td align="left">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">-Anxiety level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Before</td><td align="left">Mild anxiety</td><td align="left">Mild anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> After</td><td align="left">Low anxiety</td><td align="left">Mild anxiety</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Subgingival scaling</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Pain score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">21.54 ± 0.24</td><td align="left">27.32 ± 0.28</td><td align="left">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">-Anxiety level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Before</td><td align="left">Low Anxiety</td><td align="left">Low anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> After</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">Low anxiety</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Cavity preparations</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Pain score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">5.24 ± 0.46</td><td align="left">10.55 ± 0.32</td><td align="left">0.050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">-Anxiety level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Before</td><td align="left">Low anxiety</td><td align="left">Low anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.102<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> After</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Pulp extirpation</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Pain score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">4.36 ± 0.47</td><td align="left">7.32 ± 0.42</td><td align="left">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">-Anxiety level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Before</td><td align="left">Mild anxiety</td><td align="left">Mild anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> After</td><td align="left">No anxiety</td><td align="left">Low anxiety</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Extractions</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> -Pain score (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">21.46 ± 1.23</td><td align="left">45.49 ± 0.23</td><td align="left">0.021</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">-Anxiety level:</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Before</td><td align="left">Moderate anxiety</td><td align="left">Moderate anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> After</td><td align="left">Mild anxiety</td><td align="left">Moderate anxiety</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup><italic>*</italic></sup><italic>: None significant</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec14">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par20">Anxiety develops when patients are subjected to stressful situations, such as medical interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Our findings revealed that the anxiety associated with tooth extractions or receiving local anesthesia was greater than that associated with other dental procedures. This is consistent with other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The American Psychiatric Association classified dental anxiety as a blood-injection-injury phobia, which is consistent with our findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. This could be due to gag reflex, choking, injection action, inability to see what is going on inside the mouth, or a strong aversion to the sight or thought of blood, as reported by others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par21">In general, there is no difference between the study's findings and those of other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The overall findings of the study revealed that olfactory aromatherapy significantly reduces dental anxiety and pain intensity, resulting in better control of pain perception and emotional changes associated with dental visits. This is consistent with the findings of Paradopo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. At the end of the second phase of the study, olfactory aromatherapy reduced the MDAS and STAI by 3.4 and 4.2 times, respectively, compared to the control group. It is 2.4 times more effective than the control group in terms of pain intensity. At the end of the third phase of the study, olfaction aromatherapy reduced the MDAS, STAI, and pain intensity by 1.2, 2.2, and 1.4 times, respectively, compared to the control group. This implies that olfactory aromatherapy has a significant effect on both pain intensity and anxiety level, but it is more effective at reducing anxiety than pain intensity. Furthermore, prior to the start of dental treatment, olfactory aromatherapy has the greatest impact.</p>
              <p id="Par22">On the other hand, the study's findings contradict the results of Muzzarelli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] who stated that olfactory aromatherapy has no significant effect on anxiety levels. Furthermore, Kritsidima et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] concluded that, olfactory aromatherapy only affects the state anxiety and not the cognitive aspect of anxiety. As previously stated, state anxiety is a temporary emotional condition characterized by apprehension, tension, and fear about a specific temporary situation, whereas cognitive anxiety is associated with negative thoughts about this situation. State anxiety is characterized by muscle tension, increased heart rate, sweating, and a stressful feeling. In dental clinics, controlling state anxiety is more important than controlling cognitive anxiety, because controlling state anxiety enables dentists to control patients' behaviors on the spot, allowing them to perform dental procedures more successfully. Kritsidima et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] agreed with our findings, where they concluded that olfaction aromatherapy is used to reduce anxiety on the spot rather than as a treatment option.</p>
              <p id="Par23">Lavandula angustifolia (lavender essential oil), the main constituents of which are linalool and linalyl acetate, was used in our study to stimulate olfaction in patients. Linalool stimulates serotonin secretion in the brain, which acts as a sedative and improves the patient's mood. Linalyl acetate, on the other hand, is a narcotic that helps patients to control their behaviors. Both components act as anxiolytic, and thus lavender oil reduces anxiety in the patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, our explanation contradicts the findings of other authors, who stated that there is no evidence that pleasant odors have an inhibitory effect on anxiety, and the effect is still unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par24">Understanding the physiology of emotional responses to different stimuli, as well as how the anxiety develops in humans, could aid in explaining the findings of our study. Olfaction, like any other sensory stimuli, affects the limbic system in the brain, which regulates emotional changes either positive or negative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The amygdala is a part of the limbic system which is an important mediator of many aspects of emotional behaviors. It is responsible for processing positive emotions such as happiness, and negative ones such as fear and anxiety. Amygdala is activated by sensory stimulation, specifically the olfactory, auditory, and visual cortices. Anatomically, the olfactory bulb is intimately and directly connected to the amygdala. As a result, pleasant or unpleasant odors have a greater impact on human emotional responses than other sensory sensations because of its effect on the amygdala [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par25">If the odors are anxious, the amygdala stimulates the hypothalamus, which stimulates the pituitary gland, which stimulates the adrenal gland to secrete stress hormones (adrenaline, noradrenaline, catecholamines, and corticosteroids). Stress hormones are responsible for the fight-or-flight response, which protects the body from anxious stimuli. Cortisol also makes the patient more alert and sensitive to stimulation. If the stimulus is chronic and persistent, anxiety will develop as a result of the constant release of stress hormones, resulting in negative behavioral and emotional responses. Anxiety is also experienced as a result of sustained cortisol secretion, which inhibits serotonin secretion. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par26">On the other hand, the pleasant sent activates olfactory receptor cells connected to the olfactory bulb, which then sends signals to the amygdala and olfactory cortex. These activities cause the amygdala to initiate good memories, resulting in the release of anxiolytic neurotransmitters such as endorphins and serotonin, which improve mood and produce sedation. Furthermore, the pleasant sent reduces anxiety by inhibiting stress hormone secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Moreover, Bombail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] reported that pleasant odors produce anxiolytic effects in the brain by altering the gamma-aminobutyric acid receptors, similar to benzodiazepines, which are anxiolytic substances. Additionally, other authors claim that pleasant odors cause relaxation by modulating the adenosine monophosphate cycle, which is responsible for sedation and relaxation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. All of the aforementioned methods indicate that olfaction has a significant impact on the anxiety production system in the brain via a variety of mechanisms.</p>
              <p id="Par27">In terms of pain perception, the study's findings revealed that olfaction aromatherapy significantly reduces the intensity of pain and eliminates the need for postoperative analgesics, as also reported by Moss et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. This could be due to the ability of the pleasant sent to regulate the cognition, mood, and behavior of patients. Controlling those emotional changes and anxiety raises the pain threshold, which reduces pain perception. Many authors have shown that mental stress affects the physiological frameworks of the body by increasing cortisol production in the blood. Cortisol also makes patients more aware of their surroundings, which increases pain perception in the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. As a result, we believe that reducing anxiety indirectly decreases pain perception. According to the American Psychological Association, the nervous system is intimately connected to the stress-anxiety system in the body. Stress and anxiety, as a result, influence pain perception and cause hyperalgesia, which exaggerates pain. In contrast, other authors stated that the effect of pleasant odor is limited to anxiety levels and has no effect on pain perception. This is because it only provides relaxation and not analgesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par28">Regarding hemodynamic changes, the inhalation of the olfactory aromatherapy was significantly improving all the vital signs, except DBP. The same finding was also reported by Stanley et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. On the other hand, other authors found that its effect is only limited to SBP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. This controversy could be due to the difference between studies regarding the type of the inhaled oil, its concentration, and inhalation period. This authors’ explanation is in agreement with the opinion of Ebrahimi et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par29">The clinical importance of our study is that, up to our knowledge, it is the first study that predict to what extent the olfactory aromatherapy affects anxiety and pain perception during dental settings. Furthermore, because of the study's design and intervention, the findings could be generalized. Moreover, the findings of this study may encourage dentists to consider using lavender oil aromatherapy as a simple complementary therapy in dental settings to reduce dental anxiety and pain and avoid the risks of anxiolytic drugs. Those drugs have drawbacks, such as abuse/dependence liability, amnesia, clinical effect delay, sedation, and dizziness, all of which affect clinical adherence. Also, olfactory aromatherapy is a simple, inexpensive, non-invasive technique with few side effects, can be used to manage anxiety and pain in medical settings.</p>
              <p id="Par30">The study has some limitations, such as a small sample size, and the patients were treated by a variety of dentists who took different approaches to their patients' behavior and attitudes. Furthermore, the results of the study were obtained via a questionnaire, which had drawbacks. It has been demonstrated that the patient's mode influences his or her responses to questions. Despite this, our study has many strengths, such as the absence of confounders such as age, gender, and time lapse. Its preferred random control trial design, as well as the fact that it is a single institutional study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec15">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="Par31">Our findings suggest that olfactory enrichment and conditioning through a pleasant scent could be used to provide positive emotional responses and reduce pain perception in dental patients. After inhaling the pleasant scent, it can reduce dental anxiety by three to four times and pain by two times more than the control group. It also significantly reduces fear of dental procedures with moderate pain and anxiety scores, such as tooth extractions and the administration of local anesthesia. As a result, it can be used in conjunction with analgesics and anxiolytics to alleviate pain perception and dental anxiety.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Information</title>
              <sec id="Sec16">
                <p>
                  <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
                    <media xlink:href="12903_2023_2864_MOESM1_ESM.docx">
                      <caption>
                        <p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> Questionnaire.</p>
                      </caption>
                    </media>
                  </supplementary-material>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Not applicable</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>SMA and GAK designed the study. SAA and HSA performed data collection and sample measurements. SMA and GAK analyzed the data. SAA and HSA drafted and revised the paper. All authors approved the final manuscript for submission.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>The authors disclose that there is no financial support of any kind to the research.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar1">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par32">The necessary permissions from the practitioner colleagues and informed consent from patients were obtained; Dental Ethical Committee, College of Dentistry, Qassim University, Saudi Arabia, approved the study on 20/3/2018. The study was retrospectively registered on 11/5/2022 at the clinicalTrials.gov, and its Identifier is NCT05369936.</p>
                <p id="Par33">This study was carried out in accordance with the code of ethics of the World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki, and patients or the next of kin of the patients were informed and gave written informed consent.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar2">
                <title>Consent for publication</title>
                <p id="Par34">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par35">The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/ or publication of this article.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hawkins</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of music listening to reduce preprocedural dental anxiety in special needs patients</article-title>
                  <source>Complement Ther Clin Pract</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>101279</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctcp.2020.101279</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33388728?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33388728</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caltabiano</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Croker</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Page</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental anxiety in patients attending a student dental clinic</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-018-0507-5</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29558935?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29558935</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ainscough</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Windsor</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tahmassebi</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A review of the effect of music on dental anxiety in children</article-title>
                  <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <lpage>26</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40368-018-0380-6</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30374854?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30374854</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Appukuttan</surname>
                      <given-names>DP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Strategies to manage patients with dental anxiety and dental phobia: literature review</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Cosmet Investig Dent</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <lpage>50</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/ccide.s63626</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crego</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carrillo-Díaz</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Armfield</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Romero</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>From public mental health to community oral health: the impact of dental anxiety and fear on dental status</article-title>
                  <source>Front Public Health</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olivieri</surname>
                      <given-names>JG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de España</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Encinas</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental anxiety, fear, and root canal treatment monitoring of heart rate and oxygen saturation in patients treated during the Coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic: an observational clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <lpage>195</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2020.10.024</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33161001?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33161001</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Haperen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Preckel</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eberl</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Indications, contraindications, and safety aspects of procedural sedation</article-title>
                  <source>Curr Opin Anaesthesiol</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>769</fpage>
                  <lpage>775</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/aco.0000000000000777</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31389805?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31389805</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Waldron </surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nunn </surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mac Giolla Phadraig</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Oral hygiene interventions for people with intellectual disabilities</article-title>
                  <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev </source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>31 </volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>CD012628</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of aromatherapy on preoperative anxiety in adult patients: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>
                  <source>Complement Ther Clin Pract</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>101302</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctcp.2021.101302</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33445147?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33445147</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gazerani</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarchahi</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abavisani</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of inhalation aromatherapy of geranium on pain and physiological indices after appendectomy: a double-blind randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Surg Open</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <lpage>49</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijso.2020.12.004</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Erkilic</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kesimci</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soykut</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doger</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gumus</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kanbak</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Factors associated with preoperative anxiety levels of Turkish surgical patients: from a single center in Ankara</article-title>
                  <source>Patient Prefer Adherence</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <lpage>296</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/ppa.s127342</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>SY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yi</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between anxiety and pain in dental treatment: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>162</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034516678168</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28106507?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28106507</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matthias</surname>
                      <given-names>AT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samarasekera</surname>
                      <given-names>DN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Preoperative anxiety in surgical patients - experience of a single unit</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Anaesthesiol Taiwan</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aat.2012.02.004</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22500906?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500906</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pradopo</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinaredi</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Januarisca</surname>
                      <given-names>BV</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pandan Leaves (Pandanus Amaryllifolius) aromatherapy and relaxation music to reduce dental anxiety of pediatric patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Int Dent Med Res</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>933</fpage>
                  <lpage>937</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stanley</surname>
                      <given-names>PF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wan</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karim</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A randomized prospective placebo-controlled study of the effects of lavender aromatherapy on preoperative anxiety in cataract surgery patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Perianesth Nurs</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>403</fpage>
                  <lpage>406</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jopan.2019.12.004</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32178950?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32178950</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Armfield</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heaton</surname>
                      <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Management of fear and anxiety in the dental clinic: a review</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Dent J</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>58</volume>
                  <fpage>390</fpage>
                  <lpage>531</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/adj.12118</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24320894?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24320894</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aydinoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arslan</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Are anxiety and the presence of siblings risk factors for dental neglect and oral health status in children?</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Pediatr</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <lpage>128</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arcped.2020.12.005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33455845?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33455845</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seligman</surname>
                      <given-names>LD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hovey</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chacon</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ollendick</surname>
                      <given-names>TH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dental anxiety: an understudied problem in youth</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Psychol Rev</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>55</volume>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <lpage>40</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2017.04.004</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28478271?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28478271</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Armfield</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Towards a better understanding of dental anxiety and fear: cognitions vs. experiences</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>118</volume>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <lpage>264</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0722.2010.00740.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20572859?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20572859</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ebrahimi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mardani</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Basirinezhad</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamidzadeh</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eskandari</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of Lavender and Chamomile essential oil inhalation aromatherapy on depression, anxiety and stress in older community-dwelling people: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Explore (NY)</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <lpage>278</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.explore.2020.12.012</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33454232?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33454232</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guo</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effectiveness of aromatherapy on preoperative anxiety in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Nurs Stud</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>111</volume>
                  <fpage>103747</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103747</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32861206?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32861206</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yeo</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hong</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeon</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of lavender oil on stress, bispectral index values, and needle insertion pain in volunteers</article-title>
                  <source>J Altern Complement Med</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>823</fpage>
                  <lpage>826</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/acm.2010.0644</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21854199?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21854199</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Premkumar</surname>
                      <given-names>KS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aafaque </surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sumalsa </surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Narendan</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of aromatherapy on dental anxiety among orthodontic patients: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Cureus</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>e5306</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31592362</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nasiri</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torkaman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feizi</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bigdeli Shamloo</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of aromatherapy with Damask rose on alleviating adults' acute pain severity: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>
                  <source>Complement Ther Med</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <fpage>102596</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctim.2020.102596</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33197671?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33197671</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muzzarelli</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Force</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sebold</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Aromatherapy and reducing preprocedural anxiety: A controlled prospective study</article-title>
                  <source>Gastroenterol Nurs</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>466</fpage>
                  <lpage>471</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001610-200611000-00005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17273013?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17273013</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kritsidima</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Newton</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asimakopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of lavender scent on dental patient anxiety levels: a cluster randomized-controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <lpage>87</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0528.2009.00511.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19968674?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19968674</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malcolm</surname>
                      <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tallian</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Essential oil of lavender in anxiety disorders: ready for prime time?</article-title>
                  <source>Ment Health Clin</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <lpage>155</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9740/mhc.2017.07.147</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29955514?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29955514</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karadag</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samancioglu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ozden</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bakir</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of aromatherapy on sleep quality and anxiety of patients</article-title>
                  <source>Nurs Crit Care</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <lpage>112</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nicc.12198</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26211735?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26211735</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Filiptsova</surname>
                      <given-names>OV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gazzavi-Rogozina</surname>
                      <given-names>LV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Timoshyna</surname>
                      <given-names>IA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naboka </surname>
                      <given-names>OI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dyomina</surname>
                      <given-names> YeV, </given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ochkur </surname>
                      <given-names>AV</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of the essential oils of lavender and rosemary on the human short-term memory</article-title>
                  <source>Alex J Med</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume> 54</volume>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Babaev</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Piletti Chatain</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krueger-Burg</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inhibition in the amygdala anxiety circuitry</article-title>
                  <source>Exp Mol Med</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>16</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s12276-018-0063-8</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29628509?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628509</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bombail</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Perception and emotions: on the relationships between stress and olfaction</article-title>
                  <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>212</volume>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <lpage>108</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applanim.2018.12.013</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jerath</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crawford</surname>
                      <given-names>MW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barnes</surname>
                      <given-names>VA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harden</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-regulation of breathing as a primary treatment for anxiety</article-title>
                  <source>Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <lpage>115</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10484-015-9279-8</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25869930?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25869930</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharifi-Rad</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sureda</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tenore</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Biological activities of essential oils: from plant chemoecology to traditional healing systems</article-title>
                  <source>Molecules</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules22010070</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28045446?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28045446</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moss</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cook</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wesnes</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duckett</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Aromas of rosemary and lavender essential oils differentially affect cognition and mood in healthy adults</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Neurosci</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>113</volume>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <lpage>38</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207450390161903</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12690999?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12690999</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baskran</surname>
                      <given-names>RNR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lakshmanan</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of effect of chamomile oil on dental anxiety for patients undergoing extraction? a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Drug Invention Today</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>1875</fpage>
                  <lpage>1879</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nardarajah</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dhanraj</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jain</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of lavender aromatherapy on anxiety levels of patients undergoing mandibular third molar extraction</article-title>
                  <source>Drug Invent Today</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>1318</fpage>
                  <lpage>1322</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bikmoradi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seifi</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poorolajal</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Araghchian</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Safiaryan</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oshvandi</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of inhalation aromatherapy with lavender essential oil on stress and vital signs in patients undergoing coronary artery bypass surgery: a single-blinded randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Complement Ther Med</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
                  <lpage>338</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctim.2014.12.001</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26051567?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26051567</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
