<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:42:53Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8425377" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8425377</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jips</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Indian Prosthodont Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Indian Prosthodont Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIPS</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>The Journal of the Indian Prosthodontic Society</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0972-4052</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1998-4057</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer - Medknow</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8425377</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8425377</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8425377</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34380811</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34380811</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JIPS-21-249</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jips.jips_98_21</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Speech intelligibility, nasal resonance, and swallowing ability of maxillectomy patients with customized obturator: A non randomized controlled study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Grover</surname>
                    <given-names>Rohan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jurel</surname>
                    <given-names>Sunit Kumar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Agarwal</surname>
                    <given-names>Bhaskar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rao</surname>
                    <given-names>Jitendra</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kapoor</surname>
                    <given-names>Saumya</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mishra</surname>
                    <given-names>Niraj</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Singh</surname>
                    <given-names>Balendra Pratap</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1">Department of Prosthodontics, Crown and Bridge, Faculty of Dental Sciences, King George's Medical University, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Balendra Pratap Singh, Department of Prosthodontics, Crown and Bridge, Faculty of Dental Sciences, King George's Medical University, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="balendra02@yahoo.com">balendra02@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Jul-Sep</season>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>21</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>249</fpage>
              <lpage>255</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>17</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>30</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2021 The Journal of Indian Prosthodontic Society</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="st1">
                  <title>Aim:</title>
                  <p>To compare speech intelligibility (SI), nasal resonance, and swallowing ability in maxillectomy patients with a customized obturator to the conventional obturator.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st2">
                  <title>Settings and Design:</title>
                  <p>Non-randomized controlled study.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st3">
                  <title>Materials and Methods:</title>
                  <p>Forty-eight maxillectomy patients were recruited and assessment of SI, nasal resonance, and swallowing ability was done at three situations: without obturator, with conventional obturator, and with customized obturator. Recordings of unrehearsed conversation, counting from number 1–20 and four sets of Chapel Hill Multilingual Intelligibility Test in the Hindi language were used to assess SI and nasal resonance. SI was evaluated by untrained listeners and graded according to a 6-point scale. Nasal resonance was evaluated by speech pathologists on a 7-point scale of severity. Swallowing ability was evaluated by water drinking test.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st4">
                  <title>Statistical Analysis Used:</title>
                  <p>One-way ANOVA, <italic>Post hoc</italic> Bonferroni and Chi square test.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st5">
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>SI and nasal resonance showed a statistically significant difference between any two groups (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Water drinking time was significantly different between without obturator and with customized obturator (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), but the difference was not statistically significant between without obturator and with obturator (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.004).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st6">
                  <title>Conclusion:</title>
                  <p>SI, nasal resonance, and swallowing ability improved with customized obturator in comparison to the conventional obturator.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords:</title>
                <kwd>Clinical trial</kwd>
                <kwd>deglutition</kwd>
                <kwd>drinking</kwd>
                <kwd>oral cancer</kwd>
                <kwd>prosthesis</kwd>
                <kwd>speech intelligibility</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Carcinomas involving the maxilla could be a primary tumor or they could invade from adjacent structures.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] In most cases, because of late-onset of symptoms or late diagnosis, management involves hemi-maxillectomy. The resultant defect affects the speech, mastication, facial aesthetics, and psychological health of the patient.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Rehabilitation of such patients can be done either prosthetically or surgically.</p>
              <p>Obturator is a maxillofacial prosthesis that reinstates the integrity of the hard palate and separates the oral cavity from the nasal cavity, maxillary sinus, and orbit[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] thereby restoring the compromised oronasal functions. Many studies report an improvement in the quality of life after the use of an obturator.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] However, few problems that are often associated with obturator prostheses are hypernasality, deficits in speech, food, and liquids escaping through the nasal cavity, impaired swallowing, and mastication.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] It has been observed that among the majority of patients the obturator is not able to restore the speech and swallowing function to the presurgical level.</p>
              <p>A modification that improves a patient's swallowing and phonetics is the customization of the palatal surface of a prosthesis with a palatogram.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] A palatogram is a graphic representation of the area of the palate contacted by the tongue during specified activity, usually speech (GPT 9).[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</p>
              <p>This study was planned to assess the effect of customized definitive obturator with a palatogram on speech intelligibility (SI), nasal resonance, and swallowing ability in maxillectomy patients. We hypothesized that customizing the palatal contours of the obturator would help in improving the tongue palate contact allowing the tongue to establish contact with the palate in a more habitual and customary position.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2">
              <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
              <p>This study was conducted from April 2014 to October 2018 at a tertiary care medical University in the northern part of India. Ethical approval was taken from the Institutional ethical committee (3698/ethics/R. Cell-14). All patients were asked to sign informed consent as per the Declaration of Helsinki. The sample size for this controlled before-and-after study was calculated to be 48, using 5% as anticipated proportion in the population, level of significance at .05, and absolute precision of 8% in formula <italic>n</italic> = z<sup>2</sup><sub>1−</sub><sub>α</sub><sub>/2</sub>p (1 − p) d<sup>2</sup>. Patients were recruited in the study before maxillectomy surgery.</p>
              <p>Inclusion criteria were:</p>
              <p>
                <list list-type="order">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Male and female patients between 18 and 70 years of age</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Patients scheduled to undergo the maxillectomy surgery</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Dentate or partially dentate patients</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Ability to follow the command given during the study</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
              <p>Exclusion criteria were</p>
              <p>
                <list list-type="order">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Patients unable to wear obturator postsurgery</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Recurrence or active malignancy</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Restricted mouth opening i.e., &lt;15 mm.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
              <p>Seventy-four patients were recruited but twenty-six were excluded due to various reasons before giving definitive obturator [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>]. The remaining forty-eight patients who were fit to wear stable definitive maxillary obturator prosthesis were followed and included 17 females and 31 males. Surgeons were asked to line the reflected cheek flap with split-thickness skin graft after maxillectomy as it improves tolerance and retention of the obturator. It was also advised to keep the bony resection trans-alveolar. Different phases of obturator were given from surgical to interim with soft liner and finally definitive obturator. Definitive obturator was fabricated with open bulb design[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and followed basic prosthodontics principles of removable dental prosthesis in cobalt-chromium alloy. All clinical steps were done by two Prosthodontists having more than 6 years of experience. When patients were free from postinsertion problems of definitive obturator for at least 3 months, outcomes were assessed. SI, nasal resonance, and swallowing ability were assessed in patients at three situations: without obturator, with conventional definitive obturator, and with customized obturator.</p>
              <p>Speech stimuli of patients were recorded with and without definitive obturator, in a noiseless room using a head-mounted omnidirectional microphone (SM 10A, Shure, IL, USA), with the distance of 12 cm between the patient mouth and microphone. Speech recordings included unrehearsed conversation for 30 sec. and arithmetic counting from number 1 to 20, both in the native language and four sets of words from Chapel Hill Multilingual Intelligibility Test (CHMIT) in the Hindi language.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Recorded samples were randomly edited using personal computer-based analysis audacity software (Open-source software, GNU Public License). The assessment was made by three untrained listeners and three speech-language pathologists experienced in the field of rehabilitation of patients with head and neck cancer for evaluation of SI and nasal resonance.</p>
              <p>SI depends on the correct identification of words immediately after listening to the recording. It was evaluated by listeners by grading the recording according to 6-point scale from 1 to 6, score “1” exhibited normal, and “6” exhibited severely impaired speech.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Nasal resonance was evaluated only by speech pathologists based on 7-point scale of severity given by Darley <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] where 1 and 7 denote normal to very severe deviation from normal, respectively.</p>
              <p>Water drinking test[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] was performed twice by each patient (with-and-without obturator) to assess swallowing ability. Patient was advised to drink 30 ml of water in a single swallow. The profile of the patient while drinking was categorized in grading as illustrated in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and the time required for drinking that is from the moment when water was poured into the mouth to when the larynx returned to original position, was recorded with a stopwatch. The behavior and episode during water drinking test were also observed and characterized as illustrated in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. This allowed both quantitative and qualitative assessment of the swallowing ability.</p>
              <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Categories of the profile of patients according to water drinking test[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Profile grading</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In a single swallow and within 5 s water is drunk without cough</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suspected disability</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In single or multiple swallow water is drunk without cough but in more than 5 s</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disability</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water is drunk but always accompanied by a cough</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Categorization of behavior and episode during water drinking test[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behaviour</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Episode</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural drinking: Able to drink water without a problem</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drooling: Drooling of water from the mouth</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucking: Sucking water (sip and/or suck in)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal leakage: Leaking of water into the nose</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holding: Holding water in the mouth</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compulsory drinking: Drinking water compulsorily with unnatural head posture</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Careful drinking: Drinking water carefully</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The next phase of the study involved the fabrication of customized obturator with tissue conditioner Tissue conditioner mixed with bio-grade red-colored indicating material (Okklean; DFS Diamon, Germany) was coated on palatal surface, and the patient was instructed to say “so-so” with mouth widely open.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Obtained palatogram was compared with palatogram given by normal individual for alphabet “S” [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. If the anterior region of the palate was under contoured, it was depicted by uninterrupted, continuous area between the posterior wet region [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>]. Whereas over contoured palate exhibited a wholly wet anterior palatal region [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>]. The region requiring correction was marked with a pencil and the acrylic portion was roughened with a tungsten carbide bur (Waldent Carbide Burs WL-1, India) while cobalt-chromium surface was sandblasted to aid bonding of acrylic to surface. When the marked region was thicker than 2 mm then it was thinned to approximately 2 mm while the surface &lt;2 mm was roughened.</p>
              <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Study flow chart</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-21-249-g001"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>“S” Sound palatogram</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-21-249-g002"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Region depicting inadequate contact of the anterior palate with the tongue</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-21-249-g003"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Palatogram showing overcontoured areas of the palate which requires thinning for proper phonetics</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="JIPS-21-249-g004"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Tissue-conditioning material (Super-soft, G. C. America Inc., USA) was prepared to a thick, viscous consistency by adding 25% more powder than instructed by the manufacturer and spread only on the marked area.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Obturator was placed in the patient's mouth and asked to read speech stimuli such as spontaneous conversation, counting, and four sets of words from the CHMIT in the Hindi language, for 5 min but at an increased speaking rate than normal. After initial polymerization of tissue conditioner obturator was removed from patient's mouth and depth of tissue conditioner was assessed with help of periodontal probe (GDC, Punjab, India) which served as guide for accurate palatal contouring. Obturator with tissue conditioning material was then invested in denture processing flask (Denture Flask Varsity Pattern, National Dental Supply Company, Delhi, India) with the area of tissue conditioner was left uncovered in the first pour. After the plaster had completely set, two halves of flasks were separated, and tissue conditioning material was removed. The exposed metal surface which required correction was sandblasted and two coats of metal primer (GC Metal Primer-II, GC America, Inc., Alsip, IL) were applied to ensure chemical bonding of acrylic resin with cobalt-chromium alloy. Autopolymerising repair resin (DPI-RR Cold Cure, DPI, India) was mixed and placed on obturator to replace the tissue conditioner followed by a bench set.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] After complete polymerization of resin, the obturator was retrieved, finishing and polishing were done. This customized obturator was worn by the patient and speech was recorded and assessed for the third experimental situation.</p>
              <p>All speech recordings of three different experimental conditions were presented to listeners in a random manner so that listeners were not aware of recordings being presented. The tests for measuring swallowing ability were also repeated with customized obturator as described previously. Continuous variables were compared by one-way analysis of variance and the significance of mean difference within and between the groups was done by Bonferroni's <italic>post hoc</italic> multiple comparison tests. Categorical variables were compared by Chi-square test. <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. All analyses were performed on Statistical Packages for the Social Sciences (SPSS) (IBM Corp. Released 2012. IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 21.0. Armonk, NY: IBM Corp.).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Prevalence of Aramany class II defects was highest (50%) followed by Class I (27.08%). Majority of patients were in the age group 31–40 years (35.45%) and male (64.58%) [<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>]. Among all recruited patients, most cases (60.41%) were suffering from carcinomas and 25% cases were suffering from tumors, remaining 14.58% had undergone maxillectomy due to infections. Among 48 patients included in the present study, 22 patients (45.83%) underwent radiotherapy while 26 patients (54.16%) did not require radiotherapy post maxillary resection.</p>
              <table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Sociodemographic, clinical and treatment characteristics of patients</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients, <italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group (years)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 20-30</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 31-40</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (35.41)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 41-50</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.74)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 51-60</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (27.08)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 61-70</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (10.41)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (64.58)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (35.41)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Types of diseases</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Carcinoma</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (60.41)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tumor</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (25)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Infection</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (14.58)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiotherapy status</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (45.83)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (54.16)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aramanys’ classification</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Class I</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (27.08)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Class II</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (50.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Class III</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Class IV</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Class V</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.16)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Class VI</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (10.41)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <sec id="sec2-1">
                <title>Speech intelligibility</title>
                <p>Comparison of SI scores between three groups (measured by untrained and trained listeners-combined) showed a significant difference between any two groups: without obturator and with obturator (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001); without obturator and with customized obturator (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and with obturator and with customized obturator (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) [<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>].</p>
                <table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Comparison of speech intelligibility scores, nasal resonance scores and water drinking time among three groups (combined score measured by untrained and trained listeners)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Mean±SD<hr/></th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Bonferroni’s multiple comparison test<hr/></th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without obturator (<italic>n</italic>=48)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With obturator (<italic>n</italic>=48)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With customized obturator (<italic>n</italic>=48)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without obturator versus with obturator</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without obturator versus with customized obturator</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With obturator versus with customized obturator</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Speech intelligibility score</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6±0.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0±0.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7±0.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal resonance</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3±0.7</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6±0.8</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±0.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water drinking time</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3±4.8</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7±3.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2±1.5</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.004</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.468</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>SD: Standard deviation</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-2">
                <title>Nasal resonance</title>
                <p>Comparison of Nasal Resonance scores among three groups showed significantly different scores between any two groups (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) [<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-3">
                <title>Water drinking test</title>
                <p>Patients' profiles during water-drinking test in three groups showed statistically significant improvement between any two group (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) [<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>]. The customized obturator showed a significant reduction in mean drinking time compared to mean drinking time without obturator (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), but the difference in mean drinking time was not statistically significant between without obturator and with obturator (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.004) [<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>].</p>
                <table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Patients’ profile, patient’s behavior, and episodes during the water drinking test in three groups</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Profile</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without obturator (<italic>n</italic>=48), <italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With obturator (<italic>n</italic>=48), <italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With coustomized obturator (<italic>n</italic>=48), <italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
                        <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Water drinking test</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (50)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (62.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">19.27</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suspected disability</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (64.58)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (45.83)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (37.5)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disability</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (27.08)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.16)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Patient’s behavior during water drinking test</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal drinking</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (14.58)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (37.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (62.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">11.719</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt;0.003</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal drinking</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (85.41)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (62.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (37.5)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Episodes during the water drinking test</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural drinking</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (14.58)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (37.5 )</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (62.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">32.583</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucking</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.16)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.16)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holding</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.75)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.16)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compulsory drinking</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.75)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (12.52)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.16)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Careful drinking</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (41.66)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (29.16)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drooling</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (22.91)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.16)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal leakage</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (12.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Without prosthesis, 41 of 48 patients (85.41%) exhibited “Abnormal” behavior while only seven patients showed “Normal” drinking behavior. Behavior while water drinking improved significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.003) when the prosthesis was in place as eighteen patients (37.5%) showed normal drinking behavior with conventional obturator while thirty patients (62.5%) showed normal drinking behavior with customized obturator [<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>]. Drooling (22.9%), holding (18.75%), and compulsory drinking (18.75%) were the most common episodes observed when patients were not wearing obturator [<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>]. With conventional obturator, abnormal episodes reduced significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and it was observed that careful drinking (41.66%) and natural drinking (37.5%) were the most commonly occurring episodes while majority patients (62.5%) exhibited natural drinking behavior with the customized obturator.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Speech is produced by the configuration of various oral structures like teeth, lips, tongue and palate, pharynx, and larynx. When the tongue cannot articulate with the palate due to surgical resection it leads to distortion of sounds. The absence of proper tongue palate contact causes air to escape through the nasal cavity which leads to increased nasalance and misarticulation in the speech, making it unintelligible.</p>
              <p>SI assessment in this study revealed the least intelligibility when patients were not wearing obturator. This can be attributed to oronasal communication which alters oro-nasal resonance balance, and tongue palatal contacts, thereby reducing SI.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] Factors that can also be attributed to poor intelligibility are velopharyngeal incompetency, size of oronasal communications, and inclusion of soft palate.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] Improvement in SI after wearing both conventional and customized obturator is due to restoration of palatal continuity by obturator, allowing tongue-palate contacts and improving patient's speech.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] Customized obturator provided maximum improvement in SI score indicating that customized palatal contours provide more precise tongue palate contact resulting in an overall improvement in SI and nasal resonance.</p>
              <p>Nasalance of voice is affected by the coherence of various intra-oral structures known as articulators. If the integrity of these articulators is affected, it influences the resonance of voice.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] After maxillectomy, hypernasality of voice occurs due to escape of air through defect. Prosthetic rehabilitation reduces it to as near to normal levels as possible.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] High values of hypernasality were observed with decrease in SI while a significant reduction in hypernasality was noticed with clear speech (i.e., after use of prosthesis). Implying significant correlation between hypernasality and SI[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] because of which there was difficulty in the understanding speech of patients with high values of hypernasality. Comparison of nasal resonance scores in this study was done by trained listeners and it showed a significant difference in three experimental situations.</p>
              <p>Kumar <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] studied articulation and nasalance in patients who after maxillectomy were wearing hollow bulb obturator. They reported articulatory errors, most common being substitution and distortion in dental, dento-alveolar, affricates, and fricatives. The tongue has a customized position with palate to produce sounds, and due to resection of palate, this contact couldn't be established properly. The obturator restored palatal continuity, leading to reduction in distortion and substitution but not complete elimination implying that articulation is dependent on the tongue, hard palate, and their coordination.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] This was in accordance with our study as customized palatal contours provided for more precise tongue palate contact resulting in the overall improvement in SI and nasal resonance. Parameters such as vocal quality, pitch, rhythm, and inflection might have influenced the assessment of hypernasality by listeners. Bohle <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and Plank <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] had reported these parameters of articulation posing difficulty for listeners in differentiating speech resonance parameters from communication variables.</p>
              <p>It was also observed that in patients wearing customized obturator, mean drinking time was reduced significantly to as near to normal, signifying a quantitative improvement in swallowing ability. This was is agreement with Matsuyama <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and Jain <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] who have reported improvement in swallowing ability and speech after customization of the palatal surface by palatogram in denture and in obturator patients, respectively. In this study, drooling, holding and compulsory drinking were the most common episodes observed when the patient was not wearing obturator. With conventional obturator abnormal episodes reduced, and it was observed that careful drinking and natural drinking were the most commonly occurring episodes. Physical closure of oro-nasal communication might have directly affected this improvement of drinking behavior. After wearing customized obturator, majority patients (62.5%) had natural drinking patterns or showed careful drinking (29.10%). This signified a qualitative improvement in the swallowing ability of maxillectomy patients. The study exhibited quantitative and qualitative improvement in the swallowing ability of maxillectomy patients. This improvement in swallowing ability when wearing a customized obturator might contribute to the improved overall function of maxillectomy patients.</p>
              <p>Limitations of the study are not evaluating the effect of factors like the extent of surgical defect, radiotherapy, and other adjuvant treatment on outcomes of prosthetic rehabilitation. Swallowing rehabilitation has been evaluated via video-fluorography in head and neck cancer patients.[<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] However, video-fluorographic evaluation requires a special device and is extremely difficult to carry out chair-side and in regular clinical settings. Therefore, water drinking test was originally developed for dysphagia paralytica in cerebrovascular disease and was also applied in estimating improvement in swallowing ability of maxillectomy patients by Matsuyama <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] was used in this study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-5">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>Within limitations, the present study showed improvement in SI, decreased nasal resonance, and improved swallowing function in patients wearing customized obturators. These improvements can be attributed to palatogram patterns being drawn from these patients and customizing palatal contours of the obturator for each patient.</p>
              <sec id="sec2-4">
                <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
                <p>Nil.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-5" sec-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
                <p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgment</title>
              <p>The authors thank Prof. Vijay Kumar, Department of Surgical Oncology, KGMU, Lucknow for treatment and follow-up related to surgical procedures.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="ref1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Masuda</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kida</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ohtani</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Oral rehabilitation by prosthetic restoration after maxillectomy for malignant tumors</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Oral Surg</source>
                  <year>1979</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>356</fpage>
                  <lpage>62</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">94595</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Said</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otomaru</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aimaijiang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taniguchi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between masticatory function and oral health-related quality of life in partial maxillectomy patients</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>561</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27824974</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dos Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Caxias</surname>
                      <given-names>FP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bitencourt</surname>
                      <given-names>SB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Turcio</surname>
                      <given-names>KH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pesqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goiato</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Oral rehabilitation of patients after maxillectomy. A systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <lpage>66</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29655661</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Srinivasan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Padmanabhan</surname>
                      <given-names>TV</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rehabilitation of an acquired maxillary defect</article-title>
                  <source>J Indian Prosthodont Soc</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dholam</surname>
                      <given-names>KP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quazi</surname>
                      <given-names>GA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bachher</surname>
                      <given-names>GK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rehabilitation and assessment of speech and mastication in bilateral total maxillectomy patient</article-title>
                  <source>J Indian Prosthodont Soc</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nanda</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koli</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suryavanshi</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verma</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Alleviating speech and deglutition: Role of a prosthodontist in multidisciplinary management of velopharyngeal insufficiency</article-title>
                  <source>J Indian Prosthodont Soc</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26929526</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahanna</surname>
                      <given-names>GK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beukelman</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marshall</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gaebler</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Obturator prostheses after cancer surgery: An approach to speech outcome assessment</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>79</volume>
                  <fpage>310</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9553885</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jain</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Venkat Prasad</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ariga</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Palatogram revisited</article-title>
                  <source>Contemp Clin Dent</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24808716</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <article-title>The Glossary of Prosthodontic Terms: Ninth Edition.</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <fpage>e1</fpage>
                  <lpage>105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28418832</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jain</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thakar</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Speech rehabilitation of maxillectomy patients with hollow bulb obturator</article-title>
                  <source>Indian J Palliat Care</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <lpage>12</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23440022</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Carvalho-Teles</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
                      <given-names>MI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lauris</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Speech evaluation with and without palatal obturator in patients submitted to maxillectomy</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19089242</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Darley</surname>
                      <given-names>FL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aronson</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brown</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Differential diagnostic patterns of dysarthria</article-title>
                  <source>J Speech Hear Res</source>
                  <year>1969</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <lpage>69</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5808852</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matsuyama</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsukiyama</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koyano</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Objective clinical assessment of change in swallowing ability of maxillectomy patients when wearing obturator prostheses</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>475</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16335165</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Osawa</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maeshima</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tanahashi</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Water-Swallowing Test: Screening for aspiration in stroke patients</article-title>
                  <source>Cerebrovasc Dis</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <lpage>81</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23548854</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vero</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishra</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singh</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singh</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jurel</surname>
                      <given-names>SK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of swallowing and masticatory performance in obturator wearers: A clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>J Adv Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <lpage>14</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25722831</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kong</surname>
                      <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hansen</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Customizing palatal contours of a denture to improve speech intelligibility</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>99</volume>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18319096</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Majid</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weinberg</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chalian</surname>
                      <given-names>VA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Speech intelligibility following prosthetic obturation of surgically acquired maxillary defects</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1974</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <lpage>96</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4525512</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Plank</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weinberg</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chalian</surname>
                      <given-names>VA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of speech following prosthetic obturation of surgically acquired maxillary defects</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1981</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <fpage>626</fpage>
                  <lpage>38</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6941016</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yoshida</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Michi</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ohsawa</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prosthetic treatment for speech disorders due to surgically acquired maxillary defects</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>565</fpage>
                  <lpage>71</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2283551</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Umino</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Masuda</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ono</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fujita</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Speech intelligibility following maxillectomy with and without a prosthesis: An analysis of 54 cases</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9576601</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arigbede</surname>
                      <given-names>AO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dosumu</surname>
                      <given-names>OO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaba</surname>
                      <given-names>OP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Esan</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of speech in patients with partial surgically acquired defects: Pre and post prosthetic obturation</article-title>
                  <source>J Contemp Dent Pract</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <lpage>96</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tobey</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lincks</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Acoustic analyses of speech changes after maxillectomy and prosthodontic management</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthet Dent</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <fpage>449</fpage>
                  <lpage>55</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2685247</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohle</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                      <suffix>3rd</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rieger</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huryn</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verbel</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hwang</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zlotolow</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of speech aid prostheses for acquired defects of the soft palate and velopharyngeal inadequacy – clinical assessments and cephalometric analysis: A memorial Sloan-Kettering study</article-title>
                  <source>Head Neck</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <lpage>207</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15700291</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen</surname>
                      <given-names>EE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>LaMonte</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Erb</surname>
                      <given-names>NL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beckman</surname>
                      <given-names>KL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sadeghi</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hutcheson</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>American Cancer Society head and neck cancer survivorship care guideline</article-title>
                  <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>66</volume>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <lpage>39</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27002678</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
