<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:39:26Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9645201" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9645201</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-11-14</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bdj</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz Dent J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz Dent J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bdj</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Brazilian Dental Journal</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0103-6440</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4760</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Fundação Odontológica de Ribeirão Preto</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9645201</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9645201</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9645201</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35766713</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35766713</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0103-6440202204785</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Postoperative pain after endodontic reintervention: a randomized
clinical trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3822-1680</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Spohr</surname>
                    <given-names>Andressa Raquel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2296-0550</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Xavier</surname>
                    <given-names>Samantha Rodrigues</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5366-982X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Malta</surname>
                    <given-names>Cristiana Pereira</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5166-8233</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pereira-Cenci</surname>
                    <given-names>Tatiana</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8483-455X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pappen</surname>
                    <given-names>Fernanda Geraldo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8444-2820</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Morgental</surname>
                    <given-names>Renata Dornelles</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Graduate Program in Dentistry, Federal University of
Pelotas(UFPel), Pelotas, RS, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Graduate Program in Dental Sciences, Federal University of Santa
Maria (UFSM), Santa Maria, RS, Brazil.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Correspondence: Renata Dornelles Morgental, DDS, MSc, PhD, Adjunct
Professor, Graduate Program in Dental Sciences Federal University of Santa Maria
(UFSM), Avenida Roraima, 1000, Prédio 26F, Santa Maria, RS, Brazil, 97105-900;
+55 55 32209210 / +55 55 999786669. <email>remorgental@hotmail.com</email>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <season>May-Jun</season>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>33</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>18</fpage>
              <lpage>27</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>28</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>Este é um artigo publicado em acesso aberto sob uma licença Creative
Commons</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <p>The present randomized clinical trial compared the prevalence and intensity of
postoperative pain in cases of endodontic reintervention using manual or
engine-driven reciprocating instruments. As secondary objectives, the analgesic
intake and time required for the root canal filling removal and
re-instrumentation were also evaluated. Forty-eight individuals with an
endodontically treated single-rooted tooth diagnosed with asymptomatic apical
periodontitis were included in the study. Patients were randomly assigned to two
comparison groups (n=24/group): reintervention with stainless steel manual
instruments or a nickel-titanium reciprocating system (Reciproc; VDW, Munich,
Germany). The endodontic reintervention was performed in two sessions with a
calcium hydroxide-based intracanal medication applied for 14 days before root
canal obturation. Working time for the root canal filling removal and
re-instrumentation was recorded with a digital stopwatch. After each visit,
postoperative pain intensity was assessed at 12, 24, and 48 hours and seven days
using the Numerical Rating Scale (NRS). The patients were also asked about
analgesic intake. Data were analyzed using Pearson chi-square, T and
Mann-Whitney U tests (α=0.05). No significant differences between groups were
found regarding the prevalence and intensity of pain or the need for analgesic
intake at any time point (P &gt; 0.05). Working time was significantly shorter
in the reciprocating group (18 versus 41 minutes). In conclusion, manual and
reciprocating instruments achieved the same results in terms of prevalence and
intensity of postoperative pain and analgesic intake. However, filling material
removal and re-instrumentation of the root canals were more than twice as fast
when using the reciprocating system.</p>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <title>Resumo</title>
                <p>O objetivo deste ensaio clínico randomizado foi comparar a prevalência e a
intensidade da dor pós-operatória em casos de retratamento endodôntico,
utilizando instrumentos manuais ou reciprocantes (automatizados). O tempo
necessário para desobturação e reinstrumentação do canal radicular também foi
avaliado. Quarenta e oito indivíduos possuindo um dente unirradicular tratado
endodonticamente e portador de periodontite apical assintomática foram incluídos
no estudo. Os pacientes foram aleatoriamente distribuídos em dois grupos
(n=24/grupo): retratamento com instrumentos manuais de aço inoxidável ou um
sistema reciprocante de níquel-titânio (Reciproc; VDW, Munique, Alemanha). A
reintervenção endodôntica foi realizada em duas consultas, sendo aplicada
medicação intracanal à base de hidróxido de cálcio por 14 dias, antes da
obturação. O tempo clínico gasto com os protocolos de desobturação e
reinstrumentação do canal radicular foi registrado com um cronômetro digital.
Após cada visita, a intensidade da dor pós-operatória foi avaliada em 12, 24, 48
horas e 7 dias por meio da escala de estimativa numérica (<italic>Numerical
Rating Scale - NRS</italic>). Além do registro da dor, os pacientes foram
questionados quanto ao uso de analgésicos. Os dados obtidos foram analisados por
testes Qui-quadrado e Mann-Whitney (α=0.05). Não foi detectada diferença
significativa entre os grupos quanto à prevalência e intensidade da dor ou uso
de analgésicos em nenhum dos períodos avaliados. O tempo clínico foi
significativamente menor no grupo reciprocante (18 versus 41 minutos). Pode-se
concluir que os instrumentos manuais e reciprocantes foram equivalentes quanto à
prevalência e intensidade de dor pós-operatória e uso de analgésicos, mas a
desobturação e reinstrumentação do canal radicular foram duas vezes mais rápidas
com o sistema reciprocante.</p>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Key Words:</title>
                <kwd>Pain</kwd>
                <kwd>endodontics</kwd>
                <kwd>root canal preparation</kwd>
                <kwd>reintervention</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="2"/>
                <table-count count="2"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="25"/>
                <page-count count="10"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The success of endodontic therapy depends on the adequate cleaning, shaping, and
filling of root canals as well as satisfactory coronal sealing <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>. In cases of apical periodontitis, such actions should
lead to the elimination of endodontic pathogens or at least a reduction to a level
that enables periapical healing <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>.
Microorganisms remaining within the root canal system, especially in the apical
segment, constitute the main reason for treatment failure <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The most commonly recommended strategies for teeth with primary endodontic treatment
failure are non-surgical reintervention (retreatment), different apical surgery
modalities, or extraction and replacement with a dental implant <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>. In most cases, non-surgical
reintervention is the first choice because it is the least invasive approach.</p>
              <p>It is important to remove all root filling material during reintervention to enable
subsequent cleaning and a new filling of the endodontic space <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. The incomplete removal of gutta-percha and sealer
hinders the removal of necrotic tissues and remaining bacteria in the root canal,
which can lead to the recurrence of clinical failure <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. The techniques employed to remove the root filling
material include heated instruments, special burrs, stainless steel manual files,
nickel-titanium (NiTi) engine-driven systems, ultrasonic tips, and solvents <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Several <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have investigated the effectiveness of
manual and engine-driven (rotary and reciprocating) instruments in endodontic
reintervention <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>. Some have demonstrated greater efficacy in the removal of
filling material with the use of NiTi rotary instruments compared to the manual
technique <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>, whereas others have
demonstrated similar <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> or inferior
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> efficacy. Despite not being
originally developed for cases of reintervention, reciprocating NiTi systems have
also proved effective, with a similar <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> or better performance compared to continuous rotation and
manual techniques <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Researchers agree that the complete removal of gutta-percha and sealer poses a
challenge <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>; in this scenario, the conflicting
results found in the literature and a large number of available systems impair the
decision-making process on the part of dentists regarding what technique to use.
Despite the high initial cost, NiTi rotary/reciprocating instruments enable faster
material removal and re-instrumentation compared to manual instruments, as
demonstrated in laboratory studies <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. Thus, single-file reciprocating systems may be a
cost-effective option with a lower learning curve for cases of reintervention <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>During endodontic reintervention procedures, filling materials, irrigating solutions,
dentine shavings, tissue debris, and microorganisms can be pushed to the periapical
tissues, the so-called apical extrusion <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>. This situation is related to undesirable outcomes,
such as inflammation, postoperative pain, and delayed periapical healing process
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Postoperative pain is a relatively frequent problem among patients submitted to
endodontic procedures <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> and has
been widely studied <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>. Pain results from a complex and multifactorial process
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>, influenced by aspects
related to the patient, the tooth being treated, the dentist’s skills, and the
intervention modality <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. Despite this relatively common occurrence, little data
are found on postoperative pain, specifically in cases of endodontic reintervention
and comparing different root canal filling removal methods <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Therefore, this study aimed to investigate the prevalence and intensity of
postoperative pain after endodontic reintervention (root canal filling removal and
re-instrumentation) in single-rooted teeth with asymptomatic apical periodontitis,
comparing manual and reciprocating instruments. As secondary objectives, the
analgesic intake and the time required for the root canal filling removal and
re-instrumentation were also evaluated. The null hypothesis was that both groups
would be similar in terms of (a) prevalence and intensity of postoperative pain, (b)
analgesic intake, and (c) working time.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>The present study is a prospective, single-center, parallel, randomized clinical
trial and received approval from the local research ethics committee
(certificate number: 51074515.4.0000.5318). The protocol was registered online
(ClinicalTrial.gov; NCT03743233). This study was reported according to the
guidelines of the CONSORT Statement (www.consort-statement.org). All eligible
patients received complete information on the study’s objectives, methods, and
risks. Those who agreed to participate signed an informed consent form.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Sample size calculation</title>
                <p>A previous study evaluating the postoperative pain rate after endodontic
retreatment <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> was considered
for sample calculation using the software Sealed EnvelopeTM (Exmouth House,
London UK). An alpha-type error of 0.05 and a beta power of 0.80 were specified,
considering 43% of cases presenting no postoperative pain in 12 hours, using
manual instrumentation, 67% in the reciprocating group, and a non-inferiority
limit 2.0. The minimal estimated sample size for each group was computed as n=23
to determine the postoperative pain differences between the experimental groups.
Potential patient dropouts were considered to improve the statistical power of
acquired data.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Participant selection</title>
                <p>Approximately 350 patients sought the Dental School of the Federal University of
Pelotas (UFPel; Pelotas, RS, Brazil) with an indication for endodontic
reintervention between January 2017 and December 2018. Included participants
were male and female adults (&gt;18years) requiring endodontic reintervention in
an asymptomatic single-rooted tooth with a single canal and persistent/secondary
apical periodontitis (Periapical Index, PAI ≥ 3). PAI was evaluated in the
initial periapical radiograph by a blinded and calibrated examiner (weight kappa
= 0.853).</p>
                <p>The exclusion criteria were: use of analgesics, anti-inflammatories, or other
pain-modulating drugs, systemic disease (e.g., hypertension, arthritis, and
kidney disorder), pregnancy, untreated periodontal disease, abnormal tooth
mobility, and teeth with an excessively wide or curved canal.</p>
                <p>Individuals who met the eligibility criteria and agreed to participate in the
study were randomly allocated to two comparison groups: manual or reciprocating
technique (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Stratified
randomization was performed considering two operators (both dentists in the
graduate program of dentistry/endodontics) who had undergone previous training
for manual and reciprocating techniques. The randomization procedure was
performed by an auxiliary researcher using a list of computer-generated random
numbers (www.sealedenvelope.com / randomization / create a list). Opaque
envelopes were used to ensure allocation concealment and were opened by an
assistant only when the root filling material was going to be removed from the
root canal.</p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f1">
                    <label>Figure 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Flowchart of sample selection, treatment, and analysis following
CONSORT Statement.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="1806-4760-bdj-33-03-18-gf1" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Clinical procedures</title>
                <p>The same operator conducted each endodontic reintervention in two sessions. All
patients received infiltrative anesthesia with 2% lidocaine and 1:100,000
epinephrine (Alphacaine 100; DFL, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil). Rubber dam
isolation and removal of the previous coronal restorations were performed,
following careful measures of aseptic control. The provisory working length (WL)
was calculated from the apparent length of the tooth in the initial radiograph
subtracting 1 to 2 mm.</p>
                <p>The protocols for root canal filling removal and re-instrumentation were adapted
from Dincer et al. <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. The
initial removal of the root filling material was similar for all root canals in
both groups. A size 2 Largo drill (Dentsply-Maillefer, Ballaigues, Switzerland)
was used for removing the first 2 mm from the root canals, serving as a
reservoir for the solvent solution. Approximately 0.1 mL of eucalyptol
(Biodinâmica, Ibiporã, PR, Brazil) was placed in the canal to soften the
gutta-percha for 30 seconds before the insertion of the first instrument. That
was the only time the solvent was used.</p>
                <p>Next, the reintervention technique to be used was determined (opening of the
envelope). It was impossible to blind the operators and patients due to the very
different kinematics of the two groups.</p>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="order">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Manual reintervention: The cervical third was prepared with sizes #3
and #2 Gates-Glidden drills (Dentsply-Maillefer) in decreasing
order. The crown-down technique was then performed until reaching
the provisory WL, starting with a size #40 K-file
(Dentsply-Maillefer) and reaching a size #25. The WL was determined
using an electronic apex locator (Novapex; Forum Technologies,
Rishon Le-Zion, Israel) and confirmed with a radiograph. The WL was
defined as 1 mm short of the root apex and apical patency was
achieved with a size #15 K-file. The root canals were
re-instrumented up to a size #50 K-file apically and were flared
cervically up to size #70.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Reciprocating reintervention: A Reciproc R25 (VDW) was used for
removing the filling material until the provisory WL was reached.
The instrument was inserted into the canal, and the electric motor
(Silver; VDW) was activated, followed by the use of back-and-forth
movements with a range of 3 mm. Gentle apical pressure was applied,
combined with friction against the lateral walls, following the
manufacturer’s instructions. WL determination was performed using
electronic and radiographic methods as described above, with a size
#25 K-file. Apical patency was established with a size #15 K-file.
The root canal was then prepared using the Reciproc R50 instrument
(VDW). After three back-and-forth movements, the instrument was
removed from the canal and cleaned with sterile gauze. This
procedure was repeated until reaching the WL. As Reciproc is a
single-use instrument, only one tooth was prepared with each
instrument.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p>During root canal filling removal and re-instrumentation protocols, irrigation
was carried out with 2.5% sodium hypochlorite solution (NaOCl; Asfer, São
Caetano do Sul, SP, Brazil) in both groups. After instrument change in the
manual group or after 3‒4 pecking motions in the reciprocating group, 2 mL
irrigant was used <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. All
teeth received a total volume of 20 mL NaOCl. To achieve apical patency, a size
#15 K-file was used with balanced force movement. After chemomechanical
preparation, a new radiograph was taken without the insertion of instruments to
analyze the possible presence of remaining filling material within the root
canal. If the radiograph revealed the presence of material, the respective
technique (manual or reciprocating) was repeated with the final instruments.
H-files with the circumferential filing of the root canal walls <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> or ultrasonic tips <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> were also used, accompanied by
abundant irrigation with NaOCl to remove the remaining material.</p>
                <p>After these procedures, the root canals were flooded with 5 mL 17% EDTA
(Biodinâmica, Ibiporã, PR, Brazil) for five minutes. Then, 5 mL NaOCl was used
as the final irrigant. The canals were dried with size #50 absorbent paper tips
(Dentsply, Petrópolis, RJ, Brazil) and filled with a calcium hydroxide-based
intracanal medication (Calen-PMCC; S. S. White, Rio de Janeiro, RJ) for 14 days,
as described previously <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>.
The teeth were temporarily sealed with glass ionomer cement (Vidrion R; S. S.
White, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil).</p>
                <p>In the second session, the same root canal filling technique was performed for
all teeth in both groups. After local anesthesia and rubber dam isolation, the
intracanal medication was removed. The root canal was irrigated with NaOCl and
prepared with the master apical file. Before obturation, the smear layer removal
was performed with EDTA, as described above, and the canal was dried with
absorbent paper points (Dentsply). The gutta-percha master point was tested for
tug-back at the WL and confirmed radiographically. The root canals were filled
with gutta-percha points and AH Plus sealer (Dentsply DeTrey, Konstanz,
Germany), using the cold lateral condensation technique. Excess gutta-percha and
sealer were removed with heated condensers and a cotton pellet soaked in
alcohol. A new provisory coronal restoration was performed with glass ionomer
cement (Vidrion R; S. S. White, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil), followed by the
final radiograph. An occlusal adjustment was performed in all teeth after each
session. Finally, the patient was referred for definitive restoration at the
university clinics.</p>
                <p>At the end of each session, the participants received a pain questionnaire and a
prescription for ibuprofen (400 mg every 6 hours) in pain cases for which they
judged it necessary to take an analgesic drug <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>. If intense pain persisted after taking the
prescribed medication, the patient was instructed to contact the dentist for a
reintervention or to obtain another prescription, depending on the case.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Working time assessment</title>
                <p>The time required for the root canal filling removal and re-instrumentation was
recorded (in seconds) using a digital stopwatch (Timex T5K; Technos, Manaus, AM,
Brazil). The device was activated upon placement of the solvent until the
radiographic odontometry (T1) and from the onset of re-instrumentation to
intracanal dressing application (T2). The total time (T1 + T2) was then
calculated.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Postoperative pain evaluation</title>
                <p>Postoperative pain was assessed using an eleven-point numerical rating scale
(NRS). Each patient received verbal and written explanations of the scale at the
end of the sessions. NRS ranges from 0 (absence of pain) to 10 (worst pain
imaginable), as described by Farrar et al. <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> and validated by Ferreira-Valente et al. <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>. Pain intensity was measured
at 12, 24, and 48 hours as well as seven days after the two sessions. Any need
for analgesics and the number of pills taken were recorded. The patients were
contacted by telephone at convenient and prescheduled times. An auxiliary
researcher blinded to the technique used by the operator during the
reintervention procedures performed this contact. With the previous approval of
the participants, contacts in social media, residential addresses, and
electronic addresses were maintained to avoid loss of contact with the
patients.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Data analysis</title>
                <p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients in the two groups were
compared using Pearson Chi-square, T and Mann-Whitney U tests. The frequency of
root canal filling extrusion after endodontic reintervention was also recorded
in both groups and compared (Pearson Chi-square test). As the Shapiro-Wilk test
demonstrated non-normal distribution, data on postoperative pain and working
time were analyzed using the Mann-Whitney U test. Statistical significance was
set at P&lt;0.05, and the IBM SPSS Statistics v. 20 software (SPSS Inc.,
Chicago, IL, USA) was used for data analysis.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p><xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> displays the demographic and clinical
characteristics of the patients in the manual and reciprocating groups. Both groups
were similar in terms of sex, age, tooth group, dental arch, PAI index and apical
extrusion of the root filling material (P &gt; 0.05).</p>
              <p>After the first session (root canal filling removal and re-instrumentation), the
prevalence of pain was low and diminished over time. Nine (18.75%) of the 48
patients reported pain at 12 h, seven (14.58%) at 24 h, four (8.33%) at 48 h, and
only one (2.08%) at seven days. After the second session (endodontic obturation),
three (6.25%) of the 48 patients reported pain at 12 h, two (4.16%) at 24 h, and
only one (2.08%) at 48 h and seven days. No significant difference between manual
and reciprocating groups was found at any time point (P = 0.296 to 1.000, Chi-square
test) (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
              <p>The intensity of postoperative pain (mean pain scores on the NRS) are displayed in
<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Again, no significant
differences between groups were found at any time point (P = 0.282 to 1.000,
Mann-Whitney test).</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Demographic and clinical characteristics of patients in each
group.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="2"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manual groupn (%)(n=24)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reciprocating group n (%)(n=24)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (83.33)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (66.66)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.182<sup>*</sup></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (16.67)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (33.34)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Mean ± SD)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.25 ± 11.77</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.79 ± 10.89</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097<sup>**</sup></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Tooth group</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incisor</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (70.83)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (58.33)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.612<sup>*</sup></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canine</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8.33)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8.33)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-molar</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (20.84)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (33.34)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dental arch</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxillary</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (66.66)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (66.66)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.000<sup>*</sup></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (33.34)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (33.34)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAI [Median (Min-Max)]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3-5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3-5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073<sup>***</sup></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root canal filling extrusion</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (25)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (12.5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267<sup>*</sup></td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN1">
                      <p>PAI: Periapical Index. SD: Standard deviation. <sup>*</sup>
Chi-square test. <sup>**</sup> T-test. <sup>***</sup> Mann-Whitney
test.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <fig position="float" id="f2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Prevalence of pain in manual and reciprocating groups at different
evaluation times after first (A) and second (B) sessions.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="1806-4760-bdj-33-03-18-gf2" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>Analgesics intake was infrequent in this study. Only two patients (8.33%) in the
manual group and one (4.16%) in the reciprocating group felt the need to take the
medication, with no significant difference between groups (P = 0.551, Chi-square
test). Regarding the number of analgesics taken, the mean was higher in the manual
instrumentation (1.33 ± 5.73) compared to the reciprocating system (0.04 ± 0.20),
but the difference was non-significant (P = 0.523, Mann-Whitney test).</p>
              <p>A significant difference between groups was found regarding working time (P = 0.002,
Mann-Whitney test). The filling material removal and re-instrumentation protocol
were faster with the reciprocating instruments. The mean working time was 1136.17 ±
580.07 seconds (approximately 18 minutes) and 2462.54 ± 1800.05 seconds
(approximately 41 minutes) in the manual and reciprocating groups, respectively.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The present randomized clinical trial aimed to investigate the prevalence and
intensity of postoperative pain in cases of endodontic reintervention performed with
stainless steel manual instruments or a NiTi reciprocating system (Reciproc; VDW).
Additionally, the study evaluated the analgesic intake and the working time required
for the root canal filling removal and re-instrumentation. The null hypothesis was
partially rejected, as there was no significant difference between groups regarding
pain and analgesic intake, but working time was significantly shorter when using the
reciprocating technique. This last finding seems obvious since we compared multiple
manual instruments and a single-file reciprocating system, but it seems interesting
to know how faster the engine-driven system would perform.</p>
              <p>The postoperative pain results differ from those described in two previous studies
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>, which reported higher levels of
pain with the manual technique in comparison to the reciprocating technique in cases
of reintervention. Some researchers state that manual files cause greater extrusion
of debris during the removal of the filling material than rotary/reciprocating
systems <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>, which could explain
the greater pain experience. However, all instrumentation techniques are reported to
cause some degree of apical extrusion <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. Findings from different studies on this issue are
contradictory and some report no difference between manual and rotary/reciprocating
techniques <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Intensity of postoperative pain (Mean, SD, median, IQR, Min, Max) in
manual and reciprocating groups at different evaluation times.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manual</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reciprocating</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P*</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">1<sup>st</sup> session </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">12h</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 (1.14)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.60)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">0,671</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">24h</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (1.31)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.48)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">0,603</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">48h</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (1.97)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.20)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">0,282</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">7 days</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 (0.40)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">0,317</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">2<sup>nd</sup> session </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">12h</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 ± 0.28</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 ± 0.20</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">0,555</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">24h</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 ± 0.20</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 ± 0.20</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">1,000</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">48h</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 ± 0.00</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 ± 0.20</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">0,317</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">7 days</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 ± 0.00</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 ± 0.20</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">0,317</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN3">
                      <p>SD: Standard deviation. IQR: Interquartile range. * Mann-Whitney
test.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>Curiously, another clinical trial found less postoperative pain with the manual
technique compared to rotary/reciprocating systems <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. The authors used a modified step-back manual
technique. In the present study, a crown-down manual technique was employed, in
which the cervical and middle thirds are prepared first, largely reducing the
microbial load in the root canal and consequently reducing the possibility of
driving contaminated debris into periapical tissues <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>, which could result in pain.</p>
              <p>Furthermore, the direct comparison of studies on postoperative pain is limited due to
differences in the study design, preoperative status of the teeth involved, and the
pain scale employed <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. The numerical rating scale (NRS) was used in the present
investigation, which is widely employed in scientific studies <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> and has been validated in Portuguese <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>, the native language of the
participants. This scale has adequate reliability and cross-cultural adaptation as
well as greater sensitivity and responsiveness compared to other pain assessment
methods <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The prevalence and intensity of postoperative pain were low in the present study,
which may be related to the strict intraoperative care, in which the manual and
reciprocating instruments were handled with gentle movements accompanied by abundant
irrigation <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. Another factor that
may explain these findings is the selection of asymptomatic cases. A previous study
demonstrated that the occurrence of postoperative pain was significantly lower when
the teeth did not have a prior history of pain <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>. Moreover, the standardization of the sample with the
selection of only single-rooted teeth made the procedures easier and diminished the
likelihood of complications.</p>
              <p>As occurred with the pain outcome and as its consequence, the use of analgesics or
the number of pills taken were very low, and no significant differences between
groups were found. Ibuprofen was selected for the present study, as non-steroidal
anti-inflammatory drugs are recommended as the first-choice medication to manage
postoperative pain following endodontic treatment <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>. A recent systematic review on the Cochrane platform
found evidence supporting the use of ibuprofen as a safe, effective analgesic with
few side effects when used for acute postoperative pain in adults <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>. Moreover, ibuprofen is the most
widely cited analgesic in studies addressing the effects of instrumentation
techniques on postoperative pain following endodontic procedures <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>As expected, the time required for filling material removal and re-instrumentation of
the root canal was shorter when using the Reciproc system in comparison to manual
instrumentation. <italic>In vitro</italic> studies have obtained similar results
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. In the present investigation,
mean working time was reduced by more than half with the single-file reciprocating
system. The cost of this system has become more affordable in recent years, and this
significant reduction in clinical time can make it a viable alternative for both
public and private dental services, even in developing countries such as Brazil.
Other advantages of reciprocating systems include the high cutting capacity,
excellent centralization of the preparation when employed in the curved canals, and
the low learning curve <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Some methodological characteristics of the present study should be considered, and
care must be taken when extrapolating the results to routine clinical practice. In
this study, the reintervention was performed in two sessions with the insertion of a
calcium hydroxide-based paste as intracanal medication. Olcay et al. <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> demonstrated that reintervention
performed in multiple sessions was effective and detected a high success rate
(85.1%), which was influenced by the size of the preexisting periapical lesion. In a
recent systematic review and meta-analysis, Nunes et al. <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> reported that both reintervention modalities
(single or multiple sessions) could be considered adequate for clinical practice,
with a similar occurrence of postoperative pain. Therefore, endodontists should
consider their experience and individual characteristics of the patient when
choosing the best treatment approach <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>One of the limitations of studies addressing pain is the subjective assessment of the
patients and its multifactor nature <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. Postoperative pain can be influenced by aspects related
to the patient and the tooth involved <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. In the present study, randomization ensured that the
demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients were similar in the two
comparison groups (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). That is an
important aspect, as sex, age, tooth group, and dental arch have already been
pointed out as factors that can influence the occurrence of pain in endodontics
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. The frequency of extruded
filling material is another variable that might impact postoperative pain results.
This frequency was relatively low in this study and was equally distributed between
the groups, although a slightly higher number was identified in the manual
technique. Overfilling is not likely associated with unfavorable treatment prognosis
<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>, corroborating the
observation that the root canal filling extrusion did not influence the present
study.</p>
              <p>The strength of the present study resides in its design. This randomized clinical
trial followed all guidelines of the CONSORT Statement to ensure a transparent and
precise report. However, the results cannot be generalized to all clinical cases and
should be analyzed with caution. Therefore, the effect of instrumentation techniques
on the incidence and intensity of postoperative pain should be assessed
thoroughly.</p>
              <p>In conclusion, manual and reciprocating instruments achieved the same results
regarding the prevalence and intensity of postoperative pain and analgesic intake.
However, filling material removal and re-instrumentation of the root canal was
faster when using the reciprocating system.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gillen</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Looney</surname>
                      <given-names>SW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gu</surname>
                      <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loushine</surname>
                      <given-names>BA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weller</surname>
                      <given-names>RN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loushine</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of the quality of coronal restoration versus the quality
of root canal fillings on the success of root canal treatment: a systematic
review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>895</fpage>
                  <lpage>902</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21689541</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>Jr</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Etiologylogy of root canal treatment failure: why well-treated
teeth can fail</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11307374</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rossi-Fedele</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahmed</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of root canal filling removal effectiveness using
micro-computed tomography: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>520</fpage>
                  <lpage>526</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giuliani</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cocchetti</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pagavino</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of ProTaper universal retreatment files in removing
filling materials during root canal retreatment</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>1381</fpage>
                  <lpage>1384</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18928852</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bernardes</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duarte</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vivian</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alcalde</surname>
                      <given-names>MP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vasconcelos</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bramante</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of three retreatment techniques with ultrasonic
activation in flattened canals using micro-computed tomography and scanning
electron microscopy</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>890</fpage>
                  <lpage>897</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26280904</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zuolo</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pameijer</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banegas</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of reciprocating and rotary techniques for removing
filling material during root canal retreatment</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>947</fpage>
                  <lpage>953</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23506150</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodig</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reicherts</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Konietschke</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dullin</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hahn</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hulsmann</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of reciprocating and rotary NiTi instruments for
retreatment of curved root canals assessed by micro-CT</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>942</fpage>
                  <lpage>948</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24386931</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Comparin</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moreira</surname>
                      <given-names>EJL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De-Deus</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arias</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>EJNL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postoperative pain after endodontic retreatment using rotary or
reciprocating instruments: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1084</fpage>
                  <lpage>1088</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28477995</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mollashahi</surname>
                      <given-names>NF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saberi</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Havaei</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sabeti</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of postoperative pain after root canal preparation
with two reciprocating and rotary single-file systems: a randomized clinical
trial</article-title>
                  <source>Iran Endod J</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <lpage>19</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28179917</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>De-Deus</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neves</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mendonça</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lourenço</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Calixto</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apically extruded dentin debris by reciprocating single-file and
multi-file rotary system</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Oral Investig</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <lpage>361</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Western</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dicksit</surname>
                      <given-names>DD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical extrusion of debris in four different endodontic
instrumentation systems: A meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Conserv Dent</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28761250</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arias</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De La Macorra</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hidalgo</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azabal</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Predictive models of pain following root canal treatment: a
prospective clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>784</fpage>
                  <lpage>793</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23402273</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nekoofar</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheykhrezae</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meraji</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jamee</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jamee</surname>
                      <given-names>ASJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dummer</surname>
                      <given-names>PMH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of the effect of root canal preparation by using
WaveOne and ProTaper on postoperative pain: a randomized clinical
trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>575</fpage>
                  <lpage>578</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25720984</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arias</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azabal</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hidalgo</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De La Macorra</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Relationship between postendodontic pain, tooth diagnostic
factors, and apical patency</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <lpage>192</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19166770</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Çiçek</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koçak</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koçak</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sağlam</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Türker</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postoperative pain intensity after using different
instrumentation techniques: a randomized clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <lpage>26</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28198972</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Topçuoğlu</surname>
                      <given-names>HS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Topçuoğlu</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postoperative pain after the removal of root canal filling
material using different techniques in teeth with failed root canal therapy:
a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Odontol Scand</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <lpage>254</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28162017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dincer</surname>
                      <given-names>AN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Er</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Canakci</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of apically extruded debris during root canal
retreatment with several NiTi systems</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1194</fpage>
                  <lpage>1198</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25557631</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>LL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>XD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Residual filling material in dentinal tubules after gutta-percha
removal was observed with scanning electron microscopy</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <lpage>296</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341062</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olcay</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eyüboglu</surname>
                      <given-names>TF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Özcan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical outcomes of non-surgical multiple-visit root canal
retreatment: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>Odontology</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>107</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>536</fpage>
                  <lpage>545</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30969392</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farrar</surname>
                      <given-names>JT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Young</surname>
                      <given-names>JP</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lamoreaux</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Werth</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poole</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical importance of changes in chronic pain intensity measured
on an 11-point numerical pain rating scale</article-title>
                  <source>Pain</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>94</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <lpage>158</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11690728</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferreira-Valente</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pais-Ribeiro</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jensen</surname>
                      <given-names>MP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validity of four pain intensity rating scales</article-title>
                  <source>Pain</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>152</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>2399</fpage>
                  <lpage>2404</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21856077</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hülsmann</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peters</surname>
                      <given-names>OA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dummer</surname>
                      <given-names>PMH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mechanical preparation of root canals: shaping goals, techniques,
and means</article-title>
                  <source>Endod Topics</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <lpage>76</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mickel</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wright</surname>
                      <given-names>AP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chogle</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kantorovich</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Curd</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An analysis of current analgesic preferences for endodontic pain
management</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1146</fpage>
                  <lpage>1154</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17174670</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moore</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Derry</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aldington</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiffen</surname>
                      <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Single-dose oral analgesics for acute postoperative pain in
adults - an overview of Cochrane reviews</article-title>
                  <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>2015</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>CD008659</fpage>
                  <lpage>CD008659</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nunes</surname>
                      <given-names>GP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Delbem</surname>
                      <given-names>ACB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gomes</surname>
                      <given-names>JML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lemos</surname>
                      <given-names>CAA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pellizzer</surname>
                      <given-names>EP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postoperative pain in endodontic retreatment of one visit versus
multiple visits: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized
controlled trials</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Oral Investig</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
                  <lpage>468</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
