<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:38:19Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10122801" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10122801</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-04-24</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcorhl</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10122801</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10122801</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10122801</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37087507</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37087507</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2942</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-023-02942-y</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effect of coffee on color stability and surface roughness of newly introduced single shade resin composite materials</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6933-9473</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rohym</surname>
                    <given-names>Shaimaa</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>shaimaa.rohym@acu.edu.eg</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6344-7422</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tawfeek</surname>
                    <given-names>Hossam El Mandouh</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>hossamelhussiny@yahoo.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9622-0689</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kamh</surname>
                    <given-names>Raghda</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>Raghda-kamh@eru.edu.eg</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442461.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0490 9561</institution-id><institution>Conservative Dentistry, Al-Ahram Canadian University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fourth Industrial Zones, Giza, Egypt </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.33003.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9889 5690</institution-id><institution>Conservative Dentistry, Suez Canal University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ismailia, Egypt </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442695.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 6073 9704</institution-id><institution>Conservative Dentistry, Egyptian Russian University, </institution></institution-wrap>Cairo, Egypt </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <elocation-id>236</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>5</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">Dentists started to follow the era of using single-shade resin composite restorations to avoid color shade selection. Our study was done to evaluate and compare the color stability of two single-shade resin composite materials.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">Sixty samples were randomly allocated into two main groups (<italic>n</italic> = 30) according to the composite resin used: Group O: (Omnichroma) samples and Group V: (Venus Peral) samples. Each group was then divided into two subgroups (<italic>n</italic> = 15): group O1 and V1: samples immersed in coffee. Group O2 and V2: samples immersed in distilled water. Color changes (ΔE) and roughness values (Ra) were evaluated at baseline, first, and 14<sup>th</sup> days of immersion. The color change was assessed using Vita Easyshade V, while surface roughness was assessed using a profilometer and Atomic Force Microscope (AFM). Data were collected and statistically analyzed using two-way variance analysis (ANOVA) and Tukey's post-hoc test (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">Group O1 and V1 recorded the highest ΔE<sub>00</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.002, 0.0001, respectively) and Ra values (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) with no significant difference between both materials at 14 days.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">Single shade resin composite with innovative chromatic material technology has dramatic color change and surface roughness that sacrifice esthetic success.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Single-shade composite resin</kwd>
                <kwd>Color stability</kwd>
                <kwd>Coffee</kwd>
                <kwd>Surface roughness</kwd>
                <kwd>Atomic Force Microscope</kwd>
                <kwd>Profilometer</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>Egyptian Russian University (ERU)</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <open-access>
                  <p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p>
                </open-access>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2023</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par14">Demand for ideal esthetic material in restoring teeth impacted both materials and techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Dentists have recently preferred ceramic and resin-containing restorative materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] based on their esthetic and biological properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The Esthetic successes of dental resin composite restorations depend primarily on their surface properties and color stability.</p>
              <p id="Par15">Using nanotechnology in dentistry, manufacturers are now introducing resin composite materials with single-shade systems instead of more complex color systems. These materials have color harmony with tooth structure due to their nanofillers and nanocluster content. Recently, single-shade resin composite, which can be used for all tooth shades, has been introduced to the dentist's use. The advantage of its color-matching ability is that it eliminates the need for a shade-taking procedure. It reduces composite inventory, minimizing chair time for the patient and the wastage of unused composite shades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par16">Composite resins' color stability and surface roughness are essential for esthetic success [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Color changes have been associated with diet, chemical reactions, water absorption, and poor oral hygiene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Consumption of certain beverages may affect the esthetic and physical properties of the resin composite, thereby destabilization the quality of restorations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Beverages such as coffee, tea, cola, and wine cause different degrees of discoloration of resinous restorative materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. It was reported that a surface roughness value below 0.15 μm. Decreases the adhesion of streptococcus mutans, while when this value is above 0.2 μm creates an accessible retention area for the attachment of the bacterial plaque [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par17">In order to assess the color stability of restorative materials, many instrumental techniques could be used, such as; Digital cameras, Spectrophotometers, or colorimeters. Evaluating (ΔE) is referred to Commission International De L’éclairage (CIE) system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par18">Surface roughness is considered one of the reasons for exterior discoloration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Wear of dental resin composites denoting debonding of inorganic fillers from the resin matrix, which leaves voids, increasing the surface roughness and forming a surface susceptible to exterior stain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Mechanical and Optical profilometers, SEM (scanning electron microscope), and AFM (atomic force microscope) are widely used devices to measure and evaluate the surface roughness of restorative materials. Dental experts preferred profilometers as no preparation is required on samples to measure surface roughness, and repeated measurements are enabled [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Moreover, AFM obtains high-resolution 3D nanometric images for the material surface, offering complete surface quantification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par19">Our study examines the color stability and surface roughness of innovative chromatic resin composite after exposing them to commonly consumed beverages and coffee for 14 days using Vita Easyshade V, a contact stylus profilometer, and AFM. The null hypothesis was that there was no difference in the ΔE and Ra of both single-shade composite resins after immersing in coffee for 14 days.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Materials</title>
                <p id="Par20">
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p id="Par21">Resin Composite Materials: (Omnichroma/Venus pearl) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>)</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p id="Par22">The beverages used were coffee (Nescafe classic, Nestle, Switzerland) and distilled water (Pharmapack, Egypt).</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <table-wrap id="Tab1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Composition of the restorative materials used in this study</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">Product name</th>
                          <th align="left">Type</th>
                          <th align="left">Resin matrix</th>
                          <th align="left">Filler average size</th>
                          <th align="left">Filler volume</th>
                          <th align="left">Filler weight</th>
                          <th align="left">Product number</th>
                          <th align="left">Manufacturer</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Omnichroma</td>
                          <td align="left">Supra-nano spherical</td>
                          <td align="left">UDMA, TEGDMA</td>
                          <td align="left">260 nm</td>
                          <td align="left">68%</td>
                          <td align="left">79%</td>
                          <td align="left">1615</td>
                          <td align="left">Tokuyama-Dental, Tokyo, Japan</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Venus pearl</td>
                          <td align="left">Nano-hybrid</td>
                          <td align="left">TCD-DI-HEA UDMA, TEGDMA</td>
                          <td align="left">5 nm – 5 μm</td>
                          <td align="left">64%</td>
                          <td align="left">76%</td>
                          <td align="left">K010206</td>
                          <td align="left">Kulzer GmbH, Germany</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Methods</title>
                <sec id="Sec5">
                  <title>Study design</title>
                  <p id="Par23">Sixty samples were randomly allocated into two main groups (<italic>n</italic> = 30) according to the composite resin used. Group O: samples were obtained using single-shade composite resins (Omnichroma), and Group V: samples were obtained using single-shade composite resins (Venus Peral<bold>)</bold>. Each group was then divided into two subgroups (<italic>n</italic> = 15): group O1 and V1: samples immersed in coffee. Group O2 and V2: samples immersed in distilled water. The color change (ΔE) and roughness values (Ra) were evaluated for all samples at baseline (before immersion), and on the 1<sup>st</sup>, and 14<sup>th</sup> days of immersion. Color assessments were measured using Vita Easyshade V, while surface roughness was measured using a contact stylus profilometer and AFM. The study proposal was reviewed and approved by the Research Ethics Committees (REC) of the Faculty of Dentistry, Cairo University, Egypt, on 29/3/2022. With approval number 30.3.22.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="Sec6">
                  <title>Sample size calculation</title>
                  <p id="Par24">Sample size calculated depending on a previous study (Aydın et al.) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] as reference. According to this study, the response within each subject group was normally distributed with a standard deviation of 1.4. If the actual difference in the experimental and control means is 1.8, the study minimally needed 11 subjects in each group to reject the null hypothesis that the population means of the experimental and control groups are equal with probability (power) 0.8. The type I error probability associated with this null hypothesis test is 0.05. The total sample size increased to 15 subjects per group to compensate 20% dropout.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="Sec7">
                  <title>Samples preparation</title>
                  <sec id="FPar1">
                    <title>Resin composite specimens’ preparation</title>
                    <p id="Par25">Thirty cylindrical disk-shaped specimens (6 mm diameter and 2 mm thickness) were prepared using a customized Teflon mold, rendering 60 specimens for the two resin composite materials. A Teflon mold and copper ring were fabricated with 2 mm thickness and 20 mm diameter with a centralized hole of (6 mm diameter and 2 mm thickness) in which the resin composite was bulk packed as one increment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
                    <p id="Par26">According to the manufacturer’s recommendations, the resin composite materials were dispensed, manipulated, and polymerized. A nylon thread was incorporated into the specimen before polymerization to allow their easy handling and their suspension in the immersion solutions during all aging periods. The resin composite was bulk packed inside the central hole of the split Teflon ring. To ensure that specimens would have flat polymerized surfaces free of bubble formation after curing, both top and bottom surfaces were covered with transparent polyester matrix strips (TOR VM, Moscow, Russia) and a microscopic glass slide (1 mm thickness) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
                    <p id="Par27">Specimens were polymerized for 20 s on both surfaces (top and bottom) using a light-emitting diode unit (LED COXO DB-686 MOCHA) through the glass slide and the polyester matrix strip. LED light curing unit was used in standardized mode, emitting 1200mW/cm2 irradiance as measured with a radiometer (Kerr manufacturing product). Then the two wings of the ring were opened to remove the specimens. The dimensions of the specimens were checked with a caliper (Pirmadent Germany SS). All samples were finished and polished using Sof-Lex disks (three-step system), starting with medium grit, then fine grit, and finally superfine grit, all in a dry media for 15 s. Then rinsing and drying with a water/air syringe for a total of 6 s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Specimens were stored in distilled water in tight vials for 24 h at 37° C before the immersion procedures in the incubator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
                  </sec>
                  <sec id="FPar2">
                    <title>Test solution preparation</title>
                    <p id="Par28">With each type of resin composite, the 30 specimens were randomly allocated into two subgroups (<italic>n</italic>= 15 per subgroup), according to the immersion solution to be investigated. The two immersion solutions used were: distilled water (control solution) and coffee. The coffee solution was prepared by adding 3.6 g of coffee using a digital spoon scale to 300 ml distilled water, then boiling for 10 min to have a standardized concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Filter paper was used to remove any impurities of the prepared coffee before being poured into vials and left to be cooled. Specimens were immersed through suspension with the nylon thread of 5 ml immersion solution. The immersion solutions were changed daily till the last assessment period. After placing specimens, the vial was sealed tightly with its cap to prevent any evaporation of the immersion solutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The containers were stored at 37 °C by placing them in a thermal control unit<bold>.</bold>After each storage period, the specimens were removed from immersion solutions and allowed to dry before color assessments. Then after assessments, the identical specimens were stored again in the vials containing daily fresh solutions for the following storage period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
                  </sec>
                  <sec id="FPar3">
                    <title>Color measurements testing</title>
                    <p id="Par29">Color shade assessment using Commission International de L’Eclainge (CIELab) color system (L*, a* and b* values) at baseline before immersion, after one day, and after 14 days by digital spectrometer device Vita Easyshade V (VITA Zahnfabrik, Bad Säckingen, Germany). It is a portable spectrophotometer and a new fifth generation of Easyshade with a handpiece of fiber optic probe assembly for illuminating and receiving the reflected light from the sample. Results appear through a LED screen. The base unit has the calibration block into which the handpiece is seated. The Easyshade handpiece has a 5 mm diameter stainless steel probe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. measurements by Vita Easyshade started with a calibration process that was performed per the manufacturer's instructions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The probe was perpendicular to the recorded specimen before pressing the measurement on, and the results were displayed. According to the manufacturers’ instructions, two successive measurements were done and reported for each sample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p>
                    <p id="Par30">Color difference (ΔE<sup>∗</sup>
<sub>00</sub>) values were calculated using the following formula CIEDE2000 for each specimen against white backgrounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{\varvec{\Delta}}\mathbf{E}}_{00}\left({{\varvec{L}}}_{1}^{\boldsymbol{*}},\boldsymbol{ }\boldsymbol{ }{{\varvec{a}}}_{1}^{\boldsymbol{*}},\boldsymbol{ }\boldsymbol{ }{{\varvec{b}}}_{1}^{\boldsymbol{*}};\boldsymbol{ }{{\varvec{L}}}_{2}^{\boldsymbol{*}},\boldsymbol{ }{{\varvec{a}}}_{2}^{\boldsymbol{*}},\boldsymbol{ }{{\varvec{b}}}_{2}^{\boldsymbol{*}}\right)=\boldsymbol{ }{{\varvec{\Delta}}\mathbf{E}}_{00}^{12}={{\varvec{\Delta}}\mathbf{E}}_{00}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>00</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow/><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow/><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>00</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>00</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                    <p id="Par31">The L * value represents the lightness of an object where the value of zero equals a perfect black while the value of 100 represents a perfect reflecting diffuser. The a* value is a degree of redness of the color (positive a*; + 80) or its greenness (negative a*; − 80). Finally, the b* value counts for the degree of yellowness (positive b*; + 80) or its blueness (negative b*; − 80). The smaller the ΔE<sub>00</sub>, the lower the color change between the initial color measurement and the final color of the tooth. The perceptibility threshold (ΔE<sub>00</sub>) was 0.8 whereas the 50:50% acceptability threshold (ΔE<sub>00</sub>) was 1.8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p>
                  </sec>
                  <sec id="FPar4">
                    <title>Surface roughness testing</title>
                    <p id="Par32">The surface roughness of the materials was tested using a contact stylus profilometer (SJ- 210 Surface roughness tester Mitutyoyo Japan). Each specimen was fitted to the specimen holder, where the surface was to be measured in the horizontal direction; then, the specimen holder moved in a vertical direction up to the specimen surface, touching the measuring tip. Device calibration is done according to the manufacturer's instructions before use <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mitutoyo.com/webfoo/wp-content/uploads/Surftest_SJ-210_310.pdf">https://www.mitutoyo.com/webfoo/wp-content/uploads/Surftest_SJ-210_310.pdf</ext-link>. Five readings were recorded for each specimen at a distance of 500 microns each.</p>
                    <p>Testing parameters:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par34">Measuring distance 4 mm</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par35">Measuring Speed 0.5 mm/s. Returning 1 mm/s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par36">Measuring force 0.75 mN</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par37">Stylus profile: tip radius 2-micron, tip angle 60 degree</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par38">Evaluation parameter Ra values expressed in microns</p></list-item></list></p>
                  </sec>
                </sec>
                <sec id="Sec8">
                  <title>Surface morphology analysis using Atomic Force Microscope (AFM)</title>
                  <p id="Par39">Surface morphology analysis was gained using the Atomic Force Microscope (Tosca 200 AFM—Anton Paar GmbH – Germany, tapping mode—500 um increment—rate 1 line/second) in 'contact' mode. Four regions were chosen to have different images which can be scanned by software (Mountains® 8.2 Software—Digital Surf, Besançon, France).</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par40">All data were presented as mean &amp;standard deviation. Data were presented in 1 table &amp; 1 graph. Statistical analysis was performed with SPSS 16 ® (Statistical Package for Scientific Studies), Graph pad prism &amp; windows excel.</p>
                <p id="Par41">The given data was extracted using the Shapiro–Wilk test and Kolmogorov–Smirnov test for normality, which revealed that the significant level (<italic>P</italic>-value) was insignificant as <italic>P</italic>-value &gt; 0.05, which indicated that the alternative hypothesis was rejected. The concluded data originated from a normal distribution (parametric data) resembling a standard Bell curve.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec10">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Color measurements results</title>
                <sec id="Sec12">
                  <title>Comparison between different materials</title>
                  <p id="Par42">Comparison between different materials was performed by using the One Way ANOVA test, which revealed a significant difference between different groups after one day and after 14 days as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, followed by Tukey’s Post Hoc test for multiple comparisons, which represented that after one day, V1 was significantly the highest color changes (17.09 ± 5.87), then O1 (12.46 ± 1.89), while there was insignificant difference between V2 (2.64 ± 0.86) and O2 (2.45 ± 1.40). After 14 days, V1 (26.94 ± 6.21) and then O1 (16.69 ± 3.52), while there was an insignificant difference between V2 (3.97 ± 0.67) and O2 (2.91 ± 1.30), as presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Mean &amp; standard deviation of color changes (ΔE after one day and after 14)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Group</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">N</th><th align="left" colspan="2">ΔE<break/>After 1 day</th><th align="left" colspan="2">ΔE<break/>After 14 days</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">M</th><th align="left">SD</th><th align="left">M</th><th align="left">SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Omnichroma coffee O1</bold></td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">12.46<sup>a</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">1.89</td><td align="left">16.69<sup>a</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">3.52</td><td char="." align="char">0.002*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Venus Peral Coffee V1</bold></td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">17.09<sup>b</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">5.87</td><td align="left">26.94<sup>b</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">6.21</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Omnichroma distilled water O2</bold></td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">2.45<sup>c</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">1.40</td><td align="left">2.91<sup>c</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">1.30</td><td char="." align="char">0.003*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Venus Peral distilled water V2</bold></td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">2.64<sup>c</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.86</td><td align="left">3.97<sup>c</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.67</td><td char="." align="char">0.001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold> value</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2">&lt; 0.0001*</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&lt; 0.0001*</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>M</italic> Mean, <italic>SD</italic> Standard deviation, <italic>N</italic> Count</p><p><sup>*</sup>: Significant difference as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p><p>Means with the same superscript letters in the same column were insignificantly different as <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05</p><p>Means with different superscript letters in the same column were significantly different as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p><p><sup>a</sup>, <sup>b</sup> and <sup>c</sup> letters describes the significance determined by Turkey's post hoc test for multiple comparisons</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Bar chart representing color changes (ΔE after 1 day and after 14 days) in all groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="Sec13">
                  <title>Comparison between color changes after one day and after 14 days</title>
                  <p id="Par43">Comparison between ΔE after one day and after 14 days was performed using Paired t-test, which revealed a significant increase in color changes after 14 days in all groups, as presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec14">
                <title>Surface roughness results</title>
                <sec id="Sec15">
                  <title>Comparison between different intervals (effect of time) Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></title>
                  <table-wrap id="Tab3">
                    <label>Table 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Descriptive statistics of all groups regarding surface roughness at baseline, after one day, and after 14 days and comparison between different intervals within each group</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>Min</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>Max</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>M</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>SD</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left">
                            <bold>
                              <italic>P</italic>
                            </bold>
                            <bold> Value</bold>
                            <break/>
                            <bold>(One Way ANOVA test)</bold>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <p>
                              <bold>Omnichroma coffee</bold>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                              <bold>O1</bold>
                            </p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>Baseline</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.096</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.127</td>
                          <td align="left">0.110<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.010</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">&lt; 0.0001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 1 day</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.267</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.536</td>
                          <td align="left">0.390<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.090</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 14 days</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.238</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.760</td>
                          <td align="left">0.530<sup>c</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.140</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <p>
                              <bold>Venus Peral Coffee</bold>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                              <bold>V1</bold>
                            </p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>Baseline</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.011</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.429</td>
                          <td align="left">0.260<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.120</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">&lt; 0.0001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 1 day</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.333</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.646</td>
                          <td align="left">0.491<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.090</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 14 days</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.391</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.738</td>
                          <td align="left">0.590<sup>c</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.090</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <p>
                              <bold>Omnichroma distilled water</bold>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                              <bold>O2</bold>
                            </p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>Baseline</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.018</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.224</td>
                          <td align="left">0.12<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.060</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3"> &lt; 0.0001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 1 day</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.024</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.270</td>
                          <td align="left">0.15<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.080</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 14 days</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.148</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.503</td>
                          <td align="left">0.303<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.100</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">
                            <p>
                              <bold>Venus Peral distilled water</bold>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                              <bold>V2</bold>
                            </p>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>Baseline</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.009</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.390</td>
                          <td align="left">0.231<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.110</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="3">&lt; 0.0001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 1 day</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.034</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.483</td>
                          <td align="left">0.240<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.120</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <bold>After 14 days</bold>
                          </td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.231</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.642</td>
                          <td align="left">0.406<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">0.120</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p><italic>Min</italic> Minimum, <italic>Max</italic> Maximum, <italic>M</italic> Mean, <italic>SD</italic> Standard deviation</p>
                      <p><sup>*</sup>Significant difference as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p>
                      <p>Means with different superscript letters were significantly different as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p>
                      <p>Means with the same superscript letters were insignificantly different as <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05</p>
                      <p><sup>a</sup>, <sup>b</sup> and <sup>c</sup> letters describes the significance determined by Turkey's post hoc test for multiple comparisons</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                  <fig id="Fig2">
                    <label>Fig. 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Line chart representing surface roughness changes in all groups</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/>
                  </fig>
                  <p id="Par44">Comparison between different intervals was performed by using the One-Way ANOVA test, which revealed a significant difference in all groups as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, followed by Tukey’s Post Hoc test for multiple comparisons, which revealed that:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par45">In Omnichroma coffee O1 and Venus Peral Coffee V1, there was a significant difference between all intervals (significant increase as all with different superscript letters)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par46">In Omnichroma distilled water O2 and Venus Peral distilled water V2 there was an insignificant difference between baseline and after one day, while after two weeks was significantly the highest.</p></list-item></list></p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec16">
              <title>Comparisons between different groups Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></title>
              <table-wrap id="Tab4">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Mean and standard deviation of roughness at baseline, after one day, and after 14 days and comparison between different groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="2">Group</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="2">N</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2">Baseline</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2">After 1 day</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2">After 2 weeks</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left">M</th>
                      <th align="left">SD</th>
                      <th align="left">M</th>
                      <th align="left">SD</th>
                      <th align="left">M</th>
                      <th align="left">SD</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left">
                        <p>
                          <bold>Omnichroma coffee</bold>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                          <bold>O1</bold>
                        </p>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left">15</td>
                      <td align="left">0.11<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.01</td>
                      <td align="left">0.39<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.09</td>
                      <td align="left">0.53<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.14</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left">
                        <p>
                          <bold>Venus Peral Coffee</bold>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                          <bold>V1</bold>
                        </p>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left">15</td>
                      <td align="left">0.26<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.12</td>
                      <td align="left">0.49<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.09</td>
                      <td align="left">0.59<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.09</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left">
                        <p>
                          <bold>Omnichroma distilled water</bold>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                          <bold>O2</bold>
                        </p>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left">15</td>
                      <td align="left">0.12<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.06</td>
                      <td align="left">0.15<sup>c</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.08</td>
                      <td align="left">0.303<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.1</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left">
                        <bold>Venus Peral distilled water V2</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left">15</td>
                      <td align="left">0.23<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.11</td>
                      <td align="left">0.24<sup>c</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.12</td>
                      <td align="left">0.406<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                      <td char="." align="char">0.12</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="2">
                        <p>
                          <bold>
                            <italic>P</italic>
                          </bold>
                          <bold> value</bold>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                          <bold>(One Way ANOVA)</bold>
                        </p>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" colspan="2">&lt; 0.0001*</td>
                      <td align="left" colspan="2">&lt; 0.0001*</td>
                      <td char="." align="char" colspan="2">&lt; 0.0001*</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <p><italic>M</italic> Mean, <italic>SD</italic> Standard deviation</p>
                  <p><sup>*</sup>Significant difference as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p>
                  <p>Means with different superscript letters were significantly different as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p>
                  <p>Means with the same superscript letters were insignificantly different as <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05</p>
                  <p><sup>a</sup>, <sup>b</sup> and <sup>c</sup> letters describes the significance determined by Turkey's post hoc test for multiple comparisons</p>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <fig id="Fig3">
                <label>Fig. 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Bar chart representing a comparison between all groups regarding surface roughness at all intervals</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/>
              </fig>
              <p id="Par47">Comparison between different intervals was performed by using the One-Way ANOVA test, which revealed a significant difference in all groups as <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, followed by Tukey’s Post Hoc test for multiple comparisons, which revealed that:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par48">At baseline: Omnichroma coffee O1 and Omnichroma distilled water O2 were significantly the lowest with insignificant difference between them (same have letter a), while Venus Peral Coffee V1 and Venus Peral distilled water V2 was significantly the highest with insignificant difference between them (same have letter b).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par49">After one day: Omnichroma distilled water O2, Venus Peral distilled water V2 were significantly the lowest with insignificant difference between them (same have letter c), then Omnichroma coffee O1, while Venus Peral Coffee V2 was significantly the highest.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par50">After two weeks: Omnichroma coffee O1 and Venus Peral Coffee V1 were significantly the highest with insignificant difference between them (both have the letter a), while Omnichroma distilled water O2 and Venus Peral distilled water V2 were significantly the lowest with insignificant difference between them (same have letter b)</p></list-item></list></p>
              <sec id="Sec17">
                <title>Correlation between color changes and surface roughness</title>
                <p id="Par51">Correlation between surface roughness and color changes was calculated using Pearson`s Correlation Coefficient (r), which revealed a powerful (<italic>r</italic> &gt; 0.8), positive ( +), significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) correlation between them in both groups Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Correlation between color changes (ΔE) and surface roughness after one day and after 14 days in both groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Group</th><th align="left" colspan="2">After 1 day</th><th align="left" colspan="2">After 14 days</th></tr><tr><th align="left">r</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value</th><th align="left">r</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><p><bold>Omnichroma coffee</bold></p><p><bold>O1</bold></p></td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td><td char="." align="char">0.97</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p><bold>Venus Peral Coffee</bold></p><p><bold>V1</bold></p></td><td char="." align="char">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td><td char="." align="char">0.96</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p><bold>Omnichroma distilled water</bold></p><p><bold>O2</bold></p></td><td char="." align="char">0.96</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td><td char="." align="char">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Venus Peral distilled water V2</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td><td char="." align="char">0.97</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001*</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec18">
                <title>Atomic Force Microscope results</title>
                <p id="Par52">The surface roughness results measured by the contact stylus profilometer were explained and proved by the AFM analysis (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>AFM photographs of the surface topography of Omnichroma resin composite group O1 (<bold>a</bold>) baseline (<bold>b</bold>) after 1-day immersion in coffee (<bold>c</bold>) after 14 days immersion in distilled water</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>AFM photographs of the surface topography of Omnichroma resin composite group O2 (<bold>a</bold>) baseline (<bold>b</bold>) after 1-day immersion in distilled water (<bold>c</bold>) after 14 days immersion in coffee</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>AFM photographs of the surface topography of Venus Pearl resin composite group V1 (<bold>a</bold>) baseline (<bold>b</bold>) after 1-day immersion in coffee (<bold>c</bold>) after 14 days immersion in coffee</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>AFM photographs of the surface topography of Venus Pearl resin composite group V2 (<bold>a</bold>) baseline (<bold>b</bold>) after 1-day immersion in distilled water (<bold>c</bold>) after 14 days immersion in distilled water</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2023_2942_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec19">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par53">The wide use of the shades of adhesive composite as esthetic restoration in anterior and posterior teeth paid attention to its multiple steps and the time consumption that posed challenges for dentists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Recently, many manufacturers introduced a new single-shade resin composite as it has the advantage of reducing chair time and shade selection time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Moreover, it was reported that any discoloration in the resin composite would affect the aesthetic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Hence, the current study presented the problems of color stability of resin composite after exposure to commonly consumed drinks of different storage periods. The null hypothesis in this study was rejected due to statistically significant differences in color and surface roughness values of both resin composite materials before and after immersion at evaluation with the Vita easy shade, profilometer, and AFM.</p>
              <p id="Par54">The color stability and surface characteristics of the two single-shade resin composites depend on the different compositions, fillers, particle size, and distributed resin matrix. A commercially available supra-nanofiller resin composite (omnichroma) was compared against a nanohybrid resin composite (Venus pearl). Nanotechnology applications introduced in the fillers size range within 0.1- 100 nm to improve properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Studies evaluating the stability of single structured resin composite severely need more to assert its chemical performance. It was stated that details of the fabrication conditions for the organic filler distributed inside the Omnichroma resin could be more precise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par55">The esthetic and mechanical properties of resin composite are influenced not only by their chemical composition but also by the environment to which they are exposed such as chemical agents found in saliva, foods, and beverages either intermittently or continuously. Coffee is an intense stain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and a favorable drink used daily by most people. So, it was chosen as one of the experimental immersing solutions. While distilled water was used as a control to investigate the behavior of the resin composite itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. It is worth mentioning that artificial saliva and distilled water have the same effect on resin composite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par56">In this study, each step was made to standardize the methodology; the specimens’ thickness of 2 mm for the light cure unit, and the curing time was adjusted to 40 s with 20 s exposure time for the top and 20 s for the bottom, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], miller strip and the standardized finishing and polishing procedures. Specimens were immersed in distilled water for 24 h before immersion in the tested solutions to complete polymerization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par57">In the current in-vitro study, a static immersion was done for all specimens for one day and 14 days, equivalent to one month and 14 months of consumption, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The increase in temperature will accelerate color change in the restoration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]; specimens were incubated to adjust the temperature at 37°c all the storage time to simulate the oral environment. Coffee was replaced with a new proportion every 24 h to minimize bacterial growth. </p>
              <p id="Par58">Visual perception of color is a psychological point-view and, unfortunately, depends on the observer's skill [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In order to overcome the problem of visual assessment of the color, many color-evaluating devices have been used as Colorimeters and Spectrophotometers that are more precise than the naked eye [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Color assessments in our study were done using a digital spectrometer device, Vita Easyshade V. This device is considered a reliable tool to measure the color change not only in clinical applications but also for research purposes in evaluating color interactions of human teeth and dental materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par59">Color measurement is usually done by using the CIELAB color system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. CIE L*a*b system is prevalent, providing a standardized technique with helpful analysis of ΔE* values accurately. This system can define small color changes accurately and have many advantages, including objectivity, repeatability, and sensitivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Selecting the CIEDE 2000 color difference formula (ΔE<sub>00</sub>) that was used in this study as it could create a calculation of single-number shade pass or fail in evaluating minor to medium color discrepancies that are more sensitive than the previous CIE L*a*b system.</p>
              <p id="Par60">Surface roughness refers to the finer irregularities of the surface texture that refers to the action of the production process or the material’s features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Currently, several available methods are present to measure the surface texture of any material, including contact stylus tracing, scanning electron microscopy, and atomic force microscopy. Contact stylus tracing was used in the current study because it was fast, simple, and reliable for the comparative assessment of surface roughness properties of both tested single-shade composite resins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Atomic force microscopy (AFM) is a technique for analyzing the topography of the surface. It is an effective technique for characterizing nanoparticles and nanomaterials because it offers qualitative and quantitative information on several physical properties such as size, shape, surface texture, and roughness with a demonstrating image for any surface type, including polymers, ceramics, composites, glass, and biological materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par61">Regarding color stability, the specimens immersed in the coffee solution reported a more significant color change when compared to the specimens immersed in distilled water. This result could be due to the adsorption and absorption of the yellow stains, which have low polarity. This low polarity of yellow stain can penetrate deeper layers of resin composite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], in agreement with many studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. On the opposite side, a study found an acceptable color change after immersion in coffee for 48 h E &lt; 3.3; this may be due to differences in immersion solution preparation methods and concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par62">Perceptibility and acceptability thresholds determine if a color variation is perceptible and whether it is acceptable or not. The current study's perceptibility threshold (ΔE<sub>00</sub>) was set at 0.8. In contrast, the 50:50% acceptability threshold (ΔE<sub>00</sub>) was 1.8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In our study, it was clear that the perceptibility threshold values for all groups were higher than 0.8, as shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Moreover, the acceptability threshold values were higher than 1.8 after 14 days for all groups.</p>
              <p id="Par63">Group O2 and V2 demonstrated unacceptable color change after 14 days of immersion in distilled water which was consistent with a study that had an unacceptable color change of resin composite after immersion in distilled water for five days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Moreover, it has been reported that the water absorption of composite resins reaches its highest level in 7–60 days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In contrast to Farah and Elwi, who found that immersion in distilled water for seven days resulted in imperceptible color changes (ΔE ≤ 1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par64">Nanohybrid (Venus Pearl) composite was more color unstable than nano-filled composite (Omnichroma). According to the data provided by the manufacturer (Kulzer GmbH) who claimed that, Venus Pearl with novel low shrinkage composition of tricyclodecane (TCD)-urethane monomer, which is characterized by big molecular size that demonstrate good chemical stability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Nanohybrid (Venus Pearl) contains tricyclodecane TCD urethane-based monomer, giving high resistance to discoloration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. But lower filler content and presence of nanoclusters could be the reason for the less color resistance in comparison to the nanofilled resin composite (Omnichroma) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par65">Both resin composite materials exhibited statistically significant difference behavior regarding surface roughness at baseline. The O groups showed superior surface smoothness than the V groups, which could be related to the smaller filler size 4 and higher filler loading [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], as mentioned in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. After one day, groups O2 and V2 were significantly the lowest, followed by group O1. While group V2 was significantly the highest. After 14 days, groups O1 and V1 were significantly the highest. At the same time, Group O2 and V2 were significantly the lowest.</p>
              <p id="Par66">A strong and positive correlation between color stability and surface roughness results, as mentioned in (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>) was cleared by the ATF images. It was explained by both resin composite materials' structure and chemical composition. Based on the fact that composite resins with smaller filler sizes exhibit smoother surface properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and less color change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par67">The mean color values and surface roughness after 14 days were the highest for both Groups O1 and V1. It could be due to increased interaction between the resin and the chemicals. More water penetration inside the resin with staining substances of the coffee solution occurred. These conclusions agree with many previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par68">It was stated that when inorganic fillers deboned from the resin matrix, this may leave voids, resulting in surface roughness, forming a surface susceptible to external stains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Additionally, the resin matrix plays an essential role in staining susceptibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Many studies stated that the ability of resin composite to discolor depends on the resin matrix's hydrophilicity and the material's ability to absorb water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Both materials have a matrix composition based on triethylene glycol dimethacrylate (TEGDMA) and urethane dimethacrylate (UDMA). It was reported that TEGDMA monomer is responsible for color change due to high water absorption and increased coloration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In agreement with a study where the most color change was related to the nanofilled single shade resin composite (Omnichroma) after immersion in coffee for one day in comparison to multi-shade resin composite that could be due to TEGDMA in its composition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Different opposite studies' findings stated no correlation between color and roughness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par69">Although the present study confirmed the detrimental effects of tested solutions on single-shade resin composite material, our study has several limitations. Similarly to other in vitro studies, there are factors affecting the restorations in the oral cavity: microbiota, saliva circulation, temperature, and pH changes. Therefore, the oral cavity could not be imitated precisely [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec20">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="Par70">Based on the results gained from this study, we concluded that;<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par71">1- Type of resin composite, and immersion periods have a noticeable effect on color stability and surface roughness of single shade resin composite.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par72">2- The single-shade resin composite tested showed "extremely" high perceptibility and acceptability threshold values and surface roughness even with distilled water.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par73">3- More studies are needed to dig in-depth into the behavior of such materials.</p></list-item></list></p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ΔE</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par5">Color changes</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Ra</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par6">Roughness values</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>AFM</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par7">Atomic Force Microscope</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CIE</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par8">Commission International De L’éclairage system</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SEM</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par9">Scanning electron microscope</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>REC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par10">The Research Ethics Committees</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>TEGDMA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par11">Triethylene glycol dimethacrylate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>UDMA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par12">Urethane dimethacrylate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>TCD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par13">Tricyclodecane</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Not applicable.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>ShR: Conceptualization, methodology, investigation, resources, writing the original draft. HMT: Methodology, visualization, formal analysis, writing—review, and editing. RK: Methodology, visualization, formal analysis, writing—review, and editing. All authors reviewed the manuscript and gave final approval.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB). No funding was obtained for this study.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p>The datasets used and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar5">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par74">The study proposal was reviewed and approved by the Research Ethics Committees (REC) of the Faculty of Dentistry, Cairo University, Egypt, on 29/3/2022. With approval number 30.3.22.</p>
                <p id="Par75">No consent, as no biological or human samples were used in this study.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar6">
                <title>Consent for publication</title>
                <p id="Par76">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar7" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par77">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumari</surname>
                      <given-names>RV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nagaraj</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siddaraju</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poluri</surname>
                      <given-names>RK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the Effect of Surface Polishing, Oral Beverages and Food Colorants on Color Stability and Surface Roughness of Nanocomposite Resins</article-title>
                  <source>J Int Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <lpage>70</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26229373?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26229373</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dietschi</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Optimising aesthetics and facilitating clinical application of free-hand bonding using the ‘natural layering concept</article-title>
                  <source>Br Dent J</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>204</volume>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <lpage>185</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bdj.2008.100</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18297019?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18297019</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soliman</surname>
                      <given-names>YA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahmoud</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gepreel</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Afifi</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The ability of coffee to stain nanohybrid composite resins</article-title>
                  <source>Alexa Dent J</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <lpage>95</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aydın</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karaoğlanoğlu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oktay</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ersöz</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Investigation of single shade composite resin surface roughness and color stability</article-title>
                  <source>Atatürk Üniversitesi Diş Hekimliği Fakültesi Dergisi</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <lpage>214</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alkhadim</surname>
                      <given-names>YK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hulbah</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nassar</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Color Shift, Color Stability, and Post-Polishing Surface Roughness of Esthetic Resin Composites</article-title>
                  <source>Materials</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1376</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma13061376</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32197532?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32197532</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bansal</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acharya</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saraswathi</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of alcoholic and non-alcoholic beverages on color stability and surface roughness of resin composites: An in vitro study</article-title>
                  <source>J Conserv Dent: JCD</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <lpage>288</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0972-0707.97961</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22876020?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22876020</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bollen</surname>
                      <given-names>CML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lambrechts</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quirynen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of surface roughness of oral hard materials to the threshold surface roughness for bacterial plaque retention: a review of the literature</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Mater</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <lpage>269</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0109-5641(97)80038-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11696906?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11696906</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reddy</surname>
                      <given-names>PS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of commonly consumed beverages on surface roughness and color stability of the nano, microhybrid and hybrid composite resins: an in vitro study</article-title>
                  <source>Jo Contemp Dent Pract</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>718</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10024-1390</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aydın</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Topçu</surname>
                      <given-names>FT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karaoğlanoğlu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oktay</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Erdemir</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of finishing and polishing systems on the surface roughness and color change of composite resins</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Exp Dent</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>e446</fpage>
                  <lpage>e454</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4317/jced.58011</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33981391?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33981391</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kılıç</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gök</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of different polishing systems on the surface roughness of various bulk-fill and nano-filled resin-based composites: An atomic force microscopy and scanning electron microscopy study</article-title>
                  <source>Microsc Res Tech</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>84</volume>
                  <fpage>2058</fpage>
                  <lpage>2067</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jemt.23761</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33772935?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33772935</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Da Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferracane</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paravina</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mazur</surname>
                      <given-names>RF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roeder</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of different polishing systems on surface roughness and gloss of various resin composites</article-title>
                  <source>J Esthet Restor Dent</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <lpage>24; discussion 225-6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1708-8240.2007.00104.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17635330?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17635330</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soliman</surname>
                      <given-names>YA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahmoud</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gepreel</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Afifi</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The ability of coffee to stain nanohybrid composite resins</article-title>
                  <source>Alex Dent J</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <lpage>95</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">ManualUserGuide(VitaEasyShadeV):VITA_10180_10180E_VITA_Easyshade_V_GA_EN_V08_screen_en.pdf</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>ElAziz</surname>
                      <given-names>RHA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gadallah</surname>
                      <given-names>LK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saleh</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of Charcoal and Sea Salt-Lemon-based Whitening Toothpastes on Color Change and Surface Roughness of Stained Teeth</article-title>
                  <source>J Contemp Dent Pract</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <lpage>175</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10024-3300</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 35748445?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35748445</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morsy A, Gamal W, Riad M. Color Matching of a Single Shade Structurally Colored Universal Resin Composite with the Surrounding Hard Dental Tissues. Egyptian Dental Journal. 2020;66(Issue 4 - October (Conservative Dentistry and Endodontics)), 2721–2727.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>YıldırımBilmez</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Şeker</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Köse</surname>
                      <given-names>HD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gözüyeşil Aslan</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of liquid sorption and color stability of dental composites after exposure to common lactation teas</article-title>
                  <source>Int Dent Res</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl. 1</issue>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <lpage>233</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5577/intdentres.2021.vol11.suppl1.33</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nasim</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neelakantan</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sujeer</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Subbarao</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Color stability of microfilled, microhybrid and nanocomposite resins—an in vitro study</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>e137</fpage>
                  <lpage>e142</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2010.05.020</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20553993?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20553993</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gönülol</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of finishing and polishing techniques on surface roughness and color stability of nanocomposites</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>e64</fpage>
                  <lpage>e70</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2012.07.005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22819955?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22819955</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maesako</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kishimoto</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Horie</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Inoue</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizuno</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tomoda</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fujitani</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microstructural Properties and Surface Properties of a New Resin Composite Employing Structural Color Technology</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Hard Tissue Biology</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <lpage>12</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2485/jhtb.30.7</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gross</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moser</surname>
                      <given-names>JB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A colorimetric study of coffee and tea staining of four composite resins</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>1977</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <lpage>322</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2842.1977.tb00997.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 269919?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">269919</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hussain</surname>
                      <given-names>SK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Abbasi</surname>
                      <given-names>SW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Refaat</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hussain</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of staining and bleaching on the color of two different types of composite restoration</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Exp Dent</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>e1233</fpage>
                  <lpage>e1238</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4317/jced.58837</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34987716?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34987716</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bétrisey</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bella</surname>
                      <given-names>ED</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krejci</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ardu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of Storage Media on Color Stability of Different Resin Composites as Determined by ΔE and ΔE00</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Adv Res</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>NovinRooz</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yousefi</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Effect of Shade and Thickness on the Depth of Cure of Bulk-Fill Composites with Different Viscosities</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent (Shiraz)</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>322</fpage>
                  <lpage>329</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33344683</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rajkumar</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahalaxmi</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ragavi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mageshwaran</surname>
                      <given-names>TA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Color stability of resin composites after immersing in coffee of different temperatures - an in vitro study</article-title>
                  <source>Streamdent; SRM Univ J Dent Sci</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <lpage>95</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alghazali</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burnside</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Preston</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jarad</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Performance assessment of Vita Easy Shade spectrophotometer on color measurement of aesthetic dental materials</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Prosthodont Restor Dent</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <lpage>174</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22645803?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22645803</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marghalani</surname>
                      <given-names>HY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of filler particles on surface roughness of experimental composite series</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <lpage>67</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-77572010000100011</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20379683?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20379683</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hiremath</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thipperudrappa</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bhat</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Surface Morphology Analysis using Atomic Force Microscopy and Statistical Method for Glass Fiber Reinforced Epoxy-Zinc Oxide Nanocomposites</article-title>
                  <source>Engineered Science</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <lpage>319</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sabah</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wahhab</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alkhalidi</surname>
                      <given-names>Dr</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Emad &amp; Assist, Alkhalidi &amp; Prof, Ph. </surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Color Change of Two Different Nano-Hybrid Resin Composite Materials after Staining and Bleaching. (An in vitro Study)</article-title>
                  <source>Medico-Legal Update</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <fpage>1314</fpage>
                  <lpage>1319</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farah</surname>
                      <given-names>RI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Elwi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spectrophotometric Evaluation of Color Changes of Bleach-shade Resin-based Composites after Staining and Bleaching</article-title>
                  <source>J Contemp Dent Pract</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>587</fpage>
                  <lpage>594</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10024-1584</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25707831?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25707831</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>DCRS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Menezes</surname>
                      <given-names>LR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gatti</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>CorrerSobrinho</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferracane</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinhoreti</surname>
                      <given-names>MAC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of Nanofiller Loading on Cure Efficiency and Potential Color Change of Model Composites</article-title>
                  <source>J Esthet Restor Dent</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <lpage>177</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jerd.12189</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26880567?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26880567</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karatas</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An evaluation of surface roughness after staining of different composite resins using atomic force microscopy and a profilometer</article-title>
                  <source>Microsc Res Tech</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1251</fpage>
                  <lpage>1259</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32519401?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32519401</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bagheri</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burrow</surname>
                      <given-names>MF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tyas</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of food-simulating solutions and surface finish on susceptibility to staining of aesthetic restorative materials</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <lpage>398</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2004.10.018</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15833394?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15833394</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reinhardt</surname>
                      <given-names>JW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Balbierz</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schultz</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simetich</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beatty</surname>
                      <given-names>MW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of Tooth-Whitening Procedures on Stained Composite Resins</article-title>
                  <source>Oper Dent</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <lpage>75</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2341/17-301-L</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29570025?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29570025</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Patil</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muliya</surname>
                      <given-names>VS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pentapati</surname>
                      <given-names>KC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamath</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of Green, Tulsi, and Areca Teas on the Color Stability of Two Composite Resin Materials - an in vitro Spectrophotometric Analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Cosmet Investig Dent</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
                  <lpage>428</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CCIDE.S276858</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33116911?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33116911</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kangwankai</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sani</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Panpisut</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Monomer conversion, dimensional stability, strength, modulus, surface apatite precipitation and wear of novel, reactive calcium phosphate and polylysine-containing dental composites</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>e0187757</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0187757</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29136013?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29136013</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yikilgan</surname>
                      <given-names>İ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akgul</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hazar</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kedici Alp</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baglar</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bala</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of fresh detox juices on color stability and roughness of resin-based composites</article-title>
                  <source>J Prosthodont</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <lpage>88</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jopr.12759</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
