<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10508049" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10508049</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-09-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>dpjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dpjo</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2176-9451</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2177-6709</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dental Press International</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10508049</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10508049</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10508049</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37729286</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2177-6709.28.4.e2322220.oar</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">00302</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Short-term assessment of pain and discomfort during rapid maxillary
expansion with tooth-bone-borne and tooth-borne appliances: randomized clinical
trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0890-6179</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>PASQUA</surname>
                    <given-names>Bruno de Paula Machado</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Conception or design of the study</role>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                  <role>Fundraising</role>
                  <role>Overall responsibility</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7756-7986</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>ANDRÉ</surname>
                    <given-names>Cristiane Barros</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Conception or design of the study</role>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                  <role>Fundraising</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3178-4843</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>de PAIVA</surname>
                    <given-names>João Batista</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9124-8698</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>RINO</surname>
                    <given-names>José</given-names>
                    <suffix>NETO</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Conception or design of the study</role>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                  <role>Fundraising</role>
                  <role>Overall responsibility</role>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>University of São Paulo, School of Orthodontics (São Paulo/SP,
Brazil).</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>University of Mogi das Cruzes, Technology Research Center (Mogi das
Cruzes/SP, Brazil).</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>University of São Paulo, Department for Orthodontics (São Paulo/SP,
Brazil).</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">
                  <email>brunompasqua@yahoo.com</email>
                </corresp>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2">
                  <label>»</label>
                  <p> The authors report no commercial, proprietary or financial interest in the
products or companies described in this article.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>28</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <elocation-id>e2322220</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>ABSTRACT</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective: </title>
                  <p>The aim of this randomized clinical trial was to evaluate and compare, during
the first week of rapid maxillary expansion (RME), the impact caused by two
types of appliances: Hyrax and Hybrid Hyrax. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods: </title>
                  <p>Forty-two patients who met the eligibility criteria (aged 11-14 years, with
transverse maxillary deficiency, posterior crossbite, and presence of
maxillary first premolars and first permanent molars) were selected and
randomly divided into two groups: TBB GROUP (tooth-bone-borne expander),
treated with Hybrid Hyrax (12 females and 9 males, mean age 13.3 ± 1.3
years), and TB GROUP (tooth-borne expander), treated with Hyrax (5 females
and 16 males, mean age 13.3 ± 1.4 years). Pain and discomfort were assessed
in two times: after the first day of activation (T1) and four days after, by
means of the numerical rate scale and the instrument MFIQ (Mandibular
Functional Impairment Questionnaire). Descriptive statistics and the
Mann-Whitney test were used for comparison between groups and between sexes.
A 5% significance level was adopted. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results: </title>
                  <p>Both appliances had a negative impact, generating pain and discomfort, and
reducing functional capacity. However, the scores obtained were of low
intensity and no significant differences were observed between the groups.
Considering sexes, there were statistically significant differences, with
the female sex presenting higher scores for pain and functional limitation.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions:</title>
                  <p> Despite causing impact in pain and increase in the functional limitation,
these changes were of low intensity, with no statistical difference between
the groups. Females were more sensitive to the impact caused by the RME.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <title>RESUMO</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objetivo: </title>
                  <p>O objetivo deste ensaio clínico randomizado foi avaliar e comparar, durante a
primeira semana de expansão rápida da maxila (ERM), o impacto causado por
dois tipos de aparelhos: Hyrax e Hyrax Híbrido. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Métodos: </title>
                  <p>Quarenta e dois pacientes que atendiam aos critérios de seleção (idade de 11
a 14 anos, com deficiência transversal da maxila, mordida cruzada posterior
e presença de primeiros pré-molares e primeiros molares permanentes
superiores) foram selecionados e divididos aleatoriamente em dois grupos:
Grupo DOS (expansor dento-osseossuportado), tratado com Hyrax Híbrido (12
mulheres e 9 homens, idade média 13,3 ± 1,3 anos), e Grupo DS (expansor
dentossuportado), tratado com Hyrax (5 mulheres e 16 homens, idade média de
13,3 ± 1,4 anos). A dor e o desconforto foram avaliados em dois momentos:
após o primeiro dia de ativação (T1) e após quatro dias, por meio da escala
de frequência numérica e do instrumento MFIQ (Questionário de Limitação
Funcional Mandibular). A estatística descritiva e o teste de Mann-Whitney
foram utilizados para comparação entre os grupos e entre os sexos. Adotou-se
nível de significância de 5%. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Resultados: </title>
                  <p>Ambos os aparelhos tiveram impacto negativo, gerando dor e desconforto e
reduzindo a capacidade funcional. No entanto, os escores obtidos foram de
baixa intensidade e não foram observadas diferenças significativas entre os
grupos. Considerando os sexos, houve diferenças estatisticamente
significativas, com o sexo feminino apresentando maiores escores para dor e
limitação funcional. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusões:</title>
                  <p> Apesar de causar impacto na dor e aumento na limitação funcional, essas
alterações foram de baixa intensidade, sem diferença estatística entre os
grupos. As mulheres foram mais sensíveis ao impacto causado pela ERM.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords:</title>
                <kwd>Rapid palatal expansion</kwd>
                <kwd>Orthodontic anchorage procedures</kwd>
                <kwd>Pain</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="4"/>
                <table-count count="6"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="28"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Rapid maxillary expansion (RME) is a procedure that aims to correct maxillary
transverse deficiency and posterior crossbite by opening the midpalatal suture. This
technique has proven effective in orthodontics, and is commonly used in clinical
practice.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Although, some side effects, such as buccal tipping of posterior teeth, root
resorption of supporting teeth, and changes in buccal and palatal bone plate
thickness of maxillary premolars, have been observed with both tooth-tissue-borne
and tooth-borne appliances.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>Wilmes et al.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> developed a tooth-bone-borne expander for growing patients, with the goal of
potentiating orthopedic effects and decreasing side effects during RME. This
appliance has hybrid support: posterior dental support and anterior support provided
by means of orthodontic mini-screws in the palatal region, located posteriorly to
the third palatal rugae. This appliance is advantageous in performing RME for
patients with unerupted premolars and absent or incomplete root development;
additionally, it provides more pronounced skeletal changes, minor side effects in
the first premolar region, less tooth tipping, and low impact on the oral
health-related quality of life.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Besides that, an important finding was the more pronounced effect in the
nasal region,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> suggesting a greater increase in airway volume compared to conventional
appliances.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>Patients undergoing RME with conventional appliances often report discomfort, pain,
and even functional limitations.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> However, few studies have specifically evaluated the effects of the Hybrid
Hyrax. A recent study reported no significant differences in pain and discomfort
between Hyrax and Hybrid Hyrax.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>Several methods for measuring pain intensity have been described in the literature,
and the pain numerical rate scale (NRS) has proven to be more appropriate due to the
ease of clinical application and patient understanding.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> For the evaluation of discomfort, quality of life, as well as functional
limitations, there are psychometric instruments specific for Dentistry.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> The mandibular functional impairment questionnaire (MFIQ) specifically aims
to assess the patient’s perception of mandibular functional impairment, such as
difficulty in eating, speaking, swallowing, and yawning.<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>
</p>
              <sec>
                <title>SPECIFIC OBJECTIVES OR HYPOTHESES</title>
                <p>Considering the importance of patients’ well-being, the present study aimed to
evaluate and compare the impact of two types of maxillary expansion appliances
(tooth-bone-borne and tooth-borne) with respect to pain, discomfort, and
functional limitation during the first week of RME activation in growing
patients, by assessing pain (NRS) and functional limitation (MFIQ). Since the
Hybrid Hyrax is a new appliance, the literature on its symptomatology is scarce.
Although this appliance has shown promising results, it involves a more invasive
technique than traditional appliances, then it is necessary to understand more
broadly its impact. The null hypothesis tested was that there would be no
difference for the pain and discomfort impact between these appliances.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>ETHICAL ASPECTS AND STUDY DESIGN</title>
                <p>This was a prospective randomized clinical trial that was approved by the Ethics
Committee on Human Research of University of São Paulo, School of Dentistry,
under the protocol number: 3.311.813. This study was also registered in the
REBEC clinical trials (RBR-48g9q6). The Consolidated Standards of Reporting
Trials (CONSORT) statement and guidelines were followed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>PARTICIPANTS, ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA, AND SETTING</title>
                <p>Patients aged 11-14 years, who visited the orthodontic clinic at University of
São Paulo, School of Dentistry between January and July 2018, were screened for
eligibility. Participants who met the eligibility criteria were invited to
participate, and informed consent was obtained from all patients and their
parents or legal guardians. The inclusion criteria were as follows: age between
11 and 14 years, transverse maxillary deficiency, bilateral or unilateral
posterior crossbite, and the presence of maxillary first premolars and maxillary
first permanent molars. The exclusion criteria were: the presence of systemic
diseases, history of previous orthodontic treatment, presence of cleft lip and
palate, presence of congenital deformities, and agenesia or loss of permanent
teeth. </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>INTERVENTIONS</title>
                <p>The Hybrid Hyrax appliance used in this study was supported by two mini-implants
inserted in the anterior region of the palate, posterior to the third palatal
rugae, paramedian 2-3 mm from the palatal raphe, based on the appliance of
Wilmes et al.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> This site, known as the T-zone, has great bone thickness and density,
and is located away from structures such as roots, blood vessels, or
nerves.<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> The mini-implants were placed manually. To obtain the correct
angulation, a mini-implant hand-key was used (Peclab, Belo Horizonte/MG), with
fitting for counter-angle (Kavo do Brasil Ind. Com. Ltda, Joinville/SC, Brazil).
The upper first permanent molars were chosen as posterior anchorage and banded. </p>
                <p>Mini-implants (1.5-mm in diameter; 8-mm in length, Dental Morelli LTDA,
Sorocaba/SP, Brazil) were inserted after local anesthesia using lidocaine.
Further, a digital dental scan of the maxillary arch was performed using an
intraoral scanner (Trios Pod version, 3Shape, Copenhagen, Denmark). The model
was printed using a Form2 printer (Form labs, Somerville, Massachusetts, USA),
and the appliance was fabricated on the printed model (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>A, Hybrid Hyrax, tooth-bone-borne appliance, TBB
group).</p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f1">
                    <label>Figure 1:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>A) TBB group ( Hybrid Hyrax ). B) TB group ( Hyrax ). </title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-04-e2322220-gf1" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p>The same digital workflow was used to manufacture the Hyrax tooth-borne appliance
(TB group, <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>B), which was anchored on
four bands (first premolars and first molars). For both groups, the 11-mm
Hyrax-type expander screw (Peclab, Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil) was
used.</p>
                <p>All patients were treated by the same orthodontist, and the activation protocol
was the same in both groups: The expander screw was activated on the first day
with one full turn (four activations of ¼ turn), and in the following days, ¼
turn twice a day (every 12 h) until correction of the maxillary deficiency and
overcorrection of crossbite (occlusion of the palatal cusp of the maxillary
first permanent molars with the corresponding buccal cusp of the mandibular
first permanent molars). No analgesics were prescribed; however, the patients
were allowed to use them at their discretion. None of the patients reported
using analgesics.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>MEASUREMENTS</title>
                <sec>
                  <title> Pain intensity assessment </title>
                  <p>The pain NRS (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>) was used for the
subjective assessment of pain intensity experienced by the patients (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The participants scored the
pain in different regions of the mouth (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) using a numerical scale from 0 to 10, based on the
article by Feldman and Bazargani.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> ‘No pain’ was scored as 0, and ‘The worst possible pain’ was scored
as 10. </p>
                  <p>
                    <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
                      <label>Table 1:</label>
                      <caption>
                        <title>Questions concerning pain and discomfort, assessed at T1
(after the first day of activation) and T2 (after the fourth day
of activation) (Feldman and Bazargani<sup>15</sup>,
2017).</title>
                      </caption>
                      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                        <colgroup span="1">
                          <col span="1"/>
                          <col span="1"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                          <tr>
                            <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th>
                            <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Score (0 to 10)</th>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAIN</th>
                          </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1- Do you now have pain?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 - Do you now have pain from the
molars?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 - Do you now have pain from the
incisors?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 - Do you now have pain from the upper
jaw?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 - Do you now have pain from the
palate?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 - Do you now have pain from the
tongue?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DISCOMFORT</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 - Do you experience tensions in your
upper jaw?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 - Do you experience tensions in your
teeth?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                          <tr>
                            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 - Do you experience soreness from the
appliance?</td>
                            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          </tr>
                        </tbody>
                      </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                    <fig position="float" id="f2">
                      <label>Figure 2:</label>
                      <caption>
                        <title>Numerical rate scale ( NRS ) for pain assessment.</title>
                      </caption>
                      <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-04-e2322220-gf2" position="float"/>
                    </fig>
                  </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title> MFIQ instrument </title>
                  <p>Using the MFIQ,<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> it was possible to quantify the patient’s functional limitations
regarding functional capacity and eating. The original version comprised 17
items. In the present study, the Portuguese validated version was used.<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> The instrument was applied using an interview in the first week of
activation at two time-points (T1 - after the first day of activation, and
T2 - after the fourth day of activation), according to the methodology of
Feldmann and Bazargani.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> A score was assigned to each question that represented the level of
difficulty to develop routine activities, ranging from 0 (no difficulty) to
4 (very difficult or impossible without help). The creators of this
instrument have proposed the possibility of categorizing the results in
quantitative (ranging from 0 to 1) and qualitative (low, moderate, or severe
functional impairment) formats. A quantitative format was used to facilitate
the data interpretation. </p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>PRIMARY OUTCOME</title>
                <p>The primary outcome was the comparison between groups and sexes regarding pain
intensity, discomfort, and functional limitation during the first week of RME
activation with the two appliances evaluated.</p>
                <p>The secondary outcome was the correlation between pain and MFIQ with age and
skeletal maturation of the midpalatal suture.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>SAMPLE SIZE CALCULATION</title>
                <p>This study used the same sample as well as some statistical data of a previous
randomized clinical trial.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> However, other parameters were evaluated using new information. The
present study aimed at evaluating dental and skeletal effects of RME, using
cone-beam computed tomography (CBCT). A sample calculation was performed based
on skeletal changes after RME, observed on the coronal section of CBCT images,
specifically in the premolar region,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> reported as being on average equal to 3.33 ± 3.58 mm. Considering a
significance level of 0.05 and a type II error of 20%, the minimum number of
patients per group was calculated to be 19, using a two-tailed test. Considering
a sample loss of 10%, the final sample size was calculated as 42, with 21
patients per group.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>INTERIM ANALYSES AND STOPPING GUIDELINES</title>
                <p>No interim analysis was conducted, all data were analyzed after the study was
completed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>RANDOMIZATION</title>
                <p>The sequence of 42 numbers corresponding to the patients (each number
corresponding to a patient) was randomized into two groups using the excel
RANDOM function.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>BLINDING</title>
                <p>Double blinding was not possible due to the type of interventions administered
(clinical treatment). However, before the data assessment and statistical
analysis, the questionnaires were identified with only a coded ID number, for
another examiner to compute the scores. Therefore, the examiner did not know
which patient the scores belonged to.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</title>
                <p>The evaluated measurements were described according to groups, using means ±
standard deviations, or medians and interquartile ranges, and the values before
expansion were compared between the groups using Student’s t-test or
Mann-Whitney U test. The sex of the patients was described according to groups,
using absolute and relative frequencies; and the association between the groups
was determined using chi-square or Fisher’s exact tests.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p>For the comparison of pain and functional limitation between the groups and
between sexes, the Mann-Whitney U test was used.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Thus, for pain and the total value, each parameter was evaluated
separately (region of pain and discomfort). To interpret the MFIQ instrument,
the raw score of each of the two domains was analyzed individually; the
patient’s total functional limitation was analyzed following the methodology of
Stengenga et al.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> (calculation of the raw score component, which ranges from 0 to 1). This
comparison was performed between T1 and T2. For all the intergroup comparisons,
the observed power was calculated by the Student’s t-test, to present the
sample’s power of discrimination on the results.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p>Spearman’s correlations were calculated between pain and MFIQ and the data
regarding the initial age and midpalatal suture maturation (evaluated by the
method of Angelieri et al.<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>) to verify possible correlations between them. Differences with a
<italic>p</italic>-value of less than 5% (<italic>p</italic>&lt; 0.05) were
considered statistically significant. Analyses were performed using IBM SPSS for
Windows v. 20.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>PARTICIPANTS FLOW</title>
                <p>A total of 477 patients were screened between January and July 2018. By means of
clinical examination, 42 participants were enrolled; 431 participants were
excluded because they did not meet the eligibility criteria, and four dropped
out (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). After the recruitment,
forty-two patients were randomly assigned to the study groups in a 1:1 ratio.
Only one patient was lost because he/she missed the appointment and did not
answer the questionnaires (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). TBB
group was composed by 12 girls and 9 boys, with mean initial age of 13.3 years,
and TB group was composed by 5 girls and 16 boys with mean initial age of 13.2
years.</p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f3">
                    <label>Figure 3:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Consort flow chart diagram.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-04-e2322220-gf3" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>BASELINE DATA</title>
                <p><xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows that the sexes distribution
between groups was statistically different (<italic>p</italic>= 0.037).
Regarding the other initial characteristics, there were no statistically
significant differences between the groups.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
                    <label>Table 2:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Baseline characteristics of the groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB group Hybrid Hyrax Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB group Hyrax Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB - TB Mean difference (95% CI)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex </td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037<sup>†</sup>* </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (57.1%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (23.8%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (42.1%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (76.2%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midpalatal suture maturation</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.911<sup>§</sup>
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage A</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.1%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage B</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.3%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.1%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage C</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (16.7 %)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (16.7 %)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage D</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.1%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage E</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.5%)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.5%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 (1.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 (1.4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (-0.7; 0.9)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782 <sup>‡</sup>
</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN1">
                        <p>SD: standard deviation. CI: confidence interval. <sup>†</sup>
<italic>p-</italic>values for Pearson’s chi-square test.
<sup>§</sup>
<italic>p</italic>-values for Mann-Whitney test.
<sup>‡</sup> <italic>p-</italic>values for independent
<italic>t</italic>-test. *<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05;
**<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01;
***<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001;
****<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>NUMBERS ANALYZED FOR EACH OUTCOME, ESTIMATION, AND PRECISION</title>
                <p>No statistically significant differences were found between the groups for any of
the questions evaluated, regarding pain and discomfort, at T1 and T2 (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t3">
                    <label>Table 3:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Medians, percentile range, <italic>p-</italic>value and observed
power resulting from comparative analysis for pain. Comparisons
between groups defined by Mann-Whitney, and significance at
<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>p</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed Power</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>p</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed Power</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">T1 </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">T2 </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1">PAIN </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 - Do you now have pain?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0; 3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0; 2.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.4263</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 2)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.225</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 - Do you now have pain from the molars?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0; 4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0; 3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.4039</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0; 3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 1.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.187</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 - Do you now have pain from the
incisors?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 2)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 0)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.2849</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0; 5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 1.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.078</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.633</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 - Do you now have pain from the upper
jaw?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0; 2)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0; 1.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.7842</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 2.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0. 403</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 - Do you now have pain from the palate?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 0)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.5661</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 0)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.210</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.270</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 - Do you now have pain from the tongue?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 0)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.5144</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 0)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0; 2)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.575</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1"> DISCOMFORT </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 - Do you experience tensions in your upper
jaw?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1; 5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0; 4.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.2405</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0; 6)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (0.8; 3.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.522</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 - Do you experience tensions in your
teeth?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2; 6)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1; 4.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.3613</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1; 9)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (1; 5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0. 170</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.446</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 - Do you experience soreness from the
appliance?</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0; 5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.8; 3.5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.4339</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1; 8)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0; 3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.215</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.461</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOTAL SCORE</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.5; 2.8)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.1; 2.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.205</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5(1.6; 3.4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (0.7; 2.1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P= 0.066</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.502</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN2">
                        <p>Md: median. IQR: interquartile range.
*<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05; **<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01;
***<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001;
****<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>Regarding the analysis of pain and discomfort, there was no statistically
significant difference between the groups (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig
4</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f4">
                    <label>Figure 4:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Median values, percentile ranges, and observed power, concerning
to pain intensity (P), discomfort (D) and total score (TS) related
to RME in the first week in treatment. </title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-04-e2322220-gf4" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p>According to the intergroup comparison of MFIQ results, there was no
statistically significant difference between the groups in terms of functional
capacity, feeding, and functional limitation (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). For the comparative analysis between sexes (<xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), no statistically significant
differences were found between male and female with respect to total pain.
However, for functional capacity, nutrition, and total MFIQ, greater sensitivity
was found in females, with statistically significant differences.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t4">
                    <label>Table 4:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Medians, interquartile range, <italic>p-</italic>value and
observed power resulting from comparative analysis for Functional
capacity, Feeding, and MFIQ total score. Comparisons between groups
defined by Mann-Whitney and significance at p&lt;0.05.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed Power</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed Power</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">T1 </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">T2 </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional capacity (FC)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.1; 0.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0; 0.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.9480</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0; 0.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0; 0.6)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.592</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeding (F)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.6481</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0; 1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.396</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MFIQ total score</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0; 0.8)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2; 0.8)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.8756</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0; 0.8)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0; 0.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.433</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN3">
                        <p>Md: median. IQR: interquartile range.
*<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05; **<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01;
***<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001;
****<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t5">
                    <label>Table 5:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Medians, interquartile range, <italic>p-</italic>value and
observed power resulting from comparative analysis for Functional
capacity, Feeding, and MFIQ total score. Comparisons between genders
defined by Mann-Whitney and significance at p&lt;0.05.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed Power</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female Md (IQR)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed Power</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">T1 </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">T2 </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (0.7; 2.2)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.1; 3.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.375</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.2; 2.4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (0.9; 3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.354</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional capacity</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.1; 0.3)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.3; 0.5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.1 0.4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.2; 0.4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.492</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeding</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.3; 0.6)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.5; 0.8)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.762</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.1; 0.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.4; 0.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.600</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MFIQ total score</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.2; 0.4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.4; 0.6)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005**</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.761</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.1; 0.5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.3; 0.5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN4">
                        <p>Md: median. IQR: interquartile range.
*<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05; **<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01;
***<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001;
****<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>Finally, no significant correlations were found between pain and MFIQ and age and
maturity of the midpalatal suture at both T1 and T2 (<xref rid="t6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Orthodontic patients frequently report pain and discomfort.<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Few studies have reported these manifestations in RME.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> The RME expanders are well-accepted by patients, despite the common reports
of pain. Studies of these side effects in patients treated with tooth-bone-borne
expansion appliances are less frequent.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> In addition to analyzing the efficacy of a new treatment method, it is also
necessary to investigate the patients’ acceptance and adaptation to the new
appliance, especially the impact of pain, eating discomfort, and the patient’s
functional capacity. Efficient care is necessary for managing these signs and
symptoms, which are common during RME. </p>
              <p>Common methods to assess patients’ experiences of pain during treatment include the
use of pain scales. The visual analog scale and the NRS are the most commonly
used.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> In the present study, the numerical scale was chosen, since it has already
been presented as a method of easy applicability and understanding by the
patient.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> To evaluate the experience of pain specifically for RME, the methodology
described by Feldemann and Bazargani was used,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> since it was the only study that aimed to score the pain directed to the
areas most commonly affected by RME. </p>
              <p>The assessment of pain score and the use of MFIQ instrument were performed after the
first and fourth days of the first activation, since this is the time of greatest
patient discomfort during orthodontic treatment (first week).<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref>. In the present study the patients had mean age of 13.27 ± 1.32 years. The
choice of this age range (11 to 14 years old) was based on other studies with Hybrid
Hyrax,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> because during this period, RME indications are more sensible. Although this
is still a growth phase, the midpalatal suture may be more interdigitated, becoming
resistant to RME,<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> and hybrid anchorage is indicated in these cases. A statistically
significant difference between the groups was observed according to sex. Despite the
randomness in the selection, because it is a small sample for a categorized
variable, this unbalance can occur. Nonetheless, it was assumed that it did not
influence the results.</p>
              <p>Both appliances caused pain (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) during
the first week of activation, as well as changes in functional capacity and feeding
(<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). However, these changes were of
a low intensity. Regarding pain at T1, on a scale of 0 to 10 (considering the total
score), the medians (percentiles) were 1.7 (1.2-3.3) in the TBB group, and 1.3
(0.9-1.8) in the TB group, with no statistically significant difference between the
groups. At T2, the medians (percentiles) were 2.1 (0.9-3.9) in the TBB group and 1.1
(0.4-1.8) in the TB group, with no statistically significant difference. Considering
the different regions assessed, the most common pain was general pain (question 1 -
<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), and pain in the molar region
(question 2 - <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This occurred in both
groups and may be a consequence of the appliance support, which in both groups
occured in the first permanent molars. No statistically significant difference was
observed between the groups in any of the variables (questions) evaluated. This
indicates that both appliances are well-tolerated by patients, with respect to pain.
This is an important finding when considering RME treatment anchored on miniscrews,
since the advantages of these appliances, such as better skeletal outcomes, better
outcomes in terms of increased skeletal changes, and fewer dental side effects, have
already been observed.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Nevertheless, a more pronounced sensitivity was found in those patients
treated with the Hybrid Hyrax, unlike what was previously reported.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> This also occurred regarding discomfort, in question 9 (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), in which the Hybrid appliance showed
twice the value of the Hyrax. Despite this discrepancy, this raises an alert that
patients treated with Hybrid Hyrax may have a slight increase in sensitivity during
rapid maxillary expansion.</p>
              <p>Additionally, in both groups, the intensity of pain was lower at T2. Pain during RME
is reportedly greater in the first activation, whereas in the study of Halicioğlu et
al.,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> the peak of pain was at the fifth activation, and in the study of Nedlemann
et al.,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> it was at the sixth activation. In the present study, a higher peak of pain
was found at T1, which coincides with the fifth and sixth activations of the
appliance, which conforms with the results of these studies. This provides further
evidence of the similarity between the two types of appliances in terms of pain
symptoms.</p>
              <p>Orthodontists know that with aging, bone maturation of the midpalatal suture
increases.<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Thus, the authors of the present study believe that older patients
experience more pain due to the greater resistance to expansion caused by the
midpalatal suture, which is more interdigitated. Conversely, the results of this
study showed that, considering both groups, there was no correlation between pain
and age at both T1 and T2 (<xref rid="t6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). This
result can be explained by the short age range of patients in this study (11-14
years). The findings of the present study are consistent with those of previous
studies.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="t6">
                  <label>Table 6:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Spearman correlation coefficient (significance at
<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05).</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial age r(p)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midpalatal suture maturation r(p)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial age r(p)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midpalatal suture maturation r(p)</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">T1 </th>
                        <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">T2 </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.029 (0.859) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100 (0.532) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.041 (0.798) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.166 (0.301) </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional capacity</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.098 (0.542)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082 (0.611)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.077 (0.632)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061 (0.707)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeding</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085 (0.597)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009 (0.955)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073 (0.651)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132 (0.410)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOTAL MFIQ</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.040 (0.804)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080 (0.617)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.016 (0.919)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131 (0.413)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN5">
                      <p>*<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05; **<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01;
***<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001;
****<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>The results showed that there were statistically significant differences between
sexes, considering the variables assessed by the MFIQ instrument (<xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), with the worst experience reported
among females, which is in agreement with a previous study.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Thus, this difference regarding pain between sexes should be considered
during pain management in RME treatments. However, other studies have reported no
statistically significant differences between groups.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>Regarding the MFIQ instrument, no statistically significant differences were found
between the groups at T1 and T2 in terms of the functional capacity, nutrition, and
functional limitation. The medians obtained from the total score for functional
limitation in both groups were of low intensity. These results, reveal that the
limitation caused by both appliances was similar, as previously reported.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>A greater impact was noticed in both groups at T1 than at T2. This probably occurred
because the participants begin to get accustomed to the appliance and to the changes
that occurred in their mouth. Despite this, the scores at T2 were lower in both
groups, with no statistically significant difference between them, suggesting that
the patients were adapted. Moreover, as the pain decreased concomitantly, the
patients’ activities became unaltered. </p>
              <p>The equivalence between the symptomatology during RME and between the two evaluated
appliances is extremely important data for the literature, because both appliances
were well-tolerated by the patients. One should consider that the hybrid Hyrax
generates a slightly higher cost, due to requiring intraoral scanning. However,
considering the advantages observed in the reduction of side effects,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> more pronounced skeletal effects and better efficiency in nasal airway
improving,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> the use of this appliance seems promising. Systematic reviews are essential
to substantiate the findings of these studies.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>LIMITATIONS AND GENERALIZABILITY</title>
              <p>The sample size calculation for this study was based on skeletal changes in the
nasomaxillary region, and not on pain intensity or discomfort. The mini-implants
insertion process can generate discomfort in the first hours after insertion, and
future studies are necessary to evaluate and consider pain during mini-implants
placement.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>HARMS</title>
              <p>No serious harm was observed other than pain and discomfort during RME.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» Pain and functional limitation were common for patients in both groups
during RME at both T1 (1 day after the start of activation) and T2 (4
days after the first activation). The values obtained were of low
intensity, with no statistical difference between the groups. </p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» There was no correlation between pain and functional limitation with
age or skeletal maturation of the midpalatal suture.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» Female patients experienced higher pain perception and functional
limitations during RME.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other" id="fn1">
                <label>»</label>
                <p> Patients displayed in this article previously approved the use of their facial
and intraoral photographs.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haas</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Long-term posttreatment evaluation of rapid palatal
expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>1980</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <lpage>217</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6996533</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McNamara</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Maxillary transverse deficiency</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>567</fpage>
                  <lpage>570</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10799117</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garib</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriques</surname>
                      <given-names>JFC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coelho</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rapid maxillary expansion-tooth tissue-borne versus tooth-borne
expanders a computed tomography evaluation of dentoskeletal
effects</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>548</fpage>
                  <lpage>557</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16097223</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dindaroglu</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dogan</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Root resorption in Orthodontics</article-title>
                  <source>Turkish J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <lpage>108</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garib</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriques</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                      <given-names>AY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Periodontal effects of rapid maxillary expansion with
tooth-tissue-borne and tooth-borne expanders a computed tomography
evaluation</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>129</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>749</fpage>
                  <lpage>758</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16769493</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilmes</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nienkemper</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Drescher</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Application and effectiveness of a miniimplant-and tooth-borne
rapid palatal expansion device the hybrid Hyrax</article-title>
                  <source>World J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <lpage>330</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21490997</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gunyuz</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Germec-Cakan</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tozlu</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Periodontal, dentoalveolar, and skeletal effects of tooth-borne
and tooth-bone-borne expansion appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>148</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <lpage>109</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26124033</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kayalar</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schauseil</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuvat</surname>
                      <given-names>SV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Emekli</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Firatli</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of tooth-borne and hybrid devices in surgically
assisted rapid maxillary expansion a randomized clinical cone-beam computed
tomography study</article-title>
                  <source>J Craniomaxillofac Surg</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <lpage>293</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26782847</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pasqua</surname>
                      <given-names>BPM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>André</surname>
                      <given-names>CB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paiva</surname>
                      <given-names>JB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tarraf</surname>
                      <given-names>NE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilmes</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rino-Neto</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dentoskeletal changes due to rapid maxillary expansion in growing
patients with tooth-borne and tooth-bone-borne expanders A randomized
clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Orthod Craniofac Res</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>476</fpage>
                  <lpage>484</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951124</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kayalar</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Firalti</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Darendeliler</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dalci</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dalci</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Skeletal, dentoalveolar, and buccal bone changes using hybrid and
tooth-borne expanders for RME and SARME in different growth
stages</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Orthod J</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <lpage>367</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheung</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dalci</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mustac</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Papageorgiou</surname>
                      <given-names>SN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hammond</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Darendeliler</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The upper airway volume effects produced by Hyrax, Hybrid-Hyrax,
and Keles keyless expanders a single-centre randomized controlled
trial</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <lpage>264</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32377675</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Needleman</surname>
                      <given-names>HL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoang</surname>
                      <given-names>CD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allred</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hertzberg</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Berde C Reports of pain by children undergoing rapid palatal
expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Pediatr Dent</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <lpage>226</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10846733</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Halicioglu</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kiki</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yavuz</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Subjective symptoms of RME patients treated with three different
screw activation protocols a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Orthod J</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <lpage>231</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23304972</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gecgelen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kirdemir</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doguc</surname>
                      <given-names>DK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cesur</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koskan</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of stress and pain during rapid maxillary expansion
treatments</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>767</fpage>
                  <lpage>775</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22783926</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feldmann</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bazargani</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain and discomfort during the first week of rapid maxillary
expansion (RME) using two different RME appliances A randomized controlled
trial</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>87</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
                  <lpage>396</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28029266</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williamson</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoggart</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain a review of three commonly used pain rating
scales</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Nurs</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>798</fpage>
                  <lpage>804</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000093</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nadanovsky</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Brazilian version of the Oral
Health Impact Profile-short form</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <lpage>314</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16008638</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campos</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carrascosa</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maroco</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validity and reliability of the Portuguese version of Mandibular
Function Impairment Questionnaire</article-title>
                  <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>377</fpage>
                  <lpage>383</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22251134</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stegenga</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Bont</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Leeuw</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boering</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of mandibular function impairment associated with
temporomandibular joint osteoarthrosis and internal
derangement</article-title>
                  <source>J Orofac Pain</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <lpage>195</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8358365</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kang</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahn</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heo</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>TW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bone thickness of the palate for orthodontic mini-implant
anchorage in adults</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>131</volume>
                  <issue>4 Suppl</issue>
                  <fpage>S74</fpage>
                  <lpage>S81</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448390</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Becker</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Unland</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilmes</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tarraf</surname>
                      <given-names>NE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Drescher</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is there an ideal insertion angle and position for orthodontic
mini-implants in the anterior palate A CBCT study in humans</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>156</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
                  <lpage>354</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31474264</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kirkwood</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sterne</surname>
                      <given-names>JAC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Essential medical statistics</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Blackwell Science</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Massachusetts, USA</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Angelieri</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cevidanes</surname>
                      <given-names>LH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franchi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gonçalves</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benavides</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McNamara</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Midpalatal suture maturation classification method for individual
assessment before rapid maxillary expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>144</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>759</fpage>
                  <lpage>769</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24182592</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ngan</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kess</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Perception of discomfort by patients undergoing orthodontic
treatment Am J Orthod Dentofac</article-title>
                  <source>Orthop</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hjermstad</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fayers</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haugen</surname>
                      <given-names>DF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caraceni</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hanks</surname>
                      <given-names>GW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loge</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Studies comparing Numerical Rating Scales, Verbal Rating Scales,
and Visual Analogue Scales for assessment of pain intensity in adults a
systematic literature review</article-title>
                  <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1073</fpage>
                  <lpage>1093</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21621130</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scheurer</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Firestone</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burgin</surname>
                      <given-names>WB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Perception of pain as a result of orthodontic treatment with
fixed appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <lpage>357</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8921656</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luz</surname>
                      <given-names>CN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pasqua</surname>
                      <given-names>BDPM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paiva</surname>
                      <given-names>JB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rino-Neto</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cervical vertebrae maturation assessment as a predictive method
for midpalatal suture maturation stages in 11-to 14-year-olds retrospective
study</article-title>
                  <source>Clinical and Investigative Orthodontics</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <lpage>49</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Felippe</surname>
                      <given-names>NL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Da Silveira</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viana</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of palatal expanders on oral comfort, speech, and
mastication</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>137</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20122430</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
