<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:37:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10098465" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10098465</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-04-14</datestamp>
        <setSpec>eej</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Endod J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Endod J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">European Endodontic Journal</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>European Endodontic Journal</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2548-0839</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Kare Publishing</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Turkey</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10098465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10098465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10098465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36748451</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36748451</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">EEJ-8-047</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14744/eej.2022.42104</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Incidence of Postoperative Pain after Single Visit Root Canal Treatment using XP-endo Shaper, 2Shape and ProTaper Gold Rotary Systems: A Prospective Randomized Clinical Trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kapoor</surname>
                    <given-names>Kriti</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3407-991X" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3407-991X</ext-link>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Grewal</surname>
                    <given-names>Mandeep S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6952-0299" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6952-0299</ext-link>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Arya</surname>
                    <given-names>Ashtha</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4598-6910" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4598-6910</ext-link>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Grewal</surname>
                    <given-names>Stutee</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7762-8507" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7762-8507</ext-link>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Prasad Shetty</surname>
                    <given-names>Krishna</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5344-1454" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5344-1454</ext-link>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Conservative Dentistry and Endodontics, Faculty of Dental Sciences, Shree Guru Gobind Singh Tricentenary University, Haryana, India</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics, Santosh Dental College, Santosh University, Delhi, India</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Clinical Science, Centre of Medical and Bio Allied Health Science Research, College of Dentistry, Ajman University, Al-Jurf, UAE</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Mandeep S Grewal, Department of Conservative Dentistry and Endodontics, Faculty of Dental Sciences, Shree Guru Gobind Singh Tricentenary University, Haryana, India E-mail: <email>drmandeepsgrewal@yahoo.co.in</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>8</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>47</fpage>
              <lpage>54</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Copyright 2023 by European Endodontic Journal</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC 4.0)</ext-link></license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="st1">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>To evaluate the incidence of postoperative pain, treatment time and analgesic intake after single visit endodontic treatment of mandibular molars using XP-endo Shaper, 2Shape and ProTaper Gold rotary systems.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st2">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>150 patients with irreversible pulpitis were scheduled for single visit root canal treatment. Teeth were randomly assigned to one of the three groups: ProTaper Gold (PTG; Dentsply Tulsa Dental Specialties, Johnson City, TN), 2Shape (2S; Micro-Mega, Besancon, Cedex, France) and XP-endo Shaper (XPES; FKG Dentaire, La Chaux-de-Fonds, Switzerland). Preoperative and postoperative pain was rated by the patients at the beginning of treatment and after 24, 48, 72 hours and 7 days on Heft Parker’s visual analog scale (HP-VAS).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st3">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Highest mean postoperative pain score was recorded in PTG (P&lt;0.05), followed by 2S and XPES respectively at all time intervals. XPES exhibited maximum reduction from preoperative pain at 24 (48.67%) and 48 hours (96.90 %) with no pain at 72 hours. Treatment time was significantly least in XPES (P&lt;0.05) followed by 2S and PTG; but no significant difference in analgesic intake was noted.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="st4">
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>XPES exhibited least postoperative pain at all time intervals and treatment time, followed by 2S and PTG rotary systems respectively.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>2Shape</kwd>
                <kwd>debris</kwd>
                <kwd>postoperative pain</kwd>
                <kwd>ProTaper Gold</kwd>
                <kwd>XP-endo Shaper</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="S1">
              <title>HIGHLIGHTS</title>
              <p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Debris extrusion during chemo mechanical preparation is allegedly one of the principal causes of postoperative pain.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Maximum mean pain in all groups occurred in first 24 hours showing a gradual reduction. After 7 days, no pain was noted in any of the groups.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>The instrument design and multiple files may have resulted in higher debris production and extrusion resulting in more postoperative pain of PTG group.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>There is a direct correlation between incidence of postoperative pain, instrument design and number of instruments used for preparation of the pulp space.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="S2">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Endodontic intervention can result in postoperative pain varying from mild to severe. According to a review by Pak and White (2011), prevalence of postendodontic pain is 40% after 24 hours which falls to 11% after 7 days (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Postendodontic pain results from mechanical, chemical or microbial injury in the pulpal or periarticular tissues (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Following endodontic treatment an antigen antibody complex forms when antigens originating from pulp space are pushed beyond apical foramen leading to severe inflammatory reaction and pain (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). All instruments and instrumentation techniques result in debris extrusion (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, extent of extrusion may vary according to the preparation technique, irrigation, recapitulation, instrument design, and the number of instruments used (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p>
              <p>Over the years a number of rotary instruments have been introduced into the market. Most of these file systems use multiple files for shaping of the pulp space. The current trend is to reduce the number of files for shaping procedures so as to reduce the shaping time and improve patient comfort. This has been made possible by the introduction of improved NiTi metallurgy and innovative instrument design, thereby simplifying the shaping procedures and consequently resulting in reduction of number of instruments and instrumentation time. Literature has reported numerous studies comparing single and multiple files, rotary and reciprocating systems (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p>
              <p>The purpose of this prospective randomized clinical trial was to compare the incidence of postoperative pain and analgesic intake after root canal preparation of posterior teeth using ProTaper Gold (PTG), 2Shape (2S) and XP endo Shaper (XPES) rotary systems. The null hypothesis tested was that there is no difference in the incidence of postoperative pain after using any of the three instrumentation systems.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S3">
              <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
              <p>The protocol of this randomized clinical trial was approved by institutional review board and ethical committee of the Faculty of Dental Sciences. The clinical trial was registered in clinical trial registry (CTRI/2018/02/011652) and reported according to the consolidated standards of reporting trials CONSORT guidelines (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) and the study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. One hundred and fifty patients were recruited from Faculty of Dental sciences. To ensure standardization, all patients were treated by single operator familiar with instrumentation systems, over a period of 8 months from February to September 2018. Age, sex, tooth type of all patients included in this study were not significantly different between groups; hence, effect of these variables on results was expected to be minimal. Inclusion criteria were restorable mandibular molars of both male and female patients in good health aged between 20 to 45 years, having diagnosis of irreversible pulpitis. Exclusion criteria included presence of root curvatures, periapical radiolucency, sinus tracts, internal or external resorption, tenderness on percussion, traumatic bite, intolerance to NSAID’s, grade 2 or 3 mobility, open apex, nonvital teeth, history of medication prior to treatment, retreatments, pregnant patients, and anatomic variations All teeth selected for the study had #10 or #15 file snugly fitting at apex of root canals; to avoid variations in debris extrusion canals with apical diameter larger than 20 and smaller than 10 were excluded in the study.</p>
              <p>For sample size estimation, a power analysis was established by G*power, version 3.0.1 (Franz Faul universitat, Kiel, Germany). A sample size of 46 per group would yield 80% power to detect significant differences, with effect size of 0.27 and significance level at 0.05. To compensate for the losses in follow up this number was increased to 50 per group.</p>
              <p>The total number of patients assigned to three groups were 150 out of which, 6 patients did not report for follow up; therefore, total number of 144 patients were assessed (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Patients were asked to rate their preoperative pain on a HP VAS scale. An explanation of procedure and possible risks were explained after which informed consent was taken.</p>
              <fig position="float" id="F1">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) flow diagram showing the progress of subjects at each stage of the clinical trial</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="EEJ-8-047-g001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Diagnosis of symptomatic irreversible pulpitis was made by chief complaint of spontaneous pain, clinical examination and radiographic evaluation. A cold test (Endo frost – Roecko Langenau, Germany) was performed to confirm diagnosis of irreversible pulpitis. After rubber dam isolation, a cotton pellet saturated with Endo frost was applied for 5 seconds to the mid-third of the buccal surface of tooth’s crown. Sensibility of contralateral/ adjacent tooth with vital pulp was also examined. If the response to the cold test of the affected tooth was severe and pain persisted after removal of the cold cotton pellet, then the diagnosis was confirmed as symptomatic irreversible pulpitis.</p>
              <p>Randomization was done by SNOSE (sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes) method for allocation concealment which conceals the sequence until interventions were assigned. A piece of paper containing randomized group number was sealed in dark colored envelope with respective serial number by a clinical assistant. Patients were assigned numbers as they sequentially entered the study. The envelope was opened once the intervention was assigned. Based on group assigned, treatment was carried out by a single operating dentist for all the three groups. Patients were not aware of the file systems used. After the data was collected a second investigator who was blinded to the groups performed statistical analysis along with statistician.</p>
              <sec id="S3_1">
                <title>Treatment Protocol</title>
                <p>Administration of Inferior Alveolar Nerve Block, buccal infiltration was done using 1.8 mL 2% lidocaine with 1:80,000 epinephrine (Septodont, Saint-Maur-des- Fosses Cedex, France) at the rate of 1 ml/min. Patients were assessed for lip numbness every 5 min for 15 mins. Five minutes after full lip numbness was recorded buccal infiltration was administered. After confirmation of adequate anesthesia, under rubber dam isolation access cavity preparation was done. After confirming adequate anesthesia, under rubber dam isolation access cavity preparation was done and canals were explored in watch winding motion with a #10, #15 K type hand files (Dentsply Maillefer, Ballaigues, Switzerland) 0.5 mm beyond the apex to confirm apical patency, initial diameter of foramen and canal curvature. Working length was established using Root ZX apex locator (J Morita Corp, Kyoto, Japan). The file was withdrawn and 0.5 mm subtracted to establish final working length which was confirmed radiographically. Glide path was prepared till working length using #15 K- file in watch winding motion.</p>
                <p>The sequence of instrumentation used for treatment in each group was according to the manufacture’s recommendations:</p>
                <p><bold>Group 1: Protaper Gold (Ptg)</bold> (Dentsply Maillefer, Ballaigus, Switzerland) (n=48).</p>
                <p>For PTG group, shaping files (S1, S2) were used with a brushing action on the withdrawal stroke in order to create a straight-line radicular access. Finishing files (F1, F2) were used passively till working length. For file size S1 speed was 300 rpm and torque used was 5.1 N-cm. For PTG file S2 and F1, speed was 300 rpm and torque used was 1.50 N- cm. For files F2 speed was 300 rpm and torque were 3.10 N-cm.</p>
                <p><bold>Group 2: 2Shape (2S)</bold> (Micro-Mega, Besancon, Cedex, France) (n=47).</p>
                <p>It has two shaping instruments TS1(#25 .04) and TS2 (#25 .06) which were used at speed of 300 rpm and torque 1.2 Ncm with progressive upward circumferential filing movement. TS1 was inserted into the root canal until a resistance was felt, then two to three circumferential brushing strokes were performed to eliminate primary constraints. This was then followed by TS2 used with brushing motion till the working length.</p>
                <p><bold>Group 3: Xp- Endoshaper (XPES)</bold> (FKG Dentaire, La Chaux-de-Fonds, Switzerland) (n=49).</p>
                <p>XPES is a one file shaper with initial taper of 1%. used at speed of 800 rpm and torque was 1 N-cm. In phase one, working length was achieved with a #15 K file. This was followed by irrigation and recapitulation after every three strokes and especially after reaching working length. In phase two use 5-10 long strokes were used to create taper of 4%.</p>
                <p>During instrumentation, irrigation was done thoroughly and recapitulation done with #10 K file in all groups. A total of 2 ml 4% NaOCl was used for irrigation between each instrument change. Irrigation was performed with #30-gauge side venting needle (Maxi-i-probe, Dentsply, Rinn, Elgin, IL). After concluding instrumentation, canals were flushed with 2 ml 4% NaOCl, solution and agitated with sonic activation using Endoactivator (Dentsply Tulsa Dental Specialties, Tulsa, OK, USA) placed in canal 2 mm short of WL for 1 minute per canal followed by irrigation with 5 ml 17% EDTA solution and sonic agitation with Endoactivator for 1 minute to remove the smear layer. Final flush of the canals was done with 2 ml of 4% NaOCl.</p>
                <p>Obturation was done with continuous wave of compaction technique using AH-plus sealer (Dentsply Maillefer, Ballaigus, Switzerland) followed by composite resin restoration (Coltene/Whaledent). Time taken to complete the treatment of every patient was recorded. In the event of moderate or severe pain, patients were advised to take analgesics (400 mg Ibuprofen) as a rescue medication at a dosage of 1 tablet SOS and repeated every 6 hours if required. They were also asked to record the number of tablets taken and mark the level of pain on the HP- VAS scale chart given. They were recalled after 7 days for follow up.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S3_2">
                <title>Assessment of Pain</title>
                <p>Patients were asked to rate their pre- and postoperative pain on Heft parker visual analog scale (HP VAS). HP VAS is a 170-mm line marked with various terms describing levels of pain. The millimeter marks were removed from scale. Scale was divided into 4 categories: ‘‘no pain’’ corresponded to 0 mm; ‘‘faint, weak or mild’’ pain corresponded to 0–54 mm; ‘‘moderate’’ pain corresponded to 55–114 mm; and ‘‘strong, intense, and maximum possible’’ pain corresponded to greater than 114 mm. Patients received a questionnaire (pain assessment HP VAS chart and medication record chart) for postoperative pain.</p>
                <p>Patients were asked to mark severity of their postoperative pain on HP VAS after 24, 48, 72 hours and 7 days; and record the number of analgesic tablets taken, if any on the provided chart. They were telephonically contacted after 24, 48, 72 hours and 7 days and reminded for the same. After 7 days charts were collected from the patients for analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S3_3">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>SPSS (Statistical Package for Social Sciences) version 20. [IBM SPASS statistics (IBM corp. Armonk, NY, USA released 2011)] was used for statistical analysis. Data was checked for normalcy by Shapiro Wilk test. Data showed non–normal distribution hence, Kruskal-Wallis, non-parametric test was applied to check statistical difference of pain scores, number of analgesics taken, time taken among the groups and Post-hoc Mann-Whitney test was used for pair-wise comparison. The difference was considered statistically significant at 0.05 (P&lt;0.05). A confidence interval of 95% was obtained.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="S4">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>The baseline demographic data used in study groups is shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The mean age of 144 patients assessed in this study was 32 years. 144 patients responded to the questionnaire on postoperative pain score and analgesic intake at different time intervals (24, 48, 72 hours and 7 days). Maximum mean postoperative pain recorded was in PTG group followed by 2S and XPES groups respectively at all time intervals. The mean pain scores were found to be lower at all time intervals for all instrument systems used with statistically significant difference at 24, 48 and 72 hours (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Intergroup comparison of pain scores reveals statistically significant difference between XPES and PTG at 24, 48 and 72 hours (P&lt;0.001) and between 2S and XPES at 48 hours (P&lt;0.001) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). When comparing percentage change in preoperative and postoperative pain scores there was a significant (P&lt;0.05) reduction in pain at 24, 48 and 72 hours (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). There was a significant difference (P&lt;0.05) among the groups with respect to time taken (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). PTG group recorded highest mean time followed by 2S group and the lowest mean time was recorded in XPES group. There was no statistically significant difference in the analgesic intake between groups although XPES group consumed the least analgesic intake.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                <label>TABLE 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Baseline demographic and clinical features of patients in the study groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="border" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline demographic and clinical feature</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PTG (n=48)</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">2S (n=47)</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">XPES (n=49)</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n=144)</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.87</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.87</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.80</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.39</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.80</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular first molar</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.78</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.43</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.78</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular second molar</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.85</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.85</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.28</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TF1-1">
                    <p>PTG: Protaper Gold, 2S: 2Shape, XPES: XP-endo Shaper, n: Number of patients in a group</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                <label>TABLE 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Comparison of the Pre- and Post- operative pain scores among the three groups assessed using Kruskal-Wallis Test</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="border" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time interval</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumentation system</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kruskal- wallis</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative pain</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.19</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.63</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.04</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.87</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.45</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.41</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain after 24 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.69</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.96</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.93</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.59</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.14</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.72</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain after 48 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.77</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.38</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.02</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.70</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.369</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain after 72 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.94</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.579</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.25</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain after 7 days</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TF2-1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>: P value significant at 0.05, indicates significant difference. n: Number of patients in a group, Min: Minimum, Max: Maximum, PTG: Protaper Gold, 2S: 2Shape, XPES: XP-endo Shaper</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                <label>TABLE 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Non parametric Post Hoc Mann Whitney test to compare the pain score at all time intervals</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="border" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time interval</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PTG v/s 2S difference</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PTG v/s XPES difference</th>
                      <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">2S v/s XPES difference</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.85</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.50</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 24 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.73</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.54</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00*</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.81</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 48 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.75</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.32</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00*</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.57</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 72 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003*</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 7 days</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TF3-1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>: P value significant at 0.05/3=0.016, indicates significant difference, PTG: Protaper Gold, 2S: 2Shape, XPES: XP-endo Shaper</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                <label>TABLE 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Comparison of percentage change in pain scores using Kruskal-Wallis test</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="border" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time Interval</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumentation system</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kruskal- wallis</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change from</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-21</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.967</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">preoperative</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain to 24 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-30.85</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.73</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.96</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.13</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-48.67</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.19</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-30.16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change from</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-33.26</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.57</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-13.33</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">preoperative</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain to 48 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.96</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-56.15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-59.84</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.77</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-71.66</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-96.90</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change from</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-44.3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-93.15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.07</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">preoperative</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain to 72 hours</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-41.8</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-95.38</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.97</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change from</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">preoperative</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain to 7 days</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-100.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TF4-1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>: P value significant at 0.05, indicates significant difference. n: Number of patients in a group, Min: Minimum, Max: Maximum, PTG: Protaper Gold, 2S: 2Shape, XPES: XP-endo Shaper</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T5">
                <label>TABLE 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Kruskal Wallis Test to compare the time taken for treatment among the three groups</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="border" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumentation system</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kruskal- Wallis</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.02</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.219</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2S</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.02</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.480</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.58</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XPES</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.55</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.525</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TF5-1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>: P value significant at 0.05, indicates significant difference. n: Number of patients in a group, Min: Minimum, Max: Maximum, PTG: Protaper Gold, 2S: 2Shape, XPES: XP-endo Shaper</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S5">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Postoperative discomfort after endodontic intervention is an undesirable effect. There is a wide range in incidence of postoperative pain and flareup reported in literature ranging from 3-58% (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Postoperative inflammation following endodontic intervention may be due to mechanical, chemical or microbial injuries of periapical tissues (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Debris extrusion during chemo mechanical preparation is allegedly one of the principal cause of postoperative pain (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p>
              <p>Maximum mean postoperative pain recorded was in PTG group followed by 2S and XPES groups respectively at all time intervals. Maximum mean pain in all groups occurred in first 24 hours. This is in accordance to the previous studies, all of which have reported maximum postoperative pain at the end of 24 hours (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The results demonstrated gradual reduction of postoperative pain at all time intervals in all groups. The mean pain score was found to be lower at all time intervals with statistically significant difference at 24, 48 and 72 hours (P&lt;0.001) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). At 24-hour time interval XPES exhibited least pain as compared to other groups with statistically significant difference (P&lt;0.016) between XPES and PTG (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). After 48 hours XPES resulted in significantly (P&lt;0.016) less pain as compared to PTG and 2S (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). At 72 hours, there was further reduction in postoperative pain scores, with statistically significant difference (P&lt;0.016) between XPES and PTG (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). After 7 days, there was no pain in any of the three groups.</p>
              <p>All instrumentation techniques result in debris extrusion (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Extrusion of contaminated/noncontaminated debris into the periapical area during instrumentation can result in an inflammatory and/or immunological reaction leading to postoperative pain (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p>
              <p>There is also a significant correlation between preoperative and postoperative pain. Severe preoperative pain increases the possibility of more severe postoperative pain (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>-<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In 1986, Genet et al. (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) reported that in cases without preoperative pain, only 23% experienced postoperative pain, whereas if there had been preoperative pain on the day of treatment 65% had postoperative pain. Torabinejad et al. (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) demonstrated that patients with pain or swelling before treatment were highly susceptible to flareups whereas patients without preoperative complaints were the least susceptible group. It has also been demonstrated that mandibular molars have significantly more postoperative pain than other teeth (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). For these reasons, patient’s preoperative pain was recorded prior to treatment and mandibular molars were selected for the present study. Furthermore, as single visit root canal results in lower post treatment pain as compared to multiple visit treatment, and to avoid the possible confounding effect of intracanal medicament on postoperative pain the root canals in this study were completed in one sitting (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p>
              <p>Pain is modulated by a multitude of physical and psychological factors, thus making assessment difficult. Assessment of pain poses a significant challenge to researchers because of its highly subjective and variable nature. We have selected HP VAS as it is considered valid and reliable measurement scale for pain (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>-<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In the present study preoperative and postoperative HP VAS pain scales were recorded to eliminate potential bias in subjective nature of pain assessment.</p>
              <p>The different rotary instrumentation systems used in this study were in close match to each other in terms of tip size and taper for standardization of final preparation of root canals (PTG 0.25/.08v, 2S 0.25/.06, XPES 0.30/.04). The larger tip size of XPES was compensated by lesser taper. During instrumentation, irrigation protocol was similar for all three groups. Irrigation was done using sodium hypochlorite and apical patency was maintained using #10 K file for elimination. Moreover, occlusal reduction has been suggested as a means of managing endodontic pain but in the present study this was not done as it would have affected the postoperative pain perception (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p>
              <p>PTG exhibited more pain as compared to other groups. ProTaper instruments have sharp cutting edges, progressively increasing taper along the shaft of instrument and stiffer tip for ProTaper finishing files. This results in significantly higher amounts of debris production and debris extrusion compared to other files (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). ProTaper have a series of six instruments all of which are used for preparation of canals. In the present study PTG was used because it resulted in less debris production than PTU (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The instrument design and multiple files may have resulted in higher debris production and extrusion resulting in more postoperative pain of PTG (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p>
              <p>Two file system (2S) utilizes two files to complete cleaning and shaping procedure. They have an asymmetrical cross section design which results in non uniform, reduced contact between the canal wall and instrument. Smaller tip size of 2S along with asymmetrical design creates better space for coronal displacement of debris. 2S resulted in less postoperative pain as compared to PTG which can be attributed to reduced extrusion of debris apically (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p>
              <p>XPES produced least postoperative pain amongst all three groups. XPES is single file system, extremely flexible, having slender design with narrow taper and booster tip. The debris produced is reportedly removed more efficiently than other large core diameter instruments due to extra space available. XPES utilizes crown down technique for preparation in which early flaring of coronal root results in reduced microorganism load and apical debris extrusion (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), as greatest number of microorganisms are present in coronal third of the canal. It has also been speculated fewer instruments may contribute to lesser extrusion of bacteria/debris apically (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p>
              <p>Instrumentation with multiple file systems require a number of passes by each instrument to reach the apex and to prepare the apex to the desired size, which causes greater debris extrusion (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>-<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In single/two file systems the same work is done by one or two files with constant irrigation and recapitulation in true crown down fashion resulting in early elimination of debris. The file tip and taper in study match closely. It is well documented that there is no difference in the debris extrusion between different taper preparations therefore the effect of the slight mismatch in tip and taper should not have an effect on results of study (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>-<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Caviedes-Bucheli (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) attributed a greater expression of neuropeptides (substance P and CGRP) to increase instrumentation time generating increased mechanical stresses and debris extrusion into the periapical area.</p>
              <p>Percentage change in pain was maximum for XPES followed by 2S and PTG. On comparing preoperative pain scores to the postoperative pain there was significant reduction in pain at 24 and 48 hours. XPES exhibited maximum reduction from preoperative pain at 24 (48.67%) and 48 hours (96.90 %) with no pain at 72 hours. Reduction in pain was also observed with 2S at 24 (30.85%) and at 48 (56.15%) hours when compared to preoperative pain. PTG exhibited reduction in pain at 24 (5.13 %) and 48 hours (33.26%) although the results were not as dramatic as the other two groups (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
              <p>The results obtained from the current study may be explained by differences in the instrument design and kinematics. Based on these observations it could be inferred that there is a direct correlation between incidence of postoperative pain, instrument design and number of instruments used for preparation of the pulp space.</p>
              <p>The other criteria compared were the time taken and analgesic intake. It has been reported that longer instrumentation time may contribute to a higher degree of postoperative pain (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In the present study PTG instruments took significantly more time for preparation followed by 2S and XPES respectively (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). There was no significant difference among the groups in analgesic intake but the mean analgesic intake was lower in XPES at all time intervals.</p>
              <p>There was statistically significant difference in incidence of postoperative pain amongst the instrumentation systems assessed, therefore the null hypothesis was rejected.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="S6">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>In the present study, XPES exhibited the least amount of postoperative pain, time taken and the maximum decrease in pre and postoperative pain percentage. 2S performed better than PTG in postoperative pain, time taken and decrease in pre and postoperative pain percentage. PTG exhibited maximum pain and treatment time among the three groups.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn1">
                <p><bold>Please cite this article as:</bold> Kapoor K, Grewal MS, Arya A, Grewal S, Prasad Shetty K. Incidence of Postoperative Pain after Single visit Root Canal Treatment using XP-endo Shaper, 2Shape and ProTaper Gold Rotary Systems: A Prospective Randomized Clinical Trial. Eur Endod J 2023; 8: 47-54</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec id="S7">
              <title>Disclosures</title>
              <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="S8">
                <title>Conflict of interest:</title>
                <p>The authors deny any conflict of interest.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="S9">
              <title>Ethics Committee Approval:</title>
              <p>This study was approved by The Institutional Review Board and Ethical Committee of the Faculty of Dental Sciences. Shree Guru Gobind Singh Tricentenary University, Gurugram, Haryana, India (Date: 21/12/2017, Number: SGTU/FDS/MDS/24/1/672).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="S10">
              <title>Peer-review:</title>
              <p>Externally peer-reviewed.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="financial-disclosure" id="S11">
              <title>Financial Disclosure</title>
              <p>This study did not receive any financial support.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="S12">
              <title>Authorship contributions</title>
              <p>Concept – M.S.G.; Design – M.S.G.; Supervision – M.S.G.; Funding - K.K.; Materials - K.K.; Data collection and/or processing – K.K., A.A.; Analysis and/or interpretation – M.S.G., A.A., K.K.; Literature search – K.K., M.S.G.; Writing – K.K., M.S.G., A.A., K.P.S., S.G.; Critical Review – K.P.S., S.G.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <ref id="ref1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pak</surname>
                      <given-names>JG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>White</surname>
                      <given-names>SN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain prevalence and severity before, during, and after root canal treatment: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
                  <lpage>38</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21419285</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microbial causes of endodontic flare-ups</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>453</fpage>
                  <lpage>63</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12823700</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seltzer</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain in endodontics 1986</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15220646</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torabinejad</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eby</surname>
                      <given-names>WC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naidorf</surname>
                      <given-names>IJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inflammatory and immunological aspects of the pathogenesis of human periapical lesions</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>1985</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <lpage>88</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3913729</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koçak</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koçak</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sağlam</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Türker</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sağsen</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Er</surname>
                      <given-names>Ö</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical extrusion of debris using self-adjusting file, reciprocating single-file, and 2 rotary instrumentation systems</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1278</fpage>
                  <lpage>80</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24041391</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kirchhoff</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fariniuk</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mello</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical extrusion of debris in flat-oval root canals after using different instrumentation systems</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25447504</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vande Visse</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brilliant</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of irrigation on the production of extruded material at the root apex during instrumentation</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>1975</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1061800</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reddy</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hicks</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical extrusion of debris using two hand and two rotary instrumentation techniques</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9558583</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferraz</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gomes</surname>
                      <given-names>NV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gomes</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaia</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teixeira</surname>
                      <given-names>FB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza-Filho</surname>
                      <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical extrusion of debris and irrigants using two hand and three engine-driven instrumentation techniques</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11482718</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Türker</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uzunoğlu</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aslan</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of apically extruded bacteria associated with different nickel-titanium systems</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>953</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25799537</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rahbani Nobar</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dianat</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rahbani Nobar</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shirvani</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zargar</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kazem</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of rotary and reciprocating instrumentation motions on postoperative pain incidence in non-surgical endodontic treatments: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Eur Endod J</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>14</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33609019</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kherlakian</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cunha</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ehrhardt</surname>
                      <given-names>IC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zuolo</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kishen</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>da Silveira Bueno</surname>
                      <given-names>CE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of the incidence of postoperative pain after using 2 reciprocating systems and a continuous rotary system: a prospective randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26614017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Juszczak</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Altman</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hopewell</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schulz</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reporting of multi-arm parallel-group randomized trials: extension of the CONSORT 2010 statement</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>321</volume>
                  <issue>16</issue>
                  <fpage>1610</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31012939</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sathorn</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parashos</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Messer</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The prevalence of postoperative pain and flare-up in single-and multiple-visit endodontic treatment: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17956561</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>O'Keefe</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain in endodontic therapy: preliminary study</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>1976</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1068208</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Genet</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wesselink</surname>
                      <given-names>PR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thoden van Velzen</surname>
                      <given-names>SK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The incidence of preoperative and postoperative pain in endodontic therapy</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>1986</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3473042</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torabinejad</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cymerman</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frankson</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lemon</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maggio</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schilder</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of various medications on postoperative pain following complete instrumentation</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
                  <lpage>54</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7996097</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torabinejad</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kettering</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McGraw</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cummings</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dwyer</surname>
                      <given-names>TG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tobias</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Factors associated with endodontic interappointment emergencies of teeth with necrotic pulps</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3251982</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clem</surname>
                      <given-names>WH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Posttreatment endodontic pain</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>
                  <year>1970</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>1166</fpage>
                  <lpage>70</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5272982</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ng</surname>
                      <given-names>YL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Glennon</surname>
                      <given-names>JP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Setchell</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gulabivala</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence of and factors affecting post-obturation pain in patients undergoing root canal treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
                  <lpage>91</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15186245</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Su</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ye</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Healing rate and post-obturation pain of single-versus multiple-visit endodontic treatment for infected root canals: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21238790</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heft</surname>
                      <given-names>MW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parker</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An experimental basis for revising the graphic rating scale for pain</article-title>
                  <source>Pain</source>
                  <year>1984</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>61</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6462727</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>DiRenzo</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gresla</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnson</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rogers</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tucker</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>BeGole</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postoperative pain after 1-and 2-visit root canal therapy</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>93</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>605</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12075212</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Webster</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Drum</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reader</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fowler</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nusstein</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beck</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>How effective is supplemental intraseptal anesthesia in patients with symptomatic irreversible pulpitis?</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1453</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27663614</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parirokh</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rekabi</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ashouri</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nakhaee</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abbott</surname>
                      <given-names>PV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gorjestani</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of occlusal reduction on postoperative pain in teeth with irreversible pulpitis and mild tenderness to percussion</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23228248</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Çakici</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Çakici</surname>
                      <given-names>EB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Küçükekenci</surname>
                      <given-names>FF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uygun</surname>
                      <given-names>AD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arslan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apically extruded debris during root canal preparation using ProTaper Gold, ProTaper Universal, ProTaper Next, and RECIPROC instruments</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Artif Organs</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <lpage>31</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27034317</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chaudhury</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ananthakrishna</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumari</surname>
                      <given-names>RV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pradeep</surname>
                      <given-names>PR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shankar</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sagar</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative evaluation of apically extruded debris with Protaper Universal, Protaper Gold and Twisted File adaptive rotary instruments-an <italic>in-vitro</italic> study</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Scientific Dental Sciences</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tinoco</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De-Deus</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tinoco</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saavedra</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fidel</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sassone</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical extrusion of bacteria when using reciprocating single-file and rotary multifile instrumentation systems</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>560</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24111671</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghoneim</surname>
                      <given-names>WM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaheen</surname>
                      <given-names>NA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apically extruded debris associated with different instrumentation systems and irrigation needles</article-title>
                  <source>Tanta Dent J</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alani</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Huwaizi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of apically extruded debris and irrigants during root canal preparation using different rotary instrumentation systems: an <italic>in vitro</italic> comparative study</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Med Res Health Sci</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uslu</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Özyürek</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gündoğar</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Plotino</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apically extruded debris during root canal instrumentation with Reciproc Blue, HyFlex EDM, and XP-endo Shaper Nickel-titanium files</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>856</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29550013</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alves</surname>
                      <given-names>FRF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paiva</surname>
                      <given-names>PL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marceliano-Alves</surname>
                      <given-names>MF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cabreira</surname>
                      <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>KC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bacteria and hard tissue debris extrusion and intracanal bacterial reduction promoted by XP-endo Shaper and Reciproc instruments</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1173</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29861066</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mittal</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singla</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garg</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dhawan</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of apical bacterial extrusion in manual, ProTaper Rotary, and One Shape Rotary instrumentation techniques</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>2040</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26472680</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref34">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aprilia</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Usman</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nursasongko</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Difference in the extent of debris extrusion between instrumentation with ProTaper and ProTaper Next: an experimental laboratory study</article-title>
                  <source>J Phys: Conf Ser</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>1073</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>62007</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Çapar</surname>
                      <given-names>ID</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arslan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akçay</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ertaş</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An <italic>in vitro</italic> comparison of apically extruded debris and instrumentation times with ProTaper Universal, ProTaper Next, Twisted File Adaptive, and HyFlex instruments</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1638</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260737</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref36">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aksel</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Küçükkaya Eren</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Çakar</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Serper</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Özkuyumcu</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azim</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of instrumentation techniques and preparation taper on apical extrusion of bacteria</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1008</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28416303</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref37">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arvaniti</surname>
                      <given-names>IS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khabbaz</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of root canal taper on its cleanliness: a scanning electron microscopic study</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>871</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21787508</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref38">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azar</surname>
                      <given-names>NG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ebrahimi</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apically-extruded debris using the ProTaper system</article-title>
                  <source>Aust Endod J</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15881729</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref39">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caviedes-Bucheli</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azuero-Holguin</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gutierrez-Sanchez</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Higuerey-Bermudez</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pereira-Nava</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lombana</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of three different rotary instrumentation systems on substance P and calcitonin gene-related peptide expression in human periodontal ligament</article-title>
                  <source>J Endod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1938</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21092809</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref40">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Segura-Egea</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cisneros-Cabello</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Llamas-Carreras</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Velasco-Ortega</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pain associated with root canal treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Int Endod J</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>614</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19467050</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
