<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:48:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4692284" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4692284</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-12-31</datestamp>
        <setSpec>plosone</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4692284</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4692284</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4692284</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26694321</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26694321</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145553</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-28960</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Inequality of Experience of Dental Caries between Different Ethnic Groups of Brazilians Aged 15 to 19 Years</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Ethnic Inequality of Experience of Dental Caries in Brazil</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Drummond</surname>
                    <given-names>Andreia Maria Araújo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                    <given-names>Efigênia Ferreira</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gomes</surname>
                    <given-names>Viviane Elisangela</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Marcenes</surname>
                    <given-names>Wagner</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff001">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Institute of Dentistry, Barts and The London School of Medicine and Dentistry, Queen Mary University of London. London, United Kingdom</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <aff id="aff002">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Faculty of Dentistry, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais. Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Arakeri</surname>
                    <given-names>Gururaj</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role>Editor</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="edit1">
                <addr-line>Navoadaya Dental College and Hospital, mantralayam Road, INDIA</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001">
                  <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
                  <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AMAD EFF VEG WM. Performed the experiments: AMAD EFF VEG WM. Analyzed the data: AMAD WM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AMAD WM. Wrote the paper: AMAD EFF VEG WM.</p>
                </fn>
                <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>andreia_drummond@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>10</volume>
              <issue>12</issue>
              <elocation-id>e0145553</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>6</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2015</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2015</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2015 Drummond et al</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Drummond et al</copyright-holder>
                <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0145553.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="sec001">
                  <title>Introduction</title>
                  <p>The aim of this study was to assess inequality of experience of dental caries, based on race/ethnicity, among Brazilian adolescents aged 15 to 19 years in 2010 and test whether socioeconomic indicators fully explain ethnic differences in dental caries.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec002">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>Data from a National Oral Health Survey conducted in Brazil in 2010 was analysed. Race/ethnicity was self-assigned and modified to White, African descents, East Asian descents, Mixed Race and Indigenous descents. The prevalence of caries experience by race/ethnic group in 2010(n = 5,367) was calculated. Further analysis included conceptual hierarchical modelling and mediation analysis.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec003">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Caries experience was 76.9% in 15 to 19 year old Brazilians in 2010. While African descents were 32% more likely to have caries experience than Whites, Mixed Race were 69% more likely to have caries experience than Whites. Hierarchical conceptual modelling analysis confirmed the highly significant association between caries and race/ethnicity. Mixed Race and East Asian descents were 1.44 (95% CI 1.24–1.67) and 1.81 (95% CI 1.02–3.20) times more likely to experience caries than Whites after adjusting for age, sex, education and income. The difference in the likelihood of experiencing caries between Whites and African descents was not statistically significant after adjusting for years of education and family income. The results of mediation analysis confirmed that inequality of caries experience between Whites and Mixed Race and East Asian descents was mediated through education and income. The likelihood that Mixed Race and East Asian descents would experience caries compared to Whites was attenuated, by 14.8% and by 9.5% respectively, after adjusting for years of education and income.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec004">
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Data analysis demonstrated that Whites have benefited more from the significant reduction in dental caries experience in 15 to 19 year old Brazilians, as compared to African descents and Mixed Race. Education and income fully explained ethnic inequalities in experience of dental caries between Whites and African descents, and largely explained inequalities between Whites and Mixed Race.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <funding-statement>This research was supported by CAPES Foundation, Ministry of Education of Brazil, Brasilia — DF, 70.040-020, Brazil.</funding-statement>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="0"/>
                <table-count count="3"/>
                <page-count count="9"/>
              </counts>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta id="data-availability">
                  <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>All data are public available from the Brazilian National Oral Health Survey (SBBrasil 2010).</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
            <notes>
              <title>Data Availability</title>
              <p>All data are public available from the Brazilian National Oral Health Survey (SBBrasil 2010).</p>
            </notes>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec005">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The literature showed consistently that socially vulnerable groups had a higher prevalence of experience of dental caries [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It has been suggested in the literature that the race and ethnicity of a person may determine their oral health status [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. There is a considerable amount of literature on the utility of race and ethnicity as concepts [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. ‘Race’ and ‘ethnicity’ are terms commonly used, with similar characteristics but subtle differences. ‘Race’ typically refers to physical features, such as skin colour or hair texture, which may reflect a person’s ancestry; and examples of categories that are commonly used to describe race include White, African descents, or Asian descents. ‘Ethnicity’ is a complex term used to describe perceived social groupings based on a sense of belonging, place of origin, and other factors such as language, religion, and sometimes race [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Assessing ethnicity is difficult, and numerous proxy measures are used to capture its various components. For the purposes of this study, ‘Ethnicity’ and ‘Race’ will be viewed as synonyms. Self-reported ethnicity captures both the shared experiences/culture of an individual and their self-identity [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p>
              <p>The association between experience of dental caries and race/ethnicity is not well-defined. Worldwide, White children, adolescents, adults and the elderly were consistently found to experience lower levels of dental caries than their counterparts from other racial/ethnic groups [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, it is not clear whether these differences were due to race/ethnicity <italic>per se</italic> or due to confounding variables such as socio-economic position (“SEP”) as both are strongly related to experience of dental caries [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Data from the United States suggested that SEP may fully explain ethnic inequalities in oral health [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], while other studies have reported the persistence of these inequalities after adjustment for confounding factors [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145553.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p>
              <p>The aim of this study was to assess inequality of experience of dental caries as between different ethnic groups of Brazilian adolescents (aged 15 to 19 years) in 2010. In addition, the study sought to test whether socioeconomic indicators fully explain ethnic differences in dental caries in 2010.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec006">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>This article analyses data from a National Oral Health Survey conducted in Brazil in 2010 (SBBrasil 2010) [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The survey adopted a cross-sectional survey design and included a representative sample of young adults aged 15 to 19 years. Participants were selected using multi-stage random sampling stratified approach by the five Brazilian macro-regions. Proportional representation was adopted. Trained and calibrated dentists conducted the oral examinations using the WHO protocol [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The DMFT index was used to assess experience of dental caries. Following the clinical examination, participants answered a supervised structured questionnaire, designed especially for the research. A handheld Personal Digital Assistant (PDA model P550) was used for data collection. The questionnaire included questions on socio-demographic factors (age, sex, race/ethnicity, years of education, family income and household characteristics). Age was assessed in complete years. Race/ethnicity was self-assigned into the five Brazilian census classification [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and modified to White, African descent, East Asian descent, Mixed Race (those with mixed racial ancestry, known as “<italic>pardos</italic>”) and Indigenous descent. The participant’s ‘years of education’ were assessed in terms of the number of successfully completed school years; and ‘family income’ was reported by the head of the family, considering the total income of the household in the month prior to the interview. Detailed information on the sampling procedure can be found elsewhere [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The SBBrasil 2010 (<italic>Conselho Nacional de Etica em Pesquisa</italic>—approval ref. 15,498/2010) followed the requirements of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Brazilian Ethics Committee.</p>
              <sec id="sec007">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Data was analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics 18.0. The prevalence of experience of dental caries was calculated by reference to race/ethnic group. The SBBrasil 2010 included a sample of 5,445 participants, aged 15 to 19 years. Seventy-eight individuals (1.43%) were excluded from this data analysis due to missing information on the outcome variable (n = 5,367).</p>
                <p>Further data analysis were carried out to assess race/ethnicity inequalities of experience of dental caries. In addition, to test the estimation of precision, we also performed post hoc power analysis. The post-hoc sample calculation demonstrated that the minimum sample size needed to provide 80% statistical power to enable the identification of an odds ratio of 1.5 was estimated to be 822 [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The calculation assumed 50% of the unexposed population and 60% of the exposed population to have the outcome of interest: α equal to 0.05, and β equal to 0.20. Therefore, the sample size (n = 5,367) provides sufficient statistical power to test the hypothesis.</p>
                <p>Data manipulation was minimal. The participants’ ‘years of education’ were categorized into ‘four or less years of education’, ‘five to eight years of education’ and ‘nine or more years of education’. Family income’ was converted into U.S. dollars (US$1.00 = R$1.76 in 2010) and categorized into ‘equal to or less than US$142.00’, ‘US$143.00 to US$284.00’, ‘US$285.00 to US$852.00’, ‘US$853.00 to US$1,420.00’ and ‘US$1,421.00 or above’.</p>
                <p>Simple logistic regression analyses were carried out to assess the unadjusted association between each of the explanatory variables (race/ethnicity, sex, age, years of education and family income) and experience of dental caries. In accordance with the lax criterion [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], explanatory variables that were not statistically significantly related to the outcome at the level of 0.20 or more were excluded at this stage. Following this, conceptual hierarchical modelling [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] was carried out. The remaining variables were sequentially included as follows: (1) race/ethnicity, sex and age (2) race/ethnicity, sex, age plus years of education; (3) race/ethnicity, sex, age, years of education, plus family income. Odds Ratios (OR) were reported and the 95% confidence interval was considered. Attenuation of the OR was calculated using the formula (ORU-ORA)÷(ORU-1) [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], where ORU represents the odds ratio before including the family income and ORA reflects the odds ratio after including years of education and family income in the model. Mediation analysis included the four steps proposed by Baron and Kenny [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec008">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Frequency distribution of demographic characteristics in the SBBrasil 2010 study sample are shown in <xref rid="pone.0145553.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Experience of dental caries was 76.9% in 15 to 19 year old Brazilians in 2010. A significant difference in the distribution of experience of dental caries among race/ethnic groups was observed. African descents (77.1%), East Asian descents (83.5%), Mixed Race (81.0%) experienced significantly more dental caries than Whites (71.9%) while experience of dental caries among Indigenous descents (75.0%) was not significantly different than among Whites (<xref rid="pone.0145553.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In addition, there were statistically significant differences in the distribution of experience of dental caries by age, sex, years of education and family income. As expected, experience of dental caries increased with ageing. Participants with less than four years of education were 2.67 (95% CI 1.72–4.15) times more likely to have experience of dental caries than those with nine or more years of education. Participants with family income of US$142.00 or less were 3.52 (95% CI 2.20–5.63) times more likely to have experience of dental caries than those with a family income of US$ 1,421.00 or above (<xref rid="pone.0145553.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap id="pone.0145553.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145553.t001</object-id>
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Sample characteristics by race/ethnicity in 15 to 19 years old Brazilians in 2010.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>
                  <graphic id="pone.0145553.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0145553.t001"/>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample (n = 5367)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White (n = 2177; 40.6%)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">African descents (n = 586; 10.9%)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asian descents (n = 103; 1.9%)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed Race (n = 2453; 45.7%)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indigenous descents (n = 48; 0.9%)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1438 (26.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">552 (25.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (28.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (28.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">672 (27.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (37.5%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">973 (18.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">404 (18.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (14.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (17.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">458 (18.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (16.7%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">977 (18.2%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392 (18.0%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (17.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (24.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">451 (18.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.7%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">995 (18.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419 (19.2%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (18.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (13.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444 (18.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (16.7%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">984 (18.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410 (18.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (21.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (16.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428 (17.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (10.4%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2452 (45.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1014 (46.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (45.2%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (41.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1101 (44.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (60.4%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2915 (54.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1163 (53.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321 (54.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (58.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1352 (55.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (59.6%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 4 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (3.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (2.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (5.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (4.2%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.2%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–8 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1798 (33.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">618 (28.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236 (40.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (23.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">901 (36.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (39.6%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 9 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3357 (62.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1498 (68.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313 (53.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (72.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1445 (58.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (54.2%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Missing information</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>12</italic> (0.2%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5</italic> (0.2%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3</italic> (0.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic> (0%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4</italic> (0.2%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic> (0%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family Income</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ US$142</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (3.0%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (1.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (4.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (3.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.2%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US$143–284</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686 (12.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203 (9.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (17.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (13.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359 (14.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (12.5%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US$285–852</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2621 (48.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">943 (43.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">307 (52.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (44.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1302 (53.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (47.9%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US$853–1420</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">920 (17.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">456 (20.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (14.8%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (15.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">352 (14.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.8%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ US$1421</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">665 (12.4%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406 (18.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (6.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (8.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.2%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Missing information</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>315</italic> (5.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>133</italic> (6.10%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>25</italic> (4.3%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>13</italic> (12.6%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>139</italic> (5.7%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5</italic> (10.4%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    DMFT</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= 0 (free of caries)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1240 (23.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">611 (28.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134 (22.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (16.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">466 (19.0%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (25.0%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4127 (76.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1566 (71.9%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">452 (77.1%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (83.5%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1987 (81.0%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (75.0%)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </alternatives>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="pone.0145553.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145553.t002</object-id>
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Caries experience (DMFT&gt;0) by demographic and socioeconomic characteristics in the total sample, Brazil, 2010.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>
                  <graphic id="pone.0145553.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0145553.t002"/>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N DMFT&gt;0 (%)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref> [95%CI]</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P value</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported race/ethnicity</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1566 (71.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">African descents</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">452 (77.1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 [1.06–1.63]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>012</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asian descents</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (83.5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 [1.16–3.35]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>012</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed Race</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1987(81.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 [1.45–1.91]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indigenous descents</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (75.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 [0.60–2.26]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>640</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1854 (75.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2273 (78.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 [1.01–1.30]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>041</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1029 (71.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">735 (75.5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 [1.01–1.48]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>031</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">771 (78.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 [1.23–1.80]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">793 (79.7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 [1.29–1.89]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">799 (81.2)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 [1.41–2.09]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 4 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 (88.5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67 [1.72–4.15]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–8 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1448 (80.5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 [1.25–1.65]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 9 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2492 (74.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Missing information</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>10 (83</italic>.<italic>3)</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family Income</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ US$142</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (85.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52 [2.20–5.63]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US$143–284</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">571 (83.2)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.93 [2.27–3.79]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US$285–852</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2090 (79.7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33 [1.94–2.78]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US$853–1420</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">678 (73.7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 [1.34–2.05]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ US$1421</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418 (62.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Missing information</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>233 (74</italic>.<italic>0)</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </alternatives>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="t002fn001">
                    <p><sup>a</sup>Unadjusted logistic regression models and odds ratios (OR) reported with a 95% confidence interval</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Hierarchical conceptual modelling analysis (<xref rid="pone.0145553.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) confirmed the highly significant association between dental caries and race/ethnicity. Adjusted odds ratios confirmed that Mixed Race and East Asian descents were 1.44 (95% CI 1.24–1.67) and 1.81 (95% CI 1.02–3.20) times more likely to experience dental caries than Whites respectively. The difference in the likelihood of experiencing dental caries between Whites and African descents was not statistically significant after adjusting for years of education and family income.</p>
              <table-wrap id="pone.0145553.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145553.t003</object-id>
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Models for race/ethnic differences in caries experience (DMFT) among the total sample, Brazil, 2010.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>
                  <graphic id="pone.0145553.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0145553.t003"/>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Self-reported race/ethnic groups</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P value</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P value</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P value</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (95% CI)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (95% CI)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 [Reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 [Reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 [Reference]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">African descents</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 [1.07–1.64]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>011</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 [0.97–1.51]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>086</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 [0.83–1.30]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>762</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asian descents</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 [1.18–3.41]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>010</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04 [1.20–3.46]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>009</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 [1.02–3.20]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0</italic>.<italic>042</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed Race</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 [1.47–1.94]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 [1.40–1.86]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 [1.24–1.67]</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&lt;0</italic>.<italic>001</italic></td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </alternatives>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="t003fn001">
                    <p><sup>a</sup> Model 1 was adjusted for sex and age; Model 2 was adjusted for sex, age plus years of education; Model 3 was adjusted for sex, age, years of education plus family income.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="t003fn002">
                    <p><sup>b</sup> Logistic regression models were fitted and odds ratios (OR) reported.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The results of mediation analysis, using the four steps proposed by Baron and Kenny [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] confirmed that race/ethnic inequalities of experience of dental caries between Whites and Mixed Race and East Asian descents was mediated through education and income. Race/Ethnicity was significantly associated with experience of dental caries, education and income. Also, the likelihood that Mixed Race and East Asian descents would experience dental caries compared to Whites was attenuated by 14.8% and by 9.5% respectively after adjusting for years of education and income. <xref rid="pone.0145553.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows all models compared to the unadjusted model and, interestingly, education and income fully explained the difference in experience of dental caries between Whites and African descents.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec009">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The unadjusted results of this study corroborated previous studies worldwide that postulated that Whites experience significantly less dental caries than other race/ethnic groups [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Wu et al. [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] also conducted a hierarchical analysis and their results corroborated our findings. The findings also confirmed the well-established association between experience of dental caries and income and education worldwide [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and in the Brazilian population [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. To our knowledge, this is the only study that has conducted mediation analysis.</p>
              <p>Mediation analysis demonstrated that higher education and income may explain inequality of experience of dental caries between race/ethnic groups in Brazil. While education and income fully accounted for the difference in experience of dental caries between Whites and African descents, the likelihood that Mixed Race and East Asian descents would experience dental caries compared to Whites was significantly attenuated.</p>
              <p>Although experience of dental caries has reduced significantly among all race/ethnic groups in 15 to 19 year old Brazilians between 2003 and 2010, inequality of experience of dental caries between these groups has increased. Experience of dental caries has reduced significantly from 89.2% to 76.9% in 15 to 19 year old Brazilians between 2003 [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and 2010 [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Comparison of the results of the national studies carried out in Brazil in 2003 and 2010 showed a larger reduction in prevalence of experience of dental caries in Whites (19.4%) than in Indigenous descents (13.8%), African descents (11.2%), Mixed Race (9.7%) and East Asian descents (7.2%). Furthermore, while in 2003 African descents were 19% less likely to have experience of dental caries than Whites, in 2010 African descents were 32% more likely to have experience of dental caries than Whites. Also, while in 2003 Mixed Race and Whites had similar likelihood of experiencing caries, in 2010 Mixed Race were 69% more likely to have experience of dental caries than Whites (results not presented).</p>
              <p>In the past 10 years, the Brazilian government have been investing in health, education and income policies to reduce inequality. A Family Health Programme (FHP), which aimed to broaden access to public health services, especially in deprived areas, was introduced in Brazil in 1994. The FHP covered 94.3% of Brazilian municipalities and 50.8% of the population in 2010. The FHP offers free community based primary care, and follows the principles of decentralisation, universality and equity [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In 2003, the “<italic>Bolsa Família</italic>” (Family Allowance) programme was introduced, which is a major cash transfer programme targeting those in poverty. It aimed to promote an immediate relief of poverty, improving access to education and health care, and offering complementary social programmes to enable families to end their condition of vulnerability. Enrolment in the “<italic>Bolsa Família</italic>” programme is conditional on school attendance up to 17 years and meeting primary health care conditions such as vaccination and nutritional surveillance [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p>
              <p>In 2004, positive discrimination or social inclusion policies established racial quotas reserving 20% of available admissions in universities for students who self-identified as African descents [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, Whites may have benefited more from the Brazilian economic development and social programmes than other groups or the programmes were still insufficient to reduce inequalities between the race/ethnic groups in Brazil.</p>
              <p>Some limitations of this study need to be discussed. Measuring race/ethnicity in Brazil is challenging [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The aggregation of racial categories is necessary because of the wide range of mixed races from “darker to lighter Mixed Race”. This may lead to misclassification as light Mixed Race may classify themselves as Whites and dark Mixed Race as African descents. Brazilian government policies to reduce ethnic inequality includes positive discrimination, i.e. university entry quotas for African descents and Mixed Race [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. This may have shifted the way Brazilians have self-assessed their race/ethnicity [<xref rid="pone.0145553.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. East Asian descents and Indigenous populations are minority groups in the Brazilian population leading to a smaller sample than Whites, African descents and Mixed Race, which led to larger confidence intervals. While classifying participants into Whites and non-Whites may reduce misclassification it obscures the relevant differences. The cross-sectional design precludes establishing a cause-effect relationship. However, it is more logical to assume that race/ethnicity determines experience of dental caries than the reverse. Race/ethnicity is established at birth; and caries in the permanent dentition starts at age of 6 years. In addition, there is not any clear evidence of racial or genetic variations as determining factors of experience of dental caries. On the contrary, there is strong evidence of ethnic differences in relation to exposure to the risk factors associated with experience of dental caries.</p>
              <p>In conclusion, data analysis of the SBBrasil 2010 demonstrated that Whites have benefited more from the significant reduction in experience of dental caries in 15 to 19 year old Brazilians, as compared with African descents and Mixed Race. Education and income fully explained ethnic inequalities in experience of dental caries between Whites and African descents, and largely explained inequalities between Whites and Mixed Race.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref001">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pegoretti</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Junqueira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frazão</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Narvai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ethnic disparities in the prevalence of dental caries and restorative dental treatment in Brazilian children</article-title>. <source>International Dental Journal</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12653333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12653333</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref002">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multilevel assessment of determinants of dental caries experience in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Commun Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>152.3</lpage>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref003">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ayo-Yusuf</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ayo-Yusuf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Wyk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socio-economic inequities in dental caries experience of 12-year-old South Africans: policy implications for prevention</article-title>. <source>Journal of the South African Dental Association</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref004">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arevalo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trends in paediatric dental caries by poverty status in the United States, 1988–1994 and 1999–2004</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Paediatric Dentistry</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-263X.2009.01029.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20384828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20384828</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref005">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guiotoku</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moysés</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moysés</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>França</surname><given-names>BHS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bisinelli</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Iniquidades raciais em saúde bucal no Brasil</article-title>. <source>Rev Panam Salud Publica</source>. <year>2012</year>:<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 22522876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22522876</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref006">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gushi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dental caries in 15 to 19 year old adolescents in Sao Paulo State, Brazil, 2002</article-title>. <source>Cadernos de Saúde Pública</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1383</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16158143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16158143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref007">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Oral health of Australian Indigenous children compared to non-Indigenous children enrolled in school dental services</article-title>. <source>Aust Dent J</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/adj.12205</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25040876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25040876</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref008">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armfield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts-Thomson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Indigenous and Non-Indigenous Child Oral Health in Three Australian States and Territories</article-title>. <source>Ethnicity &amp; Health</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17132586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref009">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armfield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Indigenous child oral health at a regional and state level</article-title>. <source>Journal of Paediatrics and Child Health</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17316183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17316183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref010">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Binguis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKeown</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Switzer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Oral health inequalities between young Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal children living in Ontario, Canada</article-title>. <source>Community Dentistry and Oral Epidemiology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0528.2009.00497.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19780768?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19780768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref011">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Social disparities in dentition status among American adults</article-title>. <source>Int Dent J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/idj.12062</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24117172?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24117172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref012">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marcenes</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muirhead</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Redshaw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ethnic disparities in the oral health of three- to four-year-old children in East London</article-title>. <source>BDJ</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>215</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>E4</fpage>–<lpage>E4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2013.687</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23887556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23887556</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref013">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hurtig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>San Sebastián</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quizhpe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dental caries in 6-12-year-old indigenous and non-indigenous schoolchildren in the Amazon basin of Ecuador</article-title>. <source>Brazilian Dental Journal</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 18438566?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438566</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref014">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borrell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lassiter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Formicola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Oral Health Status of Adolescents in Northern Manhattan</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Care for the Poor and Underserved</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>814</fpage>–<lpage>832</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17982209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17982209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref015">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Piovesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ardenghi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic inequalities in the distribution of dental caries in Brazilian preschool children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Health Dentistry</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1752-7325.2010.00191.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20735719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20735719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref016">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Psoter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pendrys</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Associations of Ethnicity/Race and Socioeconomic Status with Early Childhood Caries Patterns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Health Dentistry</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16570747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16570747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref017">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plassman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Remle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oral health among white, black, and Mexican-American elders: an examination of edentulism and dental caries</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Health Dentistry</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1752-7325.2011.00273.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22320289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22320289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref018">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loveman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muniz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Measures of “Race” and the analysis of racial inequality in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Social Science Research</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssresearch.2012.06.006</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23146601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23146601</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref019">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dressler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oths</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gravlee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Race and ethinicity in Public Health Research Models to explain Health Disparities</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Anthropol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref020">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of Race and Ethnicity in Biomedical Publication</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>289</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2709</fpage>–<lpage>2716</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12771118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12771118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref021">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Travassos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>The concept and measurement of race and their relationship to public health: a review focused on Brazil and the United States</article-title>. <source>Cadernos de Saúde Pública</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15263977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15263977</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref022">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Almeida-Filho</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>A glossary for health inequalities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>652</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12177079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref023">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schwendicke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dorfer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlattmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic Inequality and Caries: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Dental Research</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034514557546</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25394849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25394849</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref024">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roncalli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sheiham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsakos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socially unequal improvements in dental caries levels in Brazilian adolescents between 2003 and 2010</article-title>. <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>516</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref025">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sabbah</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsakos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sheiham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of income and education on ethnic differences in oral health: a study in US adults</article-title>. <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>516</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.2008.082313</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19254911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19254911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref026">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plassman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Racial disparities in trajectories of dental caries experience</article-title>. <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cdoe.12045</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23465078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23465078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref027">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quarrell</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bedi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Macpherson</surname><given-names>LMD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dental caries in 5-year-old children attending multi-ethnic schools in Greater Glasgow—The impact of ethnic background and levels of deprivation</article-title>. <source>Community Dent Health</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17958077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17958077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref028">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministério da Saúde (Brasil). Banco de dados da pesquisa Condicoes de Saude Bucal da Populacao Brasileira—Levantamento Epidemiologico SB Brasil 2010. 2010. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dab.saude.gov.br/CNSB/sbbrasil/arquivos/projeto_sb2010_relatorio_final.pdf">http://dab.saude.gov.br/CNSB/sbbrasil/arquivos/projeto_sb2010_relatorio_final.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref029">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <chapter-title>Oral health surveys: basic methods</chapter-title><edition>4th Ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>1997</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref030">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatistica (Brasil). IBGE. Rio de Janeiro;2010. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://censo2010.ibge.gov.br/">http://censo2010.ibge.gov.br/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref031">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roncalli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casotti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Aspectos metodologicos do Projeto SBBrasil 2010</article-title>. <source>Cadernos de Saúde Pública</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume> (<issue>Sup</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref032">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fleiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tytun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ury</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Simple Approximation for Calculating Sample Sizes for Comparing Independent Proportions</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref033">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <source>Pratical statistics for medical research</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>; <year>1991</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref034">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Victora</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huttly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olinto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of conceptual frameworks in epidemiological analysis: a hierarchical approach</article-title>. <source>International journal of epidemiology</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9126524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9126524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref035">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Birkmeyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stukel TA Siewers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodney</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wennberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Surgeon volume and operative mortality in the United States</article-title>. <source>The New England journal of medicine</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>349</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2117</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 14645640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14645640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref036">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 3806354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3806354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref037">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministério da Saúde. Secretaria de Atenção à Saúde. Departamento de Atenção Básica. Projeto SB Brasil 2003: condições de saúde bucal da população brasileira 2002–2003: resultados principais/Ministério da Saúde, Secretaria de Atenção à Saúde, Departamento de Atenção Básica–Brasília: Ministério da Saúde (2005). 68 p.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref038">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministério da Saude (Brasil). Guia pratico do Programa Saude da Família. Brasília. 2001:125 p.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref039">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministério do Desenvolvimento Social (Brasil). Bolsa Família. Brasilia. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dab.saude.gov.br/portaldab/ape_bfa.php">http://dab.saude.gov.br/portaldab/ape_bfa.php</ext-link>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref040">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tannuri-Pianto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The redistributive equity of affirmative action: Exploring the role of race, socioeconomic status, and gender in college admissions</article-title>. <source>Economics of Education Review</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0145553.ref041">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marteleto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Educational inequality by race in Brazil, 1982–2007: structural changes and shifts in racial classification</article-title>. <source>Demography</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13524-011-0084-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22259031?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22259031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
