<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:47Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9288054" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9288054</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-17</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcorhl</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9288054</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9288054</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9288054</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35841016</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2325</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-022-02325-9</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Efficacy of 3% hydrogen peroxide solution in cleaning tongue coating before and after surgery: a randomized phase II study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Soutome</surname>
                    <given-names>Sakiko</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>sakiko@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Otsuru</surname>
                    <given-names>Mitsunobu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>ootsuru@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hayashida</surname>
                    <given-names>Saki</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>sakihaya@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Naruse</surname>
                    <given-names>Tomofumi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>naruse12@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Morishita</surname>
                    <given-names>Kota</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>k-morishita@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kurihara</surname>
                    <given-names>Kazumi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>kuririnn59jp@yahoo.co.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kawashita</surname>
                    <given-names>Yumiko</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>yumiko-t@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Funahara</surname>
                    <given-names>Madoka</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>r17funahara@fa.kyu-dent.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Umeda</surname>
                    <given-names>Masahiro</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>mumeda@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Taniguchi</surname>
                    <given-names>Hideki</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>hideki@nagasaki-med.jrc.or.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Saito</surname>
                    <given-names>Toshiyuki</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>syto@nagasaki-u.ac.jp</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.174567.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8902 2273</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral Health, </institution><institution>Nagasaki University Graduate School of Biomedical Science, </institution></institution-wrap>1-7-1 Sakamoto, Nagasaki, 852-8588 Japan </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.174567.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8902 2273</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Oral Oncology, </institution><institution>Nagasaki University Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Nagasaki, Japan </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Dentistry and Oral Surgery, Japanese Red Cross Nagasaki Genbaku Hospital, Nagasaki, Japan </aff>
                <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411238.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0372 2359</institution-id><institution>School of Oral Health Sciences, </institution><institution>Kyushu Dental University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fukuoka, Japan </aff>
                <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Breast and Endocrine Surgery, Japanese Red Cross Nagasaki Genbaku Hospital, Nagasaki, Japan </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>22</volume>
              <elocation-id>287</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>7</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">Increased bacterial presence in the tongue coating and thereby, the saliva, may be a risk factor for postoperative complications such as surgical site infection or postoperative pneumonia after cancer surgery. However, no method for cleaning tongue coating has been established experimentally. The purpose of this study was to verify the effect of brushing with 3% hydrogen peroxide on suppression of the number of bacteria in tongue coating.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">Sixteen patients with gastric cancer or colorectal cancer undergoing surgery were randomly allocated to control and intervention groups. In the control group, the tongue was brushed for 30 s with a water-moistened toothbrush, while in the intervention group, the tongue was brushed for 30 s with a toothbrush moistened with 3% hydrogen peroxide. Bacterial counts on tongue coating were measured before and 30 s after cleaning the tongue coating using the Rapid Oral Bacteria Quantification System.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">In the control group, the number of bacteria on the tongue did not decrease significantly after tongue cleaning on the day before surgery, but did on the day after surgery. In contrast, in the intervention group, the number of bacteria on the tongue decreased significantly after tongue cleaning both on the day before and the day after surgery. Furthermore, when comparing the control and intervention groups, the intervention group had a greater reduction effect.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p id="Par4">Tongue brushing with 3% hydrogen peroxide is a useful method to reduce the number of bacteria on the tongue in patients with gastrointestinal cancer undergoing surgery.</p>
                  <p id="Par5"><italic>Trial registration</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/jRCTs071200020">jRCTs071200020</ext-link> (July 3, 2020).</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Tongue coating</kwd>
                <kwd>Number of bacteria</kwd>
                <kwd>Hydrogen peroxide</kwd>
                <kwd>Tongue cleaning</kwd>
                <kwd>Cancer surgery</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2022</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par8">Tongue coating is a white moss-like deposit that covers the surface of the mucosa on the dorsum of the tongue and is usually physiologically present and not pathological. However, excessive tongue coating is known to be a major cause of bad breath [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]; furthermore, it may cause diseases such as aspiration pneumonia in older adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Aspiration pneumonia develops when three factors—pathogenic microorganisms in the saliva, dysphagia, and weakened immunity—are present simultaneously. In elderly or post-surgery patients, weakened immunity and dysphagia are often unavoidable; therefore, reducing the salivary bacterial counts is necessary to prevent the occurrence of aspiration pneumonia.</p>
              <p id="Par9">Previously, we investigated the relationship between various clinical factors and the number of salivary bacteria in 120 elderly people requiring care and found that tube feeding, inability to gargle, and a higher number of bacteria on the tongue coating were independent risk factors for bacterial growth in the saliva [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Furthermore, our prospective observational study of 54 patients who underwent oncologic or cardiac surgery under general anesthesia revealed that increased amount of tongue coating after surgery was associated with increased bacterial count in the saliva, which suggested that tongue coating should be removed after surgery to minimize the risk of postoperative aspiration pneumonia in patients undergoing major oncologic or cardiac surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par10">However, although there are various reports on cleaning tongue coating, none have been scientifically established. We previously reported in a randomized controlled trial using 32 adult participants that tongue brushing with 10% povidone iodine or 3% hydrogen peroxide (OX) was the most effective method for reducing the bacterial count in tongue coating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The purpose of this study was to clarify whether the number of bacteria coating the tongue was reduced by cleaning the tongue with OX solution on the day before and the day after surgery in patients undergoing gastrointestinal cancer surgery.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Preliminary research</title>
              <p id="Par11">As a preliminary experiment, we compared the effects of chlorhexidine (CHX) and OX solutions on reducing bacterial numbers on the tongue at concentrations approved for oral use in Japan. This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Nagasaki University, and consent for participation and publication was obtained by each participant. Twenty-four subjects who visited Nagasaki University Hospital Dentistry for dental maintenance were allocated into three groups: (1) control group, (2) CHX group, and (3) OX group. In the control, CHX, and OX groups, the tongue was brushed for 30 s with water, CHX (0.005% chlorhexidine gluconate, ConCool F®, Weltec Co., Ltd., Osaka, Japan), and OX (3% OX solution, Oxydol®, Kenei Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.)-moistened toothbrushes, respectively, and gargled with water. We found that the number of bacteria on the tongue was significantly reduced in both the CHX and OX groups as compared with the control group, but the OX group had the largest reduction effect (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Therefore, we used 3% OX solution in this study to investigate its effect on reducing the number of bacteria in tongue coating in patients with gastrointestinal cancer.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The number of bacteria on the tongue before and after tongue cleaning with water (control group), chlorhexidine (CHX group), and hydrogen peroxide (OX group). Bacterial count decreased in each group, but OX group showed the largest reduction effect</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2022_2325_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec3">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p id="Par12">This was a randomized controlled phase II study to investigate the efficacy of 3% OX solution in reducing bacterial numbers in tongue coating in patients undergoing surgery for gastric or colorectal cancer. The subjects were 16 adult patients with gastric cancer or colorectal cancer who underwent surgery at the Japanese Red Cross Nagasaki Genbaku Hospital between June 2020 and September 2021. This is a preliminary study, so, we set the number of cases to a small number of 16 cases. Those without macroscopic tongue coating were excluded from the study. Patients were referred to in-hospital dentistry when their surgeries were scheduled and received oral examinations including panoramic X-ray, oral hygiene instructions, removal of dental plaque and calculus, and dental treatment including extraction the tooth that was difficult to preserve. These dental treatments were completed at least one week before surgery. They underwent mechanical tooth cleaning by a dental hygienist (KK) and tongue coating cleaning by a dentist (SS) the day before surgery. They were randomly allocated to control and intervention groups in a 1:1 ratio using a computer software with a simple randomization method, where, the tongue was brushed for 30 s with a water and 3% OX solution (Oxydol®, Kenei Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.)-moistened toothbrush, respectively. One of the researchers supervised the randomization procedure. The head of the toothbrush used for cleaning the tongue was 20 mm × 9 mm in size. Further, it was a flat toothbrush with medium bristle hardness and a straight grip. This was followed by patients gargling with water in both groups. After oral care by a dentist and a dental hygienist the day before surgery, no oral care intervention by a dentist, dental hygienist, nurse, etc. was performed until the second measurement of this study was performed the day after surgery. Tongue cleaning and the measurement was performed from 10 to 12 AM by a single dentist (SS). All patients had not yet been orally fed at the time of measurement.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Measurement of bacterial count on tongue coating</title>
                <p id="Par13">Bacterial counts on tongue coating were measured before and 30 s after cleaning the tongue coating and gargling, using the Rapid Oral Bacteria Quantification System (DU-AA01NP-H Panasonic Healthcare Co. Ltd., Osaka, Japan), which is based on dielectrophoresis and impedance measurements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. To collect a sample, a sterile cotton swab was placed on the attached constant-pressure sample collection device, pressed against the center of the dorsum of the tongue, and rubbed back and forth for a length of approximately 2 cm.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par14">Endpoint was the total number of bacteria in the tongue coating before and after tongue cleaning on the day before and after surgery for gastrointestinal cancer. The differences in bacterial counts before and after surgery, and between the control and intervention groups were analyzed using paired and unpaired t-tests, respectively. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS software (version 26.0; Japan IBM Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). Statistical significance was set at p &lt; 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec7">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>Patient characteristics</title>
                <p id="Par15">The characteristics of patients in the control and intervention groups are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. There were 13 men and 3 women in the group, with an average age of 68.2 years. There was no significant difference in background factors between the two groups, except that there were more patients with low albumin levels in the intervention group. There were no adverse events following tongue cleaning by OX, and no postoperative pneumonia in 16 patients in the study.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Control group</th><th align="left">Intervention group</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">6</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">67.9 ± 11.4</td><td align="left">68.5 ± 7.84</td><td char="." align="char">0.900</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI</td><td align="left">22.5 ± 1.92</td><td align="left">23.5 ± 3.73</td><td char="." align="char">0.522</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Primary disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Stomach cancer</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Colon cancer</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">6</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Smoking habit</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">5</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Drinking habit</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Diabetes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">5</td><td char="." align="char">0.569</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Leukocyte (μL)</td><td align="left">6425 ± 1649</td><td align="left">7275 ± 2656</td><td char="." align="char">0.455</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hemoglobin (g/dL)</td><td align="left">12.9 ± 2.20</td><td align="left">12.6 ± 2.22</td><td char="." align="char">0.798</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Albumin (g/dL)</td><td align="left">4.39 ± 0.340</td><td align="left">3.90 ± 0.323</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Creatinine (mg/dL)</td><td align="left">0.889 ± 0.0794</td><td align="left">0.880 ± 0.180</td><td char="." align="char">0.902</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of teeth</td><td align="left">15.0 ± 13.0</td><td align="left">18.6 ± 11.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.561</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Denture use</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">5</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Operation time</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Minutes</td><td align="left">163 ± 68.8</td><td align="left">210 ± 65.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.184</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Oral feeding on the next day after surgery</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">7</td><td char="." align="char">0.569</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Number of bacteria on dorsum of the tongue before and after surgery</title>
                <p id="Par16">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the relationship between the number of bacteria on dorsum of the tongue before surgery and each variable. Univariate analysis showed a significant positive correlation between the number of teeth remaining and the number of bacteria on the tongue of preoperative patients (<italic>p</italic> = 0.045), but no other variables were associated with the bacterial count.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Relationship between each variable and number of total bacteria on the tongue at the day before surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">(i) Categorical variable</td><td align="left">Number of total bacteria (logarithm)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">7.82 ± 0.316</td><td char="." align="char">0.186§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">7.44 ± 0.430</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Primary disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Stomach cancer</td><td align="left">7.41 ± 0.583</td><td char="." align="char">0.511§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Colon cancer</td><td align="left">7.56 ± 0.362</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Smoking habit</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.54 ± 0.474</td><td char="." align="char">0.753§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">7.47 ± 0.378</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Drinking habit</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.52 ± 0.489</td><td char="." align="char">0.963§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">7.51 ± 0.375</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Diabetes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.51 ± 0.335</td><td char="." align="char">0.902§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">7.54 ± 0.711</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Denture use</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.69 ± 0.373</td><td char="." align="char">0.056§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">7.29 ± 0.406</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">(ii) Variable (continuous variable)</td><td align="left">Spearman's correlation coefficient</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">0.005</td><td char="." align="char">0.985<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Body mass index</td><td align="left">0.037</td><td char="." align="char">0.892<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Leukocyte (μL)</td><td align="left">0.136</td><td char="." align="char">0.615<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hemoglobin (g/dL)</td><td align="left"> − 0.349</td><td char="." align="char">0.185<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Albumin (g/dL)</td><td align="left"> − 0.329</td><td char="." align="char">0.213<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Creatinine (mg/dL)</td><td align="left"> − 0.165</td><td char="." align="char">0.541<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of teeth</td><td align="left">0.507</td><td char="." align="char">0.045<sup>†</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>§</sup>One-way ANOVA, <sup>†</sup>Spearman's rank correlation coefficient</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par17">The number of bacteria on the tongue on the day after surgery was significantly higher in patients who had a high number of bacteria before and after cleaning the tongue before surgery (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Relationship between each variable and number of total bacteria on the tongue at the day after surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">(i) Categorical variable</td><td align="left">Number of total bacteria (logarithm)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">7.40 ± 0.288</td><td char="." align="char">0.454§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">7.05 ± 0.753</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Primary disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Stomach cancer</td><td align="left">7.36 ± 0.493</td><td char="." align="char">0.373§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Colon cancer</td><td align="left">7.01 ± 0.767</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Smoking habit</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.25 ± 0.450</td><td char="." align="char">0.331§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">6.89 ± 0.996</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Drinking habit</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">6.93 ± 0.839</td><td char="." align="char">0.231§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">7.36 ± 0.389</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Diabetes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.30 ± 0.434</td><td char="." align="char">0.068§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">6.57 ± 1.10</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Oral feeding after surgery</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.21 ± 0.363</td><td char="." align="char">0.383§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">6.84 ± 1.34</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Denture use</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(−)</td><td align="left">7.19 ± 0.883</td><td char="." align="char">0.643§</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)</td><td align="left">7.02 ± 0.390</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">(ii) Variable (continuous variable)</td><td align="left">Spearman's correlation coefficient</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left"> − 0.010</td><td char="." align="char">0.970<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Body mass index</td><td align="left">0.082</td><td char="." align="char">0.762<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Leukocyte (μL)</td><td align="left"> − 0.084</td><td char="." align="char">0.757<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hemoglobin (g/dL)</td><td align="left"> − 0.296</td><td char="." align="char">0.266<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Albumin (g/dL)</td><td align="left"> − 0.240</td><td char="." align="char">0.371<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Creatinine (mg/dL)</td><td align="left">0.003</td><td char="." align="char">0.991<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of teeth</td><td align="left">0.294</td><td char="." align="char">0.269<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Operation time (min)</td><td align="left"> − 0.278</td><td char="." align="char">0.297<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of baacteria before tongue cleaning at the day before surgery</td><td align="left">0.617</td><td char="." align="char">0.011<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of bacteria after tongue cleaning at the day before surgery</td><td align="left">0.697</td><td char="." align="char">0.003<sup>†</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>§</sup>One-way ANOVA, <sup>†</sup>Spearman's rank correlation coefficient</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>Comparison of tongue cleaning effect of the control and intervention groups</title>
                <p id="Par18">Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the changes in the number of bacteria on dorsum of the tongue in the control and intervention groups, with the logarithm of the number of bacteria on the day before preoperative oral care being set to 1.0. In the control group, the number of bacteria on the tongue did not decrease significantly even after tongue cleaning on the day before surgery, but it decreased after tongue cleaning on the day after surgery. In contrast, in the intervention group, the number of bacteria on the tongue decreased significantly after tongue cleaning both the day before and the day after surgery. Furthermore, when comparing the control and intervention groups, the intervention group showed a greater reduction effect.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The number of bacteria on the tongue before and after tongue cleaning in the control and intervention groups. The logarithm of the number of bacteria at the baseline is 1, and it is expressed as a relative ratio. The intervention group showed a greater reduction effect than the control group</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2022_2325_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec11">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par19">This study showed that cleaning the tongue before and after surgery with OX solution can reduce the number of bacteria on the tongue in patients undergoing gastrointestinal cancer surgery.</p>
              <p id="Par20">Various complications may occur after cancer surgery. Among them, surgical site infection (SSI) after head and neck cancer or upper gastrointestinal cancer surgery, and postoperative pneumonia after esophageal cancer surgery are thought to be caused by direct exposure or aspiration of pathogenic microorganisms in saliva. Therefore, it is desirable to reduce the number of bacteria in saliva during the perioperative period as this is a controllable factor. In 2012, public medical insurance was applied for oral care before and after cancer surgery in Japan. Funahara et al. found that topical application of antimicrobial ointment on the tongue reduced the number of bacteria in saliva [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] and reported that this method can reduce the risk of SSI in oral cancer surgery with tracheotomy in a randomized controlled trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. We have reported through multicenter clinical research that perioperative oral care is effective in preventing postoperative pneumonia in esophageal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. As described above, various attempts have been made to reduce the number of bacteria in saliva and reduce the risk of complications by performing oral care before and after cancer surgery.</p>
              <p id="Par21">Tongue coating, along with dental plaque, may serve as a scaffold for the growth of oral bacteria and is thought to be one of the causes of aspiration pneumonia in elderly patients requiring nursing care as well as postoperative patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Tongue coating is formed by hyperkeratinization and elongation of the tongue papillae on the dorsal tongue, and the presence of oral bacteria, exfoliated epithelium, or food residues within the papillae. Hayashida et al. reported that tongue coating but not plaque increased the day after surgery in postoperative patients with mechanical ventilation and stated that tongue coating was more important than plaque as a risk factor for postoperative pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The oral self-cleaning effect of oral feeding does not occur immediately after surgery for postoperative fasting, and tongue coating increases. Although 0.12% CHX is used worldwide for disinfection of oral bacteria, its use on mucous membranes is prohibited because of reports of anaphylaxis in Japan, and only mouthwash of 0.0001–0.0006% solution is allowed. Therefore, we previously examined effects of three types of disinfectants on removing tongue coating, namely benzethonium chloride, povidone iodine, and OX, which are permitted to be used in the oral cavity in Japan, and reported that OX solution was superior in terms of reducing the number of bacteria upon evaluating patients. In this study, we investigated the effects of OX in reducing the number of bacteria on the tongue of patients with gastrointestinal cancer undergoing surgery. It was difficult to remove the tongue coating formed before surgery easily by mechanical brushing with water, although the newly formed tongue coating after surgery could be removed relatively easily because it had not adhered firmly to the tongue yet. On the other hand, this study indicates that brushing with OX removed the tongue coating not only after surgery but also before surgery. Therefore, 3% OX solution can be used to clean the tongue before and after gastrointestinal cancer surgery.</p>
              <p id="Par22">This study has some limitations. First, it is a preliminary study using a small number of cases, and it is difficult to generalize the results obtained. Second, the endpoint is not the onset of complications, such as SSI or postoperative pneumonia, but the number of bacteria on the tongue. Subjective and objective data on oral cleanliness and tongue coating, such as OHAT and Tongue Coating Index scores were not examined in the study. Therefore, it has not been clarified whether tongue cleaning using OX actually leads to the prevention of complications. Furthermore, the total number of bacteria was investigated using the Rapid Oral Bacteria Quantification System; however, the bacterial species were not identified, and the changes in pathogenic microorganisms are unknown. A Device using the Rapid Oral Bacteria Quantification System is now covered by public health insurance system in Japan and is widely used in clinical practice in dentistry. The bacterial count measuring device used in this study is older than the current type, but the machine's performance and methods we used in this study were the same as a new type. In the future, we would like to address these issues in a larger patient sample.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec12">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="Par23">Tongue brushing with 3% OX is a useful method to reduce the number of bacteria present in the tongue coating in patients undergoing surgery for gastrointestinal cancer.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CHX</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par6">Chlorhexidine</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>OX</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par7">Hydrogen peroxide</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>We would like to thank Editage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.editage.com">www.editage.com</ext-link>) for English language editing.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>All authors met the criteria of authorship as outlined in the ICMJE and approved this manuscript for submission. The specific contributions were as follows: Conception or design of the work: SS, MO, and MU. Acquisition: TN, SH, KM, KK, YK, MF and TS. Analysis: TS and MF; interpretation of data for the work: SS, MO, and MU; drafting the work: SS, MO, and MU; revising it critically for important intellectual content: MU, HT, and TS. Final approval of the version to be published; all authors; agreement to be accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved by all authors. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>No funds, grants, or other support was received.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and material</title>
              <p>The datasets generated during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar1">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par24">This study was conducted as a specified clinical trial in accordance with the Clinical Trials Act enacted in April 2018 in Japan and performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki (2013). This study was approved by The Clinical Research Review Board of Nagasaki University (#CRB20-013), and registered in the Japan Register of Clinical Trials on July 3, 2020 (jRCTs071200020). Written informed consent for participation and publication was obtained from all patients.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar2">
                <title>Consent for publication</title>
                <p id="Par25">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par26">The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare relevant to the contents of this article.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seerangaiyan</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jüch</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winkel</surname>
                      <given-names>EG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tongue coating: its characteristics and role in intra-oral halitosis and general health—a review</article-title>
                  <source>J Breath Res</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>034001</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1752-7163/aaa3a1</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29269592</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abe</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ishihara</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adachi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Okuda</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tongue-coating as risk indicator for aspiration pneumonia in edentate elderly</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Gerontol Geriatr</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <lpage>275</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.archger.2007.08.005</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17913263</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Takeshita</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tomioka</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shimazaki</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matsuyama</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koyano</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matsuda</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microfloral characterization of the tongue coating and associated risk for pneumonia-related health problems in institutionalized older adults</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Geniatr Società</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>58</volume>
                  <fpage>1050</fpage>
                  <lpage>1057</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2010.02867.x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soutome</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashida</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Umeda</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An analysis of the factors affecting the number of bacteria in the saliva of elderly adults in need of care</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Gerontol</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <lpage>207</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijge.2018.01.003</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yanamoto</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soutome</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashida</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Umeda</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical observation of tongue coating of perioperative patients: factors related to the number of bacteria on the tongue before and after surgery</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-018-0689-x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30572861</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soutome</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nakamura</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soh</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Honda</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hikiji</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of the efficacy of three types of disinfectants approved for oral use in Japan in reducing the bacterial count of tongue coating: a randomised-controlled study</article-title>
                  <source>Oral Health Prev Dent</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
                  <lpage>409</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34259433?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34259433</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suehiro</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yatsunami</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamada</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Quantitative estimation of biological cell concentration suspended in aqueous medium by using dielectrophoretic impedance measurement method</article-title>
                  <source>J Phys D Appl Phys</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>2814</fpage>
                  <lpage>2820</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0022-3727/32/21/316</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hirota</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Inagaki</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamada</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ishihara</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miyake</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of a rapid oral bacteria quantification system using dielectrophoresis and the impedance measurement</article-title>
                  <source>Biocontrol Sci</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <lpage>49</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4265/bio.19.45</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24670618</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashida</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sakamoto</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yanamoto</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kosai</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yanagihara</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of topical antibiotic administration on the inhibition of perioperative oral bacterial growth in oral cancer patients: a preliminary study</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>1225</fpage>
                  <lpage>1230</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijom.2015.06.002</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26119366</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yanamoto</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ueda</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ota</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishimaki</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevention of surgical site infection after oral cancer surgery by topical tetracycline: results of a multicenter randomized control trial</article-title>
                  <source>Medicine</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <fpage>e8891</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000008891</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29310375</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soutome</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yanamoto</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hasegawa</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Komori</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oho</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Preventive effect on post-operative pneumonia of Oral Health care among patients who undergo esophageal resection: a multi-center retrospective study</article-title>
                  <source>Surg Infect</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <lpage>484</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/sur.2015.158</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soutome</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yanamoto</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hasegawa</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Komori</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yamada</surname>
                      <given-names>SI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of perioperative oral care on prevention of postoperative pneumonia associated with esophageal cancer surgery: A multicenter case-control study with propensity score matching analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Medicine</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <fpage>e7436</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000007436</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28816937</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soutome</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hasegawa</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yamguchi</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aoki</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kanamura</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mukai</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevention of postoperative pneumonia by perioperative oral care in patients with esophageal cancer undergoing surgery: a multicenter retrospective study of 775 patients</article-title>
                  <source>Support Care Cancer</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>4155</fpage>
                  <lpage>4162</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00520-019-05242-w</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31897780</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashida</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funahara</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sekino</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kosai</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yanamoto</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of tooth brushing, irrigation, and topical tetracycline administration on the reduction of oral bacteria in mechanically ventilated patients: a preliminary study</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-016-0224-x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27268137</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
