<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:47:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4296661" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4296661</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-01-26</datestamp>
        <setSpec>dpjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dpjo</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2176-9451</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2177-6709</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dental Press International</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4296661</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4296661</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4296661</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25715721</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2176-9451.19.5.088-096.oar</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Rapid maxillary expansion effects: An alternative assessment method by
means of cone-beam tomography</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Melgaço</surname>
                    <given-names>Camilo Aquino</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Columbano</surname>
                    <given-names>José</given-names>
                    <suffix>Neto</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jurach</surname>
                    <given-names>Estela Maris</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nojima</surname>
                    <given-names>Matilde da Cunha Gonçalves</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sant'Anna</surname>
                    <given-names>Eduardo Franzotti</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nojima</surname>
                    <given-names>Lincoln Issamu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Professor, Rio Verde Valley University (UNINCOR)</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Assistant professor, São José College</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> Assistant professor, Federal University of Santa Maria (UFSM)</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label> Adjunct professor, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ)</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Contact address:</bold> Camilo Aquino Melgaço Rua Espírito Santo, 1111 ‒ Centro
‒ Belo Horizonte/MG - Brazil CEP: 30160-031 ‒ E-mail:
<email>camiloaquino@ig.com.br</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>Sep-Oct</season>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Sep-Oct</season>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>19</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <fpage>88</fpage>
              <lpage>96</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>01</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                  <p> This study aims to develop a method to assess the changes in palatal and lingual
cross-sectional areas in patients submitted to rapid maxillary expansion (RME).
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>METHODS:</title>
                  <p> The sample comprised 31 Class I malocclusion individuals submitted to RME and
divided into two groups treated with Haas (17 patients) and Hyrax (14 patients)
expanders. Cone-beam computed tomography scans were acquired at T<sub>0</sub>
(before expansion ) and T<sub>1</sub> (six months after screw stabilization).
Maxillary and mandibular cross-sectional areas were assessed at first permanent
molars and first premolars regions and compared at T<sub>0</sub> and
T<sub>1</sub>. Mandibular occlusal area was also analyzed. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESULTS:</title>
                  <p> Maxillary cross-sectional areas increased in 56.18 mm<sup>2</sup> and 44.32
mm<sup>2</sup> for the posterior and anterior regions. These values were
smaller for the mandible, representing augmentation of 40.32 mm<sup>2</sup> and
39.91 mm<sup>2</sup> for posterior and anterior sections. No differences were
found when comparing both expanders. Mandibular occlusal area increased
43.99mm<sup>2</sup> and mandibular incisors proclined. Increments of 1.74 mm
and 1.7 mm occurred in mandibular intermolar and interpremolar distances. These
same distances presented increments of 5.5 mm and 5.57 mm for the maxillary arch.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                  <p> Occlusal and cross-sectional areas increased significantly after RME. The method
described seems to be reliable and precise to assess intraoral area changes.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <sec>
                  <title>INTRODUÇÃO:</title>
                  <p> o presente estudo teve como objetivo desenvolver um método para avaliar as
mudanças nas áreas transversais palatinas e linguais em pacientes submetidos à
expansão rápida da maxila (ERM). </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>MÉTODOS:</title>
                  <p> a amostra foi composta por 31 indivíduos com má oclusão Classe I de Angle,
submetidos a ERM e divididos em dois grupos, tratados com expansores tipo Haas (17
pacientes) e de Hyrax (14 pacientes). Tomografias computadorizadas de feixe cônico
foram adquiridas em T<sub>0</sub> e T<sub>1</sub> (antes da expansão e seis meses
após a estabilização do parafuso). Áreas transversais da maxila e mandíbula foram
avaliadas nas regiões de primeiros molares permanentes e pré-molares e comparadas
entre T<sub>0</sub> e T<sub>1</sub>. A área oclusal mandibular também foi
analisada. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESULTADOS:</title>
                  <p> as áreas transversais maxilares aumentaram 56,18mm<sup>2</sup> e
44,32mm<sup>2</sup> para regiões posterior e anterior, respectivamente. Esses
valores foram menores para mandíbula, representando aumentos de
40,32mm<sup>2</sup> e de 39,91mm<sup>2</sup> para as seções anterior e
posterior. Não foram encontradas diferenças quando se comparam os dois expansores.
A área oclusal mandibular aumentou 43,99mm<sup>2</sup> e incisivos inferiores
vestibularizaram. Incrementos de 1,74mm e 1,7mm ocorreram entre as distâncias
intermolares e interpré-molares inferiores. Essas mesmas distâncias apresentaram
incrementos de 5,5mm e de 5,57mm para maxila. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>CONCLUSÃO:</title>
                  <p> as áreas transversais avaliadas e oclusal de mandíbula aumentaram
significativamente após a ERM. O processo descrito parece ser um método confiável
e preciso para avaliar as mudanças das área intrabucais propostas.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Orthodontics</kwd>
                <kwd>Malocclusion</kwd>
                <kwd>Palatal expander</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="4"/>
                <table-count count="3"/>
                <ref-count count="37"/>
                <page-count count="9"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Midpalatal suture in the maxilla might be split by rapid maxillary expansion (RME), a
method first described in 1860.<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Many studies
based on linear and angular analyses confirm the dentoalveolar and skeletal changes
induced by this procedure.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Increased maxillary transverse dimension is
key not only to achieve space gain for teeth alignment, but also to improve
stomatognathic functions, such as nasal cavity enlargement, and favor better tongue
position.<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> When compared to normal arches, patients with
maxillary constriction have their tongue in a lower position.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Expansion of mandibular arch widths is also observed after
RME.<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> In these cases, altered dental contacts could
incline posterior mandibular teeth buccally.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Long-term outcomes indicate spontaneous
mandibular arch response in Class I malocclusion patients treated with RME only, thereby
showing clinical stability and significant augmentation of mandibular intermolar and
intercanine widths.<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
</p>
              <p>Two types of expanders are most commonly used. Because the tooth-tissue borne expander
(Haas) has an acrylic pad in contact with the palate, it distributes expanding forces
along posterior teeth and the palatal vault. Conversely, the tooth-borne expander
(Hyrax) does not have this acrylic pad and, for this reason, it only presumably delivers
forces to the maxilla by means of appliance-supporting teeth.<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Some authors reported similar effects for both Haas and Hyrax
expanders; however, other studies suggest less teeth inclination when tooth-tissue borne
expander is used.<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Nowadays, highly developed techniques based on
tomographic images and 3D models are available and used to assess morphological changes
of the dentofacial complex.<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> However, the impact of RME treatment on
intraoral space gain has not been fully explored.<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
</p>
              <p>This study aimed at developing a method to assess palatal and lingual cross-sectional
changes in Class I malocclusion patients submitted to RME.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <p>A total of 467 adolescents from five high schools of Belo Horizonte/Brazil were examined
for potential RME treatment. In selecting the sample, the following inclusion criteria
were applied: Angle Class I malocclusion; clinical need for rapid maxillary expansion
visually determined by excessive palatal crown inclination of posterior maxillary teeth;
no posterior or anterior crossbite; good oral health conditions (no periodontal disease
or tooth decay); clinically healthy temporomandibular joints with normal range of
motion; and no functional deviations. The exclusion criteria were: Congenitally missing
teeth; craniofacial deformity; systemic diseases; history or evidence of disk
displacement, pain or joint noises. Permanent dentition without previous orthodontic
treatment was required for both arches (except for third molars).</p>
              <p>Initial sample comprised 58 individuals; however, only 34 patients with average age of
12 years and 10 months for girls and 13 years for boys, with active facial growth
(posteriorly confirmed by cervical vertebral maturation method<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), started the treatment. The sample was randomly and equally
divided into Group I (Haas) and Group II (Hyrax). Cone-beam computed tomography (CBCT)
was taken before adaptation of expanders (T<sub>0</sub>) and 6 months after screw
stabilization (T<sub>1</sub>). During the retention period, three patients were
eliminated from the study due to premature appliance removal; therefore, 17 patients
remained in Group I while 14 patients remained in Group II with a total sample
comprising 31 individuals. This project was approved by the Federal University of Rio de
Janeiro Institutional Review Board (n<sup>o</sup>. 35/2010 process n<sup>o</sup>.
62/2009). An informed consent form was signed by all patients' parents or guardians.</p>
              <p>The same laboratory manufactured all appliances using 11-mm screws (Dental Morelli, São
Paulo, Brazil). All first premolars and first molars were banded and received 1.0-mm
stainless steel wires welded to the palatal and buccal surfaces of bands. During the
first activation phase, the screws were opened 0.8 mm (a complete turn). Subsequently,
activations were based on the same protocol adopted by several authors<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> and consisted of a quarter of a turn (0.2 mm)
in the morning and a quarter of a turn in the evening. The screws were stabilized when
the tip of the palatal cusps of the maxillary permanent first molars contacted the tip
of buccal cusps of the mandibular permanent first molars, as determined by clinical
observation.</p>
              <p>During CBCT scanning, all patients were oriented to remain in maximal dental
intercuspation with their heads positioned so that the Frankfort and mid-sagittal planes
were oriented parallel and perpendicular to the floor, respectively. The same equipment
(i-CAT, Imaging Sciences International, Hatfield, PA, USA) was used according to a
standard protocol (120 KVp, 5 mA, FOV = 13 x 17, voxel = 0.4 mm and scan time = 20 sec).
Data were exported in DICOM (Digital Imaging and Communication in Medicine) format and
imported into Dolphin Imaging software<sup>(r)</sup> (version 11.0 - Dolphin Imaging
&amp; Management Solutions, Charsworth, CA, USA) so as to reconstruct 3D images for
further analysis.</p>
              <p>After images were obtained, the following landmarks were established: Maxilla - tip of
first premolars palatal cusps and first permanent molars mesio-palatal cusps. Mandible -
the center mesio-distal width of the incisal border of four incisors, tips of both
canines, buccal cusps of all premolars, tips of first permanent molars mesio-buccal and
middle cusps.</p>
              <p>In order to enable comparison at different times, all images were equally positioned at
T<sub>0</sub> and T<sub>1</sub>. The palatal plane (line connecting posterior nasal
spine and anterior nasal spine) and mandibular plane (line tangent to the right inferior
border of the mandible) were used as basis for all maxillary and mandibular
measurements. Head roll orientation was based on the transverse plane intersecting the
right and left frontozygomatic sutures. Head yaw orientation was based on vertical plane
tangent to the posterior border of both external acoustic meatus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig 1</xref>). </p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Head orientation based on axial, coronal and sagittal planes.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-19-05-00088-gf01"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>To determine the following maxillary measures, head pitch orientation was based on
palatal plane horizontally oriented: (1) intermolar distance (MD), linear distance
between right and left tips of first permanent molars mesio-palatal cusps; (2) vertical
displacement of molars (VDM), vertical distance between the tips of first permanent
molars mesio-palatal cusps and the palatal plane; (3) interpremolar distance (PMD),
linear distance between right and left tips of first premolars palatal cusps; (4)
vertical displacement of premolars (VDPM), vertical distance between the tips of first
premolars palatal cusps and the palatal plane; (5) posterior maxillary cross-sectional
area (PMA), obtained at first molars region. Coronal image slice showing the tips of
mesio-palatal cusps was used. The area was delimited by a line connecting right and left
palatal alveolar crests contouring the palatal vault; (6) anterior maxillary
cross-sectional area (AMA), the region of first premolars, the same method described for
PMA was used.</p>
              <p>Subsequently, for mandibular measures, head pitch orientation was based on mandibular
plane horizontally oriented: (7) intermolar distance (MD), linear distance between right
and left tips of first permanent molars mesio-buccal cusps; (8) vertical displacement of
molars (VDM), vertical distance between the tips of first permanent molars mesio-buccal
cusps and the lower mandibular border; (9) interpremolar distance (PMD), the linear
distance between right and left tips of first premolars buccal cusps; (10) vertical
displacement of premolars (VDPM), vertical distance between the tips of first premolars
buccal cusps and the lower mandibular border; (11) posterior mandibular cross-sectional
area (PMnA), obtained at the region of first molars. Coronal section showing the tips of
mesio-buccal cusps was used. The area was delimited by a line connecting right and left
lingual alveolar crests and contouring the lingual alveolar bones. However, there is no
lower anatomic limit for the cross-sectional areas of the mandible. Thus, a straight
line connecting the lowest points located at the mandibular border delimited these
areas; (12) anterior mandibular cross-sectional area (AMnA), the region of first
premolars, the same method described for PMnA was used to obtain this measure; (13)
mandibular occlusal area (MnOA), using an axial image slice, this area was calculated
connecting all lower dental landmarks; (14) mandibular occlusal contour (MnOC), linear
connection of all mandibular dental landmarks, using the same axial image slice
described for MnOA; (15) incisor mandibular plane angle (IMPA), the angle formed by long
axis of the right mandibular central incisor and the mandibular plane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figs 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">B</xref>). </p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Maxillary measures: (MD) intermolar distance; (VDM) vertical displacement
of molars and (PMA) posterior maxillary cross-sectional area. The same measures
were performed for premolars.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-19-05-00088-gf02"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>A) Mandibular measures: (MD) intermolar distance; (VDM) vertical
displacement of molars and (PMnA) posterior mandibular cross-sectional area.
The same measures were performed for premolars. B) Mandibular occlusal area
(MnOA) and mandibular occlusal contour (MnOC).</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-19-05-00088-gf03"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>All measures were compared at T<sub>0</sub> and T<sub>1</sub>. In order to determine
reliability and reproducibility, the same examiner used the same protocol to measure
three patients, three times with a one-week interval in between. Intraclass correlation
coefficient (ICC) was used to determine measurement consistency. Unpaired Student's
t-test was used to compare the differences between both expanders (Haas and Hyrax) while
paired Student's t-test was used to compare the results at T<sub>0</sub> and
T<sub>1</sub>. Significance level was set at 5%.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>A high ICC value of 0.963 was found, thereby indicating great measurement precision and
reliability. Comparison between Group I and Group II at T<sub>0</sub> and T<sub>1</sub>
is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>. No statistically
significant differences were found when comparing the main effects of Haas and Hyrax
expanders. Thus, the rest of the analysis considered the total sample of 31
individuals.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Comparison of the main measures of Group I and Group II. Mean values,
standard deviations and significances at T0 and T1.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">T<sub>1</sub>
</th>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">T<sub>0</sub>
</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group I</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group II</th>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group I</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group II</th>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig. P value</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig. P value</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="7" colspan="1"> Mandible</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45.32 ± 2.99</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 44.45 ± 2.87</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 46.86 ± 3.13</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 46.46 ± 2.98</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.19</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMnA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 931.47 ± 97.94</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 919.75 ± 97.36</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.26</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 971.31 ± 142.95</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 961.12 ± 87.70</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.22</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 33.27 ± 1.67</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 33.65 ± 3.45</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.12</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35.72 ± 3.12</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 34.71 ± 2.72</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.11</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AMnA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 746.66 ± 123.80</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 738.81 ± 117.25</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.30</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 787.05 ± 145.28</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 776.59 ± 100.33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.27</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MnOA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1006.42 ± 83.95</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 991.37 ± 62.18</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1045.94 ± 103.80</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1033.76 ± 91.21</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.37</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MnOC<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 83.62 ± 4.36</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 82.92 ± 4.15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.65</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 84.79 ± 4.32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 84.52 ± 4.28</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.86</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IMPA<sup>3</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 92.88 ± 4.72</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 91.97 ± 5.77</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.87</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 93.43 ± 4.55</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 94.38 ± 5.40</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.75</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="4" colspan="1"> Maxilla</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 39.80 ± 2.89</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 39.79 ± 1.99</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.61</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45.41 ± 2.66</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45.13 ± 2.10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.58</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 344.14 ± 57.91</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 341.12 ± 46.14</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.13</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 400.14 ± 58.86</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 397.74 ± 53.35</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.12</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 29.61 ± 2.43</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 28.95 ± 2.84</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.16</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 34.91 ± 2.40</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35.30 ± 2.65</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.17</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AMA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 221.77 ± 59.11</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 223.39 ± 41.86</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.63</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 267.13 ± 63.49</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 265.82 ± 67.82</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.69</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="t01TFN01">
                      <p>S.D. - standard deviation. Sig. - significance P= 0.05. 1 - values in
millimeters. 2 - values in square millimeters. 3- values in degrees.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>Maxillary intermolar and interpremolar distances increased 5.5 mm and 5.57 mm,
respectively. Similarly, mandibular intermolar and interpremolar distances increased
1.74 mm and 1.7 mm. Although these variations were smaller for lower teeth, they were
statistically significant. All first molars and first premolars underwent extrusion
movements with average values of 0.15 mm (upper teeth) and 0.78 mm (lower teeth).
However, these movements were statistically significant only for mandibular teeth.</p>
              <p>All areas augmented significantly. PMA and AMA increased 56.18 mm<sup>2</sup> and 44.32
mm<sup>2</sup>, respectively. The values for the corresponding lower areas were 40.32
mm<sup>2</sup> and 39.91 mm<sup>2</sup>. MnOA and MnOC increased 43.99 mm<sup>2</sup>
and 1.35 mm. On average, mandibular incisors proclined 1.23<sup>o</sup>. The mean
values, standard deviations, differences and significances for all maxillary and
mandibular measures are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Tables 2</xref> and
<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">3</xref>.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Mean values, standard deviations, differences and significances for all
maxillary measures at T0 and T1.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference (T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>0</sub>)</th>
                        <th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sig.<break/> P value</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="4" colspan="1"> Upper<break/> molars</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 39.79 ± 2.51</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45.29 ± 2.41</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.5 ± 1.46</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MVD*<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 21.13 ± 2.18</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 21.26 ± 2.31</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.13 ± 1.15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.54</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MVD**<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 21.38 ± 2.06</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 21.52 ± 2.24</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.14 ± 1.11</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.46</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 342.23 ± 52.53</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 398.41 ± 56.71</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 56.18 ± 28.78</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="4" colspan="1"> Upper<break/> premolars</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 29.51 ± 2.61</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35.07 ± 3.46</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.57 ± 2.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMVD*<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 23.89 ± 2.26</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 24.02 ± 2.46</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.13 ± 0.98</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.48</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMVD**<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 23.83 ± 2.38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 24.04 ± 2.33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.21 ± 0.91</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.14</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AMA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 222.5 ± 51.82</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 266.81 ± 64.22</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 44.22 ± 39.47</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="t02TFN01">
                      <p>S.D. = standard deviation. Sig. = significance P = 0.05</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="t02TFN02">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p> right side</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="t02TFN03">
                      <label>**</label>
                      <p> left side. 1 - values in millimeters. 2 - values in square millimeters.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Mean values, standard deviations, differences and significances for all
mandibular measures at T0 and T1.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" style="border-top: 1px solid black; border-bottom: 1px solid black; width: 100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1</sub>
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference (T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>0</sub>)</th>
                        <th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sig.<break/> P value</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="4" colspan="1"> Lower<break/> molars</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 44.96 ± 2..92</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 46.7 ± 3.02</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.74 ± 1.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MVD*<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 31.50 ± 3.67</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 32.19 ± 3.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.69 ± 0.81</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MVD**<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 31.52 ± 3.21</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 32.35 ± 3.13</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.83 ± 0.92</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMnA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 925.94 ± 108.64</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 966.26 ± 123.65</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 40.32 ± 57.49</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="4" colspan="1"> Lower<break/> premolars</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMD<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 33.43 ± 2.28</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35.13 ± 2.92</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.7 ± 2.69</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMVD*<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 36.22 ± 2.98</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 36.93 ± 3.22</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.71 ± 0.96</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PMVD**<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 36.07 ± 3.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 36.99 ± 3.12</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.92 ± 1.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AMnA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 742.6 ± 119.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 782.5 ± 127.97</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 39.91 ± 59.62</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MnOA<sup>2</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 995.9 ± 76.61</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1039.89 ± 99.27</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 43.99 ± 43.09</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MnOC<sup>1</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 83.33 ± 4.21</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 84.67 ± 4.23</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.35 ± 1.24</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IMPA<sup>3</sup>
</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 92.58 ± 7.48</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 93.81 ± 6.88</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.23 ± 2.41</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.00</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="t03TFN01">
                      <p>S.D. = standard deviation. Sig. = significance P= 0.05</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="t03TFN02">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p> right side</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="t03TFN03">
                      <label>**</label>
                      <p> left side. 1 - values in millimeters. 2- values in square millimeters. 3-
values in degrees.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>Intraclass correlation coefficient can be used to determine consistency, reliability and
reproducibility of quantitative measurements performed by the same or different
observers. ICC values greater than 0.75 indicate excellent reproducibility.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The high value of ICC (0.963) found in this
study indicates great measurement reliability and precision. Similar values were
described by other authors,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> thereby indicating intraoperator reliability.
The high precision of the software measurement tools used, associated with image
quality, examiner experience and absence of blurring of anatomic structures<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> justify these findings.</p>
              <p>In the present study, Haas and Hyrax expanders yielded similar results. The effects of
RME seems to be similar regardless of the expansion appliance.<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The skeletal and dentoalveolar effects
produced by these appliances have been the main focus of many studies;<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> however, when compared to Hyrax, it is assumed
that Haas produces more skeletal effects with less teeth inclination.<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> This fact is possibly explained by the
presence of the acrylic pad that distributes force through the maxilla, inducing
orthopedic modification and remodeling the alveolar processes.<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> The main purpose of this study was not simply
compare expanders, but investigate intraoral space gains after RME. However, no
statistically significant differences were observed when Haas and Hyrax linear measures
and cross-sectional space gains were assessed, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>. Nevertheless, these results are based only on quantitative
analyses. Qualitative assessments could probably reveal different results based on the
superimpositions of Haas and Hyrax cross-sectional images.</p>
              <p>Some linear measurements were taken to favor interpretation and understanding of
alterations. Intermolar and interpremolar distances increased in both the maxilla and
mandible. However, maxilla presented the highest values: 5.5 mm for molars and 5.57 mm
for premolars. Expander rigidity assures no flexion or deformation during activation or
retention.<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Consequently, more significant
movement would be expected in anchorage teeth, as stated by other authors.<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> As for the mandible, increases of 1.74 mm and
1.7 mm were observed for intermolar and interpremolar distances. These values are in
accordance with those found in other studies<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> and could be explained by the changes in
occlusal contacts after RME. These contacts induce additional loading of the buccal
cusps of mandibular teeth, causing expansion and uprighting movements.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Another plausible explanation is associated
with oral muscles. During RME, the buccinator is laterally dislocated and the internal
presence and function of the tongue could buccally tip posterior teeth, thereby
contributing to mandibular interdental distances augmentation.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
</p>
              <p>Maxillary dental extrusion is a common effect related to RME.<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In this study, all first molars and first
premolars underwent extrusion movements, as observed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">3</xref>. However, the amount
of maxillary teeth extrusion was not statistically significant and expanders rigidity
could again explain this effect.<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> This result is
in accordance with Garib et al<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> who compared 3
groups of patients (Group 1, treated with Haas and Hyrax expanders followed by edgewise
therapy; Group 2, treated only with edgewise therapy; Group 3, control group) and found
no vertical differences in facial height, maxillary first molars extrusion and overbite.
Lione Franchi and Cozza<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> conducted a systematic
review about the effects of RME in growing individuals and concluded that the vertical
changes observed after treatment are small and probably transitory. In contrast,
mandibular first molars and first premolars presented significantly extrusion. As most
patients were in cervical vertebral stage 3 (CVS3),<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> indicating that active growth was in progress, molars and premolars
uprighting movements and dentoalveolar vertical growth could have influenced these
results.</p>
              <p>A statistically significant increase in maxillary and mandibular cross-sectional areas
was observed after RME. With regard to the maxilla, the gain obtained for PMA and AMA
was 16.42% and 19.92%, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>).
In this study, maxillary separation occurred in all patients, since a gap between
maxillary central incisors appeared in all cases. Therefore, these maxillary variations
reflect not only alveolar changes resulting from bone remodeling and teeth movement, but
also represent orthopedic gains. Phatouros and Goonewardene<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> found similar results in maxillary cross-sectional areas of
patients submitted to RME. In the present study, the authors adopted palatal alveolar
crests as reference points to determine the occlusal limits. Since no significant dental
extrusion was observed in maxillary molars and premolars, augmentation does not seem to
be derived from vertical remodeling of alveolar crests. The type of expander used is
another important issue to be considered. As previously stated, some studies assert that
the acrylic pad of the tooth-tissue borne expander distributes expanding forces along
posterior teeth and the palatal vault, promoting less teeth inclination and more
alveolar bone remodeling.<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Thus, more space gain would be expected in
patients treated with Haas expanders; however, no differences were observed when both
appliances were compared. Results are based on quantitative analysis, for this reason,
further qualitative assessment including overlap of Haas and Hyrax cross-sectional
images could reveal whether space gains are related to specific anatomic regions of the
palate or not, thereby promoting better visual understanding of treatment outcomes.<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Although space gains were similar for both
appliances, differences in shape could reveal the influence of the type of expander
used.</p>
              <p>As for the mandible, increase was found for posterior (4.35%) and anterior (5.37%)
cross-sectional areas, probably as a result of lingual bone remodeling, a consequence of
dental uprighting movement, extrusion and vertical growth.<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> As previously described, the occlusal limits
of mandibular areas were determined by a line connecting the lingual alveolar crests.
Since teeth extrusion occurred, vertical bone remodeling of these crests as well as
vertical growth could justify these findings. Thus, it seems reasonable to assume that
these areas are more reliable to describe alveolar and basal bone changes occurring in
the mandible after RME.</p>
              <p>On average, MnOA and MnOC increased 43.99 mm<sup>2</sup> and 1.35 mm. As demonstrated in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>, increases in mandibular intermolar
and interpremolar distances contributed to yield such results. Other authors confirm
uprighting movements of mandibular molars and premolars after RME.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Mandibular incisors proclined significantly,
as confirmed by IMPA variation, thereby contributing to MnOA and MnOC alterations.
However, Tai et al<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> also found IMPA and
intermolar distance increases in untreated patients. Although these changes were not
statistically significant, the authors identified a natural tendency towards incisor
proclination and molar uprighting. </p>
              <p>Even though changes in MnOA and MnOC were statistically significant, the clinical
relevance of results found for MnOC is questionable. Based on the methodology adopted
herein, minor alterations in MnOC could lead to great differences in MnOA, as
demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref> which shows two examples
of mandibular occlusal images represented by blue and red landmarks. These landmarks are
1 cm apart with the total occlusal contour being the same in both examples.
Nevertheless, there is great disparity in size, which represents the real difference
between them. As a result, the occlusal area seems to represent the occlusal changes in
a more reliable manner. It is worth noting that area analysis is not reliable in
determining the amount of teeth movement, but it may be a precise tool used to assess
intraoral space gains.</p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Blue and red landmarks are 1 cm apart. The total contour is 12 cm for both
cases. However, differences are evident.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="dpjo-19-05-00088-gf04"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>The results yielded by the present study are based on two groups treated with RME by
means of two different expanders and without a control group. As stated by other
authors, the advantage of a control group to compare the results is unquestionable in
scientific investigation.<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> However, recent systematic reviews highlighted
that most studies based on RME presented some methodological problems including small
sample size and absence of a control group.<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> This is also a limitation of the present
study. The methodology adopted herein consists of a longitudinal research based on
successive tomographic images. Thus, the control group would be submitted to radiation
doses that would not bring any benefits to the individuals, thereby causing potential
problems to their health and arising serious questioning in terms of ethical approval.
Due to these facts, there were changes during RME and the retention period. The effects
of the post-retention period were not observed, once it would implicate in new
tomographic images and further radiation doses. Nevertheless, these effects are
important and help us understand the stability of this kind of treatment and should be
explored in future studies.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>Based on the studied sample and on the methodology adopted herein it is reasonable to
conclude:</p>
              <p>
                <list list-type="simple">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» Maxillary and mandibular cross-sectional areas increased significantly after
RME. Mandibular occlusal area also increased.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» No statistically significant differences were found when comparing the
effects of Haas and Hyrax expanders.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» Maxillary and mandibular intermolar and interpremolar distances increased
after RME.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» Cross-sectional and occlusal analyses seem to be alternative methods to
assess intraoral changes after RME.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>» Studies in different populations with similar methodology and the presence of
a control group would be important to confirm the present results.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>» The authors report no commercial, proprietary or financial interest in the products
or companies described in this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>» Patients displayed in this article previously approved the use of their facial and
intraoral photographs.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adkins</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nanda</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Currier</surname>
                      <given-names>GF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Arch perimeter changes on rapid palatal
expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>97</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <lpage>199</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2178393</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Angell</surname>
                      <given-names>EC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Treatment of irregularities of the permanent or adult
teeth</article-title>
                  <source>Dent Cosmos</source>
                  <year>1860</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>540</fpage>
                  <lpage>544</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baccetti</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franchi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McNamara</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The cervical vertebral maturation (CVM) method for the
assessment of optimal treatment timing in dentofacial orthopedic</article-title>
                  <source>Semin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <lpage>129</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bazargani</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feldmann</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bondemark</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Three-dimensional analysis of effects of rapid maxillary
expansion on facial sutures and bones</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1074</fpage>
                  <lpage>1082</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23745976</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chung</surname>
                      <given-names>C-H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Font</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Skeletal and dental changes in the sagittal, vertical,
and transverse dimensions after rapid palatal expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>126</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>569</fpage>
                  <lpage>575</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520689</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garib</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriques</surname>
                      <given-names>JFC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coelho</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rapid maxillary expansion: tooth-tissue-borne vs.
tooth-borne expanders: A CT evaluation of dentoskeletal effects</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>548</fpage>
                  <lpage>557</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16097223</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garib</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriques</surname>
                      <given-names>JFC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                      <given-names>AY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Periodontal effects of rapid maxillary expansion with
tooth-tissue-borne and tooth-borne expanders: a computed tomography
evaluation</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>129</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>749</fpage>
                  <lpage>758</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16769493</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garib</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henriques</surname>
                      <given-names>JFC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>PEGC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gomes</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Longitudinal effects of rapid maxillary expansion a
retrospective cephalometric study</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>77</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>442</fpage>
                  <lpage>448</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17465651</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gracco</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malaguti</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lombardo</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mazzoli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raffaeli</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Palatal volume following rapid maxillary expansion in
mixed dentition</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>80</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>159</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19852655</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gryson</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Changes in mandibular interdental distance concurrent
with rapid maxillary expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>1977</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <lpage>192</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">332017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haas</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Palatal expansion: just the beginning of dentofacial
orthopedics</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>1970</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <lpage>254</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haas</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rapid expansion of the maxillary dental arch and nasal
cavity by opening the midpalatal suture</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>1961</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <lpage>90</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haas</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The treatment of maxillary deficiency by opening the
midpalatal suture</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>1965</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <lpage>217</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14331020</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huynh</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kennedy</surname>
                      <given-names>DB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joondeph</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bollen</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Treatment response and stability of slow maxillary
expansion using Haas, hyrax, and quad-helix appliances: a retrospective
study</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>136</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
                  <lpage>339</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19732666</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Iseri</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tekkaya</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oztan</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bilgic</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The biomechanical effects of rapid maxillary expansion
on the craniofacial skeleton studied by finite element method</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
                  <lpage>356</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9753816</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jafari</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shetty</surname>
                      <given-names>KS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumor</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Study of stress distribution and displacement of various
craniofacial structures following application of transverse orthopedic forces. A
three dimensional FEM study</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12607850</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kartalian</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gohl</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adamian</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Enciso</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cone-beam computerized tomography evaluation of the
maxillary dentoskeletal complex after rapid palatal expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>486</fpage>
                  <lpage>492</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889055</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kiliç</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kiki</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oktay</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Condylar asymmetry in unilateral posterior crossbite
patients</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>133</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>382</fpage>
                  <lpage>387</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18331937</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koch</surname>
                      <given-names>GG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Intraclass correlation coefficient"</article-title>
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kotz</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnson</surname>
                      <given-names>NL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Encyclopedia of Statistical Sciences</source>
                  <edition> 4th</edition>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
                  <year>1982</year>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <lpage>217</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kusnoto</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Evans</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reliability of a 3D surface laser scanner for
orthodontic applications</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>122</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>342</fpage>
                  <lpage>348</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12411877</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lachin</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of measurement reliability in clinical
trials</article-title>
                  <source>Clinical Trials</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>553</fpage>
                  <lpage>566</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16279296</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lagravère</surname>
                      <given-names>MO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Low</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flores-Mir</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chung</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carey</surname>
                      <given-names>JP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heo</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Major</surname>
                      <given-names>PW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Intraexaminer and interexaminer reliabilities of
landmark identification on digitized lateral cephalograms and formatted
3-dimensional cone-beam computerized tomography images</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>137</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>598</fpage>
                  <lpage>604</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20451778</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palomo</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Griffith</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hans</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Accuracy and reliability of cone-beam computed
tomography for measuring alveolar bone height and detecting bony dehiscences and
fenestrations</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>137</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <lpage>119</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>RMA</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oyen</surname>
                      <given-names>OJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spontaneous mandibular arch response after rapid palatal
expansion: a long-term study on Class I malocclusion</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>126</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>576</fpage>
                  <lpage>582</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520690</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>RMA</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ruellas</surname>
                      <given-names>ACO</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Long-term anteroposterior and vertical maxillary changes
in skeletal class II patients treated with slow and rapid maxillary
expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>77</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>870</fpage>
                  <lpage>874</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17685770</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lionea</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franchib</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cozzac</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Does rapid maxillary expansion induce adverse effects in
growing subjects</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <lpage>182</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22827478</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Motoyoshi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shirai</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yano</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nakanishi</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shimizu</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Permissible limit for mandibular
expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <lpage>120</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817616</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>O'Grady</surname>
                      <given-names>PW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McNamara JA</surname>
                      <given-names>Jr</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baccetti</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franchid</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A long-term evaluation of the mandibular Schwarz
appliance and the acrylic splint expander in early mixed dentition
patients</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop.</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>130</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <lpage>213</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16905065</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Odenrick</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karlander</surname>
                      <given-names>EL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pierce</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kretschmar</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Surface resorption following two forms of rapid
maxillary expansion</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <lpage>270</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1915614</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>NL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silveira</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kusnoto</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viana</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Three-dimensional assessment of morphologic changes of
the maxilla: a comparison of 2 kinds of palatal expanders</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>126</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <lpage>362</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15356500</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ölmez</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akin</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karaçay</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Multitomographic evaluation of the dental effects of two
different rapid palatal expansion appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
                  <lpage>385</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17702798</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petrén</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bondemark</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Correction of unilateral posterior crossbite in the
mixed dentition: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop.</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>133</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>790.e7</fpage>
                  <lpage>790.13</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18538237</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Phatouros</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goonewardene</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Morphologic changes of the palate after rapid maxillary
expansion: a 3-dimensional computed tomography evaluation</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>134</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <lpage>124</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18617111</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tai</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hotokezaka</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tai</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miyajima</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kai</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishima</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Preliminary cone-beam computed tomography study
evaluating dental and skeletal changes after treatment with a mandibular Schwarz
appliance</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop.</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>262.e1</fpage>
                  <lpage>262.11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20816294</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Velázquez</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benito</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bravo</surname>
                      <given-names>LA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rapid maxillary expansion: a study of the long-term
effects</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofac Orthop</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>109</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <lpage>367</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wertz</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Skeletal and dental changes accompanying rapid
midpalatal suture opening</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1970</year>
                  <volume>58</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <lpage>66</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5269181</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>RWK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alkhal</surname>
                      <given-names>HA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rabie</surname>
                      <given-names>ABM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Use of cervical vertebral maturation to determine
skeletal age</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>136</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>484</fpage>
                  <lpage>484.e1-6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19815140</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
