<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:45:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6713051" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6713051</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05</datestamp>
        <setSpec>abcd</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cir Dig</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq Bras Cir Dig</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abcd</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cirurgia Digestiva : ABCD</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0102-6720</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2317-6326</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Colégio Brasileiro de Cirurgia Digestiva</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6713051</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6713051</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6713051</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31460597</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0102-672020190001e1437</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">00306</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>ORAL HEALTH PROMOTION IN PATIENTS WITH MORBID OBESITY AFTER
GASTROPLASTY: A RANDOMIZED CLINICAL TRIAL</article-title>
                <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
                  <trans-title>PROMOÇÃO DE SAÚDE BUCAL EM PACIENTES COM OBESIDADE MÓRBIDA APÓS
GASTROPLASTIA: ENSAIO CLÍNICO RANDOMIZADO</trans-title>
                </trans-title-group>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1615-4480</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>PORCELLI</surname>
                    <given-names>Ilma Carla de Souza</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1945-5438</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>CORSI</surname>
                    <given-names>Nathalia Maciel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1112-3156</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>FRACASSO</surname>
                    <given-names>Marina de Lourdes Calvo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8396-6016</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>PASCOTTO</surname>
                    <given-names>Renata Corrêa</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0222-8821</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>CARDELLI</surname>
                    <given-names>Alexandrina Aparecida Maciel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4631-4606</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>POLI-FREDERICO</surname>
                    <given-names>Regina Célia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5880-6427</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>NASSER</surname>
                    <given-names>Daoud</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0508-6240</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>MACIEL</surname>
                    <given-names>Sandra Mara</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Postgraduate Program in Integrated Dentistry, State University of
Maringá (UEM), Maringá, PR; </aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Postgraduate Program in Communication, State University of Londrina
(UEL), Londrina, PR; </aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Program of Graduate Nursing, State University of Londrina (UEL),
Londrina, PR; </aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Dentistry Program, University of Northern Paraná
(UNOPAR), Londrina, PR, Brazil.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1"><label>Correspondence: </label> Sandra Mara Maciel E-mail:
<email>sandramaciel53@gmail.com</email>;
<email>ilmacarlaics@gmail.com</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2">
                  <p><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> none: há</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>32</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <elocation-id>e1437</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>28</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>15</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>ABSTRACT</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Background:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>The bariatric surgery may have negative repercussions on oral conditions.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Aim:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>To evaluate the impact of oral health educational/preventive program
developed with patients submitted to gastroplasties. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Method:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>The sample consisted of 109 patients randomly allocated to two groups:
intervention group (IG), where they participated in the oral health
promotion program that include multiple educational-preventive approaches;
control group (CG), where they received usual care from the bariatric clinic
staff, without participation in the program. The oral conditions
investigated in the pre-operative and postoperative periods of one month
(1M) and six months (6M) were: dental caries, periodontal disease, tooth
wear, dental plaque and salivary flow. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Results:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>After bariatric surgery, patients in IG presented: fewer changes in enamel
(6M: p=0.004), dentin (6M: p=0.005) and gingival bleeding (6M: p&lt;0.0001),
reduction in plaque index (1M, 6M: p&lt;0.0001) and increased salivary flow
(6M: p=0.039), when compared with CG. Incipient tooth wear was recorded in
both groups (6M: p=0.713). </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Conclusion:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>There was a positive impact of the implemented program in the prevention of
the main oral health problems in patients who underwent gastroplasties,
contributing to their quality of life.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <title>RESUMO</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Racional:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>A cirurgia bariátrica pode repercutir negativamente nas condições bucais.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Objetivo:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>Avaliar o impacto de um programa educativo/preventivo em saúde bucal
desenvolvido em pacientes submetidos à gastroplastia. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Método:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>A amostra foi constituída por 109 pacientes aleatoriamente alocados em dois
grupos: grupo de intervenção (GI), onde participaram do programa de promoção
de saúde bucal com abordagens educativo-preventivas; grupo controle (GC),
onde receberam cuidado da equipe da clínica, sem participação no programa.
As condições bucais investigadas nos períodos pré e pós-operatório de um mês
(1M) e seis meses (6M) foram: cárie dentária, doença periodontal, desgaste
dentário, placa dentária e fluxo salivar. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Resultados:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>Após a gastroplastia, pacientes do GI apresentaram: menor alteração em
esmalte (6M: p=0,004), dentina (6M: p=0,005) e sangramento gengival (6M:
p&lt;0,0001); redução no índice de placa (1M, 6M: p&lt;0,0001) e aumento do
fluxo salivar (6M: p=0,039), quando comparados aos do GC. Desgaste dentário
incipiente foi registrado em ambos os grupos (6M: p=0,713). </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>
                    <italic>Conclusão:</italic>
                  </title>
                  <p>Houve impacto positivo do programa implementado na prevenção dos principais
problemas de saúde bucal em pacientes submetidos à gastroplastia,
contribuindo para sua qualidade de vida.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>HEADINGS:</title>
                <kwd>Oral health</kwd>
                <kwd>Health promotion</kwd>
                <kwd>Health education</kwd>
                <kwd>Bariatric surgery</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="pt">
                <title>DESCRITORES:</title>
                <kwd>Saúde bucal</kwd>
                <kwd>Promoção da saúde</kwd>
                <kwd>Educação em saúde</kwd>
                <kwd>Cirurgia bariátrica</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="2"/>
                <table-count count="6"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="30"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>In recent decades, obesity (body mass index BMI=30 kg/m²) rates have dramatically
increased worldwide, in such a way that the World Health Organization has classified
this trend as a real obesity “epidemic”<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. Substantial evidence exists demonstrating that obesity is associated with
and represent risk factor for a number of chronic diseases across the life
cycle<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. Morbid obesity (BMI=40kg/m²) entails far more serious health consequences
for patients and creates additional challenges for healthcare providers<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Patients with morbid obesity are at increased risk of mortality compared to
non-obese, which explains the significant increase in the indication of bariatric
surgeries<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. According to the Brazilian Bariatric and Metabolic Surgery Society, 105.642
surgeries were performed in the private sector in 2017, an increase of 5.6% in
relation to 2016. In the same period, the increase was 13.5% in the public
sector<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref>. These numbers set the country in second place in the world ranking, behind
only the United States<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p> Surgery for the treatment of morbid obesity results in greater improvement in weight
loss outcomes and reflects positively on treatment or control of comorbidities that
are usually associated with it, such as diabetes, sleep apnea, arterial
hypertension, dyslipidemia, coronary diseases, cancer and osteoarthritis, among
others<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. Moreover, there is a significant improvement in self-esteem in patients who
have undergone gastroplasty<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. Nevertheless, there are negative consequences of it, such as nutritional
deficiencies<sub>,</sub> the “dumping” syndrome (nausea, vomiting, redness,
epigastric pain, hypoglycemia symptoms by the ingestion of simple carbohydrates),
and eating disorders, such as anorexia, bulimia and compulsive eating, situations
that have a direct influence on the oral cavity<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p> The literature has correlated gastroplasty with various oral problems, such as
periodontal disease<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> increase in dental caries<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>, hyposalivation, perimolysis, aphtha, dentin sensitivity, halitosis and
alveolar bone loss as a consequence of osteoporosis<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p> Scarce longitudinal studies in the medical and dental literature have related the
impact of the complications of bariatric surgery on oral health<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>, justifying new researches that may bring to light relevant data for
promoting the oral health of these patients. Furthermore, the literature lacks
studies on the effect of specific strategies, such as the elaboration of care
protocols with educational-preventive guidelines used to prevent the most frequent
oral problems in patients that have undergone gastroplasty.</p>
              <p> Considering that the determinants of oral diseases are known - which are common risk
factors for other chronic diseases - such as diet, lack of hygiene, smoking, alcohol
consumption, risk behaviors causing injuries and stress<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>, oral health should be integrated into the strategies of general health
promotion, thereby providing gains in the quality of life and well-being of
gastroplasty patients.</p>
              <p> In this context, this study was developed with the purpose of elaborating,
implementing and evaluating a health promotion strategy to improve the oral health
conditions of patients who had undergone gastroplasty.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>METHOD</title>
              <p>This study was a randomized, controlled clinical trial following a parallel design.
It was registered in the Brazilian Clinical Trial Register (“Registro Brasileiro de
Ensaios Clínicos” - <italic>ReBEC) under Number: RBR-2KCH38,</italic> after having
received approval by the Research Ethics Committee Process number 1.113.842.</p>
              <p>The study population comprised obese individuals of both genders, who had been
referred for having bariatric surgery performed between the months of February and
July 2016, in three Morbid Obesity Surgery Centers, two located in Maringá, PR, and
one in Campo Mourão, PR, both municipalities of southern Brazil. For surgical
indication, all of them met one of the following conditions: having a BMI greater
than 40 kg/m², above 35 kg/m² with comorbidities, or between 30 and 35 kg/m², in the
presence of comorbidities classified as “severe” by the specialist phyisician<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref>. Patients attend theses centers approximately two weeks prior to their
surgery for a medical evaluation, at which time they were recruited to participate
in the research.</p>
              <p>A total of 160 patients had scheduled bariatric surgery for the period defined in the
study and were evaluated for eligibility to participate in the research. In addition
to having the surgery conducted in the established period, inclusion criteria were
age between 16-60 years, signing of the informed consent form and availability to
attend the consultations performed throughout the study. The main exclusion criteria
were presence of edentulism, difficulties in seeing and hearing, illiteracy and
physical and/or mental limitations.</p>
              <p>Patients who fulfilled the inclusion criteria and agreed to participate in the
research comprised the study sample (n=109), characterized as being of convenience.
By means of the opening of sealed opaque envelopes that contained inside the
acronyms IG and CG, provided by two trained nurses before the oral health
evaluations, the participants were randomly allocated to the intervention group
(IG), where they participated in an oral health promotion program (n=55), or to the
control group (CG), where they received the usual care from the bariatric clinic
staff, without participation in the program (n=54).</p>
              <p>The assessment of the oral health conditions was carried out by a single research
author (blinded) in the preoperative (baseline) and postoperative period of one
month (1M) and six months (6M) after bariatric surgery. Clinical examinations were
performed with both the examiner and person being examined seated, under
light-focused illumination, with the use of an air syringe, a flat oral mirror,
World Health Organization Probe (CPI probe)<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> and gauze. The records were taken by a single annotator on individualized
form.</p>
              <p>The oral conditions evaluated and respective indices used were: dental caries
(<italic>International Caries Detection and Assessment System</italic>)<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>, periodontal disease (<italic>Community Periodontal Index</italic>)<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref>, tooth wear (<italic>Tooth Wear Index</italic>) adapted by Sales-Peres et
al.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>, dental plaque (<italic>O’Leary’s Plaque Score Index)</italic>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> and salivary flow<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>By means of anthropometric measurements (weight and height), the body mass index
(BMI) was calculated at baseline and 6M after bariatric surgery, and the patients
were classified, observing the cut-off points recommended by the World Health
Organization<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref>: underweight (BMI&lt;18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), normal weight (18.5=BMI&lt;25
kg/m<sup>2</sup>), pre-obese (25=BMI&lt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), obese (BMI=30
kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and morbidly obese (BMI=40 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). The surgical
technique used in gastroplasty <italic>(Roux-en-Y gastric bypass -</italic> BGRY
<italic>or gastric sleeve</italic>) was also recorded in the individualized
form.</p>
              <p>The sociodemographic information was obtained through personal interviews with
participants, conducted at baseline, using a structured questionnaire that comprised
the following variables: gender, age, marital status, education level, occupational
condition and economic class (A1, A2, B1, B2, C1, C2, D and E), which were based on
the Brazil Economic Classification criterion<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>. For statistical purposes, classes were grouped into the following
categories: “upper” (A1, A2 and B1), “middle” (B2) and “lower” (C1, C2). No patient
was classified in classes D or E.</p>
              <p>After the oral evaluation, in order to stimulate participation in the research, a
preventive kit from Curaprox - Swiss Dental (toothbrush CS 5460, Prime Plus
interdental brush and Enzycal dentifrice), was distributed to all members of the IG
and CG, in the preoperative consultation.</p>
              <p>The educative-preventive interventions were performed by three other previously
trained research authors. According to the protocol established in the oral health
promotion program, at the preoperative consultation, they distributed to the
participants of the IG a printed leaflet containing basic care guidelines for oral
health maintenance, which were explained in detail and in an individualized way.</p>
              <p>In the postoperative period, the educational-preventive interventions continued,
directed only towards patients in IG. Individualized educational actions were
developed during the consultations for the bariatric surgery revision, scheduled
after one and three months. In addition, guidelines on oral health care were
reinforced on a monthly basis by telephone contacts until the six months of
follow-up were completed<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>. The telephone script was drawn by the research team. It contained
clarification of doubts, questions about difficulties encountered and motivation to
carry out the self-care on oral health proposed in the educational approach.</p>
              <p>To ensure that the educational actions, and the preventive practices were up to date
and correct, they were based on current scientific evidence<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>. For the prevention of dental caries, periodontal diseases and tooth
erosion, the authors tried to pass simple and clear messages to the patients about
the following topics: ingestion of a healthy, balanced diet (reduction in the
quantity and frequency of foods and beverages with added sugar, avoid eating at
night); adequate oral hygiene to remove bacterial plaque (brushing all the tooth
surfaces and gingival margin carefully, with gentle movements, at least twice a day,
with one of these times being before going to sleep; use a small amount of tooth
paste, opt for fluoridated tooth paste; choose a tooth brush with a small head and
medium bristles, which must be changed every three months; use dental floss to clean
the interdental spaces; stimulate salivary flow to avoid dry mouth (increase water
ingestion by taking a bottle with you and drinking small sips; increase the
consumption of foods rich in fiber; chew gum without sugar, but only two month after
surgery; if necessary, make use of artificial saliva; to avoid halitosis or coated
tongue, brush the tongue or use a tongue scraper); take care to avoid tooth wear
(diminish consumption of acidic foods, such as citrus fruit, vinegar and soft drinks
(sodas); drink soft drinks or fruit juices through a straw, to minimize contact with
the teeth; in case of ingesting soft drinks, never brush right afterwards, but
perform mouth rinsing with water; never brush the teeth after episodes of vomiting
or reflux, if you are not at home, perform mouth rinsing with water or chew gum
without sugar; if you are at home: perform mouth rinsing with sodium bicarbonate
(one teaspoon in half a glass of water, to alkalinize the oral medium, and wait for
half an hour before brushing your teeth).</p>
              <p>The professional preventive actions included supervised oral hygiene for plaque
control, with the purpose of preventing caries and periodontal disease, which was
performed in the post-operative periods of one (1M) and three months (3M) and
topical varnish application with 5% fluoride Clinpro White Varnish (3M ESPE) on the
teeth (postoperative of 1M). Both actions were realized at the morbid obesity
surgery centers. It is worth mentioning that, at the 3M postoperative visit, a new
preventive kit from Curaprox was distributed only to GI participants.</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Data were processed and analyzed by the Statistical Package for Social Science
(SPSS), version 20.0 software was used. By univariate analysis, the possible
associations between the study variables were verified. For comparisons between
CG and IG the Mann-Whitney, Chi-square and Exact Fisher tests were used. The
significance level was set at 5%. The diagnostic criteria used in the dental
caries evaluation were recoded according to the localization of the lesions
into: without caries (ICDAS=0), caries in enamel (ICDAS=1 and =3); and caries in
dentin (ICDAS=4 and =6). The author who performed the statistical procedures was
blinded during the analysis. Only after data collection was complete one of the
researcher broke the randomization code to input the group allocation within the
pre-existing data set.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Of the total number of bariatric patients who began the research (n=109), 78%
underwent the third evaluation in the postoperative period of six months (n=85).
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> shows the number of participants
in each stage of the research, and the procedures performed in each stage.</p>
              <p>
                <fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>FIGURE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Flow chart of the trial (CONSORT statement) </title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="0102-6720-abcd-32-02-e1437-gf1"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
              <p>At the time of baseline assessment, the mean age of the participants in the
intervention group (IG) was 36.5±10.9 and in the control group (CG), 33.4±9.5 years.
In <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, it may be observed that the
groups IG and CG were homogeneous relative to demographic and socioeconomic
characteristics and type of surgery of the participants (p&gt;0.05). In both groups,
the authors noted a higher proportion of females, who had partners, with high
educational level, remunerated occupation and who underwent the surgical bypass
technique. In addition, similar proportions of participants in the three social
classes were observed.</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Distribution of bariatric patients according to sociodemographic
variables and type of surgery performed (n=109)</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="3"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Indicators</td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Groups </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">p </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n (%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n (%)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (33.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (23.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (66.7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (76.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068**</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 17 to 27 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (29.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (21.8)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 28 to 34 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (37.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (20.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35 to 44 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (18.5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (30.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45 years or older</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (14.8)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (27.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.426</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> With partner</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (61.1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (69.1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Without partner</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (38.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (30.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110**</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5 to 8 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (16.7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9 to 11 years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (37.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (34.5)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 12 years or more</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (46.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (58.2)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupational condition</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.818*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Remunerated</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (79.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (76.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Not remunerated</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (20.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (23.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Economic class</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665**</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Upper</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (25.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (32.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (35.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (36.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Lower</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (39.6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (32.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of surgery</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665*</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleeve</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (24.1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (29.1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bypass</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (75.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (70.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN1">
                      <p>*Fisher’s Exact test; **Chi square test; p&lt;0.05</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>In the pre-operative period, the authors verified a lower bacterial plaque index
(p=0.028) and greater salivary flow for the CG (p=0.004), in comparison with the
means observed in the IG. In the postoperative period of one month, the authors were
already able to perceive a lower bacterial plaque index for IG
(p&lt;0<bold>.</bold>0001), however, in relation to salivary flow, there was no
significant difference between the groups. In the postoperative period of 6M, IG
recorded a lower plaque index (p&lt;0.0001) and higher salivary flow rate (p=0.039)
than CG (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Mean and standard deviation of plaque index and salivary flow,
according to groups in pre-operative and post-operative periods of 1 and
6 months</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="3"/>
                      <col span="3"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Groups</td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Plaque Index </td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Salivary flow </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 month</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 month</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.07 (16.40)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.40 (32.36)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.55 (31.43)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (0.68)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.65)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 (0.64)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.93 (28.57)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.70 (20.22)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.43 (15.64)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.51)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.61)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 (0.70)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.413</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN2">
                      <p>*Mann Whitney - test; p&lt;0.05</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>In the comparison between CG and IG groups relative to periodontal conditions in the
preoperative period, there was no significant difference for all the criteria of the
community periodontal index (CPI). However, in the postoperative period of six
months, there was statistical difference between the groups for gingival bleeding
(p&lt;0.0001). Better gingival conditions were observed in the bariatric patients in
IG. As regards caries prevalence, according to the ICDAS criteria, in the
preoperative period no statistical difference was found between the groups. Whereas,
after six months, significant difference was found with regard to both changes in
enamel (p=0.004), and in dentin (p=0.005). There was lower incidence of changes in
IG, compared with CG (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
              <p>
                <table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Mean and standard deviation of CPI, ICDAS and DWI indices, according
to groups in the pre-operative and post-operative periods of six
months</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col span="1"/>
                      <col span="3"/>
                      <col span="3"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Criteria</td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Pre-operative </td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Pos-operative 6 months </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPI INDEX</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Healthy </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 (3.07) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.05 (3.64) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126 </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46 (3.85) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76 (4.33) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023 </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bleeding </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 (2.42)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24 (3.11)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11 (3.68)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 (1.31)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Calculus </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 (0.48) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (0.67) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107 </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (1.30) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (0.52) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060 </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pocket 4-5 </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.60)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (1.50)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.689</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 (1.26)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.93)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.680</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pocket 6/+</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.19) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.13) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.549 </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (0.23) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 (1.07)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICDAS INDEX</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Without change </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.98 (4.73)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.13 (4.15)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.72 (11.11)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.42 (11.99)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.642</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Change in enamel </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (1.61)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (2.34)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.660</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 (2.24)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (1.13)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Change in dentin </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.50) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (0.67) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.412 </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (1.42) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 (0.54) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005 </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DWI INDEX</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.37 (6.33)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.29 (6.26) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.57 (9.83)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.09 (9.98)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Incipient</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.48 (4.42)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.29 (4.84)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00 (5.56)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.69 (5.71)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.713</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (0.40)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (1.11)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (1.41) </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.71)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="TFN3">
                      <p>*Mann-Whitney test p&lt;0.05</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
              <p>When comparing CG and IG groups in the preoperative period with respect to the Dental
Wear Index, the authors could observe a higher mean value for CG relative to the
criterion normal (p=0,003) and for IG, relative to the criterion incipient
(p=0.028). In the postoperative period of six months, there was no significant
difference between groups CG and IG, for all the criteria evaluated. No severe wear
was diagnosed in both groups (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
              <p> It is worth mentioning that there was a considerable reduction in the body mass
index of patients after bariatric surgery, only one patient in group IG remained in
obesity III and a large portion of the patients migrated to the preobese and obesity
I groups. At six months after surgery, 10% of the patients in the CG and 10.6% in IG
had attained a normal BMI.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p> As far as we know, this is the first randomized clinical trial to describe the
impact of an oral health promotion program developed with bariatric patients. The
health promotion program implemented was shown to be effective in the prevention of
the main oral health problems. Six months after the bariatric surgery, lower indices
of plaque, gingival bleeding and dental caries, in addition to an increase in
salivary flow, with reduction in the condition of xerostomia, were observed in the
patients of IG, when compared with those in CG.</p>
              <p> Repeated motivational meetings and educational actions have been described in the
literature, resulting in more significant improvements in the oral health knowledge
and behaviors of patients, when compared to an isolated oral health guidance<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>. Linked with the individual educational activities developed during the
medical review queries, the reinforcement of educational messages at regular
intervals, by means of telephone contacts, described and experienced in this study
by IG bariatric patients, with nutritional guidance related to oral health, as well
as oral hygiene care<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>, was shown to be effective for promoting the oral health of these patients
compared to those in CG. According to McGrice and Don Paul<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>, digital communication methods, such as social media, telephone
consultations, and online educational programs, should be used to increase
engagement with bariatric patients and to minimize barriers such as time, distance,
and cost.</p>
              <p> In the present study, IG participants, who have undergone various approaches to
guidance and motivation for bacterial plaque control, as well as supervised tooth
brushing, showed a significant reduction in the plaque index. It is worth mentioning
that periodic visits to the dental office were also recommended to them for plaque
control. In contrast, those in CG, who received the usual care from the bariatric
clinic staff, presented greater plaque accumulation in the postoperative period of
one and six months, which is in accordance with the report of Hague and Baechle<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>, who emphasized the high and generalized amount of bacterial plaque observed
in patients after being submitted to gastroplasty. This condition occurs, probably
due to the fact that, traditionally, the oral health care has been neglected in
bariatric surgeries settings.</p>
              <p> Regarding the periodontal conditions, in the literature there are reports of high
prevalence of periodontal disease in the morbidly obese that worsens in the first
six months after surgery<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> and that there is an increase in gingival bleeding, with a peak at six
months after gastroplasty<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>. Indeed, in this study, the main change relative to periodontal health
observed between the groups was gingival bleeding. It could be seen that the
educational actions for plaque control also exerted positive influence on the
periodontal status of the IG patients. While the CG members presented a rise in
gingival bleeding after the elapse of six months post-surgery, the participants in
the oral health promotion program (IG), presented significant reduction in gingival
bleeding (p&lt;0.0001). It is worth noting that, unlike another survey<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>, where all teeth were evaluated, we chose to use the CPI index to optimize
the evaluation time.</p>
              <p> It is known that bariatric patients experience great difficulty in drinking water
due to stomach reduction, which tended to normalize after 12 months<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>. Inadequate water intake is of concern to both the medical field, since it
is cause of dehydration, being aggravated by episodes of vomiting and diarrhea, as
for dental field, considering that it contributes to dry mouth<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. Hyposalivation is common in patients submitted to gastroplasty in the first
six months after surgery<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>. Previous study have shown that there is an increase in periodontal disease
and dental caries when the amount and/ or quality of saliva is reduced, as well as
in masticatory disorders<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p> With the purpose of encouraging and assisting the water intake and improve salivary
flow, IG patients received guidance relative to increasing water consumption
throughout the day. The importance of taking a bottle of water with them and
remembering of drinking it in small sips was constantly enhanced. This group was
also advised to use chewing gum without sugar to stimulate salivation after two
month of surgery. Thus, although the GI patients presented lower salivary flow than
those of CG at the baseline assessment, probably due to the use of medicament with
xerostomic effects, this condition was reversed in the postoperative period of six
months. There was a significant increase in the mean value of salivary flow among
the members of the GI when compared to that occurred among CG members. The increase
in salivary flow in IG was of 58.8%.</p>
              <p> Previous publications have shown a tendency to increase dental caries over time
after bariatric surgery<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. The postoperative dietary recommendations for bariatric patients may be
associated with this increase as they include eating food in smaller quantities,
dividing food intake into 4-6 meals throughout the day chewing them slowly, and
ending meals when feeling “comfortably full”<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>. The higher frequency and prolonged meal times may be related to an increase
risk of dental caries, especially when taking into account that, in many instances,
sweetened items are ingested by the choice of the patients<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>. Intake of dietary sugars is the most important risk factor for dental
caries<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref>. This eating behavior, concomitant with poor oral hygiene may result in
impairment of oral health, with the development of carious lesions<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. In this investigation, after six months, the incidence of caries was
significantly lower in IG when compared with CG, affecting both enamel (p=0.004),
and dentin (p=0.005). This positive finding was probably due to the reinforcing
guidance adopted concerning a diet with less added sugar. Dietary advice in the
dental practice is important for oral and general health preventive care<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>. Advice to eat less sugar and to reduce the frequency with which sugar foods
and drinks are consumed, aiming toward a maximum of one per day, should help bring
sugar intake in line with current guidelines<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>. The WHO recommends a reduced intake of free sugars for both children and
adults, which should not exceed 10% of total calorie intake<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p> Another preventive measure that may have contributed to a lower incidence of caries
in GI was the use of fluoridated varnish. A systematic review showed that two
applications per year of fluoridated varnish significantly reduced caries lesions in
permanent teeth<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>. In the present research, it can be assumed that the topical applications of
fluoridated varnish performed in the 1<sup>st</sup> month after surgery also had
good results for IG by preventing caries.</p>
              <p> The Roux-en-Y gastric bypass is being performed in 75% of Brazilian
gastroplasties<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref>, justifying the fact that most of the patients studied underwent this type
of surgery. The success of the technique could be verified by the weight loss
recorded and the change in obesity classification among bariatric patients of the IG
and CG, six months after surgery.</p>
              <p> Some limitations may be pointed out in the present study, such as: not all the
patients returned to the clinics up to the conclusion of the research (postoperative
period of six months), reducing the sample number in the final evaluation; the
period of six months was relatively short for evaluating the occurrence of tooth
erosion. Further researches are necessary, with longer follow-up periods, to assess
the greater benefits that an oral health promotion program could have over time.</p>
              <p> The care protocol used in this study showed that it was possible to prevent the
negative repercussions of bariatric surgery on oral health. When dentists are
included in the multidisciplinary teams that care for patients submitted to
bariatric surgery they can - through their relevant knowledge - contribute to the
well-being of these patients.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>The oral health promotion program had a positive impact on the prevention of dental
caries, periodontal disease, xerostomia and plaque accumulation in bariatric
patients. These patients need to be included in an oral health promotion program
with pre- and postoperative dental monitoring in order to prevent the development of
oral diseases, which would contribute to improvement in their quality of life.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1">
                <p><bold>Financial source:</bold> This study was financed in part by the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal
de Nível Superior - Brasil (CAPES) - Finance Code 001</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Associação Brasileira de Empresas de Pesquisa (ABEP)</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Critério Brasil 2015 e Atualização da Distribuição de Classes para
2016</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.abep.org/criterio-brasil">http://www.abep.org/criterio-brasil</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho A da</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosa R dos</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cirurgias bariátricas realizadas pelo Sistema Único de Saúde em
residentes da Região Metropolitana de Porto Alegre, Rio Grande do Sul,
2010-2016*</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol e Serviços Saúde</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <elocation-id>e2017010</elocation-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>D&amp;apos;Aniello</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Troisi</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>D&amp;apos;Amico</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sangermano</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Massa</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moccaldo</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Emerging Pathomechanisms Involved in Obesity</article-title>
                  <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>119</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25199037</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dantas</surname>
                      <given-names>RO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alves</surname>
                      <given-names>LMT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cassiani R de</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>CM dos</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of liquid ingestion after bariatric
surgery</article-title>
                  <source>Arq Gastroentero</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>De S Porcelli</surname>
                      <given-names>IC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roma</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nunes</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maciel</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pascotto</surname>
                      <given-names>RC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of Bariatric Surgery on the Oral Health of
Patients</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Dent Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.16966/2378-7090.181">http://dx.doi.
org/10.16966/2378-7090.181</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>England</surname>
                      <given-names>PH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Delivering better oral health: an evidence-based toolkit for
prevention</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gov.uk/search?q=Delivering+better+oral+health%3A+an+evidence-based+toolkit+for+prevention+and+Third+edition&amp;show_organisations_filter=true">www.gov.uk/search?q=Delivering+better+oral+health%3A+an+evidence-based+toolkit+for+prevention+and+Third+edition&amp;show_organisations_filter=true</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flink</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bergdahl</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tegelberg</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosenblad</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lagerlöf</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence of hyposalivation in relation to general health, body
mass index and remaining teeth in different age groups of
adults</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>523</fpage>
                  <lpage>531</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18422708</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garcia</surname>
                      <given-names>RI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kleinman</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holt</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Battrell</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Casamassimo</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grover</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Healthy Futures Engaging the oral health community in childhood
obesity prevention - Conference summary and recommendations</article-title>
                  <source>J Public Health Dent</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>77</volume>
                  <fpage>S136</fpage>
                  <lpage>S140</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28621818</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hague</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baechle</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Advanced caries in a patient with a history of bariatric
surgery</article-title>
                  <source>Am Dent Hyg Assoc</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harrison</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benton</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Everson-Stewart</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weinstein</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of motivational interviewing on rates of early childhood
caries: a randomized trial</article-title>
                  <source>Pediatr Dent</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18041508</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ismail</surname>
                      <given-names>AI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sohn</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tellez</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amaya</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sen</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hasson</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The International Caries Detection and Assessment System (ICDAS)
an integrated system for measuring dental caries</article-title>
                  <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <lpage>178</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17518963</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kay</surname>
                      <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vascott</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hocking</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nield</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Motivational interviewing in general dental practice A review of
the evidence</article-title>
                  <source>BDJ</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>221</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>785</fpage>
                  <lpage>791</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27982007</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>SY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holt</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tinanoff</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Nutrition Education for Oral Health Professionals A Must, Yet
Still Neglected</article-title>
                  <source>J Dent Educ</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049671</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kolotkin</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davidson</surname>
                      <given-names>LE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crosby</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hunt</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adams</surname>
                      <given-names>TD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>12-year trajectory of health-related quality of life in gastric
bypass patients versus comparison groups</article-title>
                  <source>Surg Obes Relat Dis</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1359</fpage>
                  <lpage>1365</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29884519</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mancini</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bariatric surgery - An update for the
endocrinologist</article-title>
                  <source>Arq Bras Endocrinol Metabol</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>58</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>875</fpage>
                  <lpage>888</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25627042</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marsicano</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grec PG de</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Belarmino</surname>
                      <given-names>LB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ceneviva</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peres SH de</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Interfaces between bariatric surgery and oral health: a
longitudinal survey</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Cir Bras</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <lpage>83</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22030820</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McGrice</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Don Paul</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Interventions to improve long-term weight loss in patients
following bariatric surgery challenges and solutions</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <lpage>274</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26150731</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moura-Grec</surname>
                      <given-names>PG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yamashita</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marsicano</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ceneviva</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Souza Leite</surname>
                      <given-names>CV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Brito</surname>
                      <given-names>GB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of bariatric surgery on oral health conditions: 6-months
cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>Int Dent J</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>64</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <lpage>149</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24410073</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moynihan</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sugars and Dental Caries Evidence for Setting a Recommended
Threshold for Intake</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Nutr</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <lpage>156</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26773022</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>O&amp;apos;Leary</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Drake</surname>
                      <given-names>RB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naylor</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Plaque Control Record</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>1972</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <lpage>38</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4500182</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pataro</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>FO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortelli</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortelli</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dupim Souza</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nogueira Guimarães Abreu</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of Obesity and Bariatric Surgery on the Periodontal
Condition</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <lpage>266</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21721989</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sales-Peres</surname>
                      <given-names>SHC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maia-Júnior</surname>
                      <given-names>AF*</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bastos JRM</surname>
                      <given-names>S-PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>PO050 Estudo de prevalência e de severidade de facetas de
desgaste dentário, em adultos jovens</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Oral Res</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>37</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheiham</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Oral health, general health and quality of life</article-title>
                  <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>644</fpage>
                  <lpage>644</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16211151</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sherf Dagan</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldenshluger</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Globus</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schweiger</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kessler</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kowen Sandbank</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Nutritional Recommendations for Adult Bariatric Surgery Patients
Clinical Practice</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Nutr</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>382</fpage>
                  <lpage>394</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28298280</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Sociedade Brasileira de Cirurgia Bariátrica e Metabólica</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Número de cirurgias bariátricas no Brasil aumenta 46,7%</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sbcbm.org.br/numero-de-cirurgias-bariatricas-no-brasil-aumenta-467">https://www.sbcbm.org.br/numero-de-cirurgias-bariatricas-no-brasil-aumenta-467</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sturm</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hattori</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Morbid obesity rates continue to rise rapidly in the United
States</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Obes</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>889</fpage>
                  <lpage>891</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tremblay</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brisson</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gaudet</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Association between salivary pH and metabolic syndrome in women a
cross-sectional study</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <lpage>40</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22958748</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>World Health Organization</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Oral health surveys: basic methods - 5th edition</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <size units="pages">125</size>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>World Health Organization</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Nutrition for Health and Development. Guideline: Sugars intake for
adults and children</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <size units="pages">49</size>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>World Health Organization</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Obesity: preventing and managing the global epidemic: report of a WHO
consultation</source>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <size units="pages">253</size>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
