<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:50:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5349062" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5349062</identifier>
        <datestamp>2017-03-17</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jaos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de São
Paulo</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC5349062</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5349062</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">5349062</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20835573</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20835573</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-77572010000400010</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Digital subtraction radiographic analysis of the combination of
bioabsorbable membrane and bovine morphogenetic protein pool in human periodontal
infrabony defects</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>GUIMARÃES</surname>
                    <given-names>Maria do Carmo Machado</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>PASSANEZI</surname>
                    <given-names>Euloir</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>SANT’ANA</surname>
                    <given-names>Adriana Campos Passanezi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>GREGHI</surname>
                    <given-names>Sebastião Luiz Aguiar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>TABA JUNIOR</surname>
                    <given-names>Mario</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> DDS, MSc, PhD, Adjunct Professor of Periodontics, Periodontics
Division, University of Brasilia, Brasília, DF, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> DDS, MSc, PhD, Full Professor, Department of Prosthodontics, Bauru
School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> DDS, MSc, PhD, Assistant Professor, Department of Prosthodontics, Bauru
School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> DDS, MSc, PhD, Assistant Professor, Department of Oral and
Maxillofacial Surgery and Traumatology and Periodontology, Ribeirão Preto Dental
School, University of São Paulo, Ribeirão Preto, SP, Brazil.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Maria do Carmo Machado
Guimarães - Universidade de Brasília - UnB - Departamento de
Odontologia - Campus Universitário Darcy Ribeiro, Brasília - 70910-900
- DF - Brasil - Phone: +55 61 3307 2514 - e-mail:
<email>mmgcarmo@gmail.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <season>Jul-Aug</season>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Jul-Aug</season>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>18</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>379</fpage>
              <lpage>384</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>05</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2010</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>This study assessed the bone density gain and its relationship with the
periodontal clinical parameters in a case series of a regenerative therapy
procedure.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Material and Methods</title>
                  <p>Using a split-mouth study design, 10 pairs of infrabony defects from 15 patients
were treated with a pool of bovine bone morphogenetic proteins associated with
collagen membrane (test sites) or collagen membrane only (control sites). The
periodontal healing was clinically and radiographically monitored for six months.
Standardized presurgical and 6-month postoperative radiographs were digitized for
digital subtraction analysis, which showed relative bone density gain in both
groups of 0.034 ± 0.423 and 0.105 ± 0.423 in the test and control
group, respectively (p&gt;0.05).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>As regards the area size of bone density change, the influence of the therapy was
detected in 2.5 mm<sup>2</sup> in the test group and 2 mm<sup>2</sup> in the
control group (p&gt;0.05). Additionally, no correlation was observed between the
favorable clinical results and the bone density gain measured by digital
subtraction radiography (p&gt;0.05).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>The findings of this study suggest that the clinical benefit of the regenerative
therapy observed did not come with significant bone density gains. Long-term
evaluation may lead to a different conclusions.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Alveolar bone loss</kwd>
                <kwd>Regeneration</kwd>
                <kwd>Radiography</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>The São Paulo State Research Foundation
(FAPESP)</funding-source>
                  <award-id>98/13005-9</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>The improvement in the clinical parameters shown by the reduction in probing depth,
clinical attachment gain and absence of bleeding on probing must not necessarily be
interpreted as regeneration. The nature of neoformed tissue and the occurrence of
regeneration can only be defined by means of microscopic analysis<sup><xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>Conventional radiographic analysis presents limitations as regards image quality, and is
more subject to error, especially if the images were not standardized. Similarly, it
only allows alterations to be visualized when the loss attains 30% to 60% of mineral
bone content. On the other hand, the radiographic subtraction technique allows changes
in density to be quantified by comparing alterations in the image with reference
structures, and by detecting bone alterations of 5%, with over 90% of sensitivity and
specificity<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The properties of osteoconduction and integration into bone tissue<sup><xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> have enabled the use of xenogenous
grafts derived from bovine bone (BDX) in regenerative periodontal therapy<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. The material is slowly reabsorbed by osteoclastic
activity<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Results from
histological and clinical studies have demonstrated that BDX is very well tolerated, and
up to now, no allergic reactions related to the material have been reported<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. Furthermore, since its supply is
unlimited, no donor site is required.</p>
              <p>The use of bovine bone matrix in regenerative therapy is based on the homology proved by
DNA cloning of human and bovine bone morphogenetic proteins (BMPs)<sup><xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. As the BMPs concentrate the osteogenic
potential generically attributed to the matrix, in the present study a pool containing
the extract of these proteins with the largest quantities of different types of these
proteins was applied.</p>
              <p>The aim of this study was to evaluate the bone density gain by means of radiographic
subtraction, in infra-osseous defects treated with a pool of bovine BMPs associated with
reabsorbable bovine collagen membrane. Furthermore, the aim was to establish the
correlation between the change in density of the treated defects and the variation in
the probing depth and attachment level measurements. The clinical results as regards the
reduction of probing depth and improvement in attachment level have previously been
detailed<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study design and clinical procedures</title>
                <p>Fifteen patients of both genders (age range: 26 to 57 years; mean age: 36.06 years)
were selected at the Periodontics Clinic of Bauru School of Dentistry, University of
São Paulo, Brazil. The possible types of treatment, associated risks and
benefits were explained to the patients and all signed the informed consent form
agreeing to the treatment. The study was approved by the local Research ethics
Committee.</p>
                <p>The inclusion criteria were as follows: 1) good systemic health; 2) no use of drugs
such as antibiotics, corticoids, chemotherapeutic agents, or immunological modulators
that might alter the response of the oral tissue; 3) no smoking; 4) radiographic
evidence of at least one pair of interproximal infrabony defects with 2 or 3 walls
located in the same jaw (maxilla or mandible), and the same type of tooth (premolars
or molars), without involvement of the furcations; attachment level ≥ 5 mm;
tooth mobility &lt; class II.</p>
                <p>After selection, all patients underwent initial therapy, consisting of oral hygiene
instruction and scaling and root planing. After extra and intraoral asepsis of the
surgical field, full-thickness mucoperiosteal flaps were raised by means of buccal
and lingual intracrevicular incisions up to at least two adjacent teeth - one mesial
and one distal, followed by removal of the granulation tissue and bone debridement.
Defects were divided into test and control sites in a split-mouth design. The test
sites were treated with a pool of bone morphogenetic proteins (Genpro, Baumer S.A.,
Bauru, SP, Brazil ) obtained from fetal bovine bone matrix with resorbable
hydroxyapatite carrier (HA) (BMP HA in a 1:20 ratio), with the addition of
demineralized lyophilized bovine bone matrix (BM) (Mo-Gen-Ox, Baumer S.A., Bauru, SP,
Brazil) in a 1:1 ratio in sterile saline solution, which was applied in the test
sites.</p>
                <p>The control sites were treated with BM and HA (MB-HA), in a 1:1 ratio, therefore
excluding only the pool of bovine BMPs. After filling the defects with the respective
biomaterials, both the test and control defects were covered with a resorbable
membrane obtained from bovine cortical bone (Genderme, Baumer S.A.). For all
patients, 100 mg of oral doxycycline once a day during 14 days were prescribed and
they were instructed to rinse twice daily with 0.12% digluconate chlorhexidine during
6 weeks. All patients were seen for professional prophylaxis weekly during the first
6 weeks and then monthly until 6 months postoperatively. At 6 months after surgery,
new clinical measurements were taken and new standardized radiographs were
obtained.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Radiographic Procedures</title>
                <p>Periapical radiographs were taken with the aid of an acrylic device (Resapol T 208,
Outline Fiberglass, São Vicente, SP, Brazil) made by duplication of a
positioner-matrix (Dentsply Rinn, elgin, IL, USA). The device was coupled to a bite
block made of acrylic material (Duralay, Reliance Dental Mfg. Co, Worth, IL, USA) at
each site to retain reproducible projection with exposure settings of 70 KV at 8 mA
for 1.0 second. Radiographs were taken at baseline and 6 months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). The
radiographic films were developed in an automatic radiograph processing machine
(Perio-pro II, Air Technique Inc., Melville, NY, USA). The radiographic pairs were
scanned and digitized using a 35-mm slide scanner (Polaroid SprintScan, Polaroid
Corporation, Simi Lalley, CA, US) connected to a Pentium 100 Mhz PC (Intel
Corporation, Santa Clara, CA, USA). The baseline presurgical and postoperative images
were aligned by the selection of common reference points<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. The images were subtracted and analyzed using
diagnostic subtraction radiography software, IDL- Interactive Data Language v.5.0
(Research Systems, Boulder, CO, US) developed for this purpose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>). The routines of the program work on the platform of
the envi 3,5 (ITT Visual Information Solutions, Boulder, CO, USA), software solution
for processing and analyzing images that allows development.</p>
                <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Preoperative radiograph</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jaos-18-04-0379-g01"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Six-month postoperative radiograph</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jaos-18-04-0379-g02"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Subtraction radiograph showing a bone density gain on the mesial aspect of the
mandibular first molar and mandibular first premolar</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jaos-18-04-0379-g03"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Following selection of an area of interest on the images, the post-operative film was
subtracted from the presurgical film, with the software program compensating for any
geometric projection and film contrast differences between the pairs of images.
Changes between films were depicted as a darkened area for loss of alveolar bone
mass, a neutral gray for no change in alveolar bone mass, and a lightened area for an
increase in alveolar bone mass<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.
All subtracted images were subsequently uploaded into the Image Tool software (The
University of Texas, Health Science Center in San Antonio, San Antonio, TX, USA) to
calculate the average density of areas that showed changes in subtraction and to
quantify these areas. In order to determine the changes in density in the subtracted
image, this same image was set up as a reference and the value of the density of a
neutral area, ie, an area that had supposedly not changed during the study, like the
dental enamel, for example, was used as a "standard area". After obtaining this
value, the rule of three was applied to check the value of change in the area of the
defect. The quantification of the changed area provided by the Image Tool software
was converted into millimeters.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Data analysis</title>
                <p>The t test (p&lt;0.05) was applied to indicate whether the differences with regard to
the area (quantification in mm) of alteration in bone density of the test and control
sites were statistically significant as well as to verify the differences between the
means of alteration in density of the test and control sites. Pearson’s correlation
(p&lt;0.05) was applied to verify whether there was correlation between the
alteration in bone density and variation of probing depth and attachment level
measured at baseline and after 6 months.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>According to <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>, the t-test indicated that
the differences between the test and control groups with regard to quantification of the
area of change in density were not statistically significant. The t-test indicated that
there was no statistically significant difference between the test and control sites
with regard to alteration in density by the radiographic subtraction analysis.</p>
              <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Tabela 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Quantification of the areas and mean change in bone density of the test and
control sites by the t-test (p&lt;0.05)</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Test</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Control</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Difference</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>t</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>p value</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantification of the areas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">576.89 (309.106)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507.77 (352.85)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.128</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.877</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.395 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(≅25.08 mm<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(≅22.07 mm<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean change in bone density</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034 (0.423)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105 (0.423)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.071</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.839</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.415 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>ns- Non-significant differences (P&gt;0.05). SD= Standard Deviation</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The variation in probing depth and attachment level at the buccal and lingual faces,
between the periods measured at baseline and 6 months, presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>, were correlated with the change in density
(<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>), and it can be observed that the
alteration in density presented no correlation with the variation in probing depth and
attachment level at the buccal and lingual faces, in both test and control sites.</p>
              <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Tabela 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Variation in probing depth (PD) and attachment level (AL) at the buccal (B) and
lingual (L) faces of the test and control sites, between the 6 months (6m) and
baseline (bas) periods by the t-test</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Variation</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Face</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Test</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Control</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>p value</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>mean</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>sd</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>mean</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>sd</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PD 6m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.633</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.141</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.933</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.347</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.443 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.933</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.961</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.000</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.511</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.886 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AL 6m- bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.600</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.168</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.033</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.245</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.466</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.972</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.300</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.114</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.591 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>ns- Non-significant differences (P&gt;0.05)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="t03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Tabela 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Correlation of the change in density and variation in probing depth and attachment
level at the buccal (B) and lingual (L) faces of the test and control sites by the
Pearson's correlation test (p&lt;0.05), between the 6 months (6m) and baseline
(bas) periods</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Group</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Correlation</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>r</bold>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>p value</bold>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x PD (B) 6m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x PD (L) 6m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,15</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.602 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x AL (B) 6 m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x AL (L) 6m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,25</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.368 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x PD (B) 6m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,11</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.691 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x PD (L) 6m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,34</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.212 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x AL (B) 6 m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,7</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.804 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr style="background-color:#CCCCCC">
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density x AL (L) 6m-bas</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0,42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117 ns</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>ns- Non-significant differences (P&gt;0.05)</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>The extracellular matrix of mineralized tissues constitutes a rich reservoir of
morphogenetic proteins and other growth factors. The osteogenic properties of the BMPs
in this matrix have led to their evaluation as possible adjuncts in regenerative
periodontal therapy. The findings of Urist<sup><xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> (1965) and later of Reddi and Huggins<sup><xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> (1972) demonstrated that devitalized and demineralized
bone matrix is capable of inducing heterotopic osteogenesis. Special preparatory
procedures, such as eliminating cells by autolysis and extraction of matricial antigens
have enabled this matrix to be used in the induction of new bone formation<sup><xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. The osteogenic and osteoinductive properties of BMPs present within
the organic matrix induce the formation of new bone tissue.</p>
              <p>In several reports, it was found that infra-osseous defects were filled with neoformed
bone tissue during re-entry surgery performed at 6 months postoperatively<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. In some studies that treated
infra-osseous defects with absorbable barriers<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> or other regenerative
therapies<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>, surgical re-entry
was complemented by the radiographic subtraction technique to evaluate bone density
gain.</p>
              <p>With the object of defining the nature of neoformed tissue in infra-osseous defects,
Sculean, et al.<sup><xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> (1999) performed a
microscopic analysis of teeth indicated for extraction, which had been submitted to
regenerative therapy. Camargo, et al.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
(2000) and Sculean, et al.<sup><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> (2003)
found greater gain of clinical attachment and bone filling, by means of conventional
radiographic analysis, in infra-osseous defects treated with BDX and bovine collagen
membrane, when compared to defects treated only with flap surgery. Other studies also
used conventional<sup><xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> or
digitized<sup><xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> radiographic
analysis.</p>
              <p>There are few studies involving the treatment of infra-osseous defects by means of RTG
with an absorbable barrier, associated or not with other regenerative procedures, which
included radiographic subtraction analyses<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Although the digitized image offers more resources than
conventional analysis, such as the possibility of manipulating the image to adjust the
gray levels and calculating the quantification of the area of density, as is the case
with the conventional method, it consists of subjective analysis. Therefore, it depends
on the observer’s visual acuity and degree of prior knowledge, in addition to being
subject to interferences of aspects related to the lighting of the room and screen size.
Moreover, it does not allow for a precise detection of the change in density between two
images<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p>The radiographic pairs in this study were standardized by means of making individual
acrylic film-holders with bite registers for positioning the radiographic film, in order
to minimize angular alterations that could cause geometric distortions. It should be
pointed out that this standardization consisted of a complex procedure and some
geometrical adjustments were made by the computer program used for analysis. These
adjustments did not compromise the comparison of images, in such a way that all pairs
could be analyzed. Additional care was taken, such as developing by an automatic
processor (Perio Pro II), according to the manufacturer’s instructions and under the
same conditions. In the majority of cases, this set of procedures allowed for obtaining
identical images.</p>
              <p>The mean density gains detected by means of subtraction analysis were 0.034 ±
0.423, in the test sites and 0.105 ± 0.423 in the control sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>). These results were lower than those of
other studies in which subtraction analysis was used<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> to evaluate the results
of regenerative therapy. Nevertheless, the time factor must be considered, since the
alterations in the degree of bone tissue mineralization are directly related to the
alterations in the calcium and phosphate levels, which may require a considerable time
to become evident due to biomaterial incorporation and bone remodeling<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. In the present study, the evaluation
period was a time interval of 6 months, while in other studies, the periods of analysis
exceeded 6 months<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>-<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. This may at
least partly explain the lower gain in density observed in this study. Moreover, other
differences referring to the position and size of the area of interest in the radiograph
may also explain the discrepancy in the results observed in comparison with other
studies.</p>
              <p>Subtraction analysis demonstrated that the differences between tests and controls were
not statistically significant as regards change in density, and as regards
quantification in millimeters of the area of alteration (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>).</p>
              <p>In the present study, no correlation was observed between the alteration in density and
the variation in probing depth and attachment level (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>). This means that the sites that presented greater increase in
density did not correspond to the sites with higher reduction of mean probing depths and
clinical attachment gain.</p>
              <p>In the study of Christgau, et al.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>(2006), deep infraosseous defects were treated with b-TCP granules and a
bioresorbable membrane. In test defects, autologous platelet concentrate was
additionally applied. In both test and controls sites, the clinical attachment gain was
accompanied by significant gain in bone density. The radiographic alterations were
higher than those of previous studies<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, these results must be
interpreted with caution because b-TCP is radiopaque and by radiographic methods, one
does not distinguish whether it was replaced by vital bone. Other authors have reported
that the clinical attachment gain was accompanied by increase in bone density<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.
eickholz and Hausmann<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> (1998) did not
find any correlation between attachment gain and bone filling when using digital
radiographic analysis. Similarly, eickholz and Hausmann<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> (2002) found no correlation between gain in bone density
measured by subtraction and bone gain measured clinically by the distance between the
cementoenamel junction and the base of the bone defect. On the other hand, a study with
surgical re-entry<sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> demonstrated that
the bone gain, confirmed by measurements made during re-entry, was accompanied by
significant gain in bone density detected by radiographic subtraction.</p>
              <p>The absence of correlation between bone filling and gain of clinical attachment in the
present study should be evaluated with caution. It is important to emphasize that the
anatomical characteristics of the bone defect with regard to width and depth may
interfere in the gain in bone density observed by subtraction radiography. While the
mean bone density evaluates alterations in the buccolingual direction, the gain in
attachment consists of a clinical measurement in the coronal apical direction. According
to eickholz and Hausmann<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> (2002),
these different measurements may lead to discrepant results, in accordance with the type
of defect. In narrow defects, the bone filling promoted by regenerative therapy may
result in consistent gain of clinical attachment, with a small gain in bone density.
Whereas, in wide defects, greater bone filling of the lateral walls results in
consistent gain in bone density, while little or no gain in clinical attachment is
observed.</p>
              <p>Thus, the absence of correlation between the sites with clinical attachment and bone
density gain in this study must not necessarily be interpreted as absence of
regeneration. Although some clinical studies have attributed the gain in clinical
attachment to the formation of long junctional epithelium<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>, only
histological evaluation would be able to determine the type of cure in each regenerative
therapy used in this study. If on one hand, the absence of correlation between gain in
attachment and bone filling suggests the lack of complete periodontal regeneration, on
the other hand, it must be considered the possible influence of the above-mentioned
aspects, especially the type of defect, in the analysis of correlation. Nevertheless, as
no correlation was established in this study between the characteristics of the defect
observed intra-surgically and the gain in density and or the gain in clinical
attachment, we are unable to determine the influence of these characteristics on the
clinical results. Furthermore, longer periods of evaluation would allow for better
evaluation of the effects of regenerative therapy.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>Within the limitations of the present study, the following conclusions can be pointed
out: 1. By the radiographic subtraction analysis, the use of the pool of bovine BMPs in
addition to the demineralized lyophilized bovine bone matrix for the treatment of
infra-osseous defects did not provide statistically greater gain in bone density; 2. The
absence of correlation between improvement in the clinical parameters and the increase
in bone density in both groups suggests the lack of occurrence of a complete periodontal
regeneration per se. However, longer periods of analysis are required to verify the
long-term effect of the therapy; 3. Further studies correlating the characteristics of
the bone defect, gain in bone density and gain in probing attachment level would
contribute to the evaluation of regenerative therapy in intra-osseous defects.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
              <p>This study was supported by grants from The São Paulo State Research Foundation
(FAPESP) (98/13005-9).</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="r01">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aichelmann-Reidy</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heath</surname>
                      <given-names>CD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical evaluation of calcium sulfate in combination with
demineralized freeze-dried bone allograft for the treatment of human intraosseous
defects</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <lpage>347</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15088870</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r02">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berglundh</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lindhe</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Healing around implants placed in bone defects treated with Bio-Oss.
An experimental study in the dog</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <lpage>124</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9758962</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r03">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brägger</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hämmerle</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mombelli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bürgin</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lang</surname>
                      <given-names>NP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Remodelling of periodontal tissues adjacent to sites treated according
to the principles of guided tissue regeneration (GTR)</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <issue-part>Pt 1</issue-part>
                  <fpage>615</fpage>
                  <lpage>624</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1430288</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r04">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Camargo</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lekovic</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weinlaender</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nedic</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vasilic</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wolinsky</surname>
                      <given-names>LE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A controlled re-entry study on the effectiveness of bovine porous bone
mineral used in combination with a collagen membrane of porcine origin in the
treatment of intrabony defects in humans</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>889</fpage>
                  <lpage>896</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11140555</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r05">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Christgau</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bader</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Felden</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gradl</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wenzel</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schmalz</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Guided tissue regeneration in intrabony defects using an experimental
bioresorbable polydioxanon (PDS) membrane. A 24-month split-mouth
study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>710</fpage>
                  <lpage>723</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12390568</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r06">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Christgau</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bader</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schmalz</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hiller</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wenzel</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>GTR therapy of intrabony defects using 2 different bioresorbable
membranes: 12-month results</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>499</fpage>
                  <lpage>509</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9667484</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r07">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Christgau</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moder</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wagner</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Glässl</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hiller</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wenzel</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of autologous platelet concentrate on healing in intra-bony
defects following guided tissue regeneration therapy: a randomized prospective
clinical split-mouth study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>908</fpage>
                  <lpage>921</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17092242</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r08">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Christgau</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schmalz</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wenzel</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hiller</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Periodontal regeneration of intrabony defects with resorbable and
nonresorbable membranes: 30-month results</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <lpage>27</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9049793</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r09">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <article-title>Consensus report. Periodontal diseases: epidemiology and
diagnosis</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Periodontol</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <lpage>222</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9118258</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Danesh-Meyer</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>ST</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rams</surname>
                      <given-names>Te</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Digital subtraction radiographic analysis of GTR in human intrabony
defects</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
                  <lpage>449</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12449304</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Döri</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huszár</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nikolidakis</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arweiler</surname>
                      <given-names>NB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gera</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sculean</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of platelet-rich plasma on the healing of intrabony defects
treated with an anorganic bovine bone mineral and expanded polytetrafluoroethylene
membranes</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>983</fpage>
                  <lpage>990</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17539709</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eickholz</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hausmann</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evidence for healing of interproximal intrabony defects after
conventional and regenerative therapy: digital radiography and clinical
measurements</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontal Res</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <lpage>165</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9651877</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eickholz</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hausmann</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evidence for healing of periodontal defects 5 years after conventional
and regenerative therapy: digital subtraction and bone level
measurements</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>922</fpage>
                  <lpage>928</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12445224</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eickholz</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krigar</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reitmeir</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rawlinson</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Stability of clinical and radiographic results after guided tissue
regeneration in infrabony defects</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17199537</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guida</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Annunziata</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Belardo</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farina</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scabbia</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trombelli</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of autogenous cortical bone particulate in conjunction with
enamel matrix derivative in the treatment of periodontal intraosseous
defects</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <lpage>238</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17274711</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guimarães</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Passanezi</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sant'ana</surname>
                      <given-names>ACP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Greghi</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pool of bovine morphogenetic proteins and guided tissue regeneration
in the treatment of intrabony periodontal defects. I- clinical
measurements</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <lpage>77</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21365155</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeffcoat</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>IC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reddy</surname>
                      <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Radiographic diagnosis in periodontics</article-title>
                  <source>Periodontol 2000</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <lpage>68</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9567930</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joly</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palioto</surname>
                      <given-names>DB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>AF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mota</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caffesse</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical and radiographic evaluation of periodontal intrabony defects
treated with guided tissue regeneration. A pilot study</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
                  <lpage>359</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11990435</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kulczyk</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the results of periodontal treatment by means of digital
subtraction of radiographic images</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Med Sci</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
                  <fpage>S126</fpage>
                  <lpage>S129</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matos</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guerra</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krauser</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marques</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ermida</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sanz</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical evaluation of the combination of anorganic bovine-derived
hydroxyapatite matrix/cell-binding peptide (P-15) in particulate and hydrogel form
as a bone replacement graft material in human periodontal osseous defects: 6-month
reentry controlled clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>J Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1855</fpage>
                  <lpage>1863</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18062107</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mellonig</surname>
                      <given-names>JT</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Human histologic evaluation of a bovine-derived bone xenograft in the
treatment of periodontal osseous defects</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <lpage>29</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11203545</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reddi</surname>
                      <given-names>AH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huggins</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Biochemical sequences in the transformation of normal fibroblasts in
adolescent rats</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                  <year>1972</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1601</fpage>
                  <lpage>1605</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4504376</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sailer</surname>
                      <given-names>HF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kolb</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Application of purified bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) in
cranio-maxillo-facial surgery. BMP in compromised surgical reconstructions using
titanium implants</article-title>
                  <source>J Craniomaxillofac Surg</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>2</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8175993</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sculean</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berakdar</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiantella</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donos</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arweiler</surname>
                      <given-names>NB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brecx</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Healing of intrabony defects following treatment with a bovine-derived
xenograft and collagen membrane. A controlled clinical study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <lpage>80</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12702114</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sculean</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donos</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiantella</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Windisch</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reich</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brecx</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>GTR with bioresorbable membranes in the treatment of intrabony
defects: a clinical and histologic study</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
                  <lpage>509</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709516</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Skoglund</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hising</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Young</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A clinical and histologic examination in humans of the osseous
response to implanted natural bone mineral</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <lpage>199</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9109269</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Urist</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bone: formation by autoinduction</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>1965</year>
                  <volume>150</volume>
                  <issue>698</issue>
                  <fpage>893</fpage>
                  <lpage>899</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5319761</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Urist</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Iwata</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ceccotti</surname>
                      <given-names>PL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorfman</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boyd</surname>
                      <given-names>SD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McDowell</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bone morphogenesis in implants of insoluble bone
gelatin</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
                  <year>1973</year>
                  <volume>70</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>3511</fpage>
                  <lpage>3515</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4357876</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Urist</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mikulski</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boyd</surname>
                      <given-names>SD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A chemosterilized antigenextracted autodigested alloimplant for bone
banks</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Surg</source>
                  <year>1975</year>
                  <volume>110</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>416</fpage>
                  <lpage>428</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1096848</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vouros</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aristodimou</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Konstantinidis</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Guided tissue regeneration in intrabony periodontal defects following
treatment with two bioabsorbable membranes in combination with bovine bone mineral
graft. A clinical and radiographic study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Periodontol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>908</fpage>
                  <lpage>917</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367197</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
