<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-04-29T00:35:21Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10773444" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10773444</identifier>
        <datestamp>2024-01-08</datestamp>
        <setSpec>dpjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dental Press J Orthod</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dpjo</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Dental Press Journal of Orthodontics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2176-9451</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2177-6709</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dental Press International</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10773444</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10773444</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10773444</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38198391</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2177-6709.28.6.e2323177.oar</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">00302</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Alignment efficiency and three-dimensional assessment of root resorption after alignment with conventional and copper-nickel-titanium archwires: A randomized controlled trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7128-3405</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>BHATIA</surname>
                    <given-names>Navleen Kaur</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                  <role>Fundraising</role>
                  <role>Overall responsibility</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8885-3037</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>CHUGH</surname>
                    <given-names>Vinay Kumar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Conception or design of the study</role>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                  <role>Overall responsibility</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9552-9083</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>SHANKAR</surname>
                    <given-names>Sam Prasanth</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1342-3793</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>VINAY A.P</surname>
                    <given-names>Ritvik</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Writing the article</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8990-3235</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>SINGH</surname>
                    <given-names>Surjit</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6591-0588</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>MOUNGKHOM</surname>
                    <given-names>Priyawati</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3208-191X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>SARDANA</surname>
                    <given-names>Rinkle</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <role>Data acquisition, analysis or interpretation</role>
                  <role>Critical revision of the article</role>
                  <role>Final approval of the article</role>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Department of Dentistry, Section of Orthodontics (Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India). </aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Department of Pharmacology (Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India).</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">
                  <email>drvinaychd@yahoo.com</email>
                </corresp>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn1">
                  <label>»</label>
                  <p> The authors report no commercial, proprietary or financial interest in the products or companies described in this article.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>08</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>28</volume>
              <issue>6</issue>
              <elocation-id>e2323177</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>23</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>ABSTRACT</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective: </title>
                  <p>To compare alignment efficiency and root resorption between nickel-titanium (NiTi) and copper-nickel-titanium (CuNiTi) archwires after complete alignment in mandibular anterior region. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods: </title>
                  <p>In this two-arm parallel single-blind randomized controlled trial, forty-four patients with Class I malocclusion with mandibular anterior crowding were recruited form orthodontic clinic of All India Institute of Medical Sciences (Jodhpur, India). Patients were randomly allocated into NiTi and CuNiTi groups, with a 1:1 allocation. Alignment was performed using 0.014-in, 0.016-in, 0.018-in, 0.019x0.025-in archwire sequence in the respective groups, which terminated in 0.019 x 0.025-in stainless-steel working archwire. The primary outcome was alignment efficiency, measured on study models from baseline (T0) to the first, second, third, fourth and fifth-month (T5). Secondary outcome was root resorption, measured from CBCT scans taken at T0 and T5. Mixed-factorial ANOVA was used to compare Little’s Irregularity Index (LII). For assessing the proportion of patients with complete alignment at the end of each month, Kaplan-Meier survival curve was built and time to treatment completion was compared between groups using log rank test. Paired <italic>t</italic>-test was used to assess external apical root resorption (EARR) within groups, whereas independent <italic>t</italic>-test was used to evaluate LII and EARR between the groups. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results: </title>
                  <p>Twenty-two patients were recruited in each group. One patient was lost to follow-up in the CuNiTi group. No statistically significant differences were observed in alignment efficiency between the groups (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05). Intergroup comparison revealed that the changes in root measurement in three-dimensions were not statistically significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05), except for mandibular right central incisor, which showed increased resorption at root apex in NiTi group (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion: </title>
                  <p>The two alignment archwires showed similar rate of alignment at all time points. Root resorption measurement did not differ between the NiTi and CuNiTi groups, except for the mandibular right central incisor, which showed more resorption in NiTi group.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
                <title>RESUMO</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objetivo: </title>
                  <p>Comparar os fios de níquel-titânio (NiTi) e de cobre-níquel-titânio (CuNiTi) quanto à eficiência do alinhamento e quantidade de reabsorção radicular, após alinhamento completo dos dentes da região anterior inferior. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Métodos: </title>
                  <p>Neste estudo clínico randomizado, cego, paralelo, de dois braços, quarenta e quatro pacientes com má oclusão Classe I e apinhamento anterior inferior foram recrutados na clínica ortodôntica do All India Institute of Medical Sciences (Jodhpur, India). Os pacientes foram alocados aleatoriamente nos grupos NiTi e CuNiTi, na proporção de 1:1. O alinhamento foi realizado usando a sequência de fios 0,014”, 0,016”, 0,018” e 0,019” x 0,025” nos respectivos grupos, finalizando com o arco de trabalho 0,019” x 0,025” de aço inoxidável. O desfecho primário foi a eficiência do alinhamento, medida nos modelos de estudo nos tempos inicial (T0) e após um, dois, três, quatro e cinco meses (T5). O desfecho secundário foi a reabsorção radicular, medida a partir de tomografias computadorizadas realizadas em T0 e T5. ANOVA fatorial mista foi utilizada para comparar o Índice de Irregularidade de Little (IIL). Para avaliar a proporção de pacientes com alinhamento completo ao fim de cada mês, foi construída uma curva de sobrevida pelo método de Kaplan-Meier, e o tempo até o fim do tratamento foi comparado entre os grupos por meio do teste <italic>log-rank</italic>. Um teste <italic>t</italic> pareado foi utilizado para avaliar a reabsorção radicular apical externa (RRAE) dentro dos grupos, enquanto um teste <italic>t</italic> independente foi utilizado para avaliar o IIL e a RRAE entre os grupos. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Resultados:</title>
                  <p> Vinte e dois pacientes foram recrutados em cada grupo. Um paciente perdeu o acompanhamento no grupo CuNiTi. Não foram observadas diferenças estatisticamente significativas entre os grupos quanto à eficiência do alinhamento (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0,05). A comparação intergrupos revelou que as alterações na RRAE medida em três dimensões não foram estatisticamente significativas (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0,05), exceto para o incisivo central inferior direito, que apresentou aumento da RRAE no grupo NiTi (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0,01). </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusão: </title>
                  <p>Os dois tipos de fios de alinhamento apresentaram taxa de alinhamento semelhante em todos os momentos. A medida da reabsorção radicular não diferiu entre o grupo NiTi e CuNiTi, exceto para o incisivo central inferior direito, que apresentou maior reabsorção no grupo NiTi.</p>
                </sec>
              </trans-abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords:</title>
                <kwd>Alignment</kwd>
                <kwd>Root resorption</kwd>
                <kwd>Fixed orthodontic appliances</kwd>
                <kwd>Orthodontic wires</kwd>
                <kwd>CBCT</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="3"/>
                <table-count count="10"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="42"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Clinically effective treatment aims at balancing light, continuous forces and the restriction of potential damage to the tooth and periodontal structures.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> In the first stage of orthodontic treatment, alignment archwires should have the property of delivering light continuous forces for a longer period of time. Nickel-titanium (NiTi) and copper-nickel-titanium (CuNiTi) alloys are common archwire choices to achieve ideal alignment of teeth.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Quintão et al.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> stated that the smaller force deflection of superelastic NiTi archwires, when compared with stainless steel ones, makes the former more favorable for correction of crowding. However, despite the availability of various archwires, a careful selection should be made, due to the differences in expression of their properties <italic>in vivo</italic>.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>A light continuous force is usually desired throughout the fixed orthodontic treatment. Dalaie et al.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> have shown that there is no adverse effect of leveling and alignment on root length of immature teeth. However, heavy orthodontic forces may lead to potential side-effects like pain and root resorption. According to Tripuwabhrut et al.,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> orthodontic forces represent a physical agent that is itself capable of inducing inflammatory reaction in the periodontium. Orthodontically induced external apical root resorption (EARR) is one of the most commonly seen iatrogenic damage of fixed orthodontic treatment, which is a result of inflammation caused by excessive forces. Various diagnostic modalities are available to evaluate root resorption.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Cone beam computed tomography (CBCT) appears to be a better and reliable tool to assess root resorption with marked accuracy.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> It has been used to assess EARR after rapid maxillary expansion,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> intrusion movements,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> initial alignment and leveling,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> and after complete orthodontic treatment.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Patients with detectable root resorption during the first six-months of active treatment have been reported to have greater resorption in the following six-month period.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p>Previous studies comparing different NiTi, CuNiTi or multi-stranded stainless-steel (SS) archwires did not find any significant differences in terms of alignment efficiency and EARR.<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> However, there is insufficient data to make clear recommendations regarding the superiority of any available archwire, in relation to their effectiveness and efficacy, due to the small number of robust <italic>in-vivo</italic> studies.<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> A Cochrane review stated that more extensive studies are needed to formulate specific guidelines.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> The studies evaluating root resorption after the initial phase of alignment using CBCT have assessed changes in root length mainly in sagittal section. Comprehensive three-dimensional assessment of EARR in all sections after alignment and leveling has been rarely reported. The present study is probably the first to compare three-dimensional (sagittal, coronal and axial section) changes in root measurement using CBCT between NiTi and CuNiTi groups. </p>
              <p>The primary outcome of this study was to compare the alignment efficiency. Three-dimensional assessment of root resorption was the secondary outcome. The null hypothesis was that there would be no difference in alignment efficiency and EARR after complete alignment between NiTi and CuNiTi archwires. </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>TRIAL DESIGN</title>
                <p>The study was an open-label, parallel-group and randomized clinical trial, with a 1:1 allocation ratio. No changes were made in methodology after trial commencement.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>PARTICIPANTS, ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA, AND SETTINGS</title>
                <p>Ethical approval was obtained (AIIMS/IEC/2018/610) from the Institutional Ethics Committee, All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS, Jodhpur, India). This study was also registered at Clinical Trials Registry, India (CTRI/2018/10/016038). The CONSORT statement reporting guidelines were followed (Fig 1). The recruitment of orthodontic patients was done at the post-graduate orthodontic clinic, Department of Dentistry, AIIMS (Jodhpur, India), between July 2018 and March 2020. Forty-four patients who fulfilled the inclusion criteria were invited to participate in the study. Patients having Angle’s Class I malocclusion with moderate (4-6 mm) to severe (&gt;6 mm) mandibular anterior crowding, based on the contact point displacement, were recruited for the study.<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> The inclusion and exclusion criteria of the participants are shown in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
                    <label>Table 1:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Selection criteria.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inclusion criteria</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 12 years and older at the beginning of fixed orthodontic treatment</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (4-6 mm) to severe (&gt;6 mm) mandibular anterior crowding requiring extraction of mandibular first premolars </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular permanent dentition, excluding third molars</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of root resorption in mandibular anterior teeth</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of any impacted teeth in the mandibular anterior region</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exclusion criteria</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any history of previous orthodontic treatment</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment plan involving single mandibular incisor extraction</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completely blocked-out mandibular incisor, in which engagement of the first archwire was not possible</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor gingival and periodontal health</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with any systemic, bone or metabolic disorders</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Under medication that alter tooth movements</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f1">
                    <label>Figure 1:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>CONSORT flowchart of participants through each stage of the trial.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-06-e2323177-gf1" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>RANDOMIZATION, ALLOCATION CONCEALMENT AND BLINDING</title>
                <p>Patients were randomly allocated into two groups using computer-generated variable block randomization scheme, in a specific software (Random Allocation Software 2.0, Microsoft Corporation, WA, USA). The allocation concealment was achieved using an opaque sealed envelope (sequentially numbered as per randomization scheme). Operator was handed over these envelopes by a person not involved in the trial. The outcome assessor, participants and the statistician were blinded; however, the operator could not be blinded to the allocation groups. The information of the participants was anonymized using non-identifiable codes and removing identifying information.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>INTERVENTIONS</title>
                <p>All participants were bonded with fixed appliances in both, maxillary and mandibular arches (Gemini brackets, 0.022-in MBT preadjusted Edgewise prescription; 3M Unitek, Monrovia, Calif). After performing atraumatic extractions of the mandibular first premolars, leveling and alignment was initiated using NiTi archwire (G4™ Nickel-titanium, G&amp;H, Franklin, Indiana) in the NiTi group, and CuNiTi archwire (M5™ Thermal Copper-Nickel-Titanium 35ºC, G&amp;H, Franklin, Indiana) in the CuNiTi group. The crowding measured from the initial data was recorded as T0, at the baseline. In both groups, archwires were ligated in the sequence as shown in <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. At the end of every month, archwires were changed sequentially for five-months, until the placement of 0.019 × 0.025-in SS working archwire in both groups, to produce a common end-point (T5). Lacebacks to canines were used to obtain space after extraction for alleviation of crowding. N.K.B. performed all the clinical interventions relating to the study. S.P.S. measured the outcome variables. </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
                    <label>Table 2:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Time period and archwire sequence used in the study.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time period</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archwire sequence</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0<break/> (At the baseline)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placement of fixed appliances and 0.014-in archwire</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1 <break/> (At the end of first month)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Removal of 0.014-in archwire and <break/> placement of 0.016-in archwire</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2<break/> (At the end of second month)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Removal of 0.016-in archwire and <break/> placement of 0.018-in archwire</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3<break/> (At the end of third month)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Removal of 0.018-in archwire and <break/> placement of 0.019 × 0.025-in archwire</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4<break/> (At the end of fourth month)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Removal of 0.019×0.025-in archwire and placement of working 0.019×0.025-in stainless-steel archwire</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T5<break/> (At the end of fifth month)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completion of the alignment phase</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>OUTCOMES</title>
                <p>To assess alignment efficiency, mandibular impressions were taken at the beginning of fixed orthodontic treatment and thereafter every month, up to five-months of treatment. CBCT scan of mandibular anterior region were obtained at pre-treatment and post-alignment stage. The scan was obtained using a using a CBCT unit (KODAK 9600 3D<sup>®</sup>; Carestream Health, Inc., Marne-la-Vallée, France), with reduced field of view (5x5cm)<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> and voxel size of 0.15mm, as suggested by Samandara et al.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>, with standard recommended settings (voltage = 120kV; current = 8mA; scan time = 10s). The data was then imported into Dolphin imaging software (version 11.95, Dolphin Imaging &amp; Management Solutions, Chatsworth, Calif).</p>
                <p>» Primary outcomes - Alignment efficiency was analyzed assessing the reduction in the Little’s irregularity index (LII)<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref>, to measure crowding of mandibular anterior region, on study models obtained at T0 to T5. Displacement of contact point as described in the index was measured with the help of a digital caliper with a sharpened fine edge to the nearest 0.01 mm (Standard Digital Caliper Series: EC16) on the study models.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Alignment was considered complete when LII was near zero and 0.019×0.025-in stainless-steel working archwire was passive in the bracket slots (T5).</p>
                <p>» Secondary outcomes - Changes in the root length and apical root dimensions were assessed for the four mandibular incisors at T0 and T5 in CBCT scans of mandibular anterior region, as per measurements described in <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t3">
                    <label>Table 3:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Measurement used for evaluation of root resorption.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root length (mm)</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The scan was adjusted along the long axis for the tooth to be measured, such that the horizontal reference line of software passes through cemento-enamel junction (CEJ). The length of the root was measured along the long axis of the tooth, passing from the most apical point of the root to the reference line perpendicularly. The root length measurements were made in sagittal and coronal sections for the four mandibular incisors (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>A-B).</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apical root dimension (mm)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The root length was measured from CEJ to the apex, and marked 2mm short of apex using ‘landmark’ tool in the coronal section in pre-treatment scans (T0). Axial slice was viewed at this level and labio-lingual and mesio-distal dimensions were measured to determine apical root diameter. Post-alignment scans (T5) were evaluated at the same root level from CEJ in the coronal section as T0, for the apical root measurements (Fig 2C). </td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f2">
                    <label>Figure 2:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>A) Sagittal section; B) coronal section; C) axial section showing labio-lingual thickness and mesio-distal width.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-06-e2323177-gf2" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>SAMPLE SIZE</title>
                <p>Sample size was calculated based on the previous study by Serafim et al.<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Assuming a proportion of 73% and 100% patients achieving complete alignment in the two groups, and population risk difference of 0.2, a sample size of 19 patients per group was calculated. Clinical significance level of 0.05 was established. Considering a dropout rate of about 10%, we recruited 22 patients per treatment group. Sample size was calculated using nMaster 2.0 software.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>INTERIM ANALYSES AND STOPPING GUIDELINES</title>
                <p>Not applicable.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</title>
                <p>Data were analyzed using IBM SPSS 23.0 (Armonk, NY: IBM Corp.). One calibrated blinded examiner (S.P.S.) evaluated the study models and CBCT scans. Dahlberg error<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> and intra-examiner reproducibility (repeated after two weeks) were assessed using intraclass correlation coefficients (ICC) for LII and all measurements for EARR. </p>
                <p>Normal distribution was assessed using Shapiro-Wilk tests. Descriptive statistics of means and standard deviations (SD) were calculated. Chi-square test/Fisher’s Exact test was applied to compare baseline categorical data. Mixed factorial ANOVA was used to compare differences in the alignment between the groups with time interaction. Kaplan-Meier survival curve was built to illustrate proportion of patients who completed alignment at the end of each month. Log-rank test was used to compare time to treatment completion between groups. Paired <italic>t</italic>-test was used to assess EARR, before and after alignment within groups, and an independent <italic>t</italic>-test was used to evaluate the difference in LII and EARR between the groups. The significance level was set as <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, with 95% confidence intervals (95% CI). </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>PARTICIPANT FLOW</title>
                <p>Forty-four patients were randomly allocated in a 1:1 ratio into NiTi and CuNiTi groups. One patient was lost to follow-up after randomization in the CuNiTi group, and was excluded of the analysis. A CONSORT diagram showing the flow of participants during the trial is presented in the <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Dahlberg error for LII and EARR indicated no significant measurement error (LII &lt; 0.4 mm; EARR = 0.48-0.55mm). Intra-examiner reproducibility of the main examiner was excellent for LII and good to excellent for all measurements regarding EARR (<xref rid="t1a" ref-type="table">Supplemental Table</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t1a">
                    <label>Supplemental Table:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Intraclass correlation coefficients for intra-examiner reproducibility and inter-examiner reliability.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="4"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameters </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">ICC (95% CI) </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intra-examiner reproducibility</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value*</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inter-examiner reliability</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value<sup>#</sup>
</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Study models </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Little’s Irregularity Index</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.973 (0.917 - 0.992)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.978 (0.923-0.993)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">CBCT scans </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root length-sagittal section </td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894 (0.681 - 0.965)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.959 (0.858 - 0.987)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root length-coronal section</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.908 (0.719 - 0.970)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.975 (0.922 - 0.992)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Labiolingual thickness-axial section </td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.898 (0.643 - 0.968)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.936 (0.797 - 0.979)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesiodistal width-axial section </td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.956 (0.737- 0.988)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.883 (0.388 - 0.968)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN1">
                        <p>* P-value representing intra-examiner reproducibility. <sup>#</sup>P-value representing and inter-examiner reliability ** P-value &lt; 0.05 is considered as significant; Intraclass correlation was analyzed using two-way mixed model, with absolute agreement.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>BASELINE DATA</title>
                <p><xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> presents the baseline characteristics of the patients in each treatment group. NiTi group consisted of twenty-two patients (8 males, 14 females), whereas CuNiTi group consisted of twenty-one patients (8 males, 13 females). There was no significant difference in the baseline parameters between the groups. </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t4">
                    <label>Table 4:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Baseline characteristics of participants in each study group.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NiTi n=22</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CuNiTi n=21</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial age (years) mean (SD)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9 (3.63)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 (4.64)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Sex - subjects n (%) </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (36.4)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (38.1)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (63.6)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (61.9)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Crowding - subjects n (%) </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (45.5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (47.6)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (54.5)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (52.4)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LII (mm) mean (SD)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 (2.42)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 (3.32)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN2">
                        <p>Values are presented as mean (SD), or n (%). SD = standard deviation, NiTi = nickel-titanium, CuNiTi = copper-nickel-titanium, LII = Little’s irregularity index, NS = non-significant.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>PRIMARY OUTCOME</title>
                <p>There was a significant improvement in LII after every month in NiTi and CuNiTi groups; however, the difference in LII with time was not significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05) between the two groups (<xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">Tables 5</xref> and <xref rid="t6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). The log-rank test revealed no statistically significant difference between the two types of alignment archwires (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05) in terms of survival function (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). No statistically significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05) was present in both the groups, in terms of number of patients in which alignment was incomplete at the end of five months (<xref rid="t7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).</p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t5">
                    <label>Table 5:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Mixed factorial ANOVA test for the difference between groups, according to the change in LII with time factor. </title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.809</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0 .001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time * Type of wire</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.639</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.502</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of wire</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.704</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN3">
                        <p>LII = Little’s Irregularity Index; *P &lt; 0.05 = statistically significant.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t6">
                    <label>Table 6:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of alignment efficiency using LII (mm) between NiTi and CuNiTi groups at different time intervals.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Measurement</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">NiTi (n=22) </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CuNiTi (n=21) </th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower bound</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper bound</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">LII (mm) </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">At T0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.94</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0-T1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.432</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.83</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1-T2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.61</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2-T3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.576</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.50</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3-T4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.419</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.49</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4-T5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.538</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.12</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN4">
                        <p>Values are presented as mean (SD). SD = standard deviation, NiTi = nickel-titanium, CuNiTi = copper-nickel-titanium, LII = Little’s irregularity index, CI = confidence interval; P-value for comparison of group means by independent t-test.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t7">
                    <label>Table 7:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of proportion of cases showing completion of alignment at T5, in each group.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NiTi<break/> n=22</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CuNiTi <break/> n=21</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value*</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds Ratio (OR)<break/> (95% CI)</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alignment completed/incomplete n/n (%) after 5 months</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/6 (72.8/27.2)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/5 (77.3/22.7)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2<break/> (0.304-4.743)</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN5">
                        <p>NiTi = nickel-titanium; CuNiTi = copper-nickel-titanium CI = Confidence Interval *<italic>p</italic>-value for comparison of percentage data by Fischer’s Exact test CI-Mantel-Haenszel Common odds ratio.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="f3">
                    <label>Figure 3:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Kaplan-Meier survival curves for the two groups used in the study. The y-axis gives the proportion of patients achieving complete alignment at different time points ( months on x axis ). There is no separation during the evaluation period, indicating no significant difference between the groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="2177-6709-dpjo-28-06-e2323177-gf3" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>SECONDARY OUTCOME</title>
                <p>The intragroup comparison showed significant differences (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) in root length and apical root dimension (labio-lingual and mesio-distal measurements) in all four mandibular incisors in both groups (<xref rid="t8" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>). However, the differences between the two groups were not statistically significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.05) for all measurements, except for the mandibular right central incisor, which showed significantly higher resorption in NiTi group for apical root dimension, both in mesio-distal and labio-lingual dimension (<xref rid="t9" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref>). </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t8">
                    <label>Table 8:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of linear changes in root length from T0-T5 (mm) in NiTi and CuNiTi groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="4"/>
                        <col span="4"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Measurement</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">NiTi (n=22) </th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">CuNiTi (n=21) </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0<break/> Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T5<break/> Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean<break/> diff</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0<break/> Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T5<break/> Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean<break/> diff</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Root length - SS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (1.21)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (1.34)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (0.83)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (0.93)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (1.24)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (1.34)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (0.97)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (1.11)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 (1.33)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 (1.32)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 (1.09)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 (1.24)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8 (1.27)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (1.28)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 (1.15)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 (1.18)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Root length - CS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (1.51)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (1.33)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 (0.89)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9 (1.09)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (1.48)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 (1.52)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 (0.95)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7 (1.18)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5 (1.44)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (1.37)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 (1.13)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 (1.25)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4 (1.44)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (1.48)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 (1.14)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (1.41)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Root apex (LL) - AS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (0.80)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.64)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (0.43)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (0.89)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035 ***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (0.29)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.64)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (0.56)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (1.15)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004 **</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (0.77)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (1.56)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (0.90)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (1.49)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003 **</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (0.90)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.63)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (0.78)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (1.06)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Root apex (MD) - AS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.19)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.66)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (0.22)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.38)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026 ***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (0.23)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.65)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003 **</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.20)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (0.45)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004 **</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (0.22)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.73)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.23)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.53)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.30)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.68)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.20)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.43)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005 **</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN6">
                        <p>Values are presented as mean (SD). SD = standard deviation, diff = difference; T0 = pre-alignment, T5 = post-alignment, NiTi = nickel-titanium, CuNiTi = copper-nickel-titanium, LR1 = mandibular right central incisor LL1 = mandibular left central incisor, LR2 = mandibular right lateral incisor, LL2 = mandibular left lateral incisor, SS = sagittal section, CS = coronal section, AS = axial section, LL = labio-lingual thickness, MD = mesio-distal width. <italic>p</italic>-value for comparison of group means by paired t-test.</p>
                      </fn>
                      <fn id="TFN7">
                        <p>* P &lt; 0.001, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.05.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="t9">
                    <label>Table 9:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Comparison of linear changes in root length from T0-T5 (mm) between NiTi and CuNiTi groups.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="1"/>
                        <col span="2"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Measurement</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NiTi (n=22) Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CuNiTi (n=21) Mean (SD)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">P value</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower bound</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper bound</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Root length - SS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.34)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.43)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.36</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.02</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.70)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.43)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.59</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.88)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.69) </td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.693</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.22</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.36)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.69)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.95</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Root length - CS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.13)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.77)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.698</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.19</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.25)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.78)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.35</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (1.32)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.82)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.21</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (1.36)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.76)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.14</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Root apex (LL) - AS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.28)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.67)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008 **</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.26)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.91)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.25</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.25)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (1.16)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.35</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.27)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.99)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.273</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.31</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Root apex (MD) - AS </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.64)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.33)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008 **</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL1</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.60)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.33)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.09</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.64)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.56)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.440</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.22</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LL2</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.64)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.42)</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.03</td>
                          <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="TFN8">
                        <p>Values are presented as mean (SD). SD = standard deviation, T0 = pre-alignment, T5 = post-alignment, NiTi = nickel-titanium, CuNiTi = copper-nickel-titanium, LR1 = mandibular right central incisor, LL1 = mandibular left central incisor, LR2 = mandibular right lateral incisor, LL2 = mandibular left lateral incisor, CI = confidence interval, SS = sagittal section, CS = coronal section, AS = axial section, LL = labio-lingual thickness, MD = mesio-distal width. P-value for comparison of group means by independent t-test: * P&lt;0.001, ** P&lt;0.01, *** P&lt;0.05.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>HARMS</title>
                <p>No adverse events were reported during treatment, except a slight EARR that was within the limits of usual occurrence during orthodontic treatment. </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <sec>
                <title>ALIGNMENT EFFICIENCY</title>
                <p>On evaluating alignment efficiency with both the archwires, LII scores approached zero after five-months with similar rate of alignment at each time-point. This shows that NiTi and CuNiTi were similar regarding their alignment efficiency to relieve moderate to severe crowding. Previous studies found no significant difference regarding alignment efficiency between CuNiTi and other NiTi archwires (conventional and superelastic).<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Riley and Bearn<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> conducted a systematic review and found inadequate evidence for determining the most effective archwire for alignment. In terms of alignment efficiency and sequence of aligning archwires, similar findings were reported by a meta-analysis by Papageorgiou et al.<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> A recent Cochrane review found no sufficient evidence to substantiate superiority of any archwire material for alignment and levelling.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> This review identified twelve studies, out of which only two studies compared conventional NiTi with CuNiTi, and none of them used rectangular archwires in the sequence - and therefore, may not contribute to greater evidence. The present study used conventional MBT bracket system, which was not used in both of these studies. The authors suggested a need of well-designed randomized control trial to evaluate the effectiveness of any archwire, due to presence of existing low quality of evidence.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> Therefore, all of the previous systematic reviews highlighted the requirement of a robust and well-designed randomized control trial to evaluate efficiency of various archwires. </p>
                <p>Previous studies by Abdelrahman et al.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> and Pandis et al.<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> evaluated alignment efficiency using only a single round archwire for the entire duration of the study. In the former study, 0.014-in NiTi archwire was used and an impression was taken at every 2-week for 16-weeks, while in the latter 0.016-in NiTi archwire was evaluated monthly for six months without any further change in the archwire. We believe that evaluation of alignment at every 2-weeks may not offer any additional advantage, as a significant tooth movement is unlikely to occur in such a short period. Recall visits at three weeks or less may be insufficient for archwires to completely express their alignment efficiency. In the present study, the archwires were changed after every month, which is commonly accepted.<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> Although the results of the present study are in agreement with previous studies, there is a lot of variation in evaluation periods (ranging between 2-weeks to 6-9 months) and the type and sequence of archwires used in the literature.<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p>The present study used both round and rectangular archwire sequences for complete alignment. Most studies<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> in the past included only round wires and very few reported the use of both round and rectangular wires in evaluation of alignment efficiency.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p>In the present study, the majority of the patients completed alignment within five months, with no statistically significant differences between the groups. Nearly 72.7% of subjects in NiTi group and 77.3% in CuNiTi group achieved complete alignment by the end of five months, which was in contrast with previous studies. Serafim et al.<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> reported complete alignment in 70% of cases in NiTi group and 100% of cases in CuNiTi group at the end of five months; however, mechanical properties of archwire may vary with different brands and therefore, needs to be evaluated in future studies.</p>
                <p>It appears from the ongoing discussion that NiTi and CuNiTi archwires are similar with respect to alignment efficiency, although clinically, CuNiTi may offer the advantage of better engagement in severely displaced teeth.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>ROOT RESORPTION</title>
                <p>The significance of assessing root resorption at the initial phase of the treatment is that the teeth that show EARR in first 6-months of appliance placement are likely to present greater resorption by the end of treatment.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Wang et al.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> suggested more randomized trials with sufficient duration, in which the benefits and possible disadvantages associated with different types of the archwires currently being used should be reported. </p>
                <p>In the past, periapical radiographs were commonly used to study root resorption; however, there have inaccuracies associated with it.<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> Lund et al.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> found a slanting type of root resorption in many teeth, which can only be evaluated in three-dimensional radiography. Alamadi et al.<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> in their study also found that two-dimensional radiographs, such as periapical radiographs and panoramic radiographs, underestimated root resorption, especially the slanting type of apical resorption, when compared to three-dimensional imaging methods. For detection of root resorption, three-dimensional imaging is considered superior to conventional imaging methods. The radiation exposure associated with CBCT scans may be considered a potential disadvantage for the patients; however, the newer CBCT techniques have presented reduced radiation exposure, compared to conventional machines.<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> To Samandara et al.,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> a voxel size of less than 0.2-mm is considered accurate for evaluating root resorption; therefore, a voxel size of 0.15 mm was used for evaluating root resorption in the present study, which enabled visualization of small changes in root surface.</p>
                <p>Sagittal and coronal slices of CBCT showed a significant EARR in all mandibular incisors post-alignment, irrespective of the archwire used, which is also supported by the results of previous studies.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> A recent randomized control trial, corroborating the present study, also did not find any significant difference in EARR in mandibular incisors while comparing superelastic NiTi and heat-activated NiTi archwires.<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> In a study by Neves et al.,<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> the incidence of EARR was reported to be higher in patients treated with premolar extraction, although the results were based on two-dimensional periapical radiographs and involved only maxillary incisors. </p>
                <p>There were no statistically significant differences in labiolingual and mesiodistal dimension in axial section between the two groups, except for the mandibular right central incisor, in which a significantly higher EARR was reported in NiTi group, both labio-lingually and mesio-distally, which was quite an unusual finding. A possible explanation could be the higher uncontrolled tipping produced in this particular tooth with the NiTi archwires. A previous study reported similar findings, in which mandibular left central incisor showed significantly more EARR while comparing superelastic NiTi with multi-stranded stainless-steel archwires.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> This may suggest a greater tendency for EARR in the NiTi archwires with a longer treatment duration. In the present study, we assessed mandibular incisors, which are the most commonly affected teeth after maxillary incisors.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Direct comparison with previous studies was difficult, as most of the studies evaluated root resorption using either different type of appliances,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> different archwires and their sequences,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> assessment time,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> imaging software or type of imaging modality.<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> Future studies can benefit from the uniformity in the method and timing of assessment of EARR. The results of the present study showed a significant root resorption observed in the alignment stage; therefore, a regular radiographic follow-up of the patients undergoing fixed orthodontic treatment is suggested.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS</title>
              <p>Every patient enrolled in this trial was followed-up for a period of five months, which gave adequate opportunity to evaluate alignment. Additionally, EARR was truly studied in all three-dimensions. One of the limitations of the current study was that the interventions could have been evaluated in non-extraction patients as well. At present, the available literature shows a lot of variation in three-dimensional assessment of root resorption; therefore, a standard method of assessment will facilitate meaningful comparisons associated with various appliances and treatment mechanotherapy. The results of the study cannot be generalized, as it was based on a single-center study. Since the limitations were fairly minor, without any discernible effect on the primary or secondary outcomes, the objectives of the study were achieved, with minimal impact from the above limitations. </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>The following conclusions were drawn from the study:</p>
              <p>
                <list list-type="order">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Alignment efficiency did not differ significantly between NiTi and CuNiTi groups.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>There were no statistically significant differences in root resorption in all three-dimensions between the two groups, except for mandibular right central incisor, which showed increased resorption in root apical dimension in NiTi group, when compared to the CuNiTi group.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>West</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Newcombe</surname>
                      <given-names>RG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Multiflex versus superelastic A randomized clinical trial of the tooth alignment ability of initial arch wires</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>108</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>464</fpage>
                  <lpage>471</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7484965</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bishara</surname>
                      <given-names>SE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Textbook of orthodontics</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quintão</surname>
                      <given-names>CC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cal-Neto</surname>
                      <given-names>JP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Menezes</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Elias</surname>
                      <given-names>CN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Force-deflection properties of initial orthodontic archwires</article-title>
                  <source>World J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19388430</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dalaie</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Badiee</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Behnaz</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kavousinejad</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of orthodontic forces on root length of immature mandibular second premolars a split-mouth randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Dental Press J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <elocation-id>e2119355</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35640080</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tripuwabhrut</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brudvik</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fristad</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rethnam</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Experimental orthodontic tooth movement and extensive root resorption periodontal and pulpal changes</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>118</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>596</fpage>
                  <lpage>603</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21083621</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alzahawi</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Færøvig</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brudvik</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bøe</surname>
                      <given-names>OE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mavragani</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Root resorption after leveling with super-elastic and conventional steel arch wires a prospective study</article-title>
                  <source>Prog Orthod</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <lpage>35</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24949989</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smale</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Artun</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Behbehani</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doppel</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van't Hof</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuijpers-Jagtman</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical root resorption 6 months after initiation of fixed orthodontic appliance therapy</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>128</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <lpage>67</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16027626</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Remington</surname>
                      <given-names>DN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joondeph</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Artun</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riedel</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chapko</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Long-term evaluation of root resorption occurring during orthodontic treatment</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2750719</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samandara</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Papageorgiou</surname>
                      <given-names>SN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ioannidou-Marathiotou</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kavvadia-Tsatala</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Papadopoulos</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of orthodontically induced external root resorption following orthodontic treatment using cone beam computed tomography (CBCT) a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <lpage>79</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29771300</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baysal</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karadede</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hekimoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ucar</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ozer</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Veli</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of root resorption following rapid maxillary expansion using cone-beam computed tomography</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>488</fpage>
                  <lpage>494</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21843038</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dindaroglu</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dogan</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation and comparison of root resorption between tooth-borne and tooth-tissue borne rapid maxillary expansion appliances A CBCT study</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>86</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <lpage>52</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25993251</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ding</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ye</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shi</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Volumetric measurement of root resorption following molar mini-screw implant intrusion using cone beam computed tomography</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <elocation-id>e60962</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23585866</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alam</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chauhan</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verma</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raj</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative cone-beam computed tomographic evaluation of maxillary incisor intrusion and associated root resorption Intrusion arch vs mini-implants</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>163</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>e84</fpage>
                  <lpage>e92</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36635144</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Makedonas</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lund</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gröndahl</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hansen</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Root resorption diagnosed with cone beam computed tomography after 6 months of orthodontic treatment with fixed appliance and the relation to risk factors</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <lpage>201</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21827236</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lund</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gröndahl</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hansen</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gröndahl</surname>
                      <given-names>HG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical root resorption during orthodontic treatment A prospective study using cone beam CT</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>480</fpage>
                  <lpage>487</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21919826</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Makedonas</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lund</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hansen</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Root resorption diagnosed with cone beam computed tomography after 6 months and at the end of orthodontic treatment with fixed appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <lpage>393</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23092202</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Artun</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smale</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Behbehani</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doppel</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van't Hof</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuijpers-Jagtman</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Apical root resorption six and 12 months after initiation of fixed orthodontic appliance therapy</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>919</fpage>
                  <lpage>926</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16448232</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jain</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharma</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shetty</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of two different initial archwires for tooth alignment during fixed orthodontic treatment a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod Sci</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <lpage>13</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34568209</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azizi</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Extiari</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imani</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tooth alignment and pain experience with A-NiTi versus Cu-NiTi a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>431</fpage>
                  <lpage>431</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34488744</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pandis</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polychronopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliades</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Alleviation of mandibular anterior crowding with copper-nickel-titanium vs nickel-titanium wires: a double-blind randomized control trial</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>136</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>152.e1</fpage>
                  <lpage>152.e7</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abdelrahman</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Nimri</surname>
                      <given-names>KS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al Maaitah</surname>
                      <given-names>EF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A clinical comparison of three aligning archwires in terms of alignment efficiency a prospective clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>85</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>434</fpage>
                  <lpage>439</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25090135</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mandall</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lowe</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Worthington</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sandler</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Derwent</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abdi-Oskouei</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Which orthodontic archwire sequence A randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>561</fpage>
                  <lpage>566</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041083</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ong</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ho</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miles</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Alignment efficiency and discomfort of three orthodontic archwire sequences a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <lpage>39</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21367826</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Papageorgiou</surname>
                      <given-names>SN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Konstantinidis</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Papadopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jäger</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bourauel</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A systematic review and meta-analysis of experimental clinical evidence on initial aligning archwires and archwire sequences</article-title>
                  <source>Orthod Craniofac Res</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <lpage>215</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24889143</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jian</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McIntyre</surname>
                      <given-names>GT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Millett</surname>
                      <given-names>DT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hickman</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Initial arch wires used in orthodontic treatment with fixed appliances</article-title>
                  <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>CD007859</fpage>
                  <lpage>CD007859</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30064155</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thilander</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pena</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Infante</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parada</surname>
                      <given-names>SS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mayorga</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence of malocclusion and orthodontic treatment need in children and adolescents in Bogota, Colombia An epidemiological study related to different stages of dental development</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>167</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11398553</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rekhawat</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Durgekar</surname>
                      <given-names>SG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reddy</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of root resorption, tooth inclination and changes in supporting bone in class II malocclusion patients treated with forsus appliance</article-title>
                  <source>Turk J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <lpage>30</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32284895</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Little</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The irregularity index a quantitative score of mandibular anterior alignment</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod</source>
                  <year>1975</year>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>554</fpage>
                  <lpage>563</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1059332</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nabbat</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yassir</surname>
                      <given-names>YA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A clinical comparison of the effectiveness of two types of orthodontic aligning archwire materials a multicentre randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>626</fpage>
                  <lpage>634</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32011678</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Serafim</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gurgel</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tiago</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tavarez</surname>
                      <given-names>RR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maia</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                      <suffix>Filho</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical efficiency of two sequences of orthodontic wires to correct crowding of the lower anterior teeth</article-title>
                  <source>ScientificWorldJournal</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>2015</volume>
                  <fpage>690280</fpage>
                  <lpage>690280</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26176018</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aydin</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Senisik</surname>
                      <given-names>NE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koskan</surname>
                      <given-names>Ö</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the alignment efficiency of nickel-titanium and copper-nickel-titanium archwires in patients undergoing orthodontic treatment over a 12-week period a single-center, randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Korean J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>162</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29732301</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atik</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gorucu-Coskuner</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akarsu-Guven</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taner</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparative assessment of clinical efficiency between premium heat-activated copper nickel-titanium and superelastic nickel-titanium archwires during initial orthodontic alignment in adolescents a randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Prog Orthod</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31840204</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riley</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bearn</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A systematic review of clinical trials of aligning archwires</article-title>
                  <source>J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <lpage>51</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19286875</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ulhaq</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Esmail</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamaruddin</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meadows</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daus</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vitale</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Alignment efficiency and esthetic performance of 4 coated nickel-titanium archwires in orthodontic patients over 8 weeks a multicenter randomized clinical trial</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>152</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>744</fpage>
                  <lpage>752</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29173854</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsiklakis</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donta</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gavala</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karayianni</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamenopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hourdakis</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dose reduction in maxillofacial imaging using low dose cone beam CT</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>413</fpage>
                  <lpage>417</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alamadi</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alhazmi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hansen</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lundgren</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naoumova</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparative study of cone beam computed tomography and conventional radiography in diagnosing the extent of root resorptions</article-title>
                  <source>Prog Orthod</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>37</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29152679</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sameshima</surname>
                      <given-names>GT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinclair</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Predicting and preventing root resorption Part I. Diagnostic factors</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>119</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>505</fpage>
                  <lpage>510</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11343022</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sameshima</surname>
                      <given-names>GT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinclair</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characteristics of patients with severe root resorption</article-title>
                  <source>Orthod Craniofac Res</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <lpage>114</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15180089</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neves</surname>
                      <given-names>BMD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                      <given-names>LQP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capelli</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>External apical root resorption after orthodontic treatment analysis in different chronological periods</article-title>
                  <source>Dental Press J Orthod</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <elocation-id>e2220100</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36350942</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leite</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Conti</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Navarro</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oltramari-Navarro</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of root resorption between self-ligating and conventional preadjusted brackets using cone beam computed tomography</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1078</fpage>
                  <lpage>1082</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22409394</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B41">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ajmera</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Venkatesh</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ganeshkar</surname>
                      <given-names>SV</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Volumetric evaluation of root resorption during orthodontic treatment</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Orthod</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>119</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24763679</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B42">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Puttaravuttiporn</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wongsuwanlert</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Charoemratrote</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leethanakul</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Volumetric evaluation of root resorption on the upper incisors using cone beam computed tomography after 1 year of orthodontic treatment in adult patients with marginal bone loss</article-title>
                  <source>Angle Orthod</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>88</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>710</fpage>
                  <lpage>718</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29911905</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
